CHAPTER THREE

1

For ten years after this I saw neither Isabel nor Larry. I continued to see Elliott, and indeed, for a reason that I shall tell later, more frequently than before, and from time to time I learnt from him what was happening to Isabel.But of Larry he could tell me nothing.

“For all I know he's still living in Paris, but I'm not likely to run across him. We don't move in the same circles，”he added, not without complacency.“It's very sad that he should have gone so completely to seed.He comes of a very good family.I'm sure I could have made something of him if he’d put himself in my hands.Anyhow it was a lucky escape for Isabel.”

My circle of acquaintance was not so restricted as Elliott's and I knew a number of persons in Paris whom he would have thought eminently undesirable. On my brief but not infrequent sojourns I asked one or other of them whether he had run across Larry or had news of him；a few knew him casually, but none could claim any intimacy with him and I could find nobody to give me news of him.I went to the restaurant at which he habitually dined, but found he had not been there for a long time, and they thought he must have gone away.I never saw him at any of the cafés on the Boulevard du Montparnasse which people who live in the neighbourhood are apt to go to.

His intention, after Isabel left Paris, was to go to Greece, but this he abandoned. What he actually did he told me himself many years later, but I will relate it now because it is more convenient to place events as far as I can in chronological order.He stayed on in Paris during the summer and worked without a break till autumn was well advanced.

“I thought I needed a rest from books then，”he said，“I'd been working from eight to ten hours a day for two years. So I went to work in a coal mine.”

“You did what?”I cried.

He laughed at my astonishment.

“I thought it would do me good to spend a few months in manual labour. I had a notion it would give me an opportunity to sort my thoughts and come to terms with myself.”

I was silent. I wondered whether that was the only reason for this unexpected step or whether it was connected with Isabel's refusal to marry him.The fact was, I didn't know at all how deeply he loved her.Most people when they're in love invent every kind of reason to persuade themselves that it's only sensible to do what they want.I suppose that's why there are so many disastrous marriages.They are like those who put their affairs in the hands of someone they know to be a crook, but who happens to be an intimate friend because, unwilling to believe that a crook is a crook first and a friend afterwards, they are convinced that, however dishonest he may be with others, he won’t be so with them.Larry was strong enough to refuse to sacrifice for Isabel’s sake the life that he thought was the life for him, but it may be that to lose her was bitterer to endure than he had expected.It may be that like most of us he wanted to eat his cake and have it.

“Well, go on，”I said.

“I packed my books and my clothes in a couple of trunks and got the American Express to store them. Then I putan extra suit and some linen in a grip and started off.My Greek teacher had a sister who was married to the manager of a mine near Lens and he gave me a letter to him.D'you know Lens?”

“No.”

“It's in the North of France, not far from the Belgian border. I only spent a night there, at the station hotel, and next day I took a local to the place where the mine was.Ever been to a mining village?”

“In England.”

“Well, I suppose it's much the same. There's the mine and the manager's house, rows and rows of trim little two-storey houses, all alike, exactly alike, and it's so monotonous it makes your heart sink.There's a newish, ugly church and several bars.It was bleak and cold when I got there and a thin rain was falling.I went to the manager’s office and sent in my letter.He was a little, fat man with red cheeks and the look of a guy who enjoys his food.They were short of labour, a lot of miners had been killed in the war, and there were a good many Poles working there, two or three hundred, I should think.He asked me one or two questions, he didn’t much like my being an American, he seemed to think it rather fishy, but his brother-in-law’s letter spoke well of me and anyhow he was glad to have me.He wanted to give me a job on the surface, but I told him I wanted to work down below.He said I’d find it hard if I wasn’t used to it, but I told him I was prepared for that, so then he said I could be helper to a miner.That was boy’s work really, but there weren’t enough boys to go round.He was a nice fellow；he asked me if I’d done anything about finding a lodging, and when I told him I hadn’t he wrote an address on a piece of paper and said that if I went there the woman of the house would let me have a bed.She was the widow of a miner who’d been killed and her two sons were working in the mine.

“I took up my grip and went on my way. I found the house, and the door was opened for me by a tall, gaunt woman with greying hair and big, dark eyes.She had good features and she must have been nice-looking once.She wouldn't have been bad then in a haggard way except for two missing front teeth.She told me she hadn't a room, but there were two beds in a room she'd let to a Pole and I could have the other one.Her two sons had one of the upstairs rooms and she had the other.The room she showed me was on the ground floor and supposed, I imagined, to be the living-room；I should have liked a room to myself, but I thought I'd better not be fussy；and the drizzle had turned into a steady, light rain and I was wet already.I didn't want to go farther and get soaked to the skin.So I said that would suit me and I settled in.They used the kitchen as a living-room.It had a couple of rickety armchairs in it.There was a coal shed in the yard which was also the bathhouse.The two boys and the Pole had taken their lunch with them, but she said I could eat with her at midday.I sat in the kitchen afterwards smoking and while she went on with her work she told me all about herself and her family.The others came in at the end of their shift.The Pole first and then the two boys.The Pole passed through the kitchen, nodded to me with-out speaking when our landlady told him I was to share his room, took a great kettle off the hob and went off to wash himself in the shed.The two boys were tall good-looking fellows notwithstanding the grime on their faces, and seemed inclined to be friendly.They looked upon me as a freak because I was American.One of them was nineteen, off to his military service in a few months, and the other eighteen.

“The Pole came back and then they went to clean up. The Pole had one of those difficult Polish names, but they called him Kosti.He was a big fellow, two or three inches taller than me, and heavily built.He had a pale fleshy face with a broad short nose and a big mouth.His eyes were blue and because he hadn't been able to wash the coal dust off his eyebrows and eyelashes he looked as if he was made up.The black lashes made the blue of his eyes almost startling.He was an ugly, uncouth fellow.The two boys after they'd changed their clothes went out.The Pole sat on in the kitchen, smoking a pipe and reading the paper.I had a book in my pocket, so I took it out and began reading too.I noticed that he glanced at me once or twice and presently he put his paper down.

“‘What are you reading?'he asked.

“I handed him the book to see for himself. It was a copy of the Princesse de Clèves that I’d bought at the station in Paris because it was small enough to put in my pocket.He looked at it, then at me, curiously, and handed it back.I noticed an ironical smile on his lips.

“‘Does it amuse you?'

“‘I think it's very interesting-even absorbing.'

“‘I read it at school at Warsaw. It bored me stiff.'He spoke very good French, with hardly a trace of Polish accent.‘Now I don't read anything but the newspaper and detective stories.'

“Madame Leclerc, that was our old girl's name, with an eye on the soup that was cooking for supper, sat at the table darning socks. She told Kosti that I had been sent to her by the manager of the mine and repeated what else I had seen fit to tell her.He listened, puffing away at his pipe, and looked at me with brilliantly blue eyes.They were hard and shrewd.He asked me a few questions about myself.When I told him I had never worked in a mine before his lips broke again into an ironical smile.

“‘You don't know what you're in for. No one would go to work in a mine who could do anything else.But that's your affair and doubtless you have your reasons.Where did you live in Paris?'

“I told him.

“‘At one time I used to go to Paris every year, but I kept to the Grands Boulevards. Have you ever been to Larue's?It was my favourite restaurant.'

“That surprised me a bit because, you know, it's not cheap.”

“Far from it.”

“I fancy he saw my surprise, for he gave me once more his mocking smile, but evidently didn't think it necessary to explain further. We went on talking in a desultory fashion and then the two boys came in.We had supper and when we'd finished Kosti asked me if I'd like to come to the bistro with him and have a beer.It was just a rather large room with a bar at one end of it and a number of marble-topped tables with wooden chairs around them.There was a mechanical piano and someone had put a coin in the slot and it was braying out a dance tune.Only three tables were occupied besides ours.Kosti asked me if I played belote.I'd learnt it with some of my student friends, so I said I did and he proposed that we should play for the beer.I agreed and he called for cards.I lost a beer and a second beer.Then he proposed that we should play for money.He had good cards and I had bad luck.We were playing for very small stakes, but I lost several francs.This and the beer put him in a good humour and he talked.It didn't take me long to guess both by his way of expressing himself and by his manners, that he was a man of education.When he spoke again of Paris it was to ask me if I knew So-and-so and So-and-so, American women I had met at Elliott’s when Aunt Louisa and Isabel were staying with him.He appeared to know them better than I did and I wondered how it was that he found himself in his present position.It wasn’t late, but we had to get up at the crack of dawn.

“‘Let's have one more beer before we go，'said Kosti.

“He sipped it and peered at me with his shrewd little eyes. I knew what he reminded me of then, an ill-tempered pig.

“‘Why have you come here to work in this rotten mine?'he asked me.

“‘For the experience.'

“‘Tu es fou, mon petit，'he said.

“‘And why are you working in it?'

“He shrugged his massive, ungainly shoulders.

“‘I entered the nobleman's cadet school when I was a kid, my father was a general under the Czar and I was a cavalry officer in the last war. I couldn't stand Pilsudski.We arranged to kill him, but someone gave us away.He shot those of us he caught.I managed to get across the frontier just in time.There was nothing for me but the Foreign Legion or a coal mine.I chose the lesser of two evils.'

“I had already told Kosti what job I was to have in the mine and he had said nothing, but now, putting his elbow on the marble-topped table, he said：

“‘Try to push my hand back.'

“I knew the old trial of strength and I put my open palm against his. He laughed.‘Your hand won't be as soft asthat in a few weeks.'I pushed with all my might, but I could make no effect against his huge strength and gradually he pressed my hand back and down to the table.

“‘You're pretty strong，'he was good enough to say.‘There aren't many men who keep up as long as that. Listen, my helper's no good, he's a puny little Frenchman, he hasn’t got the strength of a louse.You come along with me tomorrow and I’ll get the foreman to let me have you instead.’

“‘I'd like that，'I said.‘D'you think he'll do it?'

“‘For a consideration. Have you got fifty francs to spare?'

“He stretched out his hand and I took a note out of my wallet. We went home and to bed.I'd had a long day and I slept like a log.”

“Didn't you find the work terribly hard?”I asked Larry.

“Back-breaking at first，”he grinned.“Kosti worked it with the foreman and I was made his helper. At that time Kosti was working in a space about the size of a hotel bathroom and one got to it through a tunnel so low that you had to crawl through it on your hands and knees.It was as hot as hell in there and we worked in nothing but our pants.There was something terribly repulsive in that great white fat torso of Kosti's；he looked like a huge slug.The row of the pneumatic cutter in that narrow space was deafening.My job was to gather the blocks of coal that he hacked away and load a basket with them and drag the basket through the tunnel to its mouth, where it could be loaded into a truck when the train came along at intervals on its way to the elevators.It's the only coal mine I've ever known, so I don't know if that's the normal practice.It seemed amateurish to me and it was damned hard work.At half time we knocked off for a rest and ate our lunch and smoked.I wasn’t sorry when we were through for the day, and gosh, it was good to have a bath.I thought I’d never get my feet clean；they were as black as ink.Of course my hands blistered and they got as sore as the devil, but they healed.I got used to the work.”

“How long did you stick it out?”

“I was only kept on that job for a few weeks. The trucks that carried the coal to the elevators were hauled by a tractor and the driver was a poor mechanic and the engine was always breaking down.Once he couldn't get it going and he didn't seem to know what to do.Well, I'm a pretty good mechanic, so I had a look at it and in half an hour I got it working.The foreman told the manager and he sent for me and asked me if I knew about cars.The result was that he gave me the mechanic's job；of course it was monotonous, but it was easy, and because they didn't have any more engine trouble they were pleased with me.

“Kosti was as sore as hell at my leaving him. I suited him and he'd got used to me.I got to know him pretty well, working with him all day, going to the bistro with him after supper, and sharing a room with him.He was a funny fellow.He was the sort of man who'd have appealed to you.He didn't mix with the Poles and we didn't go to the cafés they went to.He couldn’t forget he was a nobleman and had been a cavalry officer and he treated them like dirt.Naturally they resented it, but they couldn’t do anything about it；he was as strong as an ox, and if it had ever come to a scrap, knives or no knives, he’d have been a match for half a dozen of them together.I got to know some of them all the same, and they told me he’d been a cavalry officer all right in one of the smart regiments, but it was a lie about his having left Poland for political reasons.He’d been kicked out of the Officers’Club at Warsaw and cashiered because he’d been caught cheating at cards.They warned me against playing with him.They said that was why he fought shy of them, because they knew too much about him and wouldn’t play with him.

“I'd been losing to him consistently, not much, you know, just a few francs a night, but when he won he always insisted on paying for drinks, so it didn't amount to anything really. I thought I was just having a run of bad luck or that I didn't play as well as he did.But after that I kept my eyes skinned and I was dead sure he was cheating, but d'you know, for the life of me I couldn't see how he did it.Gosh, he was clever.I knew he simply couldn’t have the best cards all the time.I watched him like a lynx.He was as cunning as a fox and I guess he saw I’d been put wise to him.One night, after we’d been playing for a while, he looked at me with that rather cruel, sarcastic smile of his which was the only way he knew how to smile, and said：

“‘Shall I show you a few tricks?'

“He took the pack of cards and asked me to name one. He shuffled them and he told me to choose one；I did, and it was the card I'd named.He did two or three more tricks and then he asked me if I played poker.I said I did and he dealt me a hand.When I looked at it I saw I'd got four aces and a king.

“‘You'd be willing to bet a good deal on that hand, wouldn't you?'he asked.

“‘My whole stack，'I answered.

“‘You'd be silly.'He put down the hand he'd dealt himself. It was a straight flush.How it was done I don't know.He laughed at my amazement.‘If I weren't an honest man I’d have had your shirt by now.’

“‘You haven't done so badly as it is，'I grinned.

“‘Chicken feed. Not enough to buy a dinner at Larue's.'

“We continued to play pretty well every night. I came to the conclusion that he cheated not so much for the money as for the fun of it.It gave him a queer satisfaction to know that he was making a fool of me, and I think he got a lot of amusement out of knowing that I was on to what he was doing and couldn't see how it was done.

“But that was only one side of him and it was the other side that made him so interesting to me. I couldn't reconcile the two.Though he boasted he never read anything but the paper and detective stories he was a cultivated man.He was a good talker, caustic, harsh, cynical, but it was exhilarating to listen to him.He was a devout Catholic and had a crucifix hanging over his bed, and he went to Mass every Sunday regularly.On Saturday nights he used to get drunk.The bistro we went to was crammed jammed full then, and the air was heavy with smoke.There were quiet, middle-aged miners with their families, and there were groups of young fellows kicking up a hell of a row, and there were men with sweaty faces round tables playing belote with loud shouts, while their wives sat by, a little behind them, and watched.The crowd and the noise had a strange effect on Kosti and he'd grow serious and start talking-of all unlikely subjects-of mysticism.I knew nothing of it then but an essay of Maeterlinck's on Ruysbroek that I'd read in Paris.But Kosti talked of Plotinus and Denis the Areopagite and Jacob Boehme the shoemaker and Meister Eckhart.It was fantastic to hear that great hulking bum, who'd been thrown out of his own world, that sardonic, bitter down-and-out, speaking of the ultimate reality of things and the blessedness of union with God.It was all new to me and I was confused and excited.I was like someone who’s lain awake in a darkened room and suddenly a chink of light shoots through the curtains and he knows he only has to draw them and there the country will be spread before him in the glory of the dawn.But if I tried to get him on the subject when he was sober he got mad at me.His eyes were spiteful.

“‘How should I know what I was talking about when I didn't know what I was saying?'he snapped.

“But I knew he was lying. He knew perfectly well what he was talking about.He knew a lot.Of course he was soused, but the look in his eyes, the rapt expression on his ugly face, weren't due only to drink.There was more to it than that.The first time he talked in that way he said something that I've never forgotten, because it horrified me；he said that the world isn't a creation, for out of nothing nothing comes；but a manifestation of the eternal nature；well, that was all right, but then he added that evil is as direct a manifestation of the divine as good.They were strange words to hear in that sordid, noisy café，to the accompaniment of dance tunes on the mechanical piano.”

2

To give the reader a moment's rest I am starting here upon a new section, but I am doing it only for his convenience；the conversation was uninterrupted. I may take this opportunity to say that Larry spoke without haste, often choosing his words with care, and though of course I do not pretend to report them exactly, I have tried to reproduce not only the matter, but the manner of his discourse.His voice, rich in tone, had a musical quality that was grateful to the ear；and as he talked without gesticulation of any kind, puffing away at his pipe and stopping now and again to relight it, he looked you in the face with a pleasant, often whimsical expression in his dark eyes.

“Then the spring came, late in that flat, dismal part of the country, cold and rainy still；but sometimes a fine warm day made it hard to leave the world above ground and go down hundreds of feet in a rickety elevator, crowded with miners in their grimy overalls, into the bowels of the earth. It was spring all right, but it seemed to come shyly in that grim and sordid landscape as though unsure of a welcome.It was like a flower, a daffodil or a lily, growing in a pot on the window-sill of a slum dwelling and you wondered what it did there.One Sunday morning we were lying in bed, we always slept late on Sunday morning, and I was reading, when Kosti said to me out of a blue sky：

“‘I'm getting out of here. D'you want to come with me?'

“I knew a lot of the Poles went back to Poland in the summer to get the harvest in, but it was early for that, and besides, Kosti couldn't go back to Poland.

“‘Where are you going?'I asked.

“‘Tramping. Across Belgium and into Germany and down the Rhine.We could get work on a farm that would see us through the summer.'

“It didn't take a minute to make up my mind.

“‘It sounds fine，'I said.

“Next day we told the foreman we were through. I found a fellow who was willing to take my grip in exchange for a rucksack.I gave the clothes I didn't want or couldn't carry on my back to the younger of Madame Leclerc's sons who was about my size.Kosti left a bag, packed what he wanted in his rucksack and the day after, as soon as the old girl had given us our coffee, we started off.

“We weren't in any hurry as we knew we couldn't get taken on at a farm at least until the hay was ready to cut, and so we dawdled along through France and Belgium by way of Namur and Liège and got into Germany through Aachen.We didn’t do more than ten or twelve miles a day.When we liked the look of a village we stopped there.There was always some kind of an inn where we could get beds and an alehouse where we could get something to eat and beer to drink.On the whole we had fine weather.It was grand to be out in the open air after all those months in the mine.I don’t think I’d ever realized before how good a green meadow is to look at and how lovely a tree is when the leaves aren’t out yet, but the branches are veiled in a faint green mist.Kosti started to teach me German and I believe he spoke it as well as he spoke French.As we trudged along he would tell me the German for the various objects we passed, a cow, a horse, a man and so on, and then repeat simple German sentences.It made the time pass and by the time we got into Germany I could at least ask for the things I wanted.

“Cologne was a bit out of our way, but Kosti insisted on going there, on account of the Eleven Thousand Virgins, he said, and when we got there he went on a bat. I didn't see him for three days and when he turned up at the room we'd taken in a sort of workmen's rooming-house he was very surly.He'd got in a fight and he had a black eye and a cut on his lip.He wasn't a pretty object, I can tell you.He went to bed for twenty-four hours, and then we started to walk down the valley of the Rhine towards Darmstadt, where he said the country was good and we stood the best chance of getting work.

“I never enjoyed anything more. The fine weather held and we wandered through towns and villages.When there were sights to see we stopped off and looked at them.We put up where we could and once or twice we slept in a loft on the hay.We ate at wayside inns, and when we got in the wine country we turned from beer to wine.We made friends with the people in the taverns we drank in.Kosti had a sort of rough joviality that inspired them with confidence and he'd play skat with them, that's a German card game, and skin them with such bluff good humour, with the earthy jokes they appreciated, that they hardly minded losing their pfennigs to him.I practised my German on them.I'd bought a little English-German conversation grammar at Cologne and I was getting on pretty well.And then at night, when he'd got a couple of litres of white wine inside him, Kosti would talk in a morbid way of the flight from the Alone to the Alone, of the Dark Night of the Soul and of the final ecstasy in which the creature becomes one with the Beloved.But when in the early morning, as we walked through the smiling country, with the dew still on the grass, I tried to get him to tell me more, he grew so angry that he could have hit me.

“‘Shut up, you fool，'he said.‘What do you want with all that stuff and nonsense?Come, let's get on with our German.'

“You can't argue with a man who's got a fist like a steam hammer and wouldn't think twice about using it. I'd seen him in a rage.I knew he was capable of laying me out cold and leaving me in a ditch and I wouldn't have put it past him to empty my pockets while I was out.I couldn’t make head or tail of him.When wine had loosened his tongue and he spoke of the Ineffable, he shed the rough obscene language that he ordinarily used, like the grimy overalls he wore in the mine, and he was well-spoken and even eloquent.I couldn’t believe he wasn’t sincere.I don’t know how it occurred to me, but I got the idea somehow that he’d taken on that hard, brutal labour of the mine to mortify his flesh.I thought he hated that great, uncouth body of his and wanted to torture it, and that his cheating and his bitterness and his cruelty were the revolt of his will against-oh, I don’t know what you’d call it-against a deep-rooted instinct of holiness, against a desire for God that terrified and yet obsessed him.

“We'd taken our time, the spring was pretty well over and the trees were in full leaf. The grapes in the vineyards were beginning to fill out.We kept to the dirt roads as much as we could and they were getting dusty.We were in the neighbourhood of Darmstadt, and Kosti said we'd better start looking for a job.Our money was getting short.I had half a dozen travellers'cheques in my pocket, but I'd made up my mind not to use them if I could possibly help it.When we saw a farmhouse that looked promising we stopped and asked if they wanted a couple of hands, I dare say we didn't look very inviting.We were dusty and sweaty and dirty.Kosti looked a terrible ruffian and I don’t suppose I looked much better either.We were turned down time after time.At one place the farmer said he’d take Kosti but couldn’t do with me and Kosti said we were buddies and wouldn’t separate.I told him to go ahead, but he wouldn’t.I was surprised.I knew Kosti had taken a fancy to me, though I couldn’t imagine why, as I didn’t begin to be the kind of guy he had any use for, but I would never have thought he liked me well enough to refuse a job on my account.I felt rather conscience-stricken as we walked on, because I didn’t really like him, in fact I found him rather repulsive, but when I tried to say something to show I was pleased with what he’d done, he bit my head off.

“But at last our luck turned. We'd just gone through a village in a hollow and we came to a rambling farmhouse that didn't look so bad.We knocked at the door and a woman opened it.We offered ourselves as usual.We said we didn't want any wages, but were willing to work for our board and lodging, and to my surprise instead of slamming the door in our face, she told us to wait.She called to someone inside the house and presently a man came out.He had a good stare at us and asked us where we came from.He asked to see our papers.He gave me another stare when he saw I was American.He didn't seem to like it very much, but anyhow he asked us to come in and have a glass of wine.He took us into the kitchen and we sat down.The woman brought a flagon and some glasses.He told us that his hired man had been gored by a bull and was in hospital and wouldn't be fit for anything till after the harvest was in.With so many men killed, and others going into the factories that were springing up along the Rhine, it was the devil’s own job to get labour.We knew that and had been counting on it.Well, to make a long story short he said he’d take us.There was plenty of room in the house, but I suppose he didn’t fancy having us there；anyway he told us there were two beds in the hayloft and that was where we were to sleep.

“The work wasn't hard. There were the cows to look after and the hogs；the machinery was in a bad way, and we had to do something about that；but I had some leisure.I loved the sweet-smelling meadows and in the evenings I used to wander about and dream.It was a good life.

“The household consisted of old Becker, his wife, his widowed daughter-in-law and her children. Becker was a heavy, grey-haired man in his late forties；he'd been through the war and still limped from a wound in the leg.It hurt him a lot and he drank to kill the pain.He was generally high by the time he got to bed.Kosti got on with him fine and they used to go down to the inn together after supper to play skat and swill wine.Frau Becker had been a hired girl.They'd got her out of an orphanage and Becker had married her soon after his wife's death.She was a good many years younger than he was, rather handsome in a way, full-blown, with red cheeks and fair hair and a hungry sensual look.It didn't take Kosti long to come to the conclusion that there was something doing there.I told him not to be a fool.Wehad a good job and we didn't want to lose it.He only jeered at me；he said Becker wasn’t satisfying her and she was asking for it.I knew it was useless to appeal to his sense of decency, but I told him to be careful；it might be that Becker wouldn’t see what he was after, but there was his daughter-in-law, and she wasn’t missing anything.

“Ellie, that was her name, was a thickset, big young woman, well under thirty, with black eyes and black hair, a sallow square face and a sullen look. She still wore mourning for her husband killed at Verdun.She was very devout and on Sunday mornings trudged down to the village to early Mass and again in the afternoon to vespers.She had three children, one of whom had been born after her husband's death, and she never spoke at meals except to scold them.She did little work on the farm, but spent most of her time looking after the kids, and in the evening sat by herself in the sitting-room, with the door open so that she could hear if one of them was crying, and read novels.The two women hated one another.Ellie despised Frau Becker because she was a foundling and had been a servant, and bitterly resented her being the mistress of the house and in a position to give orders.

“Ellie was the daughter of a prosperous farmer and had brought a good dowry with her. She hadn't gone to the village school, but to Zwingenberg, the nearest town, where there was a girl's gymnasium, and she'd got quite a good education.Poor Frau Becker had come to the farm when she was fourteen and if she could read and write that's about all she could do.That was another cause of discord between the two women.Ellie lost no opportunity of showing off her knowledge, and Frau Becker, red in the face with anger, would ask what use it was to a farmer's wife.Then Ellie would look at her husband’s identification disc which she wore on a steel chain round her wrist and with a bitter look on her sullen face say：

“‘Not a farmer's wife. Only a farmer's widow.Only the widow of a hero who gave his life for his country.'

“Poor old Becker had his work cut out to keep the peace between them.”

“But what did they make of you?”I interrupted Larry.

“Oh, they thought I'd deserted from the American Army and couldn't go back to America or I'd be put in jail. That's how they explained that I didn't care to go down to the inn and drink with Becker and Kosti.They thought I didn’t want to attract attention to myself and have the village constable asking questions.When Ellie found out I was trying to learn German she brought out her old schoolbooks and said she’d teach me.So after supper she and I would go into the sitting-room, leaving Frau Becker in the kitchen, and I’d read aloud to her while she corrected my accent and tried to make me understand words I couldn’t get the sense of.I guessed she was doing it not so much to help me as to put something over on Frau Becker.

“All this time Kosti was trying to make Frau Becker and wasn't getting anywhere. She was a jolly, merry woman and quite prepared to joke and laugh with him, and he had a way with him with women.I guess she knew what he was after and I dare say she was flattered, but when he started pinching her she told him to keep his hands to himself and smacked his face.And I bet it was a good hard smack.”

Larry hesitated a little and smiled rather shyly.

“I've never been the sort who thinks women are after me, but it occurred to me that-well, that Frau Becker had fallen for me. It made me rather uncomfortable.For one thing she was a lot older than me, and then old Becker had been very decent to us.She dished out the food at table and I couldn't help noticing that she helped me more liberally than the others, and she seemed to me to look for opportunities of being alone with me.She'd smile at me in what I suppose you'd call a provocative manner.She'd ask me if I had a girl, and say that a young fellow like me must suffer for the want of it in a place like that.You know the sort of thing.I only had three shirts and they were pretty well worn.Once she said it was a disgrace that I should wear such rags and if I’d bring them along she’d mend them.Ellie heard her and next time we were alone said that if I had anything to mend she’d do it.I said it didn’t matter.But a day or two later I found that my socks had been darned and my shirts patched and put back on the bench in the loft on which we kept our things；but which of them had done it I don’t know.Of course I didn’t take Frau Becker seriously；she was a good-natured old soul and I thought it might be just motherliness on her part；but then one day Kosti said to me：

“‘Listen, it's not me she wants；it's you. I haven't got a chance.'

“‘Don't talk such nonsense，'I said to him.‘She's old enough to be my mother.'

“‘What of it?You go ahead, my boy, I won't stand in your way. She's not so young as she might be, but she's a fine figure of a woman.'

“‘Oh, shut up.'

“‘Why d'you hesitate?Not on my account, I hope. I'm a philosopher and I know there are as good fish in the sea as ever came out.I don't blame her.You're young.I've been young too.Jeunesse ne dure qu’un moment.’

“I wasn't too pleased that Kosti was so sure of what I didn't want to believe. I didn't quite know how to deal with the situation, and then I recalled various things that hadn't struck me at the time.Things said by Ellie that I hadn't paid much attention to.But now I understood them and I was pretty sure that she too knew what was happening.She’d turn up suddenly in the kitchen when Frau Becker and I happened to be alone.I got the impression that she was watching us.I didn’t like it.I thought she was out to catch us.I knew she hated Frau Becker, and if she had half a chance she’d make trouble.Of course I knew she couldn’t catch us, but she was a malevolent creature and I didn’t know what lies she mightn’t invent and pour into old Becker’s ears.I didn’t know what to do except to pretend I was such a fool I didn’t see what the old girl was up to.I was happy at the farm and enjoying the work and I didn’t want to go till after we’d got the harvest in.”

I couldn't help smiling. I could imagine what Larry had looked like then, in his patched shirt and shorts, his face and neck burnt brown by the hot sun of the Rhine valley, with his lithe slim body, and his black eyes in their deep sockets.I could well believe that the sight of him set the matronly Frau Becker, so blonde, so full-breasted, all of a flutter with desire.

“Well, what happened?”I asked.

“Well, the summer wore on. We worked like demons there.We cut and stacked the hay.Then the cherries were ripe, Kosti and I got up on ladders and picked them, and the two women put them in great baskets and old Becker took them into Zwingenberg and sold them.Then we cut the rye.And of course there were always the animals to look after.We were up before dawn and we didn't stop work till nightfall.I supposed Frau Becker had given me up as a bad job；as far as I could without offending her, I kept her at arm's length.I was too sleepy to read much German in the evenings and soon after supper I'd take myself off to our loft and fall into bed.Most evenings Becker and Kosti went to the inn down in the village, but I was fast asleep by the time Kosti came back.It was hot in the loft and I slept naked.

“One night I was awakened. At the first moment I couldn't make out what it was；I was only half awake.I felt a hot hand on my mouth and I realized somebody was in bed with me, I tore the hand away and then a mouth was pressed to mine, two arms were thrown round me, and I felt Frau Becker's great breasts against my body.

“‘Sei still，'she whispered.‘Be quiet.'

“She pressed up against me and kissed my face with hot full lips and her hands travelled over my body and she twined her legs in mine.”

Larry stopped. I giggled.

“What did you do?”

He gave me a deprecating smile. He even flushed a little.

“What could I do?I could hear Kosti breathing heavily in his sleep in the bed next to mine. The situation of Joseph has always seemed to me faintly ridiculous.I was only just twenty-three.I couldn't make a scene and kick her out.I didn't want to hurt her feelings.I did what was expected of me.

“Then she slipped out of bed and tiptoed out of the loft. I can tell you, I heaved a sigh of relief.You know, I'd been scared.‘Gosh，'I said，‘what a risk to take！'I thought it likely that Becker had come home drunk and fallen asleep in a stupor, but they slept in the same bed, and it might be that he'd woken up and seen his wife wasn't there.And there was Ellie.She always said she didn’t sleep well.If she’d been awake she’d have heard Frau Becker go downstairs and out of the house.And then, suddenly, something struck me.When Frau Becker was in bed with me I’d felt a piece of metal against my skin.I’d paid no attention, you know one doesn’t in those circumstances, and I’d never thought of askingmyself what the devil it was.And now it flashed across me.I was sitting on the side of my bed thinking and worrying about the consequences of all this and it was such a shock that I jumped up.The piece of metal was Ellie’s husband’s identification disc that she wore round her wrist and it wasn’t Frau Becker that had been in bed with me.It was Ellie.”

I roared with laughter. I couldn't stop.

“It may seem funny to you，”said Larry.“It didn't seem funny to me.”

“Well, now you look back on it, don't you think there is just a faint element of the humorous about it?”

An unwilling smile played on his lips.

“Perhaps. But it was an awkward situation.I didn't know what it was going to lead to.I didn't like Ellie.I thought her a most unpleasant female.”

“But how could you mistake one for the other?”

“It was pitch dark. She never said a word except to tell me to keep my trap shut.They were both big stout women.I thought Frau Becker had her eye on me.It never occurred to me for a moment that Ellie gave me a thought.She was always thinking of her husband.I lit a cigarette and thought the position over and the more I thought of it the less I liked it.It seemed to me that the best thing I could do was to get out.

“I'd often cursed Kosti because he was so hard to wake. When we were at the mine I used to have to shake the life out of him to get him up in time to go to work.But I was thankful now that he slept so heavily.I lit my lantern and dressed, bundled my things into my rucksack-I hadn't got much, so it didn't take a minute-and slipped my arms through the straps.I walked across the loft in my stocking feet and didn't put my shoes on till I got to the bottom of the ladder.I blew out the lantern.It was a dark night, with no moon, but I knew my way to the road and I turned in the direction of the village.I walked fast as I wanted to get through it before anyone was up and about.It was only twelve miles to Zwingenberg and I got there just as it was stirring.I shall never forget that walk.There wasn't a sound except my footsteps on the road and now and then the crowing of a cock in a farm.Then the first greyness when it wasn’t yet light and not quite dark, and the first hint of dawn, and the sunrise with the birds all starting to sing, and that lush green country, meadows and woods and the wheat in the fields silvery gold in the cool light of the beginning day.I got a cup of coffee at Zwingenberg and a roll, then I went to the post office and sent a wire to the American Express to have my clothes and my books sent to Bonn.”

“Why Bonn?”I interrupted.

“I'd taken a fancy to it when we stopped off there on our tramp down the Rhine. I liked the way the light shone on the roofs and the river, and its old narrow streets, and its villas and gardens and avenues of chestnut trees and the rococo buildings of the university.It struck me then it wouldn't be a bad place to stay in for a bit.But I thought I'd better present a respectable appearance when I got there, I looked like a tramp and I didn't think I'd inspire much confidence if I went to a pension and asked for a room, so I took a train to Frankfurt and bought myself a grip and a few clothes.I stayed in Bonn off and on for a year.”

“And did you get anything out of your experience, at the mine, I mean, and on the farm?”

“Yes，”said Larry, nodding his head and smiling.

But he didn't tell me what it was and I knew him well enough by then to know that when he felt like telling you something he did, but when he didn't he would turn off questions with a cool pleasantry that made it useless to insist. For I must remind the reader that he narrated all this to me ten years after it happened.Till then, when I once more came in contact with him, I had no notion where he was or how he was engaged.For all I knew he might be dead.Except for my friendship with Elliott, who kept me posted with the course of Isabel's life and so reminded me of Larry, I should doubtless have forgotten his existence.

3

Isabel was married to Gray Maturin early in the June of the year after the termination of her engagement to Larry. Though Elliott hated leaving Paris at a moment when the season was at its height and he must miss a number of grand parties, his family feeling was too strong to allow him to neglect what he thought a social duty.Isabel's brothers were unable to leave their distant posts and so it behoved him to make the irksome journey to Chicago to give his niece away.Remembering that French aristocrats had gone to the guillotine in all their finery, he made a special journey to London to get himself a new morning coat, a dove-grey double-breasted waistcoat, and a silk hat.On his return to Paris he invited me to come and see them on.He was in a state of perturbation because the grey pearl he usually wore in his necktie would not make any sort of effect against the pale grey tie he had chosen as suitable to the festive occasion.I suggested his emerald-and-diamond pin.

“If I were a guest-yes，”he said.“But in the particular position I shall occupy I feel that a pearl is indicated.”

He was much pleased with the marriage, which concorded with all his ideas of propriety, and he spoke of it with the unctuousness of a dowager duchess expressing herself on the suitability of a union between a scion of the La Rochefoucaulds with a daughter of the Montmorencys. As a visible mark of his satisfaction he was taking over as a wedding present, sparing no expense, a fine portrait by Nattier of a princess of the House of France.

It appeared that Henry Maturin had bought for the young couple a house in Astor Street so that they should be close to where Mrs. Bradley lived and not too far from his own palatial residence on Lake Shore Drive.By a happy chance, in which I suspected the deft complicity of Elliott, Gregory Brabazon was in Chicago at the time the purchase was made and the decoration was entrusted to him.When Elliott returned to Europe and, throwing in his hand so far as the season in Paris was concerned, came straight to London, he brought photographs of the result.Gregory Brabazon had let himself go.In the drawing-room he had gone all George the Second and it was very grand.In the library, which was to be Gray's den, he had been inspired by a room in the Amalienburg Palace at Munich, and except that there was no place in it for books it was perfect.Save for the twin beds, Louis Quinze visiting Madame de Pompadour would have found himself perfectly at home in the bedroom Gregory had provided for this young American couple, but Isabel's bathroom would have been an eye-opener to him；it was all glass-walls, ceiling and bath-and on the walls silver fish meandered profusely among gilded aquatic plants.

“Of course it's a tiny house，”said Elliott，“but Henry told me the decoration set him back a hundred thousand dollars. A fortune to some people.”

The ceremony was performed with such pomp as the Episcopalian church could afford.

“Not like a wedding at Notre Dame，”he told me complacently，“but for a Protestant affair it didn't lack style.”

The press had behaved very handsomely and Elliott negligently tossed the cuttings to me. He showed me photographs of Isabel, hefty but handsome in her wedding-dress, and Gray, a massive but fine figure of a man, a trifle self-conscious in his formal clothes.There was a group of the young couple with bridesmaids and another group with Mrs.Bradley in a sumptuous garment and Elliott holding his new top-hat with a grace that only he could have achieved.I asked how Mrs.Bradley was.

“She's lost a good deal of weight and I don't like her colour, but she's pretty well. Of course the whole thing was a strain on her, but now it's all over she'll be able to rest up.”

A year later Isabel was delivered of a daughter, to whom, following the fashion of the moment, she gave the name of Joan；and after an interval of two years she had another daughter whom, following another fashion, she called Priscilla.

One of Henry Maturin's partners died and the other two under pressure soon afterwards retired, so that he entered into sole possession of the business over which he had always exercised despotic control. He realized the ambition he had long entertained and took Gray into partnership with him.The firm had never been so prosperous.

“They're making money hand over fist, my dear fellow，”Elliott told me.“Why, Gray at the age of twenty-five is making fifty thousand a year, and that's only a beginning. The resources of America are inexhaustible.It isn't a boom, it's just the natural development of a great country.”

His chest swelled with an unwonted patriotic fervour.

“Henry Maturin can't live for ever, high blood pressure, you know, and by the time Gray's forty he should be worth twenty million dollars. Princely, my dear fellow, princely.”

Elliott kept up a fairly regular correspondence with his sister and from time to time as the years went on passed on to me what she told him. Gray and Isabel were very happy, and the babies were sweet.They lived in a style that Elliott gladly admitted was eminently suitable；they entertained lavishly and were lavishly entertained；he told me with satisfaction that Isabel and Gray hadn't dined by themselves once in three months.Their whirl of gaiety was interrupted by the death of Mrs.Maturin, that colourless, highborn lady whom Henry Maturin had married for her connexions when he was making a place for himself in the city to which his father had come as a country bumpkin；and out of respect for her memory for a year the young couple never entertained more than six people to dinner.

“I've always said that eight was the perfect number，”said Elliott, determined to look on the bright side of things.“It's intimate enough to permit of general conversation and yet large enough to give the impression of a party.”

Gray was wonderfully generous to his wife. On the birth of their first child he gave her a square-cut diamond ring and on the birth of her second a sable coat.He was too busy to leave Chicago much, but such holidays as he could take they spent at Henry Maturin's imposing house at Marvin.Henry could deny nothing to the son whom he adored and one Christmas gave him a plantation in South Carolina so that he could get a fortnight's duck-shooting in the season.

“Of course our merchant princes correspond to those great patrons of the arts of the Italian Renaissance who made fortunes by commerce. The Medici, for instance.Two kings of France were not too proud to marry the daughters of that illustrious family and I foresee the day when the crowned heads of Europe will seek the hands of our dollar princesses.What was it Shelley said?‘The world's great age begins anew, the golden years return.'”

Henry Maturin had for many years looked after Mrs. Bradley's and Elliott's investments and they had a well-justified confidence in his acumen.He had never countenanced speculation and had put their money into sound securities, but with the great increase in values they found their comparatively modest fortunes increased in a manner that both surprised and delighted them.Elliott told me that, without stirring a finger, he was nearly twice as rich in 1926 as he had been in 1918.He was sixty-five, his hair was grey, his face lined, and there were pouches under his eyes, but he bore his years gallantly；he was as slim and held himself as erectly as ever；he had always been moderate in his habits and taken care of his appearance.He had no intention of submitting to the ravages of time so long as he could have his clothes made by the best tailor in London, his hair dressed and his face shaved by his own particular barber, and a masseur to come in every morning to keep his elegant body in perfect condition.He had long forgotten that he had ever so far demeaned himself as to engage in a trade, and without ever saying so outright, for he was not so stupid as to tell a lie that might be found out, he was inclined to suggest that in his youth he had been in the diplomatic service.I must admit that if I had ever had occasion to draw a portrait of an ambassador I should without hesitation have chosen Elliott as my model.

But things were changing. Such of the great ladies who had advanced Elliott's career as were still alive were well along in years.The English peeresses, having lost their lords, had been forced to surrender their mansions to daughters-in-law, and had retired to villas at Cheltenham or to modest houses in Regent's Park.Stafford House was turned into a museum, Curzon House became the seat of an organization, Devonshire House was for sale.The yacht on which Elliott had been in the habit of staying at Cowes had passed into other hands.The fashionable persons who occupied the stage had no use for the elderly man that Elliott now was.They found him tiresome and ridiculous.They were still willing to come to his elaborate luncheon parties at Claridge's but he was quick-witted enough to know that they came to meet one another rather than to see him.He could no longer pick and choose among the invitations that once had littered his writing-table, and much more often than he would have liked anyone to know he suffered the humiliation of dining by himself in the privacy of his suite.Women of rank in England, when a scandal has closed the doors of society to them, develop an interest in the arts and surround themselves with painters, writers and musicians.Elliott was too proud thus to humiliate himself.

“The death duties and the war profiteers have ruined English society，”he told me.“People don't seem to mind whothey know. London still has its tailors, its bootmakers, and its hatters, and I trust they'll last my time, but except for them it's finished.My dear fellow, do you know that the St.Erth's have women to wait at table?”

This he said when we were walking away from Carlton House Terrace after a luncheon party at which an unfortunate incident had occurred. Our noble host had a well-known collection of pictures, and a young American who was there, Paul Barton by name, expressed a desire to see them.

“You've got a Titian, haven't you?”

“We had. It's in America now.Some old Jew offered us a packet of money for it and we were damned hard up at the time, so my governor sold it.”

I noticed that Elliott, bristling, threw a venomous glance at the jovial marquess, and guessed that it was he who had bought the picture. He was furious at hearing himself, Virginian born and the descendant of a signatory of the Declaration, thus described.He had never in his life suffered so great an affront.And what made it worse was that Paul Barton was the object of his virulent hatred.He was a young man who had appeared in London soon after the war.He was twenty-three, blond, very good-looking, charming, a beautiful dancer, and had an ample fortune.He had brought a letter of introduction to Elliott, who with the kindness of heart natural to him had presented him to several of his friends.Not content with this he had given him some valuable hints on conduct.Delving back into his own experience, he had shown him how it was possible, by paying small attentions to old ladies and by lending a willing ear to distinguished men, however tedious, for a stranger to make his way in society.

But it was a different world that Paul Barton entered from that into which, a generation before, Elliott Templeton had penetrated by means of dogged perseverance. It was a world bent on amusing itself.Paul Barton's high spirits, pleasing exterior, and engaging manner did for him in a few weeks what Elliott had achieved only after years of industry and determination.Soon he no longer needed Elliott's help and took small pains to conceal the fact.He was pleasant to him when they met, but in an offhand way that deeply offended the older man.Elliott did not ask people to a party because he liked them, but because they helped to make it go, and since Paul Barton was popular he continued to invite him on occasion to his weekly luncheons；but the successful young man was generally engaged and twice he threw Elliott over at the last moment.Elliott had done this himself too often not to know it was because he had just had a more tempting invitation.

“I don't ask you to believe it，”Elliott told me, fuming，“but it's God's truth that when I see him now he patronizes me. ME.Titian.Titian，”he spluttered.“He wouldn't know a Titian if he saw one.”

I had never seen Elliott so angry and I guessed his wrath was caused by his belief that Paul Barton had asked about the picture maliciously, having somehow learnt that Elliott had bought it, and would make a funny story at his expense out of the noble lord's reply.

“He's nothing but a dirty little snob, and if there's one thing in the world I detest and despise it's snobbishness. He'd have been nowhere except for me.Would you believe it, his father makes office furniture.Office furniture.”He put withering scorn into the two words.“And when I tell people he simply doesn't exist in America, his origins couldn’t be more humble, they don’t seem to care.Take my word for it, my dear fellow, English society is as dead as the dodo.”

Nor did Elliott find France much better. There the great ladies of his youth, if still alive, were given over to bridge（a game he loathed），piety, and the care of their grandchildren.Manufacturers, Argentines, Chileans, American women separated or divorced from their husbands, inhabited the stately houses of the aristocracy and entertained with splendour, but at their parties Elliott was confounded to meet politicians who spoke French with a vulgar accent, journalists whose table manners were deplorable, and even actors.The scions of princely families thought it no shame to marry the daughters of shopkeepers.It was true Paris was gay, but with what a shoddy gaiety！The young, devoted to the mad pursuit of pleasure, thought nothing more amusing than to go from one stuffy little night club to another, drinking champagne at a hundred francs a bottle and dancing close-packed with the riff-raff of the town till five o'clock in the morning.The smoke, the heat, the noise made Elliott's head ache.This was not the Paris that he had accepted thirty years before as his spiritual home.This was not the Paris that good Americans went to when they died.

4

But Elliott had a flair. An inner monitor suggested to him that the Riviera was on the point of becoming once more the resort of rank and fashion.He knew the coast well from having often spent a few days in Monte Carlo at the Hôtel de Paris on his way back from Rome, whither his duties at the papal court had called him, or at Cannes in the villa of one or the other of his friends.But that was in the winter, and of late rumours had reached him that it was beginning to be well spoken of as a summer resort.The big hotels were remaining open；their summer visitors were listed in the social columns of the Paris Herald and Elliott read the familiar names with approval.

“The world is too much with me，”he said.“I have now reached a time of life when I am prepared to enjoy the beauties of nature.”

The remark may seem obscure. It isn't really.Elliott had always felt that nature was an impediment to the social life, and he had no patience with people who could bother to go to see a lake or a mountain when they had before their eyes a Regency commode or a painting by Watteau.He had at the time a considerable sum of money to spend.Henry Maturin, urged by his son and exasperated by the sight of his friends on the stock exchange who were making fortunes overnight, had surrendered at last to the current of events and, abandoning little by little his old conservatism, had seen no reason why he too should not get on the band wagon.He wrote to Elliott that he was as much opposed to gambling as he had ever been, but this was not gambling, it was an affirmation of his belief in the inexhaustible resources of the country.His optimism was based on common sense.He could see nothing to halt the progress of America.He ended by saying that he had bought on margin a number of sound securities for dear Louisa Bradley and was glad to be able to tell Elliott that she now had a profit of twenty thousand dollars.Finally, if Elliott wanted to make a little money and would allow him to act according to his judgement, he was confident that he would not be disappointed.Elliott, apt to use hackneyed quotations, remarked that he could resist anything but temptation；the consequence of which was that from then on, instead of turning to the social intelligence as he had done for many years when the Herald was brought him with his breakfast, he gave his first attention to the reports of the stock market.So successful were Henry Maturin's transactions on his behalf that now Elliott found himself with the tidy sum of fifty thousand dollars which he had done nothing to earn.

He decided to take his profit and buy a house on the Riviera. As a refuge from the world he chose Antibes, which held a strategic position between Cannes and Monte Carlo so that it could be conveniently reached from either；but whether it was the hand of Providence or his own sure instinct that led him to choose a spot that was soon to become the centre of fashion, it is impossible to say.To live in a villa with a garden had a suburban vulgarity that revolted his fastidious taste, so he acquired two houses in the old town looking on the sea, knocked them into one, and installed central heating, bathrooms, and the sanitary conveniences that American example has forced on a recalcitrant Europe.Pickling was all the rage just then, so he furnished the house with old Provençal furniture duly pickled and, surrendering discreetly to modernity, with modern fabrics.He was still unwilling to accept such painters as Picasso and Braque—“horrors, my dear fellow, horrors”—whom certain misguided enthusiasts were making such a fuss about, but felt himself at long last justified in extending his patronage to the Impressionists and so adorned his walls with some very pretty pictures.I remember a Monet of people rowing on a river, a Pissarro of a quay and a bridge on the Seine, a Tahitian landscape by Gauguin, and a charming Renoir of a young girl in profile with long yellow hair hanging down her back.His house when finished was fresh and gay, unusual, and simple with that simplicity that you knew could only have been achieved at great expense.

Then began the most splendid period of Elliott's life. He brought his excellent chef down from Paris and it was soon acknowledged that he had the best cuisine on the Riviera.He dressed his butler and his footman in white with gold straps on their shoulders.He entertained with a magnificence that never overstepped the bounds of good taste.The shores of the Mediterranean were littered with royalties from all parts of Europe：some lured there on account of theclimate, some in exile, and some because a scandalous past or an unsuitable marriage made it more convenient for them to inhabit a foreign country.There were Romanoffs from Russia, Hapsburgs from Austria, Bourbons from Spain, the two Sicilys, and Parma；there were princes of the House of Windsor and princes of the House of Bragança；there were Royal Highnesses from Sweden and Royal Highnesses from Greece：Elliott entertained them.There were princes and princesses not of royal blood, dukes and duchesses, marquesses and marchionesses, from Austria, Italy, Spain, Russia, and Belgium：Elliott entertained them.In winter the King of Sweden and the King of Denmark made sojourns on the coast；now and then Alfonso of Spain paid a hurried visit：Elliott entertained them.I never ceased to admire the way in which, while he bowed with courtly grace to those exalted personages, he managed to maintain the independent demeanour of the citizen of a country where all men are said to be born equal.

I had then, after some years of travel, bought a house on Cap Ferrat and thus saw a good deal of Elliott. I had risen so high in his good graces that sometimes he invited me to his very grandest parties.

“Come as a favour to me, my dear fellow，”he would say.“Of course I know just as well as you do that royalties ruin a party. But other people like to meet them and I think one owes it to oneself to show the poor things some attention.Though heaven knows they don't deserve it.They're the most ungrateful people in the world；they'll use you, and when they have no further use for you they'll cast you aside like a frayed shirt；they'll accept innumer-able favours from you, but there’s not one of them who’d cross the road to do the smallest thing for you in return.”

Elliott had taken pains to get on good terms with the local authorities, and the prefect of the district and the bishop of the diocese, accompanied by his vicar general, often graced his table. The bishop had been a cavalry officer before entering the Church and in the war had commanded a regiment.He was a rubicund, stoutish man, who affected the rough-and-ready language of the barracks, and his austere, cadaverous vicar general was always on pins and needles lest he should say something scandalous.He listened with a deprecating smile when his superior told his favourite stories.But the bishop conducted his diocese with remarkable competence, and his eloquence in the pulpit was no less moving than his sallies at the luncheon table were amusing.He approved of Elliott for his pious generosity to the Church and liked him for his amiability and the good food he provided；and the two became good friends.Elliott could thus flatter himself that he was making the best of both worlds and, if I may venture so to put it, effecting a very satisfactory working arrangement between God and Mammon.

Elliott was house-proud and he was anxious to show his new house to his sister；he had always felt a certain reserve in her approval of him and he wanted her to see the style in which he now lived and the friends he hobnobbed with. It was the definitive answer to her hesitations.She would have to admit that he had made good.He wrote and asked her to come over with Gray and Isabel, not to stay with him, for he had no room, but to stay as his guests at the near-by Hôtel du Cap.Mrs.Bradley replied that her travelling days were over, for her health was indifferent and she thought she was better off at home；and in any case it was impossible for Gray to absent himself from Chicago；business was booming and he was making a great deal of money and had to stay put.Elliott was attached to his sister and her letter alarmed him.He wrote to Isabel.She replied by cable that, though her mother was so far from well that she had to stay in bed one day a week, she was in no immediate danger and indeed with care might be expected to live a long time yet；but that Gray needed a rest and, with his father there to look after things, there was no reason why he should not take a holiday；so, not that summer but the next, she and Gray would come over.

On October the 23rd，1929，the New York market broke.

5

I was in London then and at first we in England did not realize how grave the situation was nor how distressing its results would be. For my own part, though chagrined at losing a considerable sum, it was for the most part paper profits that I lost, and when the dust had settled I found myself little the poorer in cash.I knew that Elliott had been gambling heavily and feared that he was badly hit, but I did not see him till we both returned to the Riviera for Christmas.He toldme then that Henry Maturin was dead and Gray ruined.

I know little of business matters and I dare say that my account of the events, given me by Elliott, will seem confused. So far as I could make out the catastrophe that had befallen the firm was due in part to Henry Maturin's self-will and in part to Gray's rashness.Henry Maturin at first would not believe that the break was serious, but persuaded himself that it was a plot of the New York brokers to put a quick one over their provincial brethren, and setting his teeth he poured forth money to support the market.He raged against the Chicago brokers who were letting themselves be stampeded by those scoundrels in New York.He had always prided himself on the fact that none of his smaller clients, widows with settled incomes, retired officers and such like, had ever lost a penny by following his advice, and now, instead of letting them take a loss, he supported their accounts out of his own pocket.He said he was prepared to go broke, he could make another fortune, but he could never hold up his head again if the little people who trusted him lost their all.He thought he was magnanimous；he was only vain.His great fortune melted and one night he had a heart attack.He was in his sixties, he had always worked hard, played hard, eaten too much, and drunk heavily；after a few hours of agony he died of coronary thrombosis.

Gray was left to deal with the situation alone. He had been speculating extensively on the side, without the knowledge of his father, and was personally in the greatest difficulty.His efforts to extricate himself failed.The banks would not lend him money；older men on the exchange told him that the only thing was to throw up the sponge.I am not clear about the rest of the story.He was unable to meet his obligations and was, I understand, declared bankrupt；he had already mortgaged his own house and was glad to hand it over to the mortgagees；his father's house on Lake Shore Drive and the house at Marvin were sold for what they would fetch；Isabel sold her jewels：all that was left them was the plantation in South Carolina, which was settled on Isabel and for which a purchaser could not be found.Gray was wiped out.

“And what about you, Elliott?”I asked.

“Oh, I'm not complaining，”he answered airily.“God tempers the wind to the shorn lamb.”

I did not question him further, for his financial affairs were no business of mine, but whatever his losses were I presumed that like the rest of us he had suffered.

The depression did not at first hit the Riviera badly. I heard of two or three people who had lost a good deal, many villas remained closed for the winter and several were put up for sale.The hotels were far from full and the Casino at Monte Carlo complained that the season was poor.But it was not for a couple of years that the draught made itself felt.Then an estate agent told me that on the stretch of coast that reaches from Toulon to the Italian border there were forty-eight thousand properties, large and small, to be sold.The shares of the Casino slumped.The great hotels put down their prices in a vain attempt to attract.The only foreigners to be seen were those who had always been so poor that they couldn't be poorer, and they spent no money because they had no money to spend.The shopkeepers were in despair.But Elliott neither diminished his staff nor lessened their wages as many did；he continued to provide choice food and choice wines to royal and titled persons.He bought himself a large new car, which he imported from America and on which he had to pay a heavy duty.He gave generously to the charity the bishop had organized to provide free meals for the families of the workless.In fact he lived as though there had never been a crisis and half the world were not staggering from its effects.

I discovered the reason by chance：Elliott had by this time ceased to go to England except for a fortnight once a year to buy clothes, but he still transferred his establishment to his apartment in Paris for three months in the autumn and for May and June, these being the periods when the Riviera was deserted by Elliott's friends；he liked the summer there, partly on account of the bathing, but chiefly, I think, because the hot weather gave him the opportunity to indulge in a gaiety of dress that his sense of decorum had always forced him to eschew. He would appear then in trousers of startling colour, red, blue, green, or yellow, and with them wear singlets of contrasting hue, mauve, violet, puce, or harlequin, and would accept the compliments his attire clamoured for with the deprecating grace of an actress who is told that she has played a new role divinely.

I happened to be spending a day in Paris in the spring on my way back to Cap Ferrat and had asked Elliott to lunch with me. We met in the Ritz bar, no longer thronged with college boys come from America to have a good time, but as deserted as a playwright after the first night of an unsuccessful play.We had a cocktail, a transatlantic habit to which Elliott had at last become reconciled, and ordered our lunch.When we had finished, he suggested that we should go round the curio shops, and though I told him I had no money to spend I was glad enough to accompany him.We walked through the Place Vendôme and he asked if I would mind going in to Charvet’s for a moment；he had ordered some things and wanted to know if they were ready.It appeared that he was having some vests made, and some drawers, and he was having his initials embroidered on them.The vests had not come in yet, but the drawers were there and the shop assistant asked Elliott if he would like to see them.

“I would，”said he, and when the man had gone to fetch them added to me；“I have them made to order on a pattern of my own.”

They were brought, and to me, except that they were of silk, looked exactly like the drawers I had frequently bought for myself at Macy's；but what caught my eye was that above the intertwined E. T.of the initials was a count's crown.I did not say a word.

“Very nice, very nice，”said Elliott.“Well, when the undershirts are ready you'll send them along.”

We left the shop and Elliott, as he walked away, turned to me with a smile.

“Did you notice the crown?To tell you the truth, I'd forgotten about it when I asked you to come in to Charvet's. I don't think I've had occasion to tell you that His Holiness has been graciously pleased to revive in my favour my old family title.”

“Your what?”I said, startled out of my politeness.

Elliott raised a disapproving eyebrow.

“Didn't you know?I am descended in the female line from the Count de Lauria who came over to England in the suite of Philip the Second and married a maid of honour of Queen Mary's.”

“Our old friend Bloody Mary?”

“That, I believe, is what heretics call her，”Elliott answered stiffly.“I don't think I ever told you that I spent September of'twenty-nine in Rome. I thought it a bore having to go because Rome is empty then, but it was fortunate for me that my sense of duty prevailed over my desire for worldly pleasures.My friends at the Vatican told me that the crash was coming and strongly advised me to sell all my American securities.The Catholic Church has the wisdom of twenty centuries behind it and I didn't hesitate for a moment.I cabled to Henry Maturin to sell everything and buy gold, and I cabled to Louisa to tell her to do the same.Henry cabled back asking me if I was crazy and said he'd do nothing until I confirmed the instructions.I immediately cabled in the most peremptory manner, telling him to carry them out and to cable me that he had done so.Poor Louisa paid no attention to my advice and suffered for it.”

“So when the crash came you were sitting pretty?”

“An Americanism, my dear fellow, which I see no occasion for you to use, but it expresses my situation with a good deal of accuracy. I lost nothing；in fact I had made what you would probably call a packet.I was able some time later to buy back my securities for a fraction of their original cost, and since I owed it all to what I can only describe as the direct interposition of Providence I felt it only right and proper that I should do something for Providence in return.”

“Oh, and how did you set about that?”

“Well, you know the Duce has been reclaiming great tracts of land in the Pontine Marshes and it was represented to me that His Holiness was gravely concerned at the lack of places of worship for the settlers. So, to cut a long story short, I built a little Romanesque church, an exact copy of one I knew in Provence, and perfect in every detail, which, though I say it myself, is a gem.It is dedicated to St.Martin because I was lucky enough to find an old stained-glass window representing St.Martin in the act of cutting his cloak in two to give half of it to a naked beggar, and as the symbolism seemed so apt I bought it and placed it over the high altar.”

I didn't interrupt Elliott to ask him what connexion he saw between the Saint's celebrated action and the rake-offon the pretty penny he had made by selling out in the nick of time which, like an agent's commission, he was paying to a higher power. But to a prosaic person like me symbolism is often obscure.He went on.

“When I was privileged to show the photographs to the Holy Father, he was gracious enough to tell me that he could see at a glance that I was a man of impeccable taste, and he added that it was a pleasure to him to find in this degenerate age someone who combined devotion to the Church with such rare artistic gifts. A memorable experience, my dear fellow, a memorable experience.But no one was more surprised than I when shortly afterwards it was intimated to me that he had been pleased to confer a title upon me.As an American citizen I feel it more modest not to use it, except of course at the Vatican, so I have forbidden my Joseph to address me as Monsieur le Comte, and I trust you will respect my confidence.I don't wish it bruited abroad.But I would not like His Holiness to think that I do not value the honour that he has done me and it is purely out of respect for him that I have the crown embroidered on my personal linen.I don't mind telling you that I take a modest pride in concealing my rank under the sober pin-stripe of an American gentleman.”

We parted. Elliott told me he would come down to the Riviera at the end of June.He did not do so.He had just made his arrangements to transfer his staff from Paris, intending to drive down leisurely in his car so that every-thing should be in perfect order on his arrival, when he received a cable from Isabel to say that her mother had suddenly taken a turn for the worse.Elliott, besides being fond of his sister, had, as I have said, a strong strain of family feeling.He took the first ship out of Cherbourg and from New York went to Chicago.He wrote to tell me that Mrs.Bradley was very ill and grown so thin that it was a shock to him.She might last a few weeks longer or even a few months, but in any case he felt it his sad duty to remain with her till the end.He said he found the great heat more supportable than he had expected, but the lack of congenial society only tolerable because at such a moment he had in any case no heart for it.He said he was disappointed with the way his fellow-countrymen had reacted to the depression；he would have expected them to take their misfortune with more equanimity.Knowing that nothing is easier than to bear other people's calamities with fortitude, I thought that Elliott, richer now than he had ever been in his life, was perhaps hardly entitled to be severe.He ended by giving me messages for several of his friends and bade me by no means forget to explain to everyone I met why it was that his house must remain closed for the summer.

Little more than a month later I received another letter from him to tell me that Mrs. Bradley had died.He wrote with sincerity and emotion.I should never have thought him capable of expressing himself with such dignity, real feeling, and simplicity, had I not long known that notwithstanding his snobbishness and his absurd affectations Elliott was a kindly, affectionate, and honest man.In the course of this letter he told me that Mrs.Bradley's affairs appeared to be in some disorder.Her elder son, a diplomatist, being chargé d’affaires in Tokyo during the absence of the ambassador, had been of course unable to leave his post.Her second son, Templeton, who had been in the Philippines when I first knew the Bradleys, had been in due course recalled to Washington and occupied a responsible position in the State Department.He had come with his wife to Chicago when his mother’s condition was recognized as hopeless, but had been obliged to return to the capital immediately after the funeral.In these circumstances Elliott felt that he must remain in America until things were straightened out.Mrs.Bradley had divided her fortune equally between her three children, but it appeared that her losses in the crash of’twenty-nine had been substantial.Fortunately they had found a purchaser for the farm at Marvin.Elliott in his letter referred to it as dear Louisa’s country place.

“It is always sad when a family has to part with its ancestral home，”he wrote，“but of late years I have seen this forced upon so many of my English friends that I feel that my nephews and Isabel must accept the inevitable with the same courage and resignation that they have. Noblesse oblige.”

They had been lucky too in disposing of Mrs. Bradley's house in Chicago.There had long been a scheme afoot to tear down the row of houses in one of which Mrs.Bradley lived and build in their stead a great block of apartments, but it had been held up by her obstinate determination to die in the house in which she had lived.But no sooner was the breath out of her body than the promoters came forward with an offer and it was promptly accepted.Yet even at that Isabel was left very ill provided for.

After the crash Gray had tried to get a job, even as a clerk in the office of such of the brokers as had weathered the storm, but there was no business. He applied to his old friends to give him something to do, however humble and however badly paid, but he applied in vain.His frenzied efforts to stave off the disaster that finally overwhelmed him, the burden of anxiety, the humiliation, resulted in a nervous breakdown, and he began to have headaches so severe that he was incapacitated for twenty-four hours and as limp as a wet rag when they ceased.It had appeared to Isabel that they could not do better than go down with the children to the plantation in South Carolina till Gray regained his health.In its day it had brought in a hundred thousand dollars a year for its rice crop, but for long now had been no more than a wilderness of marsh and gumwood, useful only to sportsmen who wanted to shoot duck, and no purchaser could be found for it.There they had lived off and on since the crash and there they proposed to return till conditions improved and Gray could find employment.

“I couldn't allow that，”Elliott wrote.“Why, my dear fellow, they live like pigs. Isabel without a maid, no governess for the children, and only a couple of coloured women to look after them.So I've offered them my apart-ment in Paris and proposed that they should stay there till things change in this fantastic country.I shall provide them with a staff, as a matter of fact my kitchen-maid is a very good cook, so I shall leave her with them and I can easily find someone to take her place.I shall arrange to settle the accounts myself so that Isabel can spend her small income on her clothes and the menus plaisirs of the family.This means of course that I shall spend much more of my time on the Riviera and so hope to see a great deal more of you, my dear fellow, than I have in the past.London and Paris being now what they are, I'm really more at home on the Riviera.It's the only place remaining where I can meet people who speak my own language.I dare say I shall go to Paris now and then for a few days, but when I do, I don't in the least mind pigging it at the Ritz.I’m glad to say that I’ve at long last persuaded Gray and Isabel to accede to my wishes and I’m bringing them all over as soon as the necessary arrangements can be made.The furniture and the pictures（very poor in quality, my dear fellow, and of the most doubtful authenticity）are being sold the week after next and meanwhile, as I thought to live in the house till the last moment would be painful to them, I have brought them to stay with me at the Drake.I shall settle them in when we get to Paris and then come down to the Riviera.Don’t forget to remember me to your royal neighbour.”

Who could deny that Elliott, that arch-snob, was also the kindest, most considerate and generous of men?

CHAPTER FIVE

1

I dawdled over my work in Paris. It was very agreeable in the springtime, with the chestnuts in the Champs Elysées in bloom and the light in the streets so gay.There was pleasure in the air, a light transitory pleasure, sensual without grossness, that made your step more springy and your intelligence more alert.I was happy in the various company of my friends and, my heart filled with amiable memories of the past, I regained in spirit at least some-thing of the glow of youth.I thought I should be a fool to allow work to interfere with a delight in the passing moment that I might never enjoy again so fully.

Isabel, Gray, Larry, and I went for excursions to places of interest within convenient distance. We went to Chantilly and Versailles, to St.Germain and Fontainebleau.Wherever we went, we lunched well and copiously.Gray ate largely to satisfy his enormous frame and was apt to drink a little too much.His health, whether owing to Larry's treatment or merely to the course of time, was certainly improved.He ceased to have racking headaches and his eyes were losing the look of bewilderment that when first I saw him on coming to Paris had been so distressing.He did not talk much except now and then to tell a long-winded story, but laughed with great loud guffaws at the nonsense Isabel and I talked.He enjoyed himself.Though not amusing, he was so good-humoured and so easily pleased that it was impossible not to like him.He was the kind of man with whom one would have hesitated to pass a lonely evening, but with whom one might cheerfully have looked forward to spending six months.

His love for Isabel was a delight to see；he adored her beauty and thought her the most brilliant, fascinating creature in the world；and his devotion, his doglike devotion to Larry was touching. Larry appeared to enjoy himself too；I had a notion that he looked upon this time as a holiday that he was taking from whatever projects he had in mind and was serenely making the most of it.He didn't talk very much either, but it didn't matter, his company was sufficient conversation；he was so easy, so pleasantly cheerful that you didn't ask more of him than what he gave, and I well knew that if the days we spent together were so happy it was due to his being with us.Though he never said a brilliant or a witty thing, we should have been dull without him.

It was on the return from one of these jaunts that I witnessed a scene that somewhat startled me. We had been to Chartres and were on our way back to Paris.Gray was driving and Larry was sitting beside him；Isabel and I were at the back.We were tired after the long day.Larry sat with his arm stretched out along the top of the front seat.His shirt-cuff was pulled back by his position and displayed his slim, strong wrist and the lower part of his brown arm lightly covered with fine hairs.The sun shone goldenly upon them.Something in Isabel's immobility attracted my attention, and I glanced at her.She was so still you might have thought her hypnotized.Her breath was hurried.Her eyes were fixed on the sinewy wrist with its little golden hairs and on that long, delicate, but powerful hand, and I have never seen on a human countenance such a hungry concupiscence as I saw then on hers.It was a mask of lust.I should never have believed that her beautiful features could assume an expression of such unbridled sensuality.It was animal rather than human.The beauty was stripped from her face；the look upon it made her hideous and frightening.It horribly suggested the bitch in heat and I felt rather sick.She was unconscious of my presence；she was conscious of nothing but the hand, lying along the rim so negligently, that filled her with frantic desire.Then as it were a spasm twitched across her face, she gave a shudder and shutting her eyes sank into the corner of the car.

“Give me a cigarette，”she said in a voice I hardly recognized, it was so raucous.

I got one out of my case and lit it for her. She smoked it greedily.For the rest of the drive she looked out of the window and never said a word.

When we arrived at their house Gray asked Larry to drive me back to my hotel and then take the car to the garage. Larry got into the driver's seat and I sat myself beside him.As they crossed the pavement Isabel took Gray's arm and, snuggling up to him, gave him a look which I could not see, but whose sense I could divine.I guessed that he would have a passionate bedfellow that night, but would never know to what prickings of conscience he owed her ardour.

June was approaching its end and I had to get back to the Riviera. Friends of Elliott's, who were going to America, had lent the Maturins their villa at Dinard and they were going there with the children as soon as their school closed.Larry was staying in Paris to work, but was buying himself a secondhand Citroën and had promised to spend a few days with them in August.On my last night in Paris I asked the three of them to dine with me.

It was on that night that we met Sophie Macdonald.

2

Isabel had conceived the desire to make a tour of the tough joints, and because I had some acquaintance with them she asked me to be their guide. I did not much like the notion, because in places of that sort in Paris they are apt to make their disapproval of sightseers from another world unpleasantly obvious.But Isabel insisted.I warned her that it would be very boring and begged her to dress plainly.We dined late, went to the Folies-Bergère for an hour, and then set out.I took them first to a cellar near Notre Dame frequented by gangsters and their molls where I knew the proprietor, and he made room for us at a long table at which were sitting some very disreputable people, but I ordered wine for all of them and we drank one another’s healths.It was hot, smoky, and dirty.Then I took them to the Sphynx where women, naked under their smart, tawdry evening dresses, their breasts, nipples and all, exposed, sit in a row on two benches opposite one another and when the band strikes up dance together listlessly with their eyes on the lookout for the men who sit round the dance hall at marble-topped tables.We ordered a bottle of warm champagne.Some of the women gave Isabel the eye as they passed us and I wondered if she knew what it meant.

Then we went on to the Rue de Lappe. It is a dingy, narrow street, and even as you enter it you get the impression of sordid lust.We went into a café.There was the usual young man, pale and dissipated, playing the piano, while another man, old and tired, scraped away on a fiddle, and a third made discordant noises on a saxophone.The place was packed and it looked as though there wasn’t a vacant table, but the patron, seeing that we were customers with money to spend, unceremoniously turned a couple out, making them take seats at a table already occupied, and settled us down.The two persons who were hustled away did not take it well, and they made remarks about us that were far from complimentary.A lot of people were dancing, sailors with the red pompon on their hats, men mostly with their caps on and handkerchiefs round their necks, women of mature age, and young girls, painted to the eyes, bareheaded, in short skirts and coloured blouses.Men danced with podgy boys with made-up eyes；gaunt, hard-featured women danced with fat women with dyed hair；men danced with women.There was a frowst of smoke and liquor and of sweating bodies.The music went on interminably and that unsavoury mob proceeded round the room, the sweat shining on their faces, with a solemn intensity in which there was something horrible.There were a few big men of brutal aspect, but for the most part they were puny and ill-nourished.I watched the three who were playing.They might have been robots, so mechanical was their performance, and I asked myself if it was possible that at one time, when they were setting out, they had thought they might be musicians whom people would come from far to hear and to applaud.Even to play the violin badly you must take lessons and practise：did that fiddler go to all that trouble just to play fox-trots till the small hours of the morning in that stinking squalor?The music stopped and the pianist wiped his face with a dirty handkerchief.The dancers slouched or sidled or squirmed back to their tables.Suddenly we heard an American voice：

“For Christ's sake.”

A woman got up from one of the tables across the room. The man she was with tried to stop her, but she pushed him aside and staggered across the floor.She was very drunk.She came up to our table and stood in front of us, swaying a little and grinning stupidly.She seemed to find the sight of us vastly amusing.I glanced at my companions.Isabel was staring at her blankly, Gray had a sullen frown on his face, and Larry gazed as though he couldn't believe hiseyes.

“Hello，”she said.

“Sophie，”said Isabel.

“Who the hell did you think it was?”she gurgled. She grabbed the waiter who was passing.“Vincent, fetch me a chair.”

“Fetch one yourself，”he said, snatching himself away.

“Salaud，”she cried, spitting at him.

“T'en fais pas, Sophie，”said a big fat fellow with a great head of greasy hair, who was sitting next to us in his shirt-sleeves.“Here's a chair.”

“Fancy meeting you all like this，”she said, still swaying.“Hello, Larry. Hello, Gray.”She sank into the chair which the man who had spoken placed behind her.“Let's all have a drink.Patron，”she screamed.

I had noticed that the proprietor had his eye on us and now he came up.

“You know these people, Sophie?”he asked, addressing her in the familiar second person singular.

“Ta gueule，”she laughed drunkenly.“They're my childhood friends. I'm buying a bottle of champagne for them.And don't you bring us any urine de cheval.Bring us something one can swallow without vomiting.”

“You're drunk, my poor Sophie，”he said.

“To hell with you.”

He went off, glad enough to sell a bottle of champagne-we for safety's sake had been drinking brandy and soda-and Sophie stared at me dully for a moment.

“Who's your friend, Isabel?”

Isabel told her my name.

“Oh?I remember, you came to Chicago once. Bit of a stuffed shirt, aren't you?”

“Maybe，”I smiled.

I had no recollection of her, but that was not surprising, since I had not been to Chicago for more than ten years and had met a great many people then and a great many since.

She was quite tall and, when standing, looked taller still, for she was very thin. She wore a bright green silk blouse, but it was crumpled and spotted, and a short black skirt.Her hair, cut short and loosely curled, but tousled, was brightly hennaed.She was outrageously made up, her cheeks rouged to the eyes, and her eyelids, upper and lower, heavily blued；her eyebrows and eyelashes were thick with mascara and her mouth scarlet with lipstick.Her hands, with their painted nails, were dirty.She looked more of a slut than any woman there and I had a suspicion that she was not only drunk but doped.But one couldn't deny that there was a certain vicious attractiveness about her；she held her head with an arrogant tilt and her make-up accentuated the startling greenness of her eyes.Sodden with drink as she was, she had a bold-faced shamelessness that I could well imagine appealed to all that was base in men.She embraced us in a sardonic smile.

“I can't say you seem so terribly pleased to see me，”she said.

“I heard you were in Paris，”said Isabel lamely, a chilly smile on her face.

“You might have called me. I'm in the phone-book.”

“We haven't been here very long.”

Gray came to the rescue.

“Are you having a good time over here, Sophie?”

“Fine. You went bust, Gray, didn't you?”

His face flushed a deeper red.

“Yes.”

“Tough on you. I guess it's pretty grim in Chicago right now.Lucky for me I got out when I did.For Christ's sake why doesn't that bastard bring us something to drink?”

“He's just coming，”I said, seeing the waiter threading his way through the tables with glasses and wine on a tray.

My remark drew her attention to me.

“My loving in-laws kicked me out of Chicago. Said I was gumming up their f-reputations.”She giggled savagely.“I'm a remittance man.”

The champagne came and was poured out. With a shaking hand she raised a glass to her lips.

“To hell with stuffed shirts，”she said. She emptied the glass and glanced at Larry.“You don't seem to have much to say for yourself, Larry.”

He had been looking at her with an impassive face. He had not taken his eyes off her since she had appeared.He smiled amiably.

“I'm not a very talkative guy.”

The music struck up again and a man came over to us. He was a tallish fellow and well built, with a great hooked nose, a mat of shining black hair, and great sensual lips.He looked like an evil Savonarola.Like most of the men there he wore no collar and his tight-fitting coat was closely buttoned to give him a waist.

“Come on, Sophie. We're going to dance.”

“Go away. I'm busy.Can't you see I'm with friends?”

“J'm'en fous de tes amis. To hell with your friends.You're dancing.”

He took hold of her arm but she snatched it away.

“Fous-moi la paix, espèce de con，”she cried, with sudden violence.

“Merde.”

“Mange.”

Gray did not understand what they were saying, but I saw that Isabel, with that strange knowledge of obscenity that the most virtuous woman seems to possess, understood perfectly, and her face went hard with a frown of disgust. The man raised his arm with his hand open, the horny hand of a workman, and was about to slap her, when Gray half raised himself from his chair.

“Allaiz vous ong，”he shouted, with his execrable accent.

The man stopped and threw Gray a furious glance.

“Take care, Coco，”said Sophie, with a bitter laugh.“He'll lay you out cold.”

The man took in Gray's great height and weight and strength. He shrugged his shoulders sullenly and, throwing a filthy word at us, slunk off.Sophie giggled drunkenly.The rest of us were silent.I refilled her glass.

“You living in Paris, Larry?”she asked after she had drained it.

“For the present.”

It's always difficult to make conversation with a drunk, and there's no denying it, the sober are at a disadvantage with him. We went on talking for a few minutes in a dreary, embarrassed way.Then Sophie pushed back her chair.

“If I don't go back to my boy friend he'll be as mad as hell. He's a sulky brute, but Christ, he's a good screw.”She staggered to her feet.“So long, folks.Come again.I'm here every night.”

She pushed her way through the dancers and we lost sight of her in the crowd. I almost laughed at the icy scorn on Isabel's classic features.None of us said a word.

“This is a foul place，”said Isabel suddenly.“Let's go.”

I paid for our drinks and for Sophie's champagne and we trooped out. The crowd was on the dance floor and we got out without remark.It was after two, and to my mind time to go to bed, but Gray said he was hungry, so I suggested that we should go to Graf's in Montmartre and get something to eat.We were silent as we drove up.I sat beside Gray to direct him.We reached the garish restaurant.There were still people sitting on the terrace.We went in and ordered bacon and eggs and beer.Isabel, outwardly at least, had regained her composure.She congratulated me, somewhat ironically perhaps, on my acquaintance with the more disreputable parts of Paris.

“You asked for it，”I said.

“I've thoroughly enjoyed myself. I've had a grand evening.”

“Hell，”said Gray.“It stank. And Sophie.”

Isabel shrugged an indifferent shoulder.

“D'you remember her at all?”she asked me.“She sat next to you the first night you came to dinner with us. She hadn't got that awful red hair then.Its natural colour is dingy beige.”

I threw my mind back. I had a recollection of a very young girl with blue eyes that were almost green and an attractive tilt to her head.Not pretty, but fresh and ingenuous with a mixture of shyness and pertness that I found amusing.

“Of course I remember. I liked her name.I had an aunt called Sophie.”

“She married a boy called Bob Macdonald.”

“Nice fellow，”said Gray.

“He was one of the best-looking boys I ever saw. I never understood what he saw in her.She married just after I did.Her parents were divorced and her mother married a Standard Oil man in China.She lived with her father's people at Marvin and we used to see a lot of her then, but after she married she dropped out of our crowd somehow.Bob Macdonald was a lawyer, but he wasn't making much money, and they had a walk-up apartment on the North Side.But it wasn't that.They didn't want to see anybody.I never saw two people so crazy about one another.Even after they'd been married two or three years and had a baby they’d go to the pictures and he’d sit with his arm round her waist and she with her head on his shoulder just like lovers.They were quite a joke in Chicago.”

Larry listened to what Isabel said, but made no comment. His face was inscrutable.

“What happened then?”I asked.

“One night they were driving back to Chicago in a little open car of theirs, and they had the baby with them. They always had to take the baby along because they hadn't any help.Sophie did everything herself, and, any-way, they worshipped it.And a bunch of drunks in a great sedan driving at eighty miles an hour crashed into them head on.Bob and the baby were killed outright, but Sophie only had concussion and a rib or two broken.They kept it from her as long as they could that Bob and the baby were dead, but at last they had to tell her.They say it was awful.She nearly went crazy.She shrieked the place down.They had to watch her night and day and once she nearly succeeded in jumping out of the window.Of course we did all we could, but she seemed to hate us.After she came out of the hospital they put her in a sanatorium and she was there for months.'

“Poor thing.”

“When they let her go she started to drink, and when she was drunk she'd go to bed with anyone who asked her. It was terrible for her in-laws.They're very nice quiet people and they hated the scandal.At first we all tried to help her, but it was impossible；if you asked her to dine she'd arrive plastered and she was quite likely to pass out before the evening was over.Then she got in with a rotten crowd and we had to drop her.She was arrested once for driving a car when she was drunk.She was with a dago she'd picked up in a speak-easy and it turned out that he was wanted by the cops.”

“But had she money?”I asked.

“There was Bob's insurance；the people who owned the car that smashed into them were insured and she got something from them. But it didn't last long.She spent it like a drunken sailor and in two years she was broke.Her grandmother wouldn't have her back at Marvin.Then her in-laws said they'd make her an allowance if she'd go and live abroad.I suppose that’s what she’s living on now.”

“The wheel comes full circle，”I remarked.“There was a time when the black sheep of the family was sent from my country to America；now apparently he's sent from your country to Europe.”

“I can't help feeling sorry for her，”said Gray.

“Can't you?”said Isabel coolly.“I can. Of course it was a shock and no one could have sympathized with Sophie more than I did.We'd known one another always.But a normal person recovers from a thing like that.If she went topieces it's because there was a rotten streak in her.She was naturally unbalanced；even her love for Bob was exaggerated.If she'd had character she'd have been able to make something of life.”

“If pots and pans……Aren't you very hard, Isabel?”I murmured.

“I don't think so. I have common sense and I see no reason to be sentimental about Sophie.God knows, no one could be more devoted to Gray and the babes than I am, and if they were killed in a motor accident I should go out of my mind, but sooner or later I'd pull myself together.Isn't that what you'd wish me to do, Gray, or would you prefer me to get blind every night and go to bed with every apache in Paris?”

Gray then came as near to making a humorous remark as I ever heard him.

“Of course I'd prefer you to hurl yourself on my funeral pyre in a new Molyneux dress, but as that's not done any more, I guess the best thing you could do would be to take the bridge. And I'd like you to remember not to go an original no-trump on less than three and a half to four quick tricks.”

It was not the occasion for me to point out to Isabel that her love for her husband and her children, though sincere enough, was scarcely passionate. Perhaps she read the thought that was passing through my mind, for she addressed me somewhat truculently.

“What have you got to say?”

“I'm like Gray, I'm sorry for the girl.”

“She's not a girl. She's thirty.”

“I suppose it was the end of the world for her when her husband and her baby were killed. I suppose she didn't care what became of her and flung herself into the horrible degradation of drink and promiscuous copulation to get even with life that had treated her so cruelly.She'd lived in heaven and when she lost it she couldn't put up with the common earth of common men, but in despair plunged headlong into hell.I can imagine that if she couldn't drink the nectar of the gods any more she thought she might as well drink bathroom gin.”

“That's the sort of thing you say in novels. It's nonsense and you know it's nonsense.Sophie wallows in the gutter because she likes it.Other women have lost their husbands and children.It wasn't that that made her evil.Evil doesn't spring from good.The evil was there always.When that motor accident broke her defences it set her free to be herself.Don’t waste your pity on her；she’s now what at heart she always was.”

All this time Larry had remained silent. He seemed to be in a brown study and I thought he hardly heard what we were saying.Isabel's words were followed by a brief silence.He began to speak, but in a strange, toneless voice, as though not to us, but to himself；his eyes seemed to look into the dim distance of past time.

“I remember her when she was fourteen with her long hair brushed back off her forehead and a black bow at the back, with her freckled, serious face. She was a modest, high-minded, idealistic child.She read everything she could get hold of and we used to talk about books.”

“When?”asked Isabel, with a slight frown.

“Oh, when you were out being social with your mother. I used to go up to her grandfather's and we'd sit under a great elm they had there and read to one another.She loved poetry and wrote quite a lot herself.”

“Plenty of girls do that at that age. It's pretty poor stuff.”

“Of course it's a long time ago and I dare say I wasn't a very good judge.”

“You couldn't have been more than sixteen yourself.”

“Of course it was imitative. There was a lot of Robert Frost in it.But I have a notion it was rather remarkable for so young a girl.She had a delicate ear and a sense of rhythm.She had a feeling for the sounds and scents of the country, the first softness of spring in the air and the smell of the parched earth after rain.”

“I never knew she wrote poetry，”said Isabel.

“She kept it a secret, she was afraid you'd all laugh at her. She was very shy.”

“She's not that now.”

“When I came back from the war she was almost grown-up. She'd read a lot about the condition of the workingclasses and she'd seen something of it for herself in Chicago.She'd got on to Carl Sandburg and was writing savagely in free verse about the misery of the poor and the exploitation of the working classes.I dare say it was rather commonplace, but it was sincere and it had pity in it and aspiration.At that time she wanted to become a social worker.It was moving, her desire for sacrifice.I think she was capable of a great deal.She wasn't silly or mawkish, but she gave one the impression of a lovely purity and a strange loftiness of soul.We saw a lot of one another that year.”

I could see that Isabel listened to him with growing exasperation. Larry had no notion that he was driving a dagger in her heart and with his every detached word twisting it in the wound.But when she spoke it was with a smile on her lips.

“How did she come to choose you for her confidant?”

Larry looked at her with his trustful eyes.

“I don't know. She was a poor girl among all of you who had plenty of dough, and I didn't belong.I was there just because Uncle Bob practised at Marvin.I suppose she felt that gave us something in common.”

Larry had no relations. Most of us have at least cousins whom we may hardly know, but who at least give us a sense that we are part of the human family.Larry's father had been an only son, his mother an only daughter；his grandfather on one side, the Quaker, had been lost at sea when a young man and his grandfather on the other side had neither brother nor sister.No one could be more alone in the world than Larry.

“Did it ever occur to you that Sophie was in love with you?”asked Isabel.

“Never，”he smiled.

“Well, she was.”

“When he came back from the war as a wounded hero, half the girls in Chicago had a crush on Larry，”said Gray in his bluff way.

“This was more than a crush. She worshipped you, my poor Larry.D'you mean to say you didn't know it?”

“I certainly didn't and I don't believe it.”

“I suppose you thought she was too high-minded.”

“I can still see that skinny little girl with the bow in her hair and her serious face whose voice trembled with tears when she read that ode of Keats's because it was so beautiful. I wonder where she is now.”

Isabel gave a very slight start and threw him a suspicious inquiring glance.

“It's getting frightfully late and I'm so tired I don't know what to do. Let's go.”

3

On the following evening I took the Blue Train to the Riviera and two or three days later went over to Antibes to see Elliott and give him news of Paris. He looked far from well.The cure at Montecatini had not done him the good he expected, and his subsequent wanderings had exhausted him.He found a baptismal font in Venice and then went on to Florence to buy the triptych he had been negotiating for.Anxious to see these objects duly placed, he went down to the Pontine Marshes and put up at a miserable inn where the heat had been hard to bear.His precious purchases were a long time on the way, but determined not to leave till he had accomplished his purpose, he stayed on.He was delighted with the effect when at last everything was in order, and he showed me with pride the photographs he had taken.The church, though small, had dignity, and the restrained richness of the interior was proof of Elliott's good taste.

“I saw an early Christian sarcophagus in Rome that took my fancy and I deliberated a long time about buying it, but in the end I thought better of it.”

“What on earth did you want with an early Christian sarcophagus, Elliott?”

“To put myself in it, my dear fellow. It was of a very good design, and I thought it would balance the font on the other side of the entrance, but those early Christians were stumpy little fellows and I shouldn't have fitted in.I wasn't going to lie there till the Last Trump with my knees doubled up to my chin like a foetus.Most uncomfortable.”

I laughed, but Elliott was serious.

“I had a better idea. I've made all arrangements, with some difficulty, but that was to be expected, to be buried in front of the altar at the foot of the chancel steps, so that when the poor peasants of the Pontine Marshes come up to take the Sacrament they'll clump over my bones with their heavy shoes.Rather chic, don't you think?Just a plain stone slab with my name on it and a couple of dates.Si monumentum quaeris, circumspice.If you seek his monument, look around, you know.”

“I do know enough Latin to understand a hackneyed quotation, Elliott，”I said tartly.

“I beg your pardon, my dear fellow. I'm so accustomed to the crass ignorance of the upper classes, I forgot for the moment that I was talking to an author.”

He scored.

“But what I wanted to say to you was this，”he continued.“I've left proper instructions in my will, but I want you to see they're carried out. I will not be buried on the Riviera among a lot of retired colonels and middle-class French people.”

“Of course I'll do what you wish, Elliott, but I don't think we need plan for anything like that for many years to come.”

“I'm getting on, you know, and to tell you the truth I shan't be sorry to go. What are those lines of Landor's?‘I've warmed both hands……'”

Though I have a bad verbal memory, the poem is very short and I was able to repeat it.

“I strove with none, for none was worth my strife.

Nature I loved, and, next to Nature, Art；

I warmed both hands before the fire of Life；

It sinks and I am ready to depart.”

“That's it，”he said.

I could not but reflect that it was only by a violent stretch of the imagination that Elliott could fit the epigram to himself.

“It expresses my sentiments exactly，”he said, however.“The only thing I could add to it is that I've always moved in the best society in Europe.”

“It would be difficult to squeeze that into a quatrain.”

“Society is dead. At one time I had hopes that America would take the place of Europe and create an aristocracy that the hoi polloi would respect, but the depression has destroyed any chance of that.My poor country is becoming hopelessly middle-class.You wouldn't believe it, my dear fellow, but last time I was in America a taxi driver addressed me as brother.”

But though the Riviera, still shaken by the crash of'twenty-nine, was not what it had been, Elliott continued to give parties and go to parties. He had never frequented Jews, making an exception only for the family of Rothschild, but the grandest parties were being given now by members of the chosen race, and when there was a party Elliott could not bear not to go to it.He wandered through these gatherings, graciously shaking the hand of one or kissing that of another, but with a kind of forlorn detachment like an exiled royalty who felt a trifle embarrassed to find himself in such company.The exiled royalties, however, had the time of their lives, and to meet a film star seemed the height of their ambitions.Nor had Elliott ever looked with approval on the modern practice of treating members of the theatrical profession as persons whom you met socially；but a retired actress had built herself a sumptuous residence in his immediate neighbourhood and kept open house.Cabinet ministers, dukes, great ladies stayed with her for weeks on end.Elliott became a constant visitor.

“Of course it's a very mixed crowd，”he told me，“but one doesn't have to talk to people one doesn't want to. She'sa compatriot of mine and I feel I ought to help her out.It must be a relief to her house guests to find someone who can talk their own language.”

Sometimes he was obviously so far from well that I asked him why he didn't take things more easily.

“My dear fellow, at my age one can't afford to fall out. You don't think I've moved in the highest circles for nearly fifty years without realizing that if you're not seen everywhere you're forgotten.”

I wondered if he realized what a lamentable confession he was then making. I had not the heart to laugh at Elliott any more；he seemed to me a profoundly pathetic object.Society was what he lived for, a party was the breath of his nostrils, not to be asked to one was an affront, to be alone was a mortification；and, an old man now, he was desperately afraid.

So the summer passed. Elliott spent it scurrying from one end of the Riviera to the other, lunching in Cannes, dining in Monte Carlo, and exercising all his ingenuity to fit in a tea party here and a cocktail party there；and however tired he felt, taking pains to be affable, chatty, and amusing.He was full of gossip and you could trust him to know the details of the latest scandal before anyone but the parties immediately concerned.He would have stared at you with frank amazement had you suggested to him that his existence was futile.He would have thought you distressingly plebeian.

4

The autumn came and Elliott decided to go to Paris for a while, partly to see how Isabel, Gray, and the children were getting on, and partly to make what he called acte de présence in the capital.Then he meant to go to London to order some new clothes and incidentally to look up some old friends.My own plan was to go straight to London, but he asked me to drive up with him to Paris, and since that is an agreeable thing to do I consented and, having done so, saw no reason why I should not spend at least a few days in Paris myself.We made the journey by easy stages, stopping at places where the food was good；Elliott had something the matter with his kidneys and drank nothing but Vichy, but always insisted on choosing my half-bottle of wine for me and, too good-natured to grudge me a pleasure he could not share, got a genuine satisfaction out of my enjoyment of a fine vintage.He was so generous that I had difficulty in persuading him to let me pay my share of the expenses.Though I grew a little tired of his stories of the great whom he had known in the past I liked the trip.Much of the country we drove through, just touched with the beginning of its autumn beauty, was very lovely.Having lunched at Fontainebleau, we did not arrive in Paris till afternoon.Elliott dropped me at my modest, old-fashioned hotel and went round the corner to the Ritz.

We had warned Isabel of our arriving, so I was not surprised to find a note from her awaiting me, but I was surprised at its contents：

Come round the moment you get in. Something terrible has happened.Don't bring Uncle Elliott.For God's sake come as soon as you can.

I am not less curious than anyone else, but I had to have a wash and put on a clean shirt；then I took a taxi and went round to the apartment in the Rue St. Guillaume.I was shown into the drawing-room.Isabel sprang to her feet.

“Where have you been all this time?I've been waiting for hours.”

It was five o'clock and, before I could answer, the butler brought in the tea-things. Isabel, her hands clenched, watched him with impatience.I couldn't imagine what was the matter.

“I've only just arrived. We dawdled over lunch at Fontainebleau.”

“God, how slow he is. Maddening！”said Isabel.

The man placed the salver with the teapot and the sugar basin and the cups on the table and with what really was exasperating deliberation arranged around it plates of bread and butter, cakes, and cookies. He went out and closed thedoor behind him.

“Larry's going to marry Sophie Macdonald.”

“Who's she?”

“Don't be so stupid，”cried Isabel, her eyes flashing with anger.“That drunken slut we met at that filthy café you took us to.God knows why you took us to a place like that.Gray was disgusted.”

“Oh, you mean your Chicago friend?”I said, ignoring her unjust reproach.“How d'you know?”

“How should I know?He came and told me himself yesterday afternoon. I've been frantic ever since.”

“Supposing you sat down, gave me a cup of tea, and told me all about it.”

“Help yourself.”

She sat behind the tea-table and watched me irritably while I poured myself out a cup. I made myself comfortable on a small sofa by the fireplace.

“We haven't seen so much of him lately, since we came back from Dinard, I mean；he came up there for a few days, but wouldn't stay with us, he stayed at a hotel. He used to come down to the beach and play with the children.They're crazy about him.We played golf at St.Briac.Gray asked him one day if he'd seen Sophie again.

“‘Yes, I've seen her several times，'he said.

“‘Why?'I asked.

“‘She's an old friend，'he said.

“‘If I were you I wouldn't waste my time on her，'I said.

“Then he smiled. You know how he smiles, as though he thought what you'd said funny, though it isn't funny at all.

“‘But you're not me，'he said.

“I shrugged my shoulders and changed the conversation. I never gave the matter another thought.You can imagine my horror when he came here and told me they were going to be married.

“‘You can't, Larry，'I said.‘You can't.'

“‘I'm going to，'he said as calmly as if he was going to have a second helping of potatoes.‘And I want you to be very nice to her, Isabel.'

“‘That's asking too much，'I said.‘You're crazy. She's bad, bad, bad.'”

“What makes you think that?”I interrupted.

Isabel looked at me with flashing eyes.

“She's soused from morning till night. She goes to bed with every tough who asks her.”

“That doesn't mean she's bad. Quite a number of highly respected citizens get drunk and have a liking for rough trade.They're bad habits, like biting one's nails, but I don't know that they’re worse than that.I call a person bad who lies and cheats and is unkind.”

“If you're going to take her part I'll kill you.”

“How did Larry meet her again?”

“He found her address in the phone-book. He went to see her.She was sick, and no wonder, with the life she leads.He got a doctor and had someone in to look after her.That's how it started.He says she's given up drink；the damned fool thinks she's cured.”

“Have you forgotten what Larry did for Gray?He's cured him, hasn't he?”

“That's different. Gray wanted to be cured.She doesn't.”

“How d'you know?”

“Because I know women. When a woman goes to pieces like that she's done for；she can never get back.If Sophie's what she is, it's because she was like that always.D'you think she'll stick to Larry?Of course not.Sooner or later she’ll break out.It’s in her blood.It’s a brute she wants, that’s what excites her, and it’s a brute she’ll go after.She’ll lead Larry a hell of a life.”

“I think it's very probable, but I don't know what you can do about it. He's going into this with his eyes open.”

“I can do nothing about it, but you can.”

“I?”

“Larry likes you and he listens to what you say. You're the only person who has any influence over him.You know the world.Go to him and tell him that he can't make such a fool of himself.Tell him that it'll ruin him.”

“He'll only tell me that it's no business of mine and he'll be quite right.”

“But you like him, at least you're interested in him, you can't sit by and let him make a hopeless mess of his life.”

“Gray's his oldest and most intimate friend. I don't think it'll do any good, but I should have thought Gray was the best person to speak to him.”

“Oh, Gray，”she said impatiently.

“You know it may not turn out so badly as you think. I've known two or three fellows, one in Spain and two in the East, who married whores, and they made them very good wives.They were grateful to their husbands, for the security they gave them, I mean, and they of course knew what pleases a man.”

“You make me tired. D'you think I sacrificed myself to let Larry fall into the hands of a raging nymphomaniac?”

“How did you sacrifice yourself?”

“I gave Larry up for the one and only reason that I didn't want to stand in his way.”

“Come off it, Isabel. You gave him up for a square-cut diamond and a sable coat.”

The words were hardly out of my mouth when a plate of bread and butter came flying at my head. By sheer luck I caught the plate, but the bread and butter was scattered on the floor.I got up and put the plate back on the table.

“Your uncle Elliott wouldn't have thanked you if you'd broken one of his Crown Derby plates. They were made for the third Duke of Dorset and they're almost priceless.”

“Pick up the bread and butter，”she snapped.

“Pick it up yourself，”I said, seating myself again on the sofa.

She got up and, fuming, picked up the scattered pieces.

“And you call yourself an English gentleman，”she exclaimed, savagely.

“No, that's a thing I've never done in all my life.”

“Get the hell out of here. I never want to see you again.I hate the sight of you.”

“I'm sorry for that, because the sight of you always gives me pleasure. Have you ever been told that your nose is exactly like that of the Psyche in the museum of Naples, and that's the loveliest representation of virginal beauty that ever existed.You've got exquisite legs, so long and shapely, and I never cease to be surprised at them, because they were thick and lumpy when you were a girl, I can't imagine how you've managed it.”

“An iron will and the grace of God，”she said angrily.

“But of course your hands are your most fascinating feature. They're so slim and so elegant.”

“I was under the impression you thought them too big.”

“Not for your height and build. I'm always amazed at the infinite grace with which you use them.Whether by nature or by art you never make a gesture without imparting beauty to it.They're like flowers sometimes and sometimes like birds on the wing.They're more expressive than any words you can say.They're like the hands of El Greco's portraits；in fact, when I look at them I’m inclined to believe Elliott’s highly improbable story of your having an ancestor who was a Spanish grandee.”

She looked up crossly.

“What are you talking about?That's the first I've heard of it.”

I told her about the Count de Lauria and Queen Mary's maid of honour from whose issue in the female line Elliott traced his descent. Meanwhile Isabel contemplated her long fingers and her manicured painted nails with complacency.

“One must be descended from someone，”she said. Then with a tiny chuckle, giving me a mischievous look in which no trace of rancour remained, she added：“You lousy bastard.”

So easy is it to make a woman see reason if you only tell her the truth.

“There are moments when I don't positively dislike you，”said Isabel.

She came and sat on the sofa beside me and, slipping her arm through mine, leant over to kiss me. I withdrew my cheek.

“I will not have my face smeared with lipstick，”I said.“If you want to kiss me, kiss me on the lips, which is what merciful Providence intended them for.”

She giggled and, her hand turning my head towards her, with her lips pressed a thin layer of paint on mine. The sensation was far from unpleasant.

“Now you've done that, perhaps you'll tell me what it is you want.”

“Advice.”

“I'm quite willing to give you that, but I don't think for a moment you'll take it. There's only one thing you can do and that is to make the best of a bad job.”

Flaring up again, she snatched her arm away and, getting up, flung herself into a chair on the other side of the fireplace.

“I'm not going to sit by and let Larry ruin himself. I'll stick at nothing to prevent him from marrying that slut.”

“You won't succeed. You see, he's enthralled by one of the most powerful emotions that can beset the human breast.”

“You don't mean to say you think he's in love with her?”

“No. That would be trifling in comparison.”

“Well?”

“Have you ever read the New Testament?”

“I suppose so.”

“D'you remember how Jesus was led into the wilderness and fasted forty days?Then, when he was a-hungered, the devil came to him and said：If thou be the son of God, command that these stones be made bread. But Jesus resisted the temptation.Then the devil set him on a pinnacle of the temple and said to him：If thou be the son of God, cast thyself down.For angels had charge of him and would bear him up.But again Jesus resisted.Then the devil took him into a high mountain and showed him the kingdoms of the world and said that he would give them to him if he would fall down and worship him.But Jesus said：Get thee hence, Satan.That's the end of the story according to the good simple Matthew.But it wasn't.The devil was sly and he came to Jesus once more and said：If thou wilt accept shame and disgrace, scourging, a crown of thorns and death on the cross, thou shalt save the human race, for greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends.Jesus fell.The devil laughed till his sides ached, for he knew the evil men would commit in the name of their redeemer.”

Isabel looked at me indignantly.

“Where on earth did you get that?”

“Nowhere. I've invented it on the spur of the moment.”

“I think it's idiotic and blasphemous.”

“I only wanted to suggest to you that self-confidence is a passion so overwhelming that beside it even lust and hunger are trifling. It whirls its victim to destruction in the highest affirmation of his personality.The object doesn't matter；it may be worth while or it may be worthless.No wine is so intoxicating, no love so shattering, no vice so compelling.When he sacrifices himself man for a moment is greater than God, for how can God, infinite and omnipotent, sacrifice himself?At best he can only sacrifice his only begotten son.”

“Oh, Christ, how you bore me，”said Isabel.

I paid no attention.

“How can you suppose that common sense or prudence will have any effect on Larry when he's in the grip of a passion like that?You don't know what he's been seeking all these years. I don't know either, I only suspect.All theseyears of labour, all these experiences he garnered weigh nothing in the balance now they're set against his desire-oh, it’s more than a desire, his urgent, clamorous need to save the soul of a wanton woman whom he’d known as an innocent child.I think you’re right, I think he’s undertaking a hopeless job；with his acute sensibility he’ll suffer the tortures of the damned；his life’s work, whatever it may be, will remain undone.The ignoble Paris killed Achilles by shooting an arrow in his heel.Larry lacks just that touch of ruthlessness that even the saint must have to win his halo.”

“I love him，”said Isabel.“God knows, I ask nothing of him. I expect nothing.No one could love anyone more unselfishly than I love him.He's going to be so unhappy.”

She began to cry and, thinking it would do her good, I let her be. I diverted myself idly with the idea that had sprung so unexpectedly into my mind.I played with it.I couldn't but surmise that the devil, looking at the cruel wars that Christianity has occasioned, the persecutions, the tortures Christian has inflicted on Christian, the unkindness, the hypocrisy, the intolerance, must consider the balance sheet with complacency.And when he remembers that it has laid upon mankind the bitter burden of the sense of sin that has darkened the beauty of the starry night and cast a baleful shadow on the passing pleasures of a world to be enjoyed, he must chuckle as he murmurs：give the devil his due.

Presently Isabel took a handkerchief from her bag and a mirror and, looking at herself, carefully wiped the corner of her eyes.

“Damned sympathetic, aren't you?”she snapped.

I looked at her pensively, but did not answer. She powdered her face and painted her lips.

“You said just now you suspected what he's been after all these years. What did you mean?”

“I can only guess, you know, and I may be quite wrong. I think he's been seeking for a philosophy, or maybe a religion, and a rule of life that'll satisfy both his head and his heart.”

Isabel considered this for a moment. She sighed.

“Don't you think it's very strange that a country boy from Marvin, Illinois, should have a notion like that?”

“No stranger than that Luther Burbank who was born on a farm in Massachusetts should have produced a seedless orange or that Henry Ford who was born on a farm in Michigan should have invented a Tin Lizzie.”

“But those are practical things. That's in the American tradition.”

I laughed.

“Can anything in the world be more practical than to learn how to live to best advantage?”

Isabel gave a gesture of lassitude.

“You don't want to lose Larry altogether, do you?”

She shook her head.

“You know how loyal he is：if you won't have anything to do with his wife he won't have anything to do with you. If you've got any sense you'll make friends with Sophie.You'll forget the past and be as nice to her as you can be when you like.She’s going to be married and I suppose she’s buying some clothes.Why don’t you offer to go shopping with her?I think she’d jump at it.”

Isabel listened to me with narrowed eyes. She seemed intent upon what I was saying.For a moment she pondered, but I could not guess what was passing through her mind.Then she surprised me.

“Will you ask her to lunch?It would be rather awkward for me after what I said to Larry yesterday.”

“Will you behave if I do?”

“Like an angel of light，”she answered with her most engaging smile.

“I'll fix it up right away.”

There was a phone in the room. I soon found Sophie's number, and after the usual delay which those who use the French telephone learn to put up with patiently, I got her.I mentioned my name.

“I've just arrived in Paris，”I said，“and heard that you and Larry are going to be married. I want to congratulate you.I hope you'll be very happy.”I smothered a cry as Isabel, who was standing by me, gave the soft of my arm a vicious pinch.“I'm only here for a verv short time and I wonder if you and Larry will come and lunch with me the dayafter tomorrow at the Ritz.I'm asking Gray and Isabel and Elliott Templeton.”

“I'll ask Larry. He's here now.”There was a pause.“Yes, we shall be glad to.”

I fixed an hour, made a civil remark, and replaced the receiver on its stand. I caught an expression in Isabel's eyes that caused me some misgiving.

“What are you thinking?”I asked her.“I don't quite like the look of you.”

“I'm sorry；I thought that was the one thing about me you did like.”

“You haven't got some nefarious scheme that you're hatching, Isabel?”

She opened her eyes very wide.

“I promise you I haven't. As a matter of fact I'm terribly curious to see what Sophie looks like now Larry has reformed her.All I hope is that she won't come to the Ritz with a mask of paint on her face.”

5

My little party did not go too badly. Gray and Isabel arrived first；Larry and Sophie Macdonald five minutes later.Isabel and Sophie kissed each other warmly and Isabel and Gray congratulated her on her engagement.I caught the appraising sweep of the eyes with which Isabel took in Sophie's appearance.I was shocked at it.When I saw her in that dive in the Rue de Lappe, outrageously painted, with hennaed hair, in the bright green coat, though she looked outrageous and was very drunk, there was something provocative and even basely alluring in her；but now she looked drab and, though certainly a year or two younger than Isabel, much older.She still had that gallant tilt of her head, but now, I don't know why, it was pathetic.She was letting her hair go back to its natural colour and it had the slatternly look that hair has when it has been dyed and left to grow.Except for a streak of red on her lips she had no make-up on.Her skin was rough and it had an unhealthy pallor.I remembered how vividly green her eyes had looked, but now they were pale and grey.She wore a red dress, obviously brand-new, with hat, shoes, and bag to match；I don't pretend to know anything about women's clothes, but I had a feeling that it was fussy and too elaborate for the occasion.On her breast was a piece of showy artificial jewellery such as you buy in the Rue de Rivoli.Beside Isabel, in black silk, with a string of cultured pearls round her neck and in a very smart hat, she looked cheap and dowdy.

I ordered cocktails, but Larry and Sophie refused them. Then Elliott arrived.His progress through the vast foyer was, however, impeded by the hands he had to shake and the hands he had to kiss as he saw one person after the other whom he knew.He behaved as though the Ritz were his private house and he were assuring his guests of his pleasure that they had been able to accept his invitation.He had been told nothing about Sophie except she had lost her husband and child in a motor accident and was now going to marry Larry.When at last he reached us he congratulated them both with the elaborate graciousness of which he was a master.We went in to the dining-room and since we were four men and two women I placed Isabel and Sophie opposite one another at the round table, with Sophie between Gray and myself；but the table was small enough for the conversation to be general.I had already ordered the luncheon and the wine waiter came along with the wine card.

“You don't know anything about wine, my dear fellow，”said Elliott.“Give me the wine card, Albert.”He turned over the pages.“I drink nothing but Vichy myself, but I can't bear to see people drink wine that isn't perfect.”

He and Albert, the wine waiter, were old friends and after an animated discussion they decided on the wine I should give my guests. Then he turned to Sophie.

“And where are you going for your honeymoon, my dear?”

He glanced at her dress and an almost imperceptible raising of his eyebrows showed me that he had formed an unfavourable opinion of it.

“We're going to Greece.”

“I've been trying to get there for ten years，”said Larry，“but somehow I've never been able to manage it.”

“It ought to be lovely at this time of the year，”said Isabel, with a show of enthusiasm.

She remembered, as I remembered, that that was where Larry proposed to take her when he wanted her to marry him. It seemed to be an idée fixe with Larry to go to Greece on a honeymoon.

The conversation flowed none too easily and I should have found it a difficult row to hoe if it hadn't been for Isabel. She was on her best behaviour.Whenever silence seemed to threaten us and I racked my brain for some-thing fresh to talk about, she broke in with facile chatter.I was grateful to her.Sophie hardly spoke except when she was spoken to and then it seemed an effort to her.The spirit had gone out of her.You would have said that something had died in her and I asked myself if Larry wasn't putting her to a strain greater than she could support.If as I suspected she had doped as well as drunk, the sudden deprivation must have worn her nerves to a frazzle.Sometimes I intercepted a look between them.In his I saw tenderness and encouragement, but in hers an appeal that was pathetic.It may be that Gray with his sweetness of disposition instinctively felt what I thought I saw, for he began to tell her how Larry had cured him of the headaches that had incapacitated him and went on to say how much he had depended on him and how much he owed him.

“Now I'm fit as a flea，”he continued.“As soon as ever I can get a job I'm going back to work. I've got several irons in the fire and I'm hoping to land something before long.Gosh, it'll be good to be back home again.”

Gray meant well, but what he had said was perhaps not very tactful if, as I supposed, Larry to cure Sophie of her aggravated alcoholism had used with her the same method of suggestion-for that to my mind was what it was-that had been successful with Gray.

“You never have headaches now, Gray?”asked Elliott.

“I haven't had one for three months and if I think one's coming on I take hold of my charm and I'm all right.”He fished out of his pocket the ancient coin Larry had given him.“I wouldn't sell it for a million dollars.”

We finished luncheon and coffee was served. The wine waiter came up and asked whether we wanted liqueurs.We all refused except Gray, who said he would have a brandy.When the bottle was brought Elliott insisted on looking at it.

“Yes, I can recommend it. That'll do you no harm.”

“A little glass for Monsieur?”asked the waiter.

“Alas, it's forbidden me.”

Elliott told him at some length that he was having trouble with his kidneys and that his doctor would not allow him to drink alcohol.

“A tear of zubrovka could do Monsieur no harm. It's well known to be very good for the kidneys.We have just received a consignment from Poland.”

“Is that true?It's hard to get nowadays. Let me have a look at a bottle.”

The wine waiter, a portly, dignified creature with a long silver chain round his neck, went away to fetch it, and Elliott explained that it was the Polish form of vodka but in every way superior.

“We used to drink it at the Radziwills when I stayed with them for the shooting. You should have seen those Polish princes putting it away；I'm not exaggerating when I tell you that they'd drink it by the tumbler without turning a hair.Good blood, of course；aristocrats to the tips of their fingers.Sophie, you must try it, and you too, Isabel.It's an experience no one can afford to miss.”

The wine waiter brought the bottle. Larry, Sophie, and I refused to be tempted, but Isabel said she would like to try it.I was surprised, for habitually she drank very little and she had had two cocktails and two or three glasses of wine.The waiter poured out a glass of pale green liquid and Isabel sniffed it.

“Oh, what a lovely smell.”

“Hasn't it?”cried Elliott.“That's the herbs they put in it；it's they that give it its delicate taste. Just to keep you company I'll have a drop.It can't hurt me for once.”

“It tastes divine，”said Isabel.“It's like mother's milk. I've never tasted anything so good.”

Elliott raised his glass to his lips.

“Oh, how it brings back the old days！You people who never stayed with the Radziwills don't know what living is. That was the grand style.Feudal, you know.You might have thought yourself back in the Middle Ages.You were met at the station by a carriage with six horses and postilions.And at dinner a footman in livery behind every person.”

He went on to describe the magnificence and luxury of the establishment and the brilliance of the parties；and the suspicion, doubtless unworthy, occurred to me that the whole thing was a put-up job between Elliott and the wine waiter to give Elliott an opportunity to discourse upon the grandeur of this princely family and the host of Polish aristocrats he hobnobbed with in their castle. There was no stopping him.

“Another glass, Isabel?”

“Oh, I daren't. But it is heavenly.I'm so glad to know about it；Gray, we must get some.”

“I'll have some sent round to the apartment.”

“Oh, Uncle Elliott, would you?”cried Isabel enthusiastically.“You are so kind to us. You must try it, Gray；it smells of freshly mown hay and spring flowers, of thyme and lavender, and it's soft on the palate and so comfort-able, it's like listening to music by moonlight.”

It was unlike Isabel to gush inordinately and I wondered if she was a trifle tight. The party broke up.I shook hands with Sophie.

“When are you going to be married?”I asked her.

“The week after next. I hope you'll come to the wedding.”

“I'm afraid I shan't be in Paris. I'm leaving for London tomorrow.”

While I was saying good-bye to the rest of my guests Isabel took Sophie aside and talked to her for a minute, then turned to Gray.

“Oh, Gray, I'm not coming home just yet. There's a dress show at Molyneux's and I'm taking Sophie to it.She ought to see the new models.”

“I'd love to，”said Sophie.

We parted. I took Suzanne Rouvier out to dinner that night and next morning started for England.

6

Elliott arrived at Claridge's a fortnight later and shortly afterwards I dropped in to see him. He had ordered himself several suits of clothes and at what I thought excessive length told me in detail what he had chosen and why.When at last I could get a word in I asked him how the wedding had gone off.

“It didn't go off，”he answered grimly.

“What do you mean?”

“Three days before it was to take place Sophie disappeared. Larry hunted everywhere for her.”

“What an extraordinary thing！Did they have a row?”

“No. Far from it.Everything had been arranged.I was going to give her away.They were taking the Orient Express immediately after the wedding.If you ask me, I think Larry's well out of it.”

I guessed that Isabel had told Elliott everything.

“What exactly happened?”I asked.

“Well, you remember that day we lunched at the Ritz with you. Isabel took her to Molyneux's.D'you remember the dress Sophie wore?Deplorable.Did you notice the shoulders?That's how you tell if a dress is well made, by the way it fits over the shoulders.Of course, poor girl, she couldn't afford Molyneux's prices, and Isabel, you know how generous she is, and after all they’ve known one another since they were children, Isabel offered to give her a dress so that at least she’d have something decent to be married in.Naturally she jumped at it.Well, to cut a long story short, Isabel asked her to come to the apartment one day at three so that they could go together for the final fitting.Sophie came all right, but unfortunately Isabel had to take one of the children to the dentist’s and didn’t get in till after four and by that time Sophie had gone.Isabel thought she’d got tired of waiting and had gone on to Molyneux’s, so she wentthere at once, but she hadn’t come.At last she gave her up and went home again.They were all going to dine together and Larry came along at dinner-time and the first thing she asked him was where Sophie was.

“He couldn't understand it and he rang up her apartment, but there was no reply, so he said he'd go down there. They held dinner up as long as they could, but neither of them turned up and so they had dinner by themselves.Of course you know what Sophie's life was before you ran into her in the Rue de Lappe；that was a most unfortunate idea of yours to take them down there.Well, Larry spent all night going around her old haunts, but couldn't find her anywhere.He went to the apartment after time, but the concierge said she hadn't been in.He spent three days hunting for her.She’d just vanished.Then on the fourth day he went to the apartment again and the concierge told him she’d been in and packed a bag and gone away in a taxi.”

“Was Larry awfully upset?”

“I didn't see him. Isabel tells me he was rather.”

“She didn't write or anything?”

“Nothing.”

I thought it over.

“What do you make of it?”I said.

“My dear fellow, exactly what you make of it. She couldn't stick it out.She went on the booze again.”

That was obvious, but for all that it was strange. I couldn't see why she had chosen just that moment to skip.

“How is Isabel taking it?”

“Of course she's sorry, but she's a sensible girl and she told me she always thought it would be a disaster if Larry married a woman like that.”

“And Larry?”

“Isabel's been very kind to him. She says that what makes it difficult is that he won't discuss it.He'll be all right, you know；Isabel says he was never in love with Sophie.He was only marrying her out of a sort of misguided chivalry.”

I could see Isabel putting a brave face on a turn of events that was certainly causing her a great deal of satisfaction. I well knew that next time I saw her she would not fail to point out to me that she had known all along what would happen.

But it was nearly a year before I saw her again and though by that time I could have told her something about Sophie that would have set her thinking, the circumstances were such that I had no inclination to. I stayed in London till nearly Christmas and then, wanting to get home, went straight down to the Riviera without stopping in Paris.I set to work on a novel and for the next few months lived in retirement.I saw Elliott now and then.It was obvious that his health was failing, and it pained me that he persisted notwithstanding in leading a social life.He was vexed with me because I would not drive thirty miles to go to the constant parties he continued to give.He thought it very conceited of me to prefer to sit at home and work.

“It's an unusually brilliant season, my dear fellow，”he told me.“It's a crime to shut yourself up in your house and miss everything that's going on. And why you had to choose a part of the Riviera to live in that's completely out of fashion I shan't be able to understand if I live to be a hundred.”

Poor nice silly Elliott；it was very clear that he would live to no such age.

By June I had finished the rough draft of my novel and thought I deserved a holiday, so, packing a bag, I got on the cutter from which in summer we used to bathe in the Baie des Fosses and set sail along the coast towards Marseilles. There was only a fitful breeze and for the most part we chugged along with the motor auxiliary.We spent a night in the harbour at Cannes, another at Sainte Maxime, and a third at Sanary.Then we got to Toulon.That is a port I have always had an affection for.The ships of the French fleet give it an air at once romantic and companionable, and I am never tired of wandering about its old streets.I can linger for hours on the quay, watching the sailors on shore leave strolling about in pairs or with their girls, and the civilians who saunter back and forth as though they had nothing in the world to do but enjoy the pleasant sunshine.Because of all these ships and the ferryboats that take the bustling crowd to variouspoints of the vast harbour, Toulon gives you the effect of a terminal on which all the ways of the wide world converge；and as you sit in a café，your eyes a little dazzled by the brightness of sea and sky, your fancy takes golden journeys to the uttermost parts of the earth.You land in a longboat on a coral beach, fringed with coconut palms, in the Pacific；you step off the gangway on to the dock at Rangoon and get into a rickshaw；you watch from the upper deck the noisy, gesticulating crowd of Negroes as your ship is made fast to the pier at Port au Prince.

We got in lateish in the morning and towards the middle of the afternoon I landed and walked along the quay, looking at the shops, at the people who passed me, and at the people sitting under the awning in the cafés.Suddenly I saw Sophie and at the same moment she saw me.She smiled and said hello.I stopped and shook hands with her.She was by herself at a small table with an empty glass before her.

“Sit down and have a drink，”she said.

“You have one with me，”I replied, taking a chair.

She wore the striped blue-and-white jersey of the French sailor, a pair of bright red slacks, and sandals through which protruded the painted nails of her big toes. She wore no hat, and her hair, cut very short and curled, was of so pale a gold that it was almost silver.She was as heavily made up as when we had run across her at the Rue de Lappe.She had had a drink or two as I judged from the saucers on the table, but she was sober.She did not seem dis-pleased to see me.

“How are all the folks in Paris?”she asked.

“I think they're all right. I haven't seen any of them since that day we all lunched together at the Ritz.”

She blew a great cloud of smoke from her nostrils and began to laugh.

“I didn't marry Larry after all.”

“I know. Why not?”

“Darling, when it came to the point I couldn't see myself being Mary Magdalen to his Jesus Christ. No, sir.”

“What made you change your mind at the last moment?”

She looked at me mockingly. With that audacious tilt of the head, with her small breasts and narrow flanks, in that get-up, she looked like a vicious boy；but I must admit that she was much more attractive than in the red dress, with its dismal air of provincial smartness, in which I had last seen her.Face and neck were deeply burnt by the sun, and though the brownness of her skin made the rouge on her cheeks and the black of her eyebrows more aggres-sive, the effect in its vulgar way was not without lure.

“Would you like me to tell you?”

I nodded. The waiter brought the beer I had ordered for myself and the brandy and seltzer for her.She lit a caporal from one she had just finished.

“I hadn't had a drink for three months. I hadn't had a smoke.”She saw my faint look of surprise and laughed.“I don't mean cigarettes.Opium.I felt awful.You know, sometimes when I was alone I'd shriek the place down；I'd say，‘I can’t go through with it, I can’t go through with it.’It wasn’t so bad when I was with Larry, but when he wasn’t there it was hell.”

I was looking at her and when she mentioned opium I scanned her more sharply；I noticed the pin-point pupils that showed she was smoking it now. Her eyes were startlingly green.

“Isabel was giving me my wedding dress. I wonder what's happened to it now.It was a peach.We'd arranged that I should pick her up and we'd go to Molyneux's together.I will say this for Isabel, what she doesn't know about clothes isn’t worth knowing.When I got to the apartment their man said she’d had to take Joan to the dentist’s and had left a message that she’d be in directly.I went into the living-room.The coffee things were still on the table and I asked the man if I could have a cup.Coffee was the only thing that kept me going.He said he’d bring me some and took the empty cups and the coffee-pot away.He left a bottle on the tray.I looked at it, and it was that Polish stuff you’d all talked about at the Ritz.”

“Zubrovka. I remember Elliott saying he'd send Isabel some.”

“You'd all raved how good it smelt and I was curious. I took out the cork and had a sniff.You were quite right；it smelt damned good.I lit a cigarette and in a few minutes the man came in with the coffee.That was good too.They talk a lot about French coffee, they can have it；give me American coffee.That's the only thing I miss here.But Isabel's coffee wasn't bad, I was feeling lousy, and after I'd had a cup I felt better.I looked at that bottle standing there.It was a terrible temptation, but I said，‘To hell with it, I won’t think of it，’and I lit another cigarette.I thought Isabel would be in any minute, but she didn’t come.I got frightfully nervous；I hate being kept waiting and there was nothing to read in the room.I started walking about and looking at the pictures, but I kept on seeing that damned bottle.Then I thought I’d just pour out a glass and look at it.It had such a pretty colour.”

“Pale green.”

“That's right. It's funny, its colour is just like its smell.It's like that green you sometimes see in the heart of a white rose.I had to see if it tasted like that, I thought just a taste couldn't hurt me；I only meant to take a sip and then I heard a sound, I thought it was Isabel coming in and I swallowed the glassful because I didn't want her to catch me.But it wasn’t Isabel after all.Gosh, it made me feel good, I hadn’t felt like that since I’d gone on the wagon.I really began to feel alive again.If Isabel had come in then I suppose I’d be married to Larry now.I wonder how it would have turned out.”

“And she didn't come in?”

“No, she didn't. I was furious with her.Who did she think she was, keeping me waiting like that?And then I saw that the liqueur glass was full again；I suppose I must have poured it out without thinking, but, believe it or not, I didn't know I had.It seemed silly to pour it back again, so I drank it.There's no denying it, it was delicious.I felt a different woman；I felt like laughing and I hadn't felt like that for three months.D'you remember that old cissie saying he’d seen fellas in Poland drink it by the tumbler without turning a hair?Well, I thought I could take what any Polish son of a bitch could take and you may as well be hanged for a sheep as a lamb, so I emptied the dregs of my coffee in the fireplace and filled the cup to the brim.Talk of mother’s milk-my arse.Then I don’t quite know what happened, but I don’t believe there was much left in the bottle by the time I was through.Then I thought I’d get out before Isabel came in.She nearly caught me.Just as I got out of the front door I heard Joanie’s voice.I ran up the stairs and waited till they were safely in the apartment and then I dashed down and got into a taxi.I told the driver to drive like hell and when he asked where to I burst out laughing in his face.I felt like a million dollars.”

“Did you go back to your apartment?”I asked, though I knew she hadn't.

“What sort of a damn fool d'you take me for?I knew Larry would come and look for me. I didn't dare go to any of the places I used to go to, so I went to Hakim's.I knew Larry'd never find me there.Besides, I wanted a smoke.”

“What's Hakim's?”

“Hakim's?Hakim's an Algerian and he can always get you opium if you've got the dough to pay for it. He was quite a friend of mine.He'll get you anything you want, a boy, a man, a woman, or a nigger.He always has half a dozen Algerians on tap.I spent three days there.I don't know how many men I didn’t have.”She began to giggle.“All shapes, sizes, and colours.I made up for lost time all right.But you know, I was scared.I didn’t feel safe in Paris, I was afraid Larry’d find me, besides I hadn’t got any money left, those bastards you have to pay them to go to bed with you, so I got out, I went back to the apartment and gave the concierge a hundred francs and told her if anyone came and asked for me to say I’d gone away.I packed my things and that night I took the train to Toulon.I didn’t feel really safe till I got here.”

“And have you been here ever since?”

“You betcha, and I'm going to stay here. You can get all the opium you want, the sailors bring it back from the East, and it's good stuff, not that muck they sell you in Paris.I've got a room at the hotel.You know, the Commerce et la Marine.When you go in there at night the corridors just reek of it.”She sniffed voluptuously.“Sweet and acrid, and you know they're smoking in their rooms, and it gives you a nice homey feeling.And they don't mind who you take in with you.They come and thump at your door at five in the morning to get the sailors up to go back to their ships, so youdon’t have to worry about that.”And then, without transition：“I saw a book of yours in the store just along the quay；if I’d known I was going to see you I’d have bought it and got you to sign it.”

When passing the bookshop I had stopped to look in the window and had noticed among other new books the translation of a novel of mine that had recently appeared.

“I don't suppose it would have amused you much，”I said.

“I don't know why it shouldn't. I can read, you know.”

“And you can write too, I believe.”

She gave me a rapid glance and began to laugh.

“Yeah, I used to write poetry when I was a kid. I guess it was pretty terrible, but I thought it fine.I suppose Larry told you.”She hesitated for a moment.“Life's hell anyway, but if there is any fun to be got out of it, you're only a god-damn fool if you don't get it.”She threw back her head defiantly.“If I buy that book will you write in it?”

“I'm leaving tomorrow. If you really want it, I'll get you a copy and leave it at your hotel.”

“That'd be swell.”

Just then a naval launch came up to the quay and a crowd of sailors tumbled out of it. Sophie embraced them with a glance.

“That'll be my boy friend.”She waved her arm at someone.“You can stand him a drink and then you better scram. He's a Corsican and as jealous as our old friend Jehovah.”

A young man came up to us, hesitated when he saw me, but on a beckoning gesture came up to the table. He was tall, swarthy, clean-shaven, with splendid dark eyes, an aquiline nose, and raven black, wavy hair.He did not look more than twenty.Sophie introduced me as an American friend of her childhood.

“Dumb but beautiful，”she said to me.

“You like'em tough, don't you?”

“The tougher the better.”

“One of these days you'll get your throat cut.”

“I wouldn't be surprised，”she grinned.“Good riddance to bad rubbish.”

“One's going to speak French, isn't one?”the sailor said sharply.

Sophie turned upon him a smile in which there was a trace of mockery. She spoke a fluent and slangy French, with a strong American accent, but this gave the vulgar and obscene colloquialisms that she commonly used a comic tang, so that you could not help but laugh.

“I was telling him that you were beautiful, but to spare your modesty I was saying it in English.”She addressed me.“And he's strong. He has the muscles of a boxer.Feel them.”

The sailor's sullenness was dispelled by the flattery and with a complacent smile he flexed his arm so that the biceps stood out.

“Feel it，”he said.“Go on, feel it.”

I did so and expressed a proper admiration. We chatted for a few minutes.I paid for the drinks and got up.

“I must be going.”

“It's nice to have seen you. Don't forget the book.”

“I won't.”

I shook hands with them both and strolled off. On my way I stopped at the bookshop, bought the novel, and wrote Sophie's name and my own.Then, because it suddenly occurred to me I could think of nothing else, I wrote the first line of Ronsard's lovely little poem which is in all the anthologies：

Mignonne, allons voir si la rose……

I left it at the hotel. It is on the quay and I have often stayed there because when you are awakened at dawn by theclarion that calls the men on night leave back to duty the sun rising mistily over the smooth water of the harbour invests the wraithlike ships with a shrouded loveliness.Next day we sailed for Cassis, where I wanted to buy some wine, and then to Marseilles to take up a new sail that we had ordered.A week later I got home.

7

I found a message from Joseph, Elliott's manservant, to tell me that Elliott was ill in bed and would be glad to see me, so next day I drove over to Antibes. Joseph, before taking me up to see his master, told me that Elliott had had an attack of uraemia and that his doctor took a grave view of his condition.He had come through it and was getting better, but his kidneys were diseased and it was impossible that he should ever completely recover.Joseph had been with Elliott for forty years and was devoted to him, but though his manner was regretful it was impossible not to notice the inner satisfaction with which, like so many members of his class, catastrophe in the house filled him.

“Ce pauvre monsieur，”he sighed.“Evidently he had his manias but at bottom he was good. Sooner or later he must die.”

He spoke already as though Elliott were at his last gasp.

“I'm sure he's provided for you, Joseph，”I said grimly.

“One must hope it，”he said mournfully.

I was surprised when he ushered me into the bedroom to find Elliott very spry. He was pale and looked old, but was in good spirits.He was shaved and his hair was neatly brushed.He wore pale blue silk pyjamas, on the pocket of which were embroidered his initials surmounted by his count's crown.These, much larger and again with the crown, were heavily embroidered on the turned-down sheet.

I asked him how he felt.

“Perfectly well，”he said cheerfully.“It's only a temporary indisposition. I shall be up and about again in a few days.I've got the Grand Duke Dimitri lunching with me on Saturday, and I've told my doctor he must put me to rights by then at all costs.”

I spent half an hour with him, and on my way out asked Joseph to let me know if Elliott had a relapse. I was astonished a week later when I went to lunch with one of my neighbours to find him there.Dressed for a party, he looked like death.

“You oughtn't to be out, Elliott，”I told him.

“Oh, what nonsense, my dear fellow. Frieda is expecting the Princess Mafalda.I've known the Italian royal family for years, ever since poor Louisa was en poste at Rome, and I couldn't let poor Frieda down.”

I did not know whether to admire his indomitable spirit or to lament that at his age, stricken with mortal illness, he should still retain his passion for society. You would never have thought he was a sick man.Like a dying actor when he has the grease paint on his face and steps on the stage, who forgets for the time being his aches and pains, Elliott played his part of the polished courtier with his accustomed assurance.He was infinitely amiable, flatter-ingly attentive to the proper people, and amusing with that malicious irony at which he was an adept.I think I had never seen him display his social gift to greater advantage.When the Royal Highness had departed（and the grace with which Elliott bowed, managing to combine respect for her exalted rank with an old man's admiration for a comely woman, was a sight to see）I was not surprised to hear our hostess tell him that he had been the life and soul of the party.

A few days later he was in bed again and his doctor forbade him to leave his room. Elliott was exasperated.

“It's too bad this should happen just now. It's a particularly brilliant season.”

He reeled off a long list of persons of importance who were spending the summer on the Riviera.

I went to see him every three or four days. Sometimes he was in bed, but sometimes he lay on a chaise longue in a gorgeous dressing-gown.He seemed to have an inexhaustible supply of them, for I do not remember that I ever saw him in the same one twice.On one of these occasions, it was the beginning of August by now, I found Elliott unusually quiet.Joseph had told me when he let me into the house that he seemed a little better so I was surprised that he was so listless.I tried to amuse him with such gossip of the coast as I had picked up, but he was plainly uninterested.There was a slight frown between his eyes, and a sullenness in his expression that was unusual with him.

“Are you going to Edna Novemali's party?”he asked me suddenly.

“No, of course not.”

“Has she asked you?”

“She's asked everybody on the Riviera.”

The Princess Novemali was an American of immense wealth who had married a Roman prince, but not an ordinary prince such as go for two a penny in Italy, but the head of a great family and the descendant of a condottiere who had carved out a principality for himself in the sixteenth century. She was a woman of sixty, a widow, and since the Fascist regime demanded too large a slice of her American income to suit her, she had left Italy and built herself, on a fine estate behind Cannes, a Florentine villa.She had brought marble from Italy with which to line the walls of her great reception rooms and imported painters to paint the ceilings.Her pictures, her bronzes, were uncommonly fine and even Elliott, though he didn't like Italian furniture, was obliged to admit that hers was magnificent.The gardens were lovely and the swimming-pool must have cost a small fortune.She entertained largely and you never sat down less than twenty at table.She had arranged to give a fancy-dress party on the night of the August full moon, and although it was still three weeks ahead nothing else was being talked of on the Riviera.There were to be fireworks and she was bringing down a coloured orchestra from Paris.The exiled royalties were telling one another with envious admiration that it would cost her more than they had to live on for a year.

“It's princely，”they said.

“It's crazy，”they said.

“It's in bad taste，”they said.

“What are you going to wear?”Elliott asked me.

“But I told you, Elliott, I'm not going. You don't think I'm going to dress myself up in fancy dress at my time of life.”

“She hasn't asked me，”he said hoarsely.

He looked at me with haggard eyes.

“Oh, she will，”I said coolly.“I dare say all the invitations haven't gone out yet.”

“She's not going to ask me.”His voice broke.“It's a deliberate insult.”

“Oh, Elliott, I can't believe that. I'm sure it's an oversight.”

“I'm not a man that people overlook.”

“Anyhow, you wouldn't have been well enough to go.”

“Of course I should. The best party of the season！If I were on my deathbed I'd get up for it.I've got the costume of my ancestor, the Count de Lauria, to wear.”

I did not quite know what to say and so remained silent.

“Paul Barton was in to see me just before you came，”Elliott said suddenly.

I cannot expect the reader to remember who this was, since I had to look back myself to see what name I had given him. Paul Barton was the young American whom Elliott had introduced into London society and who had aroused his hatred by dropping him when he no longer had any use for him.He had been somewhat in the public eye of late, first because he had adopted British nationality and then because he had married the daughter of a news-paper magnate who had been raised to the peerage.With this influence behind him and with his own adroitness it was evident that he would go far.Elliott was very bitter.

“Whenever I wake up in the night and hear a mouse scratching away in the wainscoat I say：‘That's Paul Barton climbing.'Believe me, my dear fellow, he'll end up in the House of Lords. Thank God, I shan't be alive to see it.”

“What did he want?”I asked, for I knew as well as Elliott that this young man did nothing for nothing.

“I'll tell you what he wanted，”said Elliott, snarling.“He wanted to borrow my Count de Lauria costume.”

“Nerve！”

“Don't you see what it means?It means he knew Edna hadn't asked me and wasn't going to ask me. She put him up to it.The old bitch.She'd never have got anywhere without me.I gave parties for her.I introduced her to everyone she knows.She sleeps with her chauffeur；you knew that of course.Disgusting！He sat there and told me that she's having the whole garden illuminated and there are going to be fireworks.I love fireworks.And he told me that Edna was being pestered by people who were asking for invitations, but she had turned them all down because she wanted the party to be really brilliant.He spoke as though there were no question of my being invited.”

“And are you lending him the costume?”

“I'd see him dead and in hell first. I'm going to be buried in it.”Elliott, sitting up in bed, rocked to and fro like a woman distraught.“Oh, it's so unkind，”he said.“I hate them, I hate them all.They were glad enough to make a fuss of me when I could entertain them, but now I'm old and sick they have no use for me.Not ten people have called to inquire since I've been laid up, and all this week only one miserable bunch of flowers.I’ve done every-thing for them.They’ve eaten my food and drunk my wine.I’ve run their errands for them.I’ve made their parties for them.I’ve turned myself inside out to do them favours.And what have I got out of it?Nothing, nothing, nothing.There’s not one of them who cares if I live or die.Oh, it’s so cruel.”He began to cry.Great heavy tears trickled down his withered cheeks.“I wish to God I’d never left America.”

It was lamentable to see that old man, with the grave yawning in front of him, weep like a child because he hadn't been asked to a party：shocking and at the same time almost intolerably pathetic.

“Never mind, Elliott，”I said，“it may rain on the night of the party. That'll bitch it.”

He caught at my words like the drowning man we've all heard about at a straw. He began to giggle through his tears.

“I've never thought of that. I'll pray to God for rain as I've never prayed before.You're quite right；that'll bitch it.”

I managed to divert his frivolous mind into another channel and left him, if not cheerful, at least composed. But I was not willing to let the matter rest, so on getting home I called up Edna Novemali and, saying I had to come to Cannes next day, asked if I could lunch with her.She sent a message that she'd be pleased but there'd be no party.Nevertheless when I arrived I found ten people there besides herself.She was not a bad sort, generous and hospitable, and her only grave fault was her malicious tongue.She could not help saying beastly things about even her intimate friends, but she did this because she was a stupid woman and knew no other way to make herself interesting.Since her slanders were repeated she was often not on speaking terms with the objects of her venom, but she gave good parties and most of them found it convenient after a while to forgive her.I did not want to expose Elliott to the humiliation of asking her to invite him to her big do, so waited to see how the land lay.She was excited about it and the conversation at luncheon was concerned with nothing else.

“Elliott will be delighted to have an opportunity to wear his Philip the Second costume，”I said as casually as I could.

“I haven't asked him，”she said.

“Why not?”I replied, with an air of surprise.

“Why should I?He doesn't count socially any more. He's a bore and a snob and a scandalmonger.”

Since these accusations could with equal truth be brought against her, I thought this a bit thick. She was a fool.

“Besides，”she added，“I want Paul to wear Elliott's costume. He'll look simply divine in it.”

I said nothing more, but determined by hook or by crook to get poor Elliott the invitation he hankered after. After luncheon Edna took her friends out into the garden.That gave me the chance I was looking for.On one occasion I had stayed in the house for a few days and knew its arrangement.I guessed that there would still be a number of invitation cards left over and that they would be in the secretary's room.I whipped along there, meaning to slip one in my pocket, write Elliott's name on it, and post it.I knew he was much too ill to go, but it would mean a great deal to him to receive it.I was taken aback when I opened the door to find Edna's secretary at her desk.I had expected her to be still at lunch.She was a middle-aged Scotch woman, called Miss Keith, with sandy hair, a freckled face, pince-nez, and an air of determined virginity.I collected myself.

“The Princess is taking the crowd around the garden, so I thought I'd come in and smoke a cigarette with you.”

“You're welcome.”

Miss Keith spoke with a Scotch burr and when she indulged in the dry humour which she reserved for her favourites she so broadened it as to make her remarks extremely amusing, but when you were overcome with laughter she looked at you with pained surprise as though she thought you daft to see anything funny in what she said.

“I suppose this party is giving you a hell of a lot of work. Miss Keith，”I said.

“I don't know whether I'm standing on my head or on my heels.”

Knowing I could trust her, I went straight to the point.

“Why hasn't the old girl asked Mr. Templeton?”

Miss Keith permitted a smile to cross her grim features.

“You know what she is. She's got a down on him.She crossed his name out on the list herself.”

“He's dying, you know. He'll never leave his bed again.He's awfully hurt at being left out.”

“If he wanted to keep in with the Princess he'd have been wiser not to tell everyone that she goes to bed with her chauffeur. And him with a wife and three children.”

“And does she?”

Miss Keith looked at me over her pince-nez.

“I've been a secretary for twenty-one years, my dear sir, and I've made it a rule to believe all my employers as pure as the driven snow. I'll admit that when one of my ladies found herself three months gone in the family way when his lordship had been shooting lions in Africa for six, my faith was sorely tried, but she took a little trip to Paris, a very expensive little trip it was too, and all was well.Her ladyship and I shared a deep sigh of relief.”

“Miss Keith, I didn't come here to smoke a cigarette with you, I came to snitch an invitation card and send it to Mr. Templeton myself.”

“That would have been a very unscrupulous thing to do.”

“Granted. Be a good sport, Miss Keith.Give me a card.He won't come and it'll make the poor old man happy.You've got nothing against him, have you?”

“No, he's always been very civil to me. He's a gentleman, I will say that for him, and that's more than you can say for most of the people who come here and fill their fat bellies at the Princess's expense.”

All important persons have about them someone in a subordinate position who has their ear. These dependents are very susceptible to slights, and, when they are not treated as they think they should be, will by well-directed shafts, constantly repeated, poison the minds of their patrons against those who have provoked their animosity.It is well to keep in with them.This Elliott knew better than anybody and he had always a friendly word and a cordial smile for the poor relation, the old maidservant or the trusted secretary.I was sure he had often exchanged pleasant badinage with Miss Keith and at Christmas had not forgotten to send her a box of chocolates, a vanity case, or a handbag.

“Come on, Miss Keith, have a heart.”

Miss Keith fixed her pince-nez more firmly on her prominent nose.

“I am sure you wish me to do nothing disloyal to my employer, Mr. Maugham, besides which the old cow would fire me if she found out I'd disobeyed her.The cards are on the desk in their envelopes.I am going to look out of the window, partly to stretch my legs which are cramped from sitting too long in one position and also to observe the beauty of the prospect.What happens when my back is turned neither God nor man can hold me responsible for.”

When Miss Keith resumed her seat the invitation was in my pocket.

“It's been nice to see you, Miss Keith，”I said, holding out my hand.“What are you wearing at the fancy-dressparty?”

“I am a minister's daughter, my dear sir，”she replied.“I leave such foolishness to the upper classes. When I have seen that the representatives of the Herald and the Mail get a good supper and a bottle of our second-best champagne, my duties will be terminated and I shall retire to the privacy of my bedchamber with a detective story.”

8

A couple of days later, when I went to see Elliott, I found him beaming.

“Look，”he said，“I've had my invitation. It came this morning.”

He took the card out from under his pillow and showed it to me.

“It's what I told you，”I said.“You see, your name begins with a T. The secretary has evidently only just reached you.”

“I h a v e n'tans we red yet.I'll do it to morrow.”

I had a moment's fright at that.

“Would you like me to answer it for you?I could post it when I leave you.”

“No, why should you?I'm quite capable of answering invitations myself.”

Fortunately, I thought, the envelope would be opened by Miss Keith and she would have the sense to suppress it. Elliott rang the bell.

“I want to show you my costume.”

“You're not thinking of going, Elliott?”

“Of course I am. I haven't worn it since the Beaumont's ball.”

Joseph answered the bell and Elliott told him to bring the costume. It was in a large flat box, wrapped in tissue paper.There were long white silk hose, padded trunks of cloth of gold slashed with white satin, a doublet to match, a cloak, a ruff to wear round the neck, a flat velvet cap, and a long gold chain from which hung the order of the Golden Fleece.I recognized it as a copy of the gorgeous dress worn by Philip the Second in Titian's portrait at the Prado, and when Elliott told me it was exactly the costume the Count de Lauria had worn at the wedding of the King of Spain with the Queen of England I could not but think that he was giving rein to his imagination.

On the following morning while I was having breakfast I was called to the telephone. It was Joseph to tell me that Elliott had had another bad attack during the night and the doctor, hurriedly summoned, doubted whether he would last through the day.I sent for the car and drove over to Antibes.I found Elliott unconscious.He had resolutely refused to have a nurse, but I found one there, sent for by the doctor from the English hospital between Nice and Beaulieu, and was glad to see her.I went out and telegraphed to Isabel.She and Gray were spending the summer with the children at the inexpensive seaside resort of La Baule.It was a long journey and I was afraid they would not get to Antibes in time.Except for her two brothers, whom he had not seen for years, she was Elliott's only living relative.

But the will to live was strong in him, or it may be that the doctor's medicaments were effective, for during the course of the day he rallied. Though shattered, he put on a bold front and amused himself by asking the nurse indecent questions about her sex life.I stayed with him most of the afternoon, and next day, on going to see him again, found him, though very weak, sufficiently cheerful.The nurse would only let me stay with him a short time.I was worried at not having received an answer to my telegram.Not knowing Isabel's address at La Baule I had sent it to Paris and feared that the concierge had delayed to forward it.It was not till two days later that I got a reply to say that they were starting at once.As ill luck would have it, Gray and Isabel were on a motor trip in Brittany and had only just had my wire.I looked up the trains and saw that they could not arrive for at least thirty-six hours.

Early next morning Joseph called me again to tell me that Elliott had had a very bad night and was asking for me. I hurried over.When I arrived Joseph took me aside.

“Monsieur will excuse me if I speak to him on a delicate subject，”he said to me.“I am of course a freethinker andbelieve all religion is nothing but a conspiracy of the priests to gain control over the people, but Monsieur knows what women are. My wife and the chambermaid insist that the poor gentleman should receive the last sacraments and evidently the time is growing short.”He looked at me in rather a shamefaced way.“And the fact remains, one never knows, perhaps it is better, if one's got to die, to regularize one's situation with the Church.”

I understood him perfectly. However freely they mock, most Frenchmen, when the end comes, prefer to make their peace with the faith that is part of their blood and bones.

“Do you want me to suggest it to him?”

“If Monsieur would have the goodness.”

It was not a job I much fancied, but after all Elliott had been for many years a devout Catholic, and it was fitting that he should conform to the obligations of his faith. I went up to his room.He was lying on his back, shrivelled and wan, but perfectly conscious.I asked the nurse to leave us alone.

“I'm afraid you're very ill, Elliott，”I said.“I was wondering, I was wondering if you wouldn't like to see a priest?”

He looked at me for a minute without answering.

“D'you mean to say I'm going to die?”

“Oh, I hope not. But it's just as well to be on the safe side.”

“I understand.”

He was silent. It is a terrible moment when you have to tell someone what I had just told Elliott.I could not look at him.I clenched my teeth because I was afraid I was going to cry.I was sitting on the edge of the bed, facing him, with my arm outstretched for support.

He patted my hand.

“Don't be upset, my dear fellow. Noblesse oblige, you know.”

I laughed hysterically.

“You ridiculous creature, Elliott.”

“That's better. Now call up the bishop and say that I wish to make my confession and receive Extreme Unction.I would be grateful if he'd send the Abbé Charles.He’s a friend of mine.”

The Abbé Charles was the bishop’s vicar general whom I had occasion to mention before.I went downstairs and telephoned.I spoke to the bishop himself.

“Is it urgent?”he asked.

“Very.”

“I will attend to it at once.”

The doctor arrived and I told him what I had done. He went up with the nurse to see Elliott and I waited on the ground floor in the dining-room.It is only twenty minutes'drive from Nice to Antibes and little more than half an hour later a black sedan drew up at the door.Joseph came to me.

“C'est Monseigneur en personne, Monsieur，”he said in a flurry.“It's the bishop himself.”

I went out to receive him. He was not as usual accompanied by his vicar general, but, why I did not know, by a young abbé who bore a casket that contained, I supposed, the utensils needed to administer the sacrament.The chauffeur followed with a shabby black valise.The bishop shook hands with me and presented his companion.

“How is our poor friend?”

“I'm afraid he's very ill, Monseigneur.”

“Will you be so obliging as to show us into a room where we can enrobe?”

“The dining-room is here, Monseigneur, and the drawing-room is on the next floor.”

“The dining-room will do very well.”

I ushered him in. Joseph and I waited in the hall.Presently the door opened and the bishop came out, followed by the abbé holding in both hands the chalice surmounted by a little platter on which lay the consecrated wafer.They were covered by a cambric napkin so fine that it was transparent.I had never seen the bishop but at a dinner or luncheonparty, and a very good trencherman he was, who enjoyed his food and a glass of good wine, telling funny and sometimes ribald stories with verve.He had struck me then as a sturdy, thickset man of no more than average height.Now, in surplice and stole, he looked not only tall, but stately.His red face, puckered as a rule with malicious yet kindly laughter, was grave.There was in his appearance nothing left of the cavalry officer he had once been；he looked, what indeed he was, a great dignitary of the Church.I was hardly surprised to see Joseph cross himself.The bishop inclined his head in a slight bow.

“Conduct me to the sick man，”he said.

I made way for him to ascend the stairs before me, but he bade me precede him. We went up in solemn silence.I entered Elliott's room.

“The bishop has come himself, Elliott.”

Elliott struggled to raise himself to a sitting position.

“Monseigneur, this is an honour I did not venture to expect.”

“Do not move, my friend.”The bishop turned to the nurse and me.“Leave us.”And then to the abbé：“I will call you when I am ready.”

The abbé glanced around and I guessed that he was looking for a place to set down the chalice.I pushed aside the tortoiseshell-backed brushes on the dressing-table.The nurse went downstairs and I led the abbé into the adjoining room which Elliott used as a study.The windows were open to the blue sky and he went over and stood by one of them.I sat down.A race of Stars was in progress and their sails gleamed dazzling white against the azure.A big schooner with a black hull, her red sails spread, was beating up against the breeze towards the harbour.I recognized her for a lobster boat, bringing a catch from Sardinia to supply the gala dinners at the casinos with a fish course.Through the closed door I could hear the muffled murmur of voices.Elliott was making his confession.I badly wanted a cigarette, but feared the abbé would be shocked if I lit one.He stood motionless, looking out, a slender young man, and his thick waving black hair, his fine dark eyes, his olive skin revealed his Italian origin.There was the quick fire of the South in his aspect and I asked myself what urgent faith, what burning desire had caused him to abandon the joys of life, the pleasures of his age, and the satisfaction of his senses, to devote himself to the service of God.

Suddenly the voices in the next room were still and I looked at the door. It was opened and the bishop appeared.

“Venez，”he said to the priest.

I was left alone. I heard the bishop's voice once more and I knew he was saying the prayers that the Church has ordained should be said for the dying.Then there was another silence and I knew that Elliott was partaking of the body and the blood of Christ.From I know not what feeling, inherited, I suppose, from far-away ancestors, though not a Catholic I can never attend Mass without a sense of tremulous awe when the little tinkle of the servitor's bell informs me of the Elevation of the Host；and now, similarly, I shivered as though a cold wind ran through me, I shivered with fear and wonder.The door was opened once more.

“You may come in，”said the bishop.

I entered. The abbé was spreading the cambric napkin over the cup and the little gilt plate on which the consecrated wafer had lain.Elliott’s eyes shone.

“Conduct Monseigneur to his car，”he said.

We descended the stairs. Joseph and the maids were waiting in the hall.The maids were crying.There were three of them and one after the other they came forward and, dropping to their knees, kissed the bishop's ring.He blessed them with two fingers.Joseph's wife nudged him and he advanced, fell to his knees too, and kissed the ring.The bishop smiled faintly.

“You are a freethinker, my son?”

I could see Joseph making an effort over himself.

“Yes, Monseigneur.”

“Do not let it trouble you. You have been a good and faithful servant to your master.God will overlook the errorsof your understanding.”

I went out into the street with him and opened the door of his car. He gave me a bow as he stepped in and smiled indulgently.

“Our poor friend is very low. His defects were of the surface；he was generous of heart and kindly towards his fellow men.”

9

Thinking that Elliott might want to be alone after the ceremony in which he had taken part, I went up to the drawing-room and began to read, but no sooner had I settled myself than the nurse came in to tell me that he wanted to see me. I climbed the flight of stairs to his room.Whether owing to a shot that the doctor had given him to help him to support the Ordeal before him or whether from the excitement of it, he was calmly cheerful and his eyes were bright.

“A great honour, my dear fellow，”he said.“I shall enter the kingdom of heaven with a letter of introduction from a prince of the Church. I fancy that all doors will be open to me.”

“I'm afraid you'll find the company very mixed，”I smiled.

“Don't you believe it, my dear fellow. We know from Holy Writ that there are class distinctions in heaven just as there are on earth.There are seraphim and cherubim, archangels and angels.I have always moved in the best society in Europe and I have no doubt that I shall move in the best society in heaven.Our Lord has said：The House of my Father hath many mansions.It would be highly unsuitable to lodge the hoi polloi in a way to which they're entirely unaccustomed.”

I suspected that Elliott saw the celestial habitations in the guise of the châteaux of a Baron de Rothschild with eighteenth-century panelling on the walls, Buhl tables, marquetry cabinets, and Louis Quinze suites covered with their original petit-point.

“Believe me, my dear fellow，”he went on after a pause，“there'll be none of this damned equality in heaven.”

He dropped off quite suddenly into a doze. I sat down with a book.He slept off and on.At one o'clock the nurse came in to tell me that Joseph had luncheon ready for me.Joseph was subdued.

“Fancy Monseigneur the Bishop coming himself. It is a great honour he has done our poor gentleman.You saw me kiss his ring?”

“I did.”

“It's not a thing I would have done of myself！I did it to satisfy my poor wife.”

I spent the afternoon in Elliott's room. In the course of it a telegram came from Isabel to say that she and Gray would arrive by the Blue Train next morning.I could hardly hope they would be in time.The doctor came.He shook his head.Towards sunset Elliott awoke and was able to take a little nourishment.It seemed to give him a momentary strength.He beckoned to me and I went up to the bed.His voice was very weak.

“I haven't answered Edna's invitation.”

“Oh, don't bother about that now, Elliott.”

“Why not?I've always been a man of the world；there's no reason why I should forget my manners as I'm leaving it. Where is the card?”

It was on the chimney piece and I put it in his hand, but I doubt whether he could see it.

“You'll find a pad of writing paper in my study. If you'll get it I'll dictate my answer.”

I went into the next room and came back with writing materials. I sat down by the side of his bed.

“Are you ready?”

“Yes.”

His eyes were closed, but there was a mischievous smile on his lips and I wondered what was coming.

“Mr. Elliott Templeton regrets that he cannot accept Princess Novemali's kind invitation owing to a previousengagement with his Blessed Lord.”

He gave a faint, ghostly chuckle. His face was of a strange blue-white, ghastly to behold, and he exhaled the nauseating stench peculiar to his disease.Poor Elliott who had loved to spray himself with the perfumes of Chanel and Molyneux.He was still holding the purloined invitation card and, thinking it incommoded him, I tried to take it out of his hand, but he tightened his grip on it.I was startled to hear him speak quite loudly.

“The old bitch，”he said.

These were the last words he spoke. He sank into a coma.The nurse had been up with him all the previous night and looked very tired, so I sent her to bed, promising to call her if necessary, and said I would sit up.There was indeed nothing to do.I lit a shaded lamp and read till my eyes ached and then, turning it off, I sat in darkness.The night was warm and the windows wide open.At regular intervals the flash of the lighthouse swept the room with a passing glimmer.The moon, which when full would look upon the vacuous, noisy gaiety of Edna Novemali's fancy-dress party, set, and in the sky, a deep, deep blue, the countless stars shone with their terrifying brilliance.I think I may have dropped off into a light sleep, but my senses were still awake, and I was suddenly startled into intense consciousness by a hurried, angry sound, the most awe-inspiring sound anyone can hear, the death rattle.I went over to the bed and by the gleam of the lighthouse felt Elliott's pulse.He was dead.I lit the lamp by his bedside and looked at him.His jaw had fallen.His eyes were open and before closing them I stared into them for a minute.I was moved and I think a few tears trickled down my cheeks.An old, kind friend.It made me sad to think how silly, useless, and trivial his life had been.It mattered very little now that he had gone to so many parties and had hobnobbed with all those princes, dukes, and counts.They had forgotten him already.

I saw no reason to wake the exhausted nurse, so I returned to my chair by the window. I was asleep when she came in at seven.I left her to do whatever she thought fit and had breakfast, then I went to the station to meet Gray and Isabel.I told them that Elliott was dead, and since there was no room for them in his house asked them to stay with me, but they preferred to go to a hotel.I went back to my own house to have a bath, shave, and change.

In the course of the morning Gray called me to say that Joseph had given them a letter addressed to me that Elliott had entrusted to him. Since it might contain something for my eyes alone I said I would drive over at once, and so less than an hour later I once more entered the house.The letter, marked on the envelope：To be delivered immediately after my death, contained instruc-tions for his obsequies.I knew that he had set his heart on being buried in the church that he had built and I had already told Isabel.He wished to be embalmed and mentioned the name of the firm to which the commission should be given.“I have made inquiries，”he continued，“and I am informed that they make a very good job of it.I trust you to see that it is not scamped.I desire to be dressed in the dress of my ancestor the Count de Lauria, with his sword by my side and the order of the Golden Fleece on my breast.I leave the choice of my coffin to you.It should be unpretentious but suitable to my posi-tion.In order to give no one unnecessary trouble I desire that Thomas Cook and Son should make all arrangements for the transportation of my remains and that one of their men should accompany the coffin to its final resting-place.”

I remembered that Elliott had said he wanted to be buried in that fancy dress of his, but I had taken it for a passing whim and hadn't thought he meant it seriously. Joseph was insistent that his wishes be carried out and there seemed no reason why they should not be.The body was duly embalmed and then I went with Joseph to dress it in those absurd clothes.It was a gruesome business.We slipped his long legs into the white silk hose and pulled the cloth-of-gold over them.It was a job to get his arms through the sleeves of the doublet.We fixed the great starched ruff and draped the satin cape over his shoulders.Finally we placed the flat velvet cap on his head and the collar of the Golden Fleece round his neck.The embalmer had rouged his cheeks and reddened his lips.Elliott, the costume too large now for his emaciated frame, looked like a chorus man in an early opera of Verdi's.The sad Don Quixote of a worthless purpose.When the undertaker's men had put him in the coffin I laid the property sword down the length of his body, between his legs, with his hands on the pommel as I have seen the sword laid on the sculptured tomb of a Crusader.

Gray and Isabel went to Italy to attend the funeral.

CHAPTER SEVEN

1

One morning, six months later, in April, I was busy writing in my study on the roof of my house at Cap Ferrat when a servant came up to say that the police of St. Jean（my neighbouring village）were below and wished to see me.I was vexed at being interrupted and could not imagine what they wanted.My conscience was at ease and I had already given my subscription to the Benevolent Fund.In return I had received a card, which I kept in my car so that if I was stopped for exceeding the speed limit or found parked on the wrong side of a street I could unostentatiously let it be seen while producing my driving licence and so escape with an indulgent caution.I thought it more likely then that one of my servants had been the victim of an anonymous denunciation, that being one of the amenities of French life, because her papers were not in order；but being on good terms with the local cops, whom I never allowed to leave my house without a glass of wine to speed them on their way, I anticipated no great difficulty.But they, for they worked in pairs, had come on a very different errand.

After we had shaken hands and inquired after our respective healths, the senior of the two-he was called a brigadier and had one of the most imposing moustaches I ever saw-fished a notebook out of his pocket. He turned over the pages with a dirty thumb.

“Does the name Sophie Macdonald say something to you?”he asked.

“I know a person of that name，”I replied cautiously.

“We have just been in telephonic communication with the police station at Toulon and the chief inspector requests you to betake yourself there（vous prie de vous y rendre）without delay.”

“For what reason?”I asked.“I am only slightly acquainted with Mrs. Macdonald.”

I jumped to the conclusion that she had got into trouble, probably connected with opium, but I didn't see why I should be mixed up in it.

“That is not my affair. There is no doubt that you have had dealings with this woman.It appears that she has been missing from her lodgings for five days and a body has been fished out of the harbour which the police have reason to believe is hers.They want you to identify it.”

A cold shiver passed through me. I was not, however, too much surprised.It was likely enough that the life she led would incline her in a moment of depression to put an end to herself.

“But surely she can be identified by her clothes and her papers.”

“She was found stark naked with her throat cut.”

“Good God！”I was horrified. I reflected for an instant.For all I knew the police could force me to go and I thought I had better submit with good grace.“Very well.I will take the first train I can.”

I looked up a timetable and found that I could catch one that would get me to Toulon between five and six. The brigadier said he would phone the chief inspector to that effect and asked me on my arrival to go straight to the police station.I did no more work that morning.I packed a few necessary things in a suitcase and after luncheon drove to the station.

2

On presenting myself at the headquarters of the Toulon police I was immediately ushered into the room of the chief inspector. He was sitting at a table, a heavy, swarthy man of saturnine appearance whom I took to be a Corsican.He threw me, perhaps from force of habit, a suspicious glance；but noticing the ribbon of the Legion of Honour, which I had taken the precaution to put in my buttonhole, with an unctuous smile asked me to sit down and proceeded to make profuse apologies for having been obliged to incommode a person of my distinction.Adopting a similar tone, I assured him that nothing could make me happier than to be of service to him.Then we got down to brass tacks and he resumed his brusque, rather insolent manner.Looking at some papers before him, he said：

“This is a dirty business. It appears that the woman Macdonald had a very bad reputation.She was a drunkard, a dope fiend, and a nymphomaniac.She was in the habit of sleeping not only with sailors off the ships, but with the riffraff of the town.How does it happen that a person of your age and respectability should be acquainted with such a character?”

I was inclined to tell him that it was no business of his, but from a diligent perusal of hundreds of detective stories I have learnt that it is well to be civil with the police.

“I knew her very little. I met her when she was a girl in Chicago, where she afterwards married a man of good position.I met her again in Paris a year or so ago through friends of hers and mine.”

I had been wondering how on earth he had ever connected me with Sophie, but now he pushed forward a book.

“This volume was found in her room. If you will kindly look at the dedication you will see that it hardly suggests that your acquaintance with her was as slight as you claim.”

It was the translation of that novel of mine that she had seen in the bookshop window and asked me to write in. Under my own name I had written“Mignonne, allons voir si la rose，”because it was the first thing that occurred to me.It certainly looked a trifle familiar.

“If you are suggesting that I was her lover, you are mistaken.”

“It would be no affair of mine，”he replied, and then with a gleam in his eye：“And without wishing to say anything offensive to you I must add that from what I have heard of her proclivities I should not say you were her type. But it is evident that you would not address a perfect stranger as mignonne.”

“That line, monsieur le commissaire, is the first line of a celebrated poem by Ronsard, whose works I am certain are familiar to a man of your education and culture. I wrote it because I felt sure she knew the poem and would recall the following lines, which might suggest to her that the life she was leading was, to say the least of it, indiscreet.”

“Evidently I have read Ronsard at school, but with all the work I have to do I confess that the lines you refer to have escaped my memory.”

I repeated the first stanza and knowing very well he had never heard the poet's name till I mentioned it, had no fear that he would recall the last one which can hardly be taken as an incitement to virtue.

“She was apparently a woman of some education. We found a number of detective stories in her room and two or three volumes of poetry.There was a Baudelaire and a Rimbaud and an English volume by someone called Eliot.Is heknown?”

“Widely.”

“I have no time to read poetry. In any case I cannot read English.If he is a good poet it is a pity he doesn't write in French, so that educated people could read him.”

The thought of my chief inspector reading The Waste Land filled me with pleasure. Suddenly he pushed a snapshot towards me.

“Have you any idea who that is?”

I immediately recognized Larry. He was in bathing trunks, and the photograph, a recent one, had been taken, I guessed, during the summer part of which he had spent with Isabel and Gray at Dinard.My first impulse was to say I did not know, for I wanted nothing less than to get Larry mixed up in this hateful business, but I reflected that if the police discovered his identity my assertion would look as if I thought there was something to hide.

“He's an American citizen called Laurence Darrell.”

“It was the only photograph found among the woman's effects. What was the connexion between them?”

“They both came from the same village near Chicago. They were childhood friends.”

“But this photograph was taken not long ago, I suspect at a seaside resort in the North or on the West of France. It would be easy to discover the exact place.What is he, this individual?”

“An author，”I said boldly. The inspector slightly raised his bushy eyebrows and I guessed that he did not attribute high morality to members of my calling.“Of independent means，”I added to make it sound more respectable.

“Where is he now?”

Again I was tempted to say I didn't know, but again decided it would only make things awkward if I did. The French police may have many faults, but their system enables them to find anyone they want without delay.

“He's living at Sanary.”

The inspector looked up and it was clear that he was interested.

“Where?”

I had remembered Larry telling me that Auguste Cottet had lent him his cottage and on my return at Christmas I had written to ask him to come and stay with me for a while, but as I fully expected he had refused. I gave the inspector his address.

“I'll telephone to Sanary and have him brought here. It might be worth while to question him.”

I could not but see that the inspector thought that here might be a suspect, but I was only inclined to laugh；I was convinced that Larry could easily prove that he had nothing to do with the affair. I was anxious to hear more about Sophie's lamentable end, but the inspector only told me in somewhat greater detail what I already knew.Two fishermen had brought the body in.It was a romantic exaggeration of my local policeman's that it was stark naked.The murderer had left girdle and brassière.If Sophie had been dressed in the same way as I had seen her he had had to strip her only of her slacks and her jersey.There was nothing to identify her and the police had inserted a description in the local paper.This had brought a woman to the station who kept a small rooming-house in a back street, what the French call a maison de passe, to which men could bring women or boys.She was an agent of the police, who liked to know who frequented her house and what for.Sophie had been turned out of the hotel on the quay at which she was living when I ran across her because her conduct was more scandalous than even the tolerant proprietor could put up with.She had offered to engage a room with a tiny sitting-room beside it in the house of the woman I have just mentioned.It was more profitable to let it two or three times a night for short periods, but Sophie offered to pay so handsomely that the woman consented to rent it to her by the month.She came to the police station now to state that her tenant had been absent for several days, she had not bothered, thinking she had gone for a trip to Marseilles or to Villefranche, where ships of the British fleet had lately arrived, an event that always attracted women, young and old, from all along the coast；but she had read the description of the deceased in the paper and thought it might apply to her tenant.She had been taken to see the body and after a trifling hesitation declared it was that of Sophie Macdonald.

“But if the body's been identified, what do you want me for?”

“Madame Bellet is a woman of high honourability and excellent character，”said the inspector，“but she may have reasons for identifying the dead woman that we do not know；and in any case I think she should be seen by someone who was more closely connected with her so that the fact may be confirmed.”

“Do you think you have any chance of catching the murderer?”

The inspector shrugged his massive shoulders.

“Naturally we are making inquiries. We have questioned a number of persons at the bars she used to go to.She may have been killed out of jealousy by a sailor whose ship has already left the port, or by a gangster for whatever money she had on her.It appears that she always had on her a sum that would seem large to a man of that sort.It may be that some people have a strong suspicion who the culprit is, but in the circles she moved it is unlikely that anyone will speak unless it is to his advantage.Consorting with the bad characters she did, such an end as she has come to was only too probable.”

I had nothing to say to this. The inspector asked me to come next morning at nine o'clock, by which time he would have seen“this gentleman of the photograph”，after which a policeman would take us to the nearest morgue to see the body.

“And how about burying her?”

“If after identifying the body you claim it as friends of the deceased and are prepared to undertake the expense of the funeral yourselves, you will receive the necessary authorization.”

“I'm sure that Mr. Darrell and I would like to have it as soon as possible.”

“I quite understand. It is a sad story and it is better that the poor woman should be laid to rest without delay.And that reminds me that I have here the card of an undertaker who will arrange the matter for you on reasonable terms and with dispatch.I will just write a line on it so that he may give you every attention.”

I was pretty sure he would get a rake-off on the amount paid, but I thanked him warmly, and when he had ushered me out with every expression of esteem I went forthwith to the address on the card. The undertaker was brisk and businesslike.I chose a coffin, neither the cheapest nor the most expensive, accepted his offer to get me two or three wreaths from a florist of his acquaintance—“to save monsieur a painful duty and out of respect for the dead，”he said-and arranged for the hearse to be at the morgue at two o'clock next day.I could not but admire his efficiency when he told me that I need not trouble to see about a grave, he would do all that was necessary, and“Madame was a Protestant, I assume，”furthermore he would, if I wished it, have a pastor waiting at the cemetery to read the burial service.But since I was a stranger and a foreigner he was sure that I would not take it amiss if he asked me to be good enough to give him a cheque in advance.He named a larger sum than I had foreseen, evidently expecting me to beat him down, and I discerned a look of surprise, perhaps even of disappointment, on his face when I took out my cheque-book and wrote out a cheque without demur.

I took a room at an hotel and next morning returned to the police station. I was kept waiting for some time and then was bidden to go into the chief inspector's office.I found Larry, looking grave and distressed, sitting in the chair I had sat in the day before.The inspector greeted me with joviality.I might have been a long-lost brother.

“Well, mon cher monsieur, your friend has answered all the questions it was my duty to put him with the utmost frankness. I have no reason to disbelieve his statement that he had not seen this poor woman for eighteen months.He has accounted for his movements during the last week in a perfectly satisfactory manner as well as for the fact that his photograph was found in her room.It was taken at Dinard and he happened to have it in his pocket one day when he was lunching with her.I have had excellent reports of the young man from Sanary and I am besides, I say it without vanity, a good judge of character myself；I am convinced that he is incapable of committing a crime of this nature.I have ventured to offer him my sympathy that a friend of his childhood, brought up with all the advantages of a healthy family life, should have turned out so badly.But such is life.And now, my dear gentlemen, one of my men will accompany you to the morgue and when you have identified the body, your time is at your own disposal.Go and have agood lunch.I have a card here of the best restaurant in Toulon and I will just write a word on it which will assure you of the patron's best attention.A good bottle of wine will do you both good after this harrowing experience.”

He was by now positively beaming with good will. We walked to the mortuary with a policeman.They were not doing a lively business in that establishment.There was a body on one slab only.We went up to it and the mortuary attendant uncovered the head.It was not a pleasant sight.The sea water had taken the curl out of the dyed silvery hair and it was plastered dankly on the skull.The face was horribly swollen and it was ghastly to look at, but there was no doubt that it was Sophie's.The attendant drew the covering sheet down to show us what we both would rather not have seen, the horrid gash across the throat that stretched from ear to ear.

We went back to the station. The chief inspector was busy, but we said what we had to say to an assistant；he left us and presently returned with the necessary papers.We took them to the undertaker.

“Now let's have a drink，”I said.

Larry hadn't uttered a word since we left the police station to go to the mortuary except on our return there to declare that he identified the body as that of Sophie Macdonald. I led him down to the quay and we sat in the café in which I had sat with her.A strong mistral was blowing and the harbour, usually so smooth, was flecked with white foam.The fishing-boats were gently rocking.The sun shone brightly and, as always happens with a mistral, every object in sight had a peculiar sparkling sharpness as though you looked at it through glasses focused with more than common accuracy.It imparted a nerve-racking, throbbing vitality to everything in sight.I drank a brandy and soda, but Larry never touched the one I had ordered for him.He sat in moody silence and I did not disturb him.

Presently I looked at my watch.

“We'd better go and have something to eat，”I said.“We've got to be at the mortuary at two.”

“I'm hungry, I didn't have any breakfast.”

Having judged from his appearance that the chief inspector knew where the food was good, I took Larry to the restaurant he had told us of. Knowing that Larry seldom ate meat, I ordered an omelette and a grilled lobster and then, asking for the wine list, chose, again following the policeman's counsel, a vintage wine.When it appeared I poured out a glass for Larry.

“You damn well drink it，”I said.“It may suggest a topic of conversation to you.”

He obediently did as I bade him.

“Shri Ganesha used to say that silence also is conversation，”he murmured.

“That suggests a jolly social gathering of intellectual dons at the University of Cambridge.”

“I'm afraid you'll have to stand the racket of this funeral by yourself，”he said.“I haven't any money.”

“I'm quite prepared to do that，”I answered. Then the implication of his remark hit me.“You haven't been and gone and done it really?”

He did not answer for a moment. I noticed the whimsical, teasing glint in his eyes.

“You haven't got rid of your money?”

“Every cent except what I need to last me till my ship comes in.”

“What ship?”

“The man who has the next cottage to mine at Sanary is the Marseilles agent of a line of freighters that run from the Near East to New York. They've cabled him from Alexandria that they've had to put off a couple of sick men there from a ship that's coming on to Marseilles and asked him to get two more to take their place.He's a buddy of mine and he's promised to get me on.I’m giving him my old Citroën as a parting present.When I step on board I shall have nothing but the clothes I stand up in and a few things in a grip.”

“Well, it's your own money. You're free, white, and twenty-one.”

“Free is the right word. I've never been happier or felt more independent in my life.When I get to New York I shall have my wages and they'll carry me on till I can get a job.”

“What about your book?”

“Oh, it's finished and printed. I made a list of people I wanted it sent to-you ought to get a copy in a day or two.”

“Thank you.”

There was not much more to say and we finished our meal in amiable silence. I ordered coffee.Larry lit a pipe and I a cigar.I looked at him thoughtfully.He felt my eyes upon him and threw me a glance；his own were lit with an impish twinkle.

“If you feel like telling me I'm a damned fool, don't hesitate. I wouldn't in the least mind.”

“No, I don't particularly feel like that. I was only wondering if your life wouldn't have fallen into a more perfect pattern if you'd married and had children like everybody else.”

He smiled. I must have remarked twenty times on the beauty of his smile, it was so cosy, trustful, and sweet.It reflected the candour, the truthfulness of his charming nature；but I must do so once again, for now, besides all that, there was in it something rueful and tender.

“It's too late for that now. The only woman I've met whom I could have married was poor Sophie.”

I looked at him with amazement.

“Can you say that after all that's happened?”

“She had a lovely soul, fervid, aspiring, and generous. Her ideals were greathearted.There was even at the end a tragic nobility in the way she sought destruction.”

I was silent. I did not know what to make of these strange assertions.

“Why didn't you marry her then?”I asked.

“She was a child. To tell you the truth, it never occurred to me when I used to go over to her grandfather's and we read poetry together under the elm tree that there was in that skinny brat the seed of spiritual beauty.”

I could not but think it surprising that at this juncture he made no mention of Isabel. He could not have forgotten that he had been engaged to her and I could only suppose that he regarded the episode as a foolishness without consequence of two young things not old enough to know their own minds.I was ready to believe that the suspicion had never so much as fugitively crossed his mind that ever since she had been eating her heart out for him.

It was time for us to go. We walked to the square where Larry had left his car, very shabby now, and drove to the mortuary.The undertaker was as good as his word.The businesslike efficiency with which everything was accomplished, under that garish sky, with the violent wind bending the cypresses of the cemetery, added a last note of horror to the proceedings.When it was all over the undertaker shook hands with us cordially.

“Well, gentlemen, I hope you are satisfied. It went very well.”

“Very well，”I said.

“Monsieur will not forget that I am always at his disposition if he has need of my services. Distance is no object.”

I thanked him. When we came to the gate of the cemetery Larry asked me if there was anything further I wanted him for.

“Nothing.”

“I'd like to get back to Sanary as soon as possible.”

“Drop me at my hotel, will you?”

We spoke never a word as we drove. When we arrived I got out.We shook hands and he went off.I paid my bill, got my bag, and took a taxi to the station.I too wanted to get away.

3

A few days later I started for England. My intention had been to go straight through, but after what had happened I particularly wanted to see Isabel, so I decided to stop in Paris for twenty-four hours.I wired to her to ask if I could come in late in the afternoon and stay to dinner；when I reached my hotel I found a note from her to say that she and Gray were dining out, but that she would be very glad to see me if I would come not before half past five as she had afitting.

It was chilly and raining off and on quite heavily, so that I presumed Gray would not have gone to Mortefontaine to play golf. This did not suit me very well, since I wanted to see Isabel alone, but when I arrived at the apartment the first thing she said was that Gray was at the Travellers playing bridge.

“I told him not to be too late if he wanted to see you, but we're not dining till nine, which means we needn't get there before nine-thirty, so we've got plenty of time for a good talk. I've got all sorts of things to tell you.”

They had sublet the apartment, and the sale of Elliott's collection was to take place in a fortnight. They wanted to attend it and were moving into the Ritz.Then they were sailing.Isabel was selling everything except the modern pictures that Elliott had had in his house at Antibes.Though she didn't care much for them she thought quite rightly that they would be a prestige item in their future home.

“It's a pity poor Uncle Elliott wasn't more advanced. Picasso, Matisse, and Rouault, you know.I suppose his pictures are good in their way, but I'm afraid they'll seem rather old-fashioned.”

“I wouldn't bother about that if I were you. Other painters will come along in a few years and Picasso and Matisse won't seem any more up to date than your Impressionists.”

Gray was in process of concluding his negotiations and with the capital provided by Isabel was to enter a flourishing business as vice-president. It was connected with oil and they were to live at Dallas.

“The first thing we shall have to do is to find a suitable house. I want a nice garden so that Gray can have somewhere to potter about when he comes home from work and I must have a really large living-room so that I can entertain.”

“I wonder yon don't take Elliott's furniture over with you.”

“I don't think it would be very suitable. I shall make it all modern, with perhaps just a little touch of Mexican here and there to give it a note.As soon as I get to New York I'll find out who is the decorator everyone's going to now.”

Antoine, the manservant, brought in a tray with an array of bottles, and Isabel, always tactful, knowing that nine men out of ten are convinced they can mix a better cocktail than any woman（and they're right），asked me to shake a couple. I poured out the gin and the Noilly-Prat and added the dash of absinthe that transforms a dry Martini from a nondescript drink to one for which the gods of Olympus would undoubtedly have abandoned their home-brewed nectar, a beverage that I have always thought must have been rather like Coca-Cola.I noticed a book on the table as I handed Isabel her glass.

“Hello！”I said.“Here's Larry's book.”

“Yes, it came this morning, but I've been so busy, I had a thousand things to do before lunch and I was lunching out and I was at Molyneux's this afternoon. I don't know when I shall have a moment to get down to it.”

I thought with melancholy how an author spends months writing a book, and may be puts his heart's blood into it, and then it lies about unread till the reader has nothing else in the world to do. It was a volume of three hundred pages nicely printed and neatly bound.

“I suppose you know Larry has been in Sanary all the winter. Did you see him by any chance?”

“Yes, we were at Toulon together only the other day.”

“Were you?What were you doing there?”

“Burying Sophie.”

“She's not dead?”cried Isabel.

“If she hadn't been we'd have had no plausible reason to bury her.”

“That's not funny.”She paused for a second.“I'm not going to pretend I'm sorry. A combination of drink and dope, I suppose.”

“No, she had her throat cut and was thrown into the sea stark naked.”

Like the brigadier at St. Jean I found myself impelled a trifle to exaggerate her undress.

“How horrible！Poor thing. Of course leading the life she did she was bound to come to a bad end.”

“That's what the commissaire de police at Toulon said.”

“Do they know who did it?”

“No, but I do. I think you killed her.”

She gave me a stare of amazement.

“What are you talking about?”Then with the ghost of a chuckle：“Guess again；I have a cast-iron alibi.”

“I ran across her at Toulon last summer. I had a long talk with her.”

“Was she sober?”

“Sufficiently. She told me how it happened that she'd disappeared so unaccountably just a few days before she was going to be married to Larry.”

I noticed Isabel's face stiffen. I proceeded to tell her exactly what Sophie had told me.She listened warily.

“I've thought of her story a good deal since then and the more I've thought about it the more convinced I am that there's something fishy about it. I've lunched here twenty times and you never have liqueurs for luncheon.You'd been lunching alone.Why should there have been a bottle of zubrovka on the tray with the coffee-cup?”

“Uncle Elliott had just sent it to me. I wanted to see if I liked it as much as when I'd had it at the Ritz.”

“Yes, I remember how you raved about it then. I was surprised, as you never drink liqueurs anyway；you're much too careful of your figure for that.I had at the time an impression that you were trying to tantalize Sophie.I thought it was just malice.”

“Thank you.”

“On the whole you're very good at keeping appointments. Why should you have gone out when you were expecting Sophie for something so important to her and interesting to you as a fitting of her wedding dress?”

“She told you that herself. I wasn't happy about Joan's teeth.Our dentist is very busy and I just had to take the time he could give me.”

“When one goes to a dentist one makes the next appointment before leaving.”

“I know. But he called me up in the morning and said he had to break it, but could give me three o'clock that afternoon instead, so of course I jumped at it.”

“Couldn't the governess have taken Joan?”

“She was scared, poor darling, I felt she'd be happier if I went with her.”

“And when you came back and found the bottle of zubrovka three parts empty and Sophie gone, weren't you rather surprised?”

“I thought she'd got tired of waiting and gone on to Molyneux's by herself. I couldn't make it out when I went there and they told me she hadn't been.”

“And the zubrovka?”

“Well, I did notice that a good deal had been drunk. I thought Antoine had drunk it and I very nearly spoke to him about it, but Uncle Elliott was paying for him and he was a friend of Joseph's, so I thought I'd better ignore it.He's a very good servant and if he takes a little nip now and then who am I to blame him?”

“What a liar you are, Isabel.”

“Don't you believe me?”

“Not for a moment.”

Isabel got up and walked over to the chimney-piece. There was a wood fire and it was pleasant on that dreary day.She stood with one elbow on the mantel-shelf in a graceful attitude which it was one of her most charming gifts to be able to assume without any appearance of intention.Like most French women of distinction she dressed in black in the daytime, which peculiarly suited her rich colouring, and on this occasion she wore a dress the expensive simplicity of which displayed her slender figure to advantage.She puffed at her cigarette for a minute.

“There's no reason why I shouldn't be perfectly frank with you. It was most unfortunate that I had to go out and of course Antoine should never have left the liqueur and the coffee-things in the room.They ought to have been takenaway when I went out.When I came back and saw the bottle was nearly empty of course I knew what had happened, and when Sophie disappeared I guessed she'd gone off on a bat.I didn't say anything about it because I thought it would only distress Larry, and he was worried enough as it was.”

“Are you sure the bottle wasn't left there on your explicit instructions?”

“Quite.”

“I don't believe you.”

“Don't then.”She flung the cigarette viciously into the fire. Her eyes were dark with anger.“All right, if you want the truth you can have it and to hell with you.I did it and I'd do it again.I told you I'd stick at nothing to prevent her from marrying Larry.You wouldn't do a thing, either you or Gray.You just shrugged your shoulders and said it was a terrible mistake.You didn't care a damn.I did.”

“If you'd left her alone she'd be alive now.”

“Married to Larry and he'd be utterly miserable. He thought he'd make a new woman of her.What fools men are！I knew that sooner or later she'd break down.It stuck out a mile.You saw yourself when we were all lunching together at the Ritz how jittery she was.I noticed you looking at her when she was drinking her coffee；her hand was shaking so, she was afraid to take the cup with one hand, she had to put both her hands to it to get it up to her mouth.I noticed her watching the wine when the waiter filled our glasses；she followed the bottle with those horrible washed-out eyes of hers like a snake following the fluttering of a new-fledged chick and I knew she'd give her soul for a drink.”

Isabel faced me now, her eyes flashing with passion, and her voice was harsh. She couldn't get the words out quickly enough.

“The idea came to me when Uncle Elliott made all that fuss about that damned Polish liqueur. I thought it beastly, but I pretended it was the most wonderful stuff I'd ever tasted.I was certain that if she got a chance she'd never have the strength to resist.That's why I took her to the dress show.That's why I offered to make her a present of her wedding dress.That day, when she was going to have the last fitting, I told Antoine I'd have the zubrovka after lunch and then I told him I was expecting a lady and to ask her to wait and offer her some coffee and to leave the liqueur in case she fancied a glass.I did take Joan to the dentist’s, but of course we hadn’t an appointment and he couldn’t see us, so I took her to a newsreel.I’d made up my mind that if I found Sophie hadn’t touched the stuff I’d make the best of things and try to be friends with her.That’s true, I swear it.But when I got home and saw the bottle I knew I’d been right.She’d gone and I’d have bet any money in the world she’d gone for good.”

Isabel was actually panting when she finished.

“That's more or less what I imagined had happened，”I said.“You see, I was right；you cut her throat as surely as if you'd drawn the knife across it with your own hands.”

“She was bad, bad, bad. I'm glad she's dead.”She threw herself into a chair.“Give me a cocktail, damn you.”

I went over and mixed another.

“You are a mean devil，”she said as she took it from me. Then she allowed herself to smile.Her smile was like a child's that knows it's been naughty, but thinks it can wheedle you by its ingenuous charm not to be cross.“You won't tell Larry, will you?”

“I wouldn't dream of it.”

“Cross your heart?Men are so untrustworthy.”

“I promise you I won't. But even if I wanted to, I shouldn't have an opportunity as I don't suppose I shall ever see him again in my life.”

She sat bolt upright.

“What do you mean?”

“At this moment, he's on a freighter, either as a deck hand or a stoker, on his way to New York.”

“You don't mean that?What a strange creature he is！He was up here a few weeks ago for something to do with his book that he had to look up at the public library, but he never said a word about going to America. I'm glad；that meanswe shall see him.”

“I doubt it. His America will be as remote from your America as the Gobi desert.”

Then I told her what he had done and what he intended to do. She listened to me open-mouthed.Consternation was written on her face.She interrupted me now and then with an interjection“He's crazy.He's crazy.”When I had finished she hung her head and I saw two tears trickle down her cheeks.

“Now I really have lost him.”

She turned away from me and wept, leaning her face against the back of the chair. Her lovely face was twisted with the grief she did not care to hide.There was nothing I could do.I didn't know what vain, conflicting hopes she had cherished that my tidings had finally shattered.I had a vague notion that to see him occasionally, at least to know that he was part of her world, had been a bond of union, however tenuous, that his action had finally severed so that she knew herself for ever bereft.I wondered what unavailing regret afflicted her.I thought it would do her good to cry.I picked up Larry's book and looked at the table of contents.My copy had not arrived when I left the Riviera and I could not now hope to get it for several days.It was not in the least the sort of thing I expected.It was a collection of essays of about the same length as those in Lytton Strachey's Eminent Victorians, upon a number of famous persons.The choice he had made puzzled me.There was one on Sulla, the Roman dictator who, having achieved absolute power, resigned it to return to private life；there was one on Akbar, the Mogul conqueror who won an empire；there was one on Rubens, there was one on Goethe, and there was one on the Lord Chesterfield of the Letters.It was obvious that each of the essays had needed a tremendous amount of reading and I was no longer surprised that it had taken Larry so long to produce this book, but I could not see why he had thought it worth while to give it so much time or why he had chosen those particular men to study.Then it occurred to me that every one of them in his own way had made a supreme success of life and I guessed that this was what had interested Larry.He was curious to see what in the end it amounted to.

I skimmed a page to see how he wrote. His style was scholarly, but lucid and easy.There was nothing in it of the pretentiousness or the pedantry that too often characterizes the writing of the amateur.One could tell that he had frequented the best authors as assiduously as Elliott Templeton frequented the nobility and gentry.I was interrupted by a sigh from Isabel.She sat up and finished with a grimace the cocktail which was now luke-warm.

“If I don't stop crying my eyes'll be terrible and we're going out to dinner tonight.”She took a mirror out of her bag and looked at herself anxiously.“Yes, half an hour with an ice bag over my eyes, that's what I want.”She powdered her face and reddened her lips. Then she looked at me reflectively.“Do you think any the worse of me for what I did?”

“Would you care?”

“Strange as it may seem to you, I would. I want you to think well of me.”

I grinned.

“My dear, I'm a very immoral person，”I answered.“When I'm really fond of anyone, though I deplore his wrongdoing it doesn't make me less fond of him. You're not a bad woman in your way and you have every grace and every charm.I don't enjoy your beauty any the less because I know how much it owes to the happy combination of perfect taste and ruthless determination.You only lack one thing to make you completely enchanting.”

She smiled and waited.

“Tenderness.”

The smile died on her lips and she gave me a glance that was totally lacking in amenity, but before she could collect herself to reply Gray lumbered into the room. In the three years he had been in Paris Gray had put on a good many pounds, his face had grown redder, and his hair was thinning rapidly, but he was in rude health and in high spirits.He was unaffectedly pleased to see me.Gray's conversation was composed of clichés.However shop-worn, he uttered them with an obvious conviction that he was the first person to think of them.He never went to bed, but hit the hay, where he slept the sleep of the just；if it rained, it rained to beat the band and to the very end Paris to him was Gay Paree.But he was so kindly, so unselfish, so upright, so reliable, so unassuming that it was impossible not to like him.I had areal affection for him.He was excited now over their approaching departure.

“Gosh, it'll be great to get into harness again，”he said.“I'm feeling my oats already.”

“Is it all settled then?”

“I haven't signed on the dotted line yet, but it's on ice. The fella I'm going in with was a room-mate of mine at college, and he's a good scout, and I'm dead sure he wouldn’t hand me a lemon.But as soon as we get to New York I’ll fly down to Texas to give the outfit the once-over, and you bet I’ll keep my eyes peeled for a nigger in the woodpile before I cough up any of Isabel’s dough.”

“Gray's a very good businessman, you know，”she said.

“I wasn't raised in a barn，”he smiled.

He went on to tell me at somewhat excessive length about the business he was entering, but I understood little of such matters and the only concrete fact I gathered was that he stood a good chance of making a lot of money. He grew so interested in what he was saying that presently he turned to Isabel and said：

“Look here, why shouldn't we cut this lousy party and us three go and have a slap-up dinner at the Tour d'Argent by ourselves?”

“Oh, darling, we can't do that. They're giving the party for us.”

“Anyhow, I couldn't come now，”I interrupted.“When I heard you were fixed up this evening I called up Suzanne Rouvier and arranged to take her out.”

“Who's Suzanne Rouvier?”asked Isabel.

“Oh, one of Larry's gals，”I said to tease her.

“I always suspected Larry had a little floozie tucked away somewhere，”said Gray, with a fat chuckle.

“Nonsense，”snapped Isabel.“I know all about Larry's sex life. There isn't any.”

“Well, let's have one more drink before we part，”said Gray.

We had it and then I said good-bye to them. They came into the hall with me and while I was putting on my coat Isabel slipped her arm through Gray's and, nestling up to him, looked into his eyes with an expression that imitated very well the tenderness I had accused her of lacking.

“Tell me, Gray-frankly-do you think I'm hard-boiled?”

“No, darling, far from it. Why, has anybody been saying you were?”

“No.”

She turned her head away so that he shouldn't see, and in a manner that Elliott would certainly have thought very unladylike put out her tongue at me.

“It's not the same thing，”I murmured as I stepped out of the door and closed it behind me.

4

When I passed through Paris again the Maturins had gone and other people lived in Elliott's apartment. I missed Isabel.She was good to look at and easy to talk to.She was quick on the uptake and bore no malice.I have never seen her since.I am a poor and dilatory correspondent and Isabel was no letter writer.If she could not communicate with you by telephone or telegram she did not communicate with you.I had a Christmas card from her that Christmas with a pretty picture on it of a house with a Colonial portico surrounded by live oaks, which I took to be the house of the plantation that they had been unable to sell when they wanted the money and which now they were probably willing to keep.The postmark showed that it had been posted at Dallas, so I concluded that the deal had gone through satisfactorily and they were settled there.

I have never been to Dallas, but I suppose that, like other American cities I know, it has a residential district within easy motoring distance of the business section and the country club where the affluent have fine houses in large gardens with a handsome view of hill or dale from the living-room windows. In such a district and in such a house, furnishedfrom cellar to attic in the latest mode by the most fashionable decorator in New York, Isabel certainly dwells.I can only hope that her Renoir, her flower piece by Manet, her landscape by Monet, and her Gauguin do not look too dated.The dining-room is doubtless of a convenient size for the women's luncheons which she gives at frequent intervals and at which the wine is good and the food superlative.Isabel learnt a great deal in Paris.She would not have settled on the house unless she had seen at a glance that the living-room would do very well for the sub-deb dances which it would be her pleasant duty to give as her daughters grew older.Joan and Priscilla must be now of a marriageable age.I am sure that they have been admirably brought up；they have been sent to the best schools and Isabel has taken care that they should acquire the accomplishments that must make them desirable in the eyes of eligible young men.Though I suppose Gray by now is still a little redder in the face, more jowly, balder, and a good deal heavier, I can't believe that Isabel has changed.She is still more beautiful than her daughters.The Maturins must be a great asset to the community and I have little doubt that they are as popular as they deserve to be.Isabel is entertaining, gracious, complaisant, and tactful；Gray, of course, is the quintessence of the Regular Guy.

5

I continued to see Suzanne Rouvier from time to time until an unexpected change in her condition caused her to leave Paris and she too went out of my life. One afternoon, roughly two years after the events that I have just related, having spent an hour pleasantly browsing over the books in the galleries of the Odéon and with nothing to do for a while, I thought I would call on Suzanne.I had not seen her for six months.She opened the door, a palette on her thumb and a paintbrush between her teeth, clad in a smock covered with paint.

“Ah, c'est vous, cher ami. Entrez, je vous en prie.”

I was a little surprised at this formal address, for generally we spoke to one another in the second person singular, but I stepped into the small room that served both as living-room and studio. There was a canvas on the easel.

“I'm so busy, I don't know which way to turn, but sit down and I will go on with my work. I haven't a moment to waste.You wouldn't believe it, but I'm giving a one-man show at Meyerheim’s, and I have to get thirty canvases ready.”

“At Meyerheim's?That's wonderful. How on earth have you managed that?”

For Meyerheim is not one of those fly-by-night dealers in the Rue de la Seine who have a small shop that is always on the verge of closing for lack of money to pay the rent. Meyerheim has a fine gallery on the moneyed side of the Seine and he has an international reputation.An artist whom he takes up is well on the way to fortune.

“Monsieur Achille brought him to see my work and he thinks I have a lot of talent.”

“À d’autres, ma vieille，”I replied, which I think can best be translated by：“Tell that to the marines, old girl.”

She threw me a glance and giggled.

“I'm going to be married.”

“To Meyerheim?”

“Don't be an idiot.”She put down her brushes and her palette.“I've been working all day and I deserve a rest. Let us have a little glass of porto and I'll tell you all about it.”

One of the less agreeable features of French life is that you are apt to be pressed to drink a glass of vinegary port at an unseasonable hour. You must resign yourself to it.Suzanne fetched a bottle and two glasses, filled them, and sat down with a sigh of relief.

“I've been standing for hours and my varicose veins are aching. Well, it's like this.Monsieur Achille's wife died at the beginning of this year.She was a good woman and a good Catholic, but he did not marry her from inclination, he married her because it was good business, and though he esteemed and respected her it would be an exaggeration to say that her death left him inconsolable.His son is suitably married and is doing well in the firm and now a marriage has been arranged between his daughter and a count.Belgian it is true, but authentic, with a very pretty château in theneighbourhood of Namur.Monsieur Achille thought his poor wife would not wish the happiness of two young people to be deferred on her account, so the marriage, notwithstanding that they are in mourning, is to take place as soon as the financial arrangements are completed.Evidently Monsieur Achille will be lonely in that large house at Lille, and needs a woman not only to minister to his comfort, but also to run the important establishment necessary to his position.To cut a long story short, he has asked me to take the place of his poor wife, for as he very reasonably said：‘I married for the first time to eliminate competition between two rival firms, and I do not regret it, but there is no reason why I should not marry the second time to please myself.’”

“I congratulate you，”said I.

“Evidently I shall miss my liberty. I have enjoyed it.But one has to think of the future.Between ourselves, I don't mind telling you that I shall never see forty again.Monsieur Achille is at a dangerous age；where should I be if he suddenly took it into his head to run after a girl of twenty?And then there is my daughter to think of.She is now sixteen and promises to be as beautiful as her father.I have given her a good education.But it is no good denying facts that stare you in the face；she has neither the talent to be an actress nor the temperament to be a whore like her poor mother：I ask you then, what has she to look forward to?A secretaryship or a job in the post office.Monsieur Achille has very generously agreed that she should live with us and has promised to give her a handsome dot so that she can make a good marriage.Believe me, my dear friend, people can say what they like, but marriage still remains the most satisfactory profession a woman can adopt.Obviously when my daughter's welfare was concerned I could not hesitate to accept a proposition even at the cost of certain satisfactions which in any case, as the years go by, I should find it more difficult to obtain；for I must tell you that when I am married I propose to be of a ferocious virtue（d'une vertu farouche），for my long experience has convinced me that the only basis of a happy marriage is complete fidelity on both sides.”

“A highly moral sentiment, my pretty，'I said.“And will Monsieur Achille continue to make his fortnightly visits to Paris on business?”

“Oh, la la, for whom do you take me, my little one?The first thing I said to Monsieur Achille when he asked for my hand was：‘Now listen, my dear, when you come to Paris for your board meetings it is understood that I come too. I am not going to trust you here by yourself.'‘You cannot imagine that I am capable of committing follies at my age，'he answered.‘Monsieur Achille，'I said to him，‘you are a man in the prime of life and no one knows better than I that you have a passionate temperament.You have a fine presence and a distinguished air.You have everything to please a woman；in short I think it better that you should not be exposed to temptation.'In the end he agreed to give up his place on the board to his son, who will come to Paris instead of his father.Monsieur Achille pretended to think me unreasonable, but he was in point of fact enormously flattered.”Suzanne gave a sigh of satisfaction.“Life would be even harder for us poor women than it is if it were not for the unbelievable vanity of men.”

“All that is very fine, but what has it got to do with your having a one-man show at Meyerheim's?”

“You are a little stupid today, my poor friend. Have I not told you for years that Monsieur Achille is a highly intelligent man?He has his position to think of and the people of Lille are censorious.Monsieur Achille wishes me to take the place in society which as the wife of a man of his importance it will be my right to occupy.You know what these provincials are, they love to poke their long noses in other people's affairs, and the first thing they will ask is：who is Suzanne Rouvier?Well, they will have their answer.She is the distinguished painter whose recent show at the Meyerheim Gallery had a remarkable and well-deserved success.‘Madame Suzanne Rouvier, the widow of an officer in the colonial infantry, has with the courage characteristic of our Frenchwomen for some years supported herself and a charming daughter deprived too soon of a father's care by means of her talent, and we are happy to know that the general public will soon have the opportunity to appreciate the delicacy of her touch and the soundness of her technique at the galleries of the ever perspicacious Monsieur Meyerheim.'”

“What gibberish is that?”I said, pricking up my ears.

“That, my dear, is the advance publicity that Monsieur Achille is putting out. It will appear in every paper inFrance of any consequence.He has been magnificent.Meyerheim's terms were onerous, but Monsieur Achille accepted them as if they were a bagatelle.There will be a champagne d'honneur at the private view and the Minister of Fine Arts, who is under an obligation to Monsieur Achille, will open the exhibition with an eloquent speech in which he will dwell upon my virtues as a woman and my talent as a painter and which he will end with the declaration that the state, whose duty and privilege it is to reward merit, has bought one of my pictures for the national collections.All Paris will be there and Meyerheim is looking after the critics himself.He has guaranteed that their notices will be not only favourable but lengthy.Poor devils, they earn so little, it is a charity to give them an opportunity of making something on the side.”

“You've deserved it all, my dear. You've always been a good sort.”

“Et ta soeur，”she replied, which is untranslatable.“But that's not all. Monsieur Achille has bought in my name a villa on the coast at St.Rafael, so I shall take my place in Lille society not only as a distinguished artist, but as a woman of property.In two or three years he is going to retire and we shall live on the Riviera like gentlefolks（comme des gens bien）.He can paddle in the sea and catch shrimps while I devote myself to my art.Now I will show you my pictures.”

Suzanne had been painting for several years and she had worked through the manner of her various lovers to arrive at a style of her own. She still could not draw, but she had acquired a pretty sense of colour.She showed me landscapes that she had painted while staying with her mother in the province of Anjou, bits of the gardens at Versailles and the forest at Fontainebleau, street scenes that had taken her fancy in the suburbs of Paris.Her painting was vaporous and unsubstantial, but it had a flowerlike grace and even a certain careless elegance.

There was one picture that took my fancy and because I thought she would be pleased I offered to buy it. I cannot remember whether it was called A Glade in the Forest or The White Scarf and subsequent examination has left me uncertain to this day.I asked the price, which was reasonable, and said I would take it.

“You're an angel，”she cried.“My first sale. Of course you can't have it till after the show, but I'll see that it gets into the papers that you've bought it.After all, a little publicity can do you no harm.I'm glad you’ve chosen that one, I think it’s one of my best.”She took a hand mirror and looked at the picture in it.“It has charm，”she said, screwing up her eyes.“No one can deny that.Those greens-how rich they are and yet how delicate！And that white note in the middle, that is a real find；it ties the picture together, it has distinction.There’s talent there, there can be no doubt of it, there’s real talent.”

I saw that she was already a long way on the road to being a professional painter.

“And now, my little one, we've gossiped long enough, I must get back to work.”

“And I must be going，”I said.

“À propos, is that poor Larry still among the Redskins?”

For that was the disrespectful way in which she was accustomed to refer to the inhabitants of God's Own Country.

“So far as I know.”

“It must be hard for someone like him who is so sweet and gentle. If one can believe the movies life is terrible over there with all those gangsters and cowboys and Mexicans.Not that those cowboys haven't physical attraction which says something to you.Oh, la la！But it appears that it is excessively dangerous to go out into the streets of New York without a revolver in your pocket.”

She came to the door to see me out and kissed me on both cheeks.

“We've had some good times together. Keep a good recollection of me.”

6

This is the end of my story. I have heard nothing of Larry, nor indeed did I expect to.Since he generally did what he proposed, I think it likely that on his return to America he got a job in a garage and then drove a truck till he had acquired the knowledge he wanted of the country from which he had for so many years absented himself.When he had done that he may very well have carried out his fantastic suggestion of becoming a taxi driver：true, it was only arandom idea thrown across a café table in jest, but I shouldn’t be altogether surprised if he had put it into effect；and I have never since taken a taxi in New York without glancing at the driver on the chance that I might meet Larry’s gravely smiling, deep-set eyes.I never have.War broke out.He would have been too old to fly, but he may be once more driving a truck, at home or abroad；or he may be working in a factory.I should like to think that in his leisure hours he is writing a book in which he is trying to set forth whatever life has taught him and the message he has to deliver to his fellow-men；but if he is, it may be long before it is finished.He has plenty of time, for the years have left no mark on him and to all intents and purposes he is still a young man.

He is without ambition and he has no desire for fame；to become anything of a public figure would be deeply distasteful to him；and so it may be that he is satisfied to lead his chosen life and be no more than just himself. He is too modest to set himself up as an example to others；but it may be he thinks that a few uncertain souls, drawn to him like moths to a candle, will be brought in time to share his own glowing belief that ultimate satisfaction can only be found in the life of the spirit, and that by himself following with selflessness and renunciation the path of perfection he will serve as well as if he wrote books or addressed multitudes.

But this is conjecture. I am of the earth, earthy；I can only admire the radiance of such a rare creature, I cannot step into his shoes and enter into his innermost heart as I sometimes think I can do with persons more nearly allied to the common run of men.Larry has been absorbed, as he wished, into that tumultuous conglomeration of humanity, distracted by so many conflicting interests, so lost in the world's confusion, so wishful of good, so cocksure on the outside, so diffident within, so kind, so hard, so trustful, and so cagey, so mean and so generous, which is the people of the United States.That is all I can tell of him：I know it is very unsatisfactory；I can't help it.But as I was finishing this book, uneasily conscious that I must leave my reader in the air and seeing no way to avoid it, I looked back with my mind's eye on my long narrative to see if there was any way in which I could devise a more satisfactory ending；and to my intense surprise it dawned upon me that without in the least intending to I had written nothing more or less than a success story.For all the persons with whom I have been concerned got what they wanted：Elliott social eminence；Isabel an assured position backed by a substantial fortune in an active and cultured community；Gray a steady and lucrative job, with an office to go to from nine till six every day；Suzanne Rouvier security；Sophie death；and Larry happiness.And however superciliously the highbrows carp, we the public in our heart of hearts all like a success story；so perhaps my ending is not so unsatisfactory after all.

第一章

巡航小帆船奈莉号的帆并未抖动，便抛下了锚，稳稳停好。潮涨了，风也几乎止住，她要往下游开去，只能静等退潮。

泰晤士河的入海口在我们面前铺展开，像一个起点，通向一条漫无尽头的航道。远远望去，海天交融，浑然一体。从那片明亮之处，随潮飘来艘艘大帆船，那些久晒成棕褐色的帆，仿佛寂然不动，红红地堆起来，帆顶尖尖的，斜杠上明灭着清漆的幽光。烟迷的河岸低低地延伸开去，渐渐消失不见。格雷夫森德[1]上空，天色黯然，再往深处更是仿佛凝成一片愁云惨雾，死寂地摧压在世上最大，亦最伟大的城市之上[2]。

公司的主任是我们的船长兼东家。他站在船头向海远望时，我们四人热切地盯着他的背影。在整条河流上，唯这一幕最富于航海色彩。他像引航员，水手的依靠。然而他的工作竟不在那个明亮的河湾上，而在他身后那片压得人喘不过气的阴云之下。

在我们之间，我之前也说过，有着海洋的纽带。除了在漫长的别离中，让我们彼此牵挂，它还有一种奇效，令我们足以忍受彼此信口说出的奇闻逸事，甚至是荒诞离奇的信念。那位律师——最讨人喜欢的长者——因为资历深厚和德高望重，占用了船上唯一一个靠垫，并躺在唯一一条小毯子上。会计之前拿了一盒多米诺骨牌出来，正在拿牌搭房子。马洛盘腿坐在船尾，背倚着后桅。他双颊深陷，面色蜡黄，腰身挺拔，像个苦行僧。他双臂下垂，双掌外翻，又像尊神像。主任见锚抓稳了，便放了心，走到船尾，在我们中间坐下。大家只懒洋洋地说了几句话，然后船上一片沉静。不知怎的我们没有玩起多米诺骨牌来。我们仿佛满腔心事，对什么都无情无绪，只管睁着眼睛出神。夜幕徐徐降临，安宁静谧，晚霞烂漫。水面泛起粼粼波光，柔静细碎，天空了无纤尘，温和辽阔，澄净生光。埃塞克斯沼泽地上那片薄雾，像流彩溢辉的轻纱，从内陆高地的树林上垂下，柔柔地笼罩住低处的河岸，清透的褶皱隐隐飘拂。只有西方那片摧压着上游的阴云，在一分一秒地益发阴沉下去，仿佛因为落日的步步逼近赫然而怒。

终于，太阳沿着弧线悄然沉没，从灿白变成滞红，光消热散，像突然熄灭一般，撞死在那片芸芸众生头顶上的阴云里。

水上风光顿改。褪去光辉的静谧变得更为深沉。夜幕降临之时，这条古老的河流安然地置身于它宽阔的河道里。千百年来，它惠及了居于两岸的种族，而现在，它顺着这一条通往天涯海角的水道，从容而庄严地，柔柔舒展着身躯。在我们眼中，这是一条令人肃然起敬的河流，照亮它的并不是朝生暮死的浮丽日光，而是庄严的记忆之光，历经世世代代，永不磨灭。事实上，对于一个俗语里心怀敬畏和爱慕“漂洋而生”[3]的人来说，途经泰晤士河下游，最能触发过往的万丈豪情。潮汐日日复年年地来来去去，载着回家安歇或者出海战斗的人和船进进出出，堆积起层层叠叠的记忆。这个国家引以为傲的人物，它无一不认识并接待过，从弗朗西斯·德雷克[4]先生到约翰·富兰克林[5]先生，所有了不起的骑士——所有那些海上的英雄好汉，不论是否拥有真正的骑士头衔。它接送过每一艘名声远扬的船只，它们的名字耀若珠宝，在时间长河的黑夜里熠熠生辉。从那一艘双侧船舱满载财宝归来，引得女皇殿下亲临迎接，荣冠一时的金鹿号[6]，到外出征讨其他地方却一别茫茫的埃里布斯号与恐怖号。它都在场，亲眼见证。人和船从德特福特、格林尼治和埃利斯出发——冒险者和殖民者，皇家帆船和商人的商船，船长、海军将领、暗地里从东方贸易分羹的“走私犯”，还有东印度舰队雇佣的“将军”。追名逐利之徒都从那条河流出发，利剑随身，也常常携带火炬。他们是该国强权的使者，手握神圣之火的火种。天下闻名的一切，都曾经随着这条河流的退潮漂浮出海，流去某片未知陆地的神秘之中……人类的梦想，共和国的种子，帝国的幼芽。

日落了，河面上天色渐暗，岸边亮起星星灯火。三条腿的查普曼灯塔矗立在海滨泥地上，发着强光。船的灯火流过河道——许许多多的灯光，热热闹闹地沿着河道上上下下。西边的上游处，坐落着那个大得畸形的城市，那不祥的标记仍在上空盘桓不去——残阳里的阴霾，群星下的鬼火。

“而这个地方，”马洛突然说，“也一直是世界上最黑暗的地方之一。”

他是我们之中唯一一个仍然“漂洋而生”的人。若要指责他，最多也只能说他没有代表自己的阶级。他是一个海员，却也是一个流浪者。然而几乎所有海员的生活，如果可以这样说的话，都有点安土重迁。他们满脑子都是居家的知识，去哪里都带着自己的家——船。他们也总是走不出自己的国家——海洋。船和船之间差异不大，海洋则处处相同。在千篇一律的环境中，异国的海岸，陌生的脸孔，截然不同的生活，浮光掠影般流转着，相隔的不是一层神秘的面纱，却是带着淡淡轻侮的蒙昧，因为对海员而言，唯有海洋本身是神秘的，它主宰他们的存在，和命运之神一般喜怒无常。而大陆的所有秘密，等辛劳的工作结束后，上岸闲逛一回，或肆意狂欢一番，便一览无遗，但一般他们对那些秘密兴味索然。海员随口说出来的奇闻逸事有着一种简单粗暴的直率，其中含义一目了然，仿佛碎果壳里无处藏身的果仁。然而听说马洛是个例外（如果不提他胡诌杜撰的癖好）。对他而言，事件的意义并非像果仁藏在壳内一样，隐潜于字里行间，而是像灼热的光生出来的烟雾，披裹在外，犹如朦胧的月晕，有时候正是仰仗了森冷的月光才得以显现。

大家似乎对他说的话全然不觉得惊讶。马洛平时就这么说话。大家报以沉默，甚至都懒得发牢骚。他马上接着说下去，慢条斯理地——

“我想起那个古远的时代，罗马人初次踏上这片土地，一千九百年前——好像还只是几天前的事……这条河的明光可以追溯到——你说那些骑士？倒也不错。但这道光像火光蹿过平原，像闪电掠过乌云。我们就活在那忽明忽灭的光明之中——但愿只要老旧的地球还转得动，它就别彻底熄掉！但这里昨天是黑暗的。试想一下那种感觉，一个船长正指挥着一艘漂亮体面的——叫什么名字来着？——地中海三桨战船，却突然被调往北方，不得不匆匆忙忙地穿越高卢地区去指挥这些罗马军团的小船——军团的士兵也一定是些能工巧匠，这些小船他们几个月就能造出成百上千艘来，如果书本没有骗人。想象一下，假如那船长来到这个鬼地方——世界的尽头，海洋是铅灰的，天空是烟黑的，船差不多和六角手风琴一样不听使唤——指挥小船沿着这条河驶往上游，船上装满了军需品，或者订购的货物，或者随便你们高兴说的什么。沙岸、沼泽、森林、土人——对一个文明人来说，能吃的太少太珍贵，能喝的也只有泰晤士河的河水。这里没有法洛尼恩葡萄酒[7]，上岸也没有。军营孤零零地散落在荒野中偶尔可见，就像针掉在干草堆里一样——冷啊，雾啊，狂风暴雨啊，疾病啊，流亡啊，还有死亡——死神就潜伏在空气里、水里和丛林里。他们肯定像苍蝇一样死在这里。噢，是的——那船长活下来了，毫无疑问还大捞了一笔，当然其实他也没太拿这当回事儿，也许不过就是过后向人吹嘘吹嘘当年他有多么英勇。他们可都是浑身是胆的好汉，面对那片黑暗时毫不怯场。而也许正是因为他一心想着升职，认为只要在罗马有靠得住的好兄弟，并能够熬过这该死的气候，有朝一日总能被调到拉文纳[8]去指挥舰队，才能一直那么兴冲冲的。又或者，你们想象一下一个体面的年轻市民，穿着古罗马的托加袍——大概是赌骰子输得够呛——跟着某个市长、税务员或者甚至是生意人跑出来做发财梦。在某片沼泽地上岸，用两条腿穿过森林，走到某个内地的驿站时，突然发现身边是一片凶残的荒凉，凶残得毫无商量，把他围得密不透风——所有那些谜一样的生活，充满了在森林里、丛林里和土人心里蠢蠢欲动的野性。这些谜团无法破解，他只能一直活在这不可理喻而又可恶至极的环境之中。然而这环境也有一种令他着迷的魔力，憎恶的魔力——想想那不断增长的悔恨，那逃走的渴望，那令人彻骨地疲倦的厌恶，那自暴自弃和那怨毒。”

他暂时闭上了口。

“不过要注意，”他又开始道，弯起一条手臂，外翻手掌，加上在身前盘着的双腿，他的姿势像个正在布道的佛像，只不过穿的是欧式衣服，身下也没有莲花座——“要注意，我们现在谁也无法准确地对此感同身受了。多亏了效率——对效率的虔诚追求。不过这些家伙也算不上是什么大人物，真的。他们算不上是殖民者，他们的所谓行政只不过是去压榨当地人，我怀疑。他们是征服者，需要的只是残忍的武力——拥有这种力量没什么好夸耀的，别人只是意外地比他们弱小罢了。他们为达目的，从不放过能抢走的一切。这不过是肆无忌惮的暴力抢劫，罪加一等的大肆屠杀，他们却疯了一样前仆后继——要对付黑暗，倒也合该如此。征服土地，大多数情况下意味着抢走它，从那些肤色与我们不同，或者是鼻梁比我们稍稍塌一点的人那里。要是刨根问底，就会发现这不够光彩。能给它挽回一点面子的，就只有这样一个信念，隐藏在征服背后的，不是虚伪的感情，而是一个信念，以及对这个信念毫无私心的信仰——可以供奉起来，对它鞠躬，献上牺牲品的……”

他打住了。河上流转着团团小小的火焰，绿色的，红色的，白色的，你追我赶，争先恐后，分分合合，交相穿越——然后或快或慢地分道扬镳。在无眠的河流上，夜色越益沉暗，那巨城的交通夜以继日。我们静观其变——潮水涨停之前我们无事可做。沉默了许久之后，他用迟疑的声音说：“你们这些家伙应该还记得吧？我的确曾经干过一阵子内河水手。”这下好了，在开始退潮之前，马洛又要讲一段他那些不了了之的经历，想不听都不行。

“我不想给你们唠叨我那些老掉牙的个人经历，”他说，他属于那一类往往不知道听众最想听什么的人，这句话正好暴露出这类人的弱点，“然而，要理解它对我产生的影响，你们得先知道我是怎样跑到了那儿去，看见了什么，怎样沿河而上去到那个地方，初次见到了那个可怜的家伙。那是航海的尽头，也是我这辈子经历的最高潮。不知怎的，它好像点亮了我身边的一切——也点亮了我的思想。它很令人哀伤——也很悲惨——怎么看也很普通——也不明不白。就是不明不白的。然而它似乎给了我一点启发。”

“你们应该还记得，那时我刚回到伦敦，在跑了很多趟印度洋、太平洋和中国海之后——那是东方的常规航线——这条航线我跑了有六年左右。回到伦敦后，我无所事事，在你们的上班时间去打搅你们工作，上你们家去找麻烦，仿佛我身负神圣的使命，要去教化你们。刚开始很开心，但不久我就感觉闲得烦透了。然后我开始去找一艘船——我想尝试一下地球上最艰苦的工作。但没人理我。我对这个游戏也烦透了。”

“我小时候可喜欢看地图了。我会一连好几个小时盯着南美洲、非洲或者澳洲出神，为那些辉煌光荣的探险伟业心荡神驰。那时地图上有很多空白的空间，每当我看见一处看起来特别诱人的地方（但它们看起来都这样），就会把手指放在上面，说长大后一定要去那里。北极就是其中之一，我记得，不过我还没去过北极，也不打算去了。它的魔力已经消失了。其他空白空间散布在赤道周围和东西半球的各个纬度上。我去过其中一些地方，然后——唔，别谈这个了。但还有一个地方——可以说是最大最空的——我还渴望去看看。”

“确实，它现在已经不再空白。从我小时候起，它就渐渐被填上河流、湖泊和地名。它不再是一块谜样的空白，充满乐趣——一块可以让男孩梦想光荣的空白。它变得一片黑暗。但那里有一条很特别的河，一条巨大的河，你可以在地图上看到它，就像一条硕大无朋的蛇，头淹在海里，身子一动不动地蜷曲着，穿过一片广袤的土地，尾巴消失在内陆深处。当我透过商店的橱窗，看着它的地图时，被深深迷住了，像一只被蛇迷住的鸟——蠢得要命的小鸟。然后我想起来，那条河上有一家大公司，大贸易公司。老天！我暗暗地想，要在那么大一条河上做生意，他们总要用到船吧——他们肯定有汽船！我干吗不试试去应聘船长？我沿着舰队街[9]走啊走，但这个念头一直缠着我。那条蛇弄得我五迷三道的。”

“要知道那是一家欧洲大陆的公司，那个贸易公司。我倒是有很多亲戚住在大陆上，他们说因为那里生活成本低，也不像看起来那么糟糕。”

“我厚颜无耻地去托他们替我打点。对我而言，这完全是一条新的人生道路。我不习惯这一套。我总是用自己的腿，走自己的路，去自己想去的地方。过后我都无法相信自己变成了那样，但是，那会儿——你们瞧——我真是鬼迷心窍，觉得反正我就是要达到目的，不择手段也在所不惜。于是我去托他们替我打点。男人们说完‘我亲爱的老朋友’便全无下文。然后——真难为情——我尝试向女士们下手。我，查利·马洛，打发女人们去替我跑腿——帮我找一份差事。天啊！要怪就怪那个念头。我有一个姨妈，一个可亲的热心人。她给我写信说：‘定然是一件令人愉悦的工作。我必定竭尽所能助你成功。该想法极佳。我认识一位公司高官的太太，和另一位有头面的先生……’等等。她下定决心，不畏艰难，一定要帮我当上内河船长，让我得偿所愿。”

“我得到了那份工作——那是当然的，但比想象中快得多。听说这家公司收到消息，说他们有个船长在和当地人的一场混战中一命呜呼了。真是千载难逢的好机会，这样一来我更加迫不及待要去接替他了。很多个月后，我试图去取回那个船长的尸体，才听说他和当地人嚷嚷起来的原因，是由几只母鸡引发的一场误会。没错，是两只黑母鸡。弗雷斯勒文——那个家伙的名字，一个丹麦人——认为自己在这笔买卖中上当受骗吃了亏，所以冲上岸，抄起一根棍子痛打那个村长。唔，尽管有同事告诉我，弗雷斯勒文是用两条腿行走的生物中最温和沉静的一个，我对这个故事也并不感到丝毫惊讶。他肯定是那样的人。但他已经在外为这崇高的事业打拼了好几年，可能终于感到有必要向别人证明一下他也是有自尊心的，于是他残忍地痛打那个老黑人，当着一大群村民的面，把他们吓得大气不敢出，直到某个男子汉——听说是村长的儿子——听到那个老家伙喊得撕心裂肺的，实在忍无可忍，拿起长矛向那白人试探性地一刺——一下子就刺进了两片肩胛骨之间。全村人马上逃进森林，等着大祸降临，然而，另一方面，本来听命于弗雷斯勒文的汽船慌慌张张地离开了，我相信是轮机手指挥的。过后似乎没有人为弗雷斯勒文的遗体操心，直到我被派去接替他的职位。尽管我不能置之不理，但等到我终于有机会与我的前任相见的时候，从他肋骨之间长出的荒草已经高得足以淹没他的骸骨了。倒也齐全。这一个超自然的人物倒下后，完全没被碰过。村子已经荒废了，那些茅屋张大了黑洞洞的嘴巴，腐烂着，在倒塌了的围栏内东倒西歪。这里肯定横遭了灾劫。村民都消失了。大难当前，疯狂的恐怖情绪在村民之间迅速传播，他们四散狂奔，男人，女人，还有儿童，全都跑进灌木丛中，一去不回。我也不知道后来那些母鸡怎么样了，但说它们为进步事业献了身总还是可以的。然而，多亏了这一桩光荣的事件，我被任命为船长。那时我都还没来得及对得到这个职位心生希望呢。”

“我发了疯似的东奔西走，准备赴任，不到四十八小时就已经穿越英吉利海峡，见到我的雇主，签订好合同。不过短短几个小时，我便到了一个城市，那个城市总是让我想起一个精心粉刷过的巨大坟墓。那当然是一种偏见。我毫不费力就找到了公司的办公地点。它是这座城市的老大，我所遇到的每一个人都和它纠缠不清。他们正盘算着要营建一个海外帝国，通过贸易赚取源源不断的利润。”

“我来到一条阴黑的街道上，狭窄荒凉，房屋都高高的，有无数带百叶窗的窗户，一片死寂，小草从石头之间探出头来，两边都是气派的马车拱道，巨大而沉重的双扇门阴森地半开着。我找到一条门缝溜进去，走上一道打扫得干干净净的楼梯，那楼梯很简陋，像沙漠一样了无生气。我推开碰上的第一扇门，看见两位女士，一胖一瘦，正坐在垫了草垫的扶手椅里织黑毛线。瘦的那个站起来，径直向我走过来——仍然低头织着毛线——她好像是个梦游者，我正想着给她让道，她却站住了，抬起头来看看我。她的衣服平整得像个伞套。她默默转身，把我带进一个候见室。我报上姓名，在房间里东张西望。中央有一张松木桌，墙根散放着普通的椅子，房间一头挂着一张巨大的地图，闪闪发光，上面用彩虹的七色做了密密麻麻的标记。有很多标记成红色的地方——红色任何时候看起来都赏心悦目，因为那意味着实实在在的工作成果。蓝色的地方也非常多，还有一小片绿色，几点橙色，在东海岸则有一小块紫色，表示那些兴高采烈的进步先锋们正在那里大喝令人兴高采烈的拉格啤酒[10]。然而，这些地方我都不想去。我要去标记成黄色的地方，地图的正中央。那条河正好在那儿——勾魂摄魄——阴森狰狞——像一条蛇。啊！门开了，秘书的脑袋露出来，满头白发，一副悲天悯人的表情。他用瘦骨嶙峋的食指把我招呼到密室里去。密室里黑灯瞎火的，中间摆着一张沉重的写字台。我渐渐看清楚写字台后面的人影，白白胖胖，穿着双排扣长礼服。他就是老大。我看他大概五尺六寸高，动动手指头就能调用成百上千万英镑。他和我握手，大概是对我的法语很满意吧，口齿不清地说了句：一路顺风[11]。”

“大约四十五秒后，我又回到了候见室，和那个悲天悯人的秘书待在一起。那个人满怀伤感和同情地让我签了一份文件。我相信自己肯定做出了很多保证，包括不能泄露任何贸易秘密。我本来也没想过要那样做的嘛。”

“我开始感到有些不对劲儿。你们也知道我对这些官方程序很不习惯，而且那种气氛让人觉得不吉利，就好像我被卷入某个阴谋里似的——我也说不清——反正就不是什么好事。从那个房间出来，我觉得轻松多了。那两个女人还在外间紧张地埋头织着黑毛线。不断有人进来，那个年轻一些的走来走去给他们引路。年纪大的那个坐在椅子上。她把平底布拖鞋抵在一个脚炉上，膝上躺着一只猫。她头上包着一块浆过的白布，也看不出是什么材料的，一边脸上有颗疣子，一副银边眼镜架在鼻尖上。她从眼镜上方迅速扫了我一眼，漠然得好像我是空气似的，真没礼貌。又走过去两个年轻人，看起来蠢得要命，却又一脸喜相，她也同样那么冷漠地看了他们一眼，好像她是个很有智慧的人似的。她似乎洞悉我们的一切。我不寒而栗。她仿佛有一种操控命运的神秘力量。在我远赴他乡的时候，常常想起这两个女人，镇守着黑暗的大门，用黑羊毛织着温暖的裹尸布，一个负责带路，不断把人带到没有人认识的地方，另一个瞪着那双冷漠森然的老眼来检查那些愉快而愚蠢的脸蛋。万福！[12]织黑毛线的老人家。即将赴死的将士向您致敬。[13]领教过她这种目光的人，没几个能再见到她——不到一半，远远不到。”

“还要去找医生。‘例行手续而已。’秘书向我保证，好让我放心，好像对于我所有的疑虑，他完全了解，而且深表同情。于是一个歪戴着帽子盖住左眼眉的年轻伙计，大概是个文书吧——公司里肯定有文书，尽管这座房子就跟建在了坟墓里似的，死气沉沉——从楼上某个地方走下来带我去找医生。他穿得又破又旧，一点儿也不讲究。外套袖子上沾着墨水迹，皱巴巴的围巾松垮垮地围在脖子上，下巴像旧靴子的鞋尖一样。时间还早，我提议去喝一杯，他马上喜笑颜开。我们点了苦艾酒[14]，他边喝边把公司的生意吹得天上有地下无，我随口表示好奇，问他为什么不自己出去闯闯。他马上变得又冷淡又严肃。‘借用柏拉图对他门徒说的话，我没看起来那么笨。’他简短地说，好像很壮烈地干了他的酒。我们站起身来。”

“那位老医生给我诊脉时，明显有些心不在焉。‘好，去那儿没问题。’他嘟嘟囔囔地说，然后热切地问我愿不愿意让他量一量我的头。我有些惊讶地说可以，他就拿出一个像卡尺一样的工具，从所有角度把我的头骨量了一遍，仔细地记录下来。他是个小个子，胡子拉碴的，穿着一件很旧的外套，像是工作服，踩着拖鞋，我觉得他是一个对人无害的笨蛋。‘为了科学的发展，凡是要到那里去的人，我都求他们让我量量头盖骨。’他说。‘等他们回来了，您会再量一遍吗？’我问。‘哦，我没见过他们回来，’他说，‘再说了，变化是内在的，对不对？’他笑了，好像自己讲了个隐晦的笑话。‘所以你是要到那里去了。真了不起。有趣极了。’他用锐利的目光扫了我一眼，又记下一条笔记。‘你的家族有精神病史吗？’他用就事论事的语气问道。我气炸了。‘这也是为了科学的发展吗？’‘在科学上，’他说，并没有注意到我有多么生气，‘当场密切关注个人精神状态的变化是很有意义的，但是……’‘您是个精神病学家吗？’我打断他。‘应该每个医生都——多少懂一点儿吧。’那个怪人若无其事地说，‘我有这么一个小观点，麻烦你们这些到那里去的先生们务必帮我证实一下。我们国家有那么多属地，想要什么有什么，我这要求也不算过分。这是我唯一能留给他人的财富。请不要为我的问题生气，但你是我检查的第一个英国人……’我忙告诉他我可一点儿也不具有代表性。‘要是我有，’我说，‘就不会这么没礼貌。’‘你这话够深奥的，不过事实也许并非如此。’他大笑着说，‘避免暴怒，比避免暴晒更重要。慢走。[15]你们英国人是怎么说的来着？再会。啊！再会。慢走。[16]在热带地区，不管遇到什么事情，都要记住保持冷静……’他举起一根食指，以示警告……‘冷静，冷静。慢走。’[17]”

“还要去做一件事情——向我那杰出的姨妈告辞。她见到我，欣喜若狂。我喝了杯茶——之后无数天我都喝不上这么像样的茶了——在一个最最舒服的房间里，那可是贵妇的会客室，你们能想象得出有多舒服它就有多舒服。我们在火炉旁安安静静地聊了很久很久。这时我才知道，她把我推荐给那位高官的夫人，还有天晓得其他多少人，说我天赋非凡——对公司来说简直是天降奇福——是百年不遇的人才。天啊！我不过是要去指挥一条不值几个钱的内河汽船，它的汽笛几乎不要钱！然而，那表明我也是一个名副其实的‘工作人员’，也算是光明的使者，低级传教士。当时书报上和言谈里满是这种蠢话，而那位杰出的女士正好生活在那阵鬼话的浪潮之中，被冲得晕头转向，快连自己是谁都不知道了。她大谈‘帮助那数百万无知的土人戒除陋习’，说个不停，我都要听不下去了。我壮起胆来，暗示说公司就是想赚钱而已。”

“‘我亲爱的查理，你忘了，他们也是通过付出劳动赚取钱财的。’她说，好像很聪明伶俐似的。真是奇怪，女人怎么会这么天真！她们活在自己的世界里，这样的世界从前没有，以后也不会有。它太美好了，就算她们真的建起了这么一个世界，它也熬不过第一个日落。我们男人从创世之日起便坦然对待的某个混账事实，会蹦出来打碎它。”

“完了她拥抱我，嘱咐我要穿上法兰绒上衣，记得常常来信，等等——之后我就走了。在大街上——不知怎的——可奇怪了，我忽然觉得自己是个大骗子。太奇怪了，我这个人向来是接到通知之后二十四小时内就能出发去任何地方的，就跟大多数人过马路一样，不需要思前想后，但有那么一瞬间——面对这么一件区区小事，虽说不上是犹豫不决，我却有点临阵退缩。这么解释最好了：有那么几秒钟，我觉得我要去的是地球的中心，而不是大陆的中心。”

“我坐一艘法国轮船离开，她经停每一个属于公司的混账港口，据我了解就只是为了送士兵和海关官员上岸。我一路盯着海岸看。看着海岸滑过轮船，就像在猜谜。它就在眼前——笑着，皱着眉，欢迎着，宏伟，残忍，无聊，或野蛮，好像一路在无声地对人轻轻说着：来看看我葫芦里卖的是什么药！这片海岸平淡无奇，好像还没修好似的，只是一味的阴森凄凉。那一大片丛林的边缘绿得发黑，镶着白色的海浪，仿佛用尺子画出来的白线，笔直地沿着一片蓝色的海洋延伸开去，薄雾慢慢升上来，遮住海水的闪光。烈日炎炎，陆地仿佛也在放光，冒着水汽，湿淋淋的。白浪里不时冒出一些灰白的斑点，有些顶上飘着旗。是居民点——这些有着几百年历史的居民点，在那片未被开发的辽阔背景下，不过像针尖一般渺小。我们乘风破浪，靠岸，丢下几个士兵；继续前进，在关税站丢下几个海关职员——那些关税站就是些用马口铁做的棚子，支着旗杆，隐没在一片仿佛被上帝遗弃了的荒野中；再丢下几个士兵——大概是要他们去保护那些海关职员吧。听说有些士兵掉到海里淹死了，但似乎没人在意。把他们送到目的地就完事了，我们继续前进。海岸每天看起来都一模一样，我们仿佛在原地打转，但实际上我们已经驶过了许多地方——贸易点——叫什么大巴萨姆啊、小波波啊之类的，这些名字让人想到那些在狰狞的幕布前演出的下流闹剧。乘客的日子百无聊赖，而且我和同行的人没共同语言，别提有多孤单了。那片海洋像被油污了似的，令人昏昏欲睡，加上那永远面目沉暗的海岸，仿佛远离了真实的世界，弄得我情绪低落，整日胡思乱想，简直要发疯。不时传来的海浪声欢快清新，仿佛兄弟的笑语。那自然的声音，有它自己的因缘和含义。忽然一条船从岸边划过来，暂时地将这画面变成了一道现世的风景。黑人们在划桨，远远地就能看见他们那些白得发亮的眼珠。他们大喊大叫，放声歌唱；他们大汗淋漓；他们的脸像古怪的面具——这些家伙啊；但他们有骨头，有肌肉，有一种狂野的生命力，动作散发着无穷的力量，就像岸边的海浪一样自然真实。他们仿佛天然地就应该出现在那里。看着他们，但觉心旷神怡。那一阵子我会感到自己又回到了那个无遮无掩的现实世界，但那种感觉终归是短暂的，总有点什么会冒出来惊散它。我记得有一次我们偶遇一艘停泊在岸边的军舰。岸上连一间棚屋都没有，那军舰却在向灌木丛使劲儿放炮，看来法国人正在那附近打仗。她的船旗像块破布一样死沉沉地耷拉着，船身低处的八英寸长筒炮全部升了起来。油污的海浪一闪一闪，懒洋洋地把它抛上抛下，那单薄的桅杆东摇西摆。在这一片巨大的虚空中，只有大地、天空和海洋，她却在那里不可理喻地向一片大陆开着火。砰！一门八英寸长筒炮开火了，一小团火焰狂奔而出，转眼就熄灭了，那缕瘦瘦的白烟也随之消失，一颗小小的炮弹低低地惨叫一声——然后什么事也没有。能有什么事呢？这个过程真有点神经兮兮的，一个可笑又可叹的场面。船上有人一本正经地向我解释说那里有一个土著的军营——他竟然叫他们敌人！——藏在岸上某个地方，说得言之凿凿的。但那并不能改变我的感受。”

“我们把信送到那条船上（听说在那艘孤独的船上，每天都有三个人死于热病）后继续前进。我们又在一些名字古怪的港口靠岸，它们像热得过分的地下古墓，宁静的空气里弥漫着泥土味，死神和贸易在墓里翩翩起舞。我们沿着没有固定形状的海岸前行，浪花冷酷凶险地拍着岸，就像大自然正自发努力想要挡开入侵者。一条又一条的河，死亡之流源源不绝地流出流入，把河岸腐蚀成烂泥，河水变污变稠，摧毁着扭曲的红树林，那些树好像在向我们痛苦地扭动着，极端绝望，束手无策。我们在任何一个地方都待不长，无法留下特别详细的印象，只是笼统地觉得有一种日益滋长的疑惑，模糊而滞闷。就像走不完的旅程，无聊透顶，仿佛一场噩梦。”

“走了三十多天，终于看到那条大河的河口。我们的船停泊在政府所在地附近的岸边。但我还要往前走两百多英里才能开工。所以我逮住一个机会，出发去上游三十英里的一个地方。”

“我坐的是一条航海小汽船。船长是瑞典人，听说我是个水手，就请我到驾驶台上去。他很年轻，瘦削白皙，神情阴郁，头发细长，走起路来拖泥带水。我们离开那个凄惨的小码头时，他轻蔑地向岸边甩甩头。‘您就住那儿？’他问。我说：‘没错。’‘那些政府官员真够意思——不是吗？’他继续说，说的是英文，用语极度精确，话里藏针，‘真是有意思，有些人为了一个月挣那几个法郎，简直什么都做得出来。我真想知道上游是什么光景。’我告诉他我很快就能看到了。‘这样啊！’他惊叫起来。他横拖着步子走了几步，警觉地注视着前方。‘不要掉以轻心，’他继续说道，‘前几天我救起了一个家伙，他在路上上吊自杀。也是个瑞典人。’‘上吊自杀！天啊！有什么看不开的？’我喊了出来。他依然保持着警觉。‘谁知道呢？实在受不了那大太阳，又或者是那鬼地方。’”

“最后，我们驶进一条开阔的水道，看见一道岩石满布的悬崖，岸边翻出成堆的泥土，一座小山上有许多房子。在被挖出来的一堆堆废物之间，在山坡上，散落着其他用铁皮做顶的房子。上方不断传来急流的响声，在这片住了人的废墟上回旋激荡。很多人，几乎都是黑皮肤，赤身裸体，像蚂蚁一样窜来窜去。一个小码头伸入河中。阳光忽然变得刺眼，让人什么都看不见。‘那就是您公司的贸易站，’瑞典人说，指着三间像兵营一样的木屋子，它们颤巍巍地架在满是岩石的斜坡上，‘我找人帮您把东西运上去。您是说四个箱子吧？祝您好运。再见。’”

“我在路上碰上一个深埋在草丛里的锅炉，又发现了一条通上山的小路。这条路绕开了所有挡道的大石头，以及一节轮子朝天的铁皮火车车厢。其中一个轮子不见了。这节车厢躺在那里一动不动，就像某只动物的尸体一样。一路上我看见更多朽烂的机器和一堆生锈的铁轨。在路的左边，一片树林投下一块浓荫，里面似乎有些什么黑暗的物体在衰弱地蠕动着。我眨眨眼，前面的路很陡。路的右边传来号角声，我看见很多黑人跑过。突然响起一阵沉闷的爆炸声，地动山摇，悬崖上冒出一股烟，然后一切恢复正常。岩石的外表没有发生任何变化。他们正在修铁路。那悬崖并没有挡道，但这种盲目的爆破就是他们的全部工作。”

“我身后传来一阵轻细的叮当声，引得我回过头看。六个黑人排成一排，艰难地沿着小路往上爬。他们挺直身子，慢慢地爬，头上顶着装满土的小篮，小心翼翼，每走一步便是一阵叮当声。他们的腰部缠着黑色的破布，后面垂下短短的一截，像尾巴一样摇来摇去。他们的每条肋骨都清晰可见，四肢的关节就像绳子上打的结。每个人颈上都有一个铁项圈，一条铁链把所有项圈拴在一起，链环在他们之间左摇右晃，发出节奏清晰的叮当声。从悬崖那边又传来一阵爆炸声，我突然想起之前看到过的那艘军舰，向陆地开火的那艘。一样是不吉祥的声音。但再异想天开些，眼前这些人也不会像敌人。他们被称为罪犯，那被忤逆了的法律，就像炸开了的炮弹一样击中了他们，是一个来自海洋的谜，无法解释。他们瘦弱的胸膛全在一起喘着气，撑开了的鼻孔颤抖着，眼光呆滞地盯着山上。他们就这样从我身边经过，离我不到六英寸，没有看我一眼，浑身上下透着土人在遭难时那种完全的冷漠，就好像他们已经死了。在这些生番后面，走着一个已经受过教化的黑人。他是新势力得势后的产物，提着一支来复枪半死不活地慢慢走着。他穿一件掉了一个纽扣的制服外套，看见路上有个白人，连忙把武器举到肩膀。这么做只是慎重起见。隔这么远，白人看起来都是一个样的，他无法分辨我可能是什么人。他很快放下心来，绽开一个大大的笑容，猥琐下流，充分展露了他的白牙。他扫了一眼他负责看管的犯人，仿佛邀请我去和他一起分享这份光荣的职责。毕竟，这项崇高正义的伟业方兴未艾，而我是其中一部分。”

“我没有往上爬，转身从左边下坡。我这么做，是想等看不见这排锁在铁链里的人之后再上山。我可不是个温婉的家伙，迫不得已的时候我也曾奋起自卫过。有时候我也被逼反抗和进攻——进攻只是一种反抗的方式——这样的一时冲动可能会改变我的人生，带来种种后果，然而我无暇精打细算。我见识过暴力的魔鬼、贪婪的魔鬼和渴望的魔鬼，但是，上天做证！这些魔鬼都强大、健壮和双眼发红，迷惑并奴役着人——是的，是人。但当我站在这个山腰上，我能预见到在那块土地上，夺目的阳光里，我将很快认识一个新的魔鬼，他贪得无厌，笨得要死，满身赘肉，故作姿态，鼠目寸光。再过几个月，再走一千英里，我就能知道他有多么阴毒奸狡。我突然站定了，满心恐惧，好像受到了警告一般。最后我七弯八拐地下了山，去找之前看到的那片树林。”

“我绕开一个人工挖出来的大洞，那洞好像挖了很久，但挖来干什么，我无从猜测。反正不是采石场或者采沙坑，就只是个洞。也许是有人忽发善心，想要让那些罪犯有事可做吧。我不知道。然后我差点掉进一条非常狭窄的山沟，它不过就像山腰上的一道小疤痕。我发现有很多供居民点使用的排水管被扔在沟里。那可是千里迢迢运来的，现在却没一根是好的。真是一团糟。后来我终于找到了那片树林。我本来是想在树荫下散会儿步的，但一走进去，就好像踏进了某个地狱的一圈阴影里。急流近在咫尺，在寂静得哀伤的小树林里，只听见那阵猛烈的水声，持续不断，单调乏味，急急忙忙。树林里一丝风也没有，所有树叶都凝滞不动，却有那么一阵神秘的声响——仿佛地球那轰轰隆隆的脚步声突然变得清晰可闻。”

“许多黑色的人影蜷伏着、躺着或是倚着树干坐在树与树之间，他们仿佛长在地里，一半暴露在地上，一半隐没在阴影中，做出各种痛苦、听天由命和绝望的姿势。悬崖那边又爆炸了，我脚下的土地一阵轻轻战栗。人们还在那边工作着。工作！那些无法再工作的人，就来这里等死。”

“他们正慢慢死去——非常明显。他们不是敌人，他们不是罪犯，他们不再是现世的存在物——什么也不是，只是疾病和饥饿的黑影，乱糟糟地躺在墨绿色的阴影中。通过完全合法的定期合同，有人把他们从沿岸各个隐蔽之处招聘来。他们在这恶劣的环境中茫然无助，食物吃不惯，生了病，无法继续工作，就被允许爬到这里来休息。这些奄奄一息的影子就像空气一样轻飘飘的——也差不多跟空气一样稀薄。我开始看见树下有许多眼睛在泛着光。然后，我低头看时，发现手边有一张脸。一副黑色的人骨挺得笔直，一个肩膀抵着树，眼皮缓缓抬起，凹陷的眼睛翻上来看看我，巨大而空洞，一种盲人似的白光在眼底微微闪烁，慢慢熄灭。似乎还很年轻——几乎是个小孩儿——但很难看出他们的真实年龄。我觉得好像应该做点什么，便从口袋里掏出一块我乘坐的那上好的瑞典船上的饼干给他。他的手指慢慢闭拢起来，抓住了那块饼干——再没有其他动作，也没有再看我一眼。他的脖子上绑着一缕白色的精纺毛线——为什么？他从哪儿得来的？那是一个记号——一种装饰——一个符咒——还是一种祈愿的仪式？它到底有没有含义？这一缕属于海洋彼岸的白毛线，竟然缠在他的脖子上，实在有些格格不入。”

“在这棵树旁边，还有两副尖瘦的黑骨头抱膝而坐。其中一个把下巴支在膝盖上，呆呆地瞪着眼睛，那神情恐怖非常，让人不敢多看。他的同伴，另一个幽灵则把额头枕在膝盖上，像被巨大的疲倦打垮了。其他人分散在各处，姿势各异，扭曲着苟延残喘，就像画里面大屠杀或者大瘟疫的场景。我站在那里，震惊得呆若木鸡，忽然一个幽灵用手和膝盖撑起身来，手脚并用，爬向河边喝水。他舔干双手，在阳光中坐起来，盘起双腿，不多久，他那毛茸茸的脑袋便沉沉地垂到胸骨上。”

“我不愿久留，匆忙逃向贸易站。走近那片建筑物的时候，我碰到一个白人，他的装束出乎意料的优雅，乍一看还以为是幻觉。我看见一个高高的衣领，浆得挺直，干干净净的白袖口，浅色的羊驼毛夹克，雪白的长裤，鲜亮的领带，擦得锃亮的皮靴。他没戴帽子。分头，头发刷得油亮亮的，一只大白手撑着一把绿纹遮阳伞。他真是神奇，耳后还夹着一管自来水笔杆。”

“我和这一奇迹握手，得知他是公司的会计主任，公司所有账目都归这个贸易站整理和登记。他溜出来一小会儿，按他的话说，‘出来透透气’。这话听起来奇怪得很，背后是没完没了的案牍生活。要不是我是从他嘴里第一次听到另一个人的名字，而这另一个人又是这段回忆不可或缺的一部分，我根本不会向你们提及他。况且，我也尊敬这个家伙。我尊敬他。我尊敬他的衣领，他那巨大的袖口，他那刷得油亮亮的脑袋。他看起来确实跟理发店橱窗里的假人模特一式一样，但在这样一片毫无生气的土地上，他竟保住了光鲜的外表，多么有骨气！他那浆硬的领子和胸部笔挺的衬衫代表着人格的成就。他到这里来差不多有三年了，我忍不住问他是怎样把衣服打理得那么像样的。他双颊微微泛红，谦虚地说：‘我在教站里的一个土著女人做事。真是不容易，她本来可讨厌这些业务了。’这么说来，这个人还真有点贡献。他也倾尽心思在账簿上，把它们整理得井井有条。”

“站里其他的一切都杂乱无章——人啊，物啊，房子啊。商队，一队队八字脚的黑人，风尘仆仆地来来去去，工业产品、劣质的棉花、珠子和铜线络绎不绝地被运进黑暗深处，涓涓细流一般地换回珍稀的象牙。”

我要在这个贸易站等十天——简直望不到头。我在院子里支了个帐篷住着，但为了避开那片混乱，我有时会躲进会计办公室。那是用横条木板建成的，手工很差，会计主任在高高的书桌上伏案工作的时候，浑身上下满是一条条窄窄的阳光。不用拉开百叶窗也能看到外面。办公室里也很热，大苍蝇恶毒地嗡嗡作响，虽然不叮人，却四处撞人。我一般坐在地上，他则高高地坐在高脚凳上写个不停，一身装束无懈可击（甚至微微生香）。有时他站起来活动筋骨。有人匆匆忙忙地把一张装有脚轮的矮床推进办公室，上面躺着一个病人（某个从内地来的代理人），他表示出微微的恼怒。‘这位病人的呻吟声，’他说，‘使我无法集中精神。在这种气候里，如果不能高度集中精神，算错账是很难避免的。’

一天他低着头说：‘在内地，您肯定会见到库尔茨先生。’我问库尔茨先生是何方神圣，他说是个头等的代理人。看见我对这个信息流露出失望之情，他搁下笔，继续慢慢地说：‘他可是个相当了不起的人。’我追问下去，他说库尔茨先生现在负责一个贸易站，那个贸易站可重要了，在真正的象牙之乡，在‘那里的最深处。他送来的象牙跟其他人加起来的一样多……’他又提笔工作。病人虚弱得已经无力呻吟了。在一片巨大的宁静中，只有苍蝇在嗡嗡叫个不停。

突然传来一阵越来越大的说话声和沉重有力的脚步声。一个商队进站了。木板的另一边爆发出一阵粗野狂烈的声音，吵吵嚷嚷地不知道在说什么。所有搬运工都在说话，在一片吵闹之中，我们听见站长用悲痛的声音在说：‘我们尽力了。’那句话他那天带着哭腔说了有二十遍……会计主任慢慢起身。‘真是吵死人了。’他说。他轻轻地走到屋子另一边去看看病人，又折回来，对我说：‘他什么都听不见。’‘你说什么！他死了吗？’我问，真是吓坏了。‘不，还没有死。’他不动声色地说。然后，他朝外间的喧闹声甩甩头，暗示道：‘当你不得不把账记清楚的时候，实在是无法不讨厌这些野蛮人——真是烦死他们了！’他思索了一会儿，‘您看见库尔茨先生的时候，’他接着说，‘请告诉他这里的每一件东西’——他斜了桌子一眼——‘都非常令人满意。我不喜欢给他写信——我们的信使都靠不住，天知道他们会把信送到谁手里——在那个中央贸易站。’他用那双温和而突出的眼睛盯着我看了一会儿，‘哦，他前途无限，无可限量，’他又说，‘不久就会变成管理部门的要人。他们，那些高层——欧洲的董事会——很赏识他。’

他继续埋头工作。外面终于安静了。过了一会儿，我要出去，走到门口又停住了。苍蝇还在不知疲倦地嗡嗡叫着，将要被运送回国的代理人躺在那里，脸涨得通红，已然没有了意识。屋子里另一个人正趴在账簿上，清清楚楚地记着账，毫无差错。门阶下方五十英尺的地方，我看得见那片死亡之林寂静不动的树梢。

第二天，我终于跟一个六十个人的商队离开了那个贸易站，开始了一段两百英里长的徒步旅程。

那段旅程没什么好说的。反正到处都是小路。人们踩出来一张路网，网住那片空荡荡的土地，穿过长长的草地，穿过被火烧过的草地，穿过灌木丛，穿越寒冷的峡谷，翻越闪着火光的石山。荒凉又荒凉，一个人也没有，一间茅屋也没有。居民很久之前就跑光了。试想想，如果有很多神秘的黑人，武装着各种可怕的武器，突然开始流窜在迪尔和格雷夫森德[18]之间的大路上，把住在路两旁的英国佬都抓去做搬运工，那一带所有农场和村庄肯定也会很快荒废掉。只是这里连房子都不见了。但我沿途也见到好几个被遗弃的村庄。那些残破不堪的草墙像一种可悲的儿戏。六十双光脚的踏步声和划地声日复一日地跟在我身后，每一双脚上面都有六十磅的重物。扎营，做饭，睡觉，拔营，跋涉。不时一个搬运工背着重物倒下，长眠在路边高高的草丛中，一个空的水葫芦和一根长棍子会陪在他身边。四周和上空是一片逃不出的死寂。也许在某个安静的夜晚，能听见遥远的鼓声，战栗着，沉下去，又响起来，茫茫荒野里的挣扎，软弱无力的。这个怪异的声音，魅惑的，暗示的，野性的——说不定和基督教国家的钟声一样意味深远。有一次我们看见一个白人，制服的纽扣都开了，带着一个高高瘦瘦的桑格巴尔人——他的武装护卫——在路边扎营，他友善而快活——肯定是喝醉了。他声称自己在检查这条马路的养护工作。哪里有什么马路需要养护！他们也什么都没干。倒是前头三英里处有一具中年黑人的尸体，额头被子弹打出一个洞，确实是把我绊了一跤，可能他把这叫作一个永恒的改善。我还有一个白人同伴，人倒不坏，但有点儿胖过头了，有一个不断加剧的毛病：一爬上炎热的山坡就要晕过去，而最近的一点树荫和水源还在好几英里之外。真可恶，我们不得不把外套撑起来给他当遮阳伞，遮住他的头，等他慢慢苏醒。有一次我忍不住问他到底为什么要跑这儿来。‘当然是为了挣钱。不然呢？’他不屑地说。后来他发起烧来，我们只好把他放进吊床，挂在木杆上抬着他走。为此搬运工跟我吵了不知道有多少次，因为他足足重十六英石[19]。他们消极怠工，逃跑，夜里带着行囊偷偷溜走——简直是造反。所以，一个晚上，我比手画脚地用英语发表了演讲，我面前那六十双雪亮的眼睛都明白了我的意思，第二天早晨他们就在我面前乖乖抬着吊床出发了。但一个小时后，我在灌木丛里发现了整个这一切的残骸——那家伙，吊床，呻吟声，毯子，恐惧。沉重的木杆擦破了他的鼻子，真可怜。他非常急切地要求我杀死某个人，但附近连一个搬运工的影子都没有。我记起那个老医生说的话——‘当场密切关注个人精神状态的变化是很有意义的’——我感到我要开始对科学的发展产生意义了。然而我并不觉得那有什么用。在第十五天，我又看见了那条大河，便一瘸一拐地走进了中央贸易站。它坐落在河湾上，藏在灌木丛和森林之中，一面是用臭泥巴做成的边界，破破烂烂的，另外三面被疯长的灯芯草篱笆团团围住，一个没人修整的缺口就是它唯一的门口。一看就知道这里的主管是个窝囊废。几个手里拿着长棍的白人从房子之间懒洋洋地走出来，不紧不慢地晃上来看了我一眼，又走开不见了。其中有一个蓄着黑胡子的胖子，很是大惊小怪，我一告诉他我是谁，他就滔滔不绝、东拉西扯地告诉我，我的汽船沉到河底去了。我仿佛遭到五雷轰顶。什么，怎么回事，为什么？哦，‘没关系。’‘经理本人’就在船上。一切如常。‘每个人的表现都值得表扬！值得表扬！’——‘您务必，’他颤抖着说，‘马上去见经理。他在等您！’

我一时还不明白船沉了意味着什么。我想我现在明白了，但不敢确定——一点儿也不。这件事情摆明就是太愚蠢了——每当我想起它——简直就蠢得出奇。但……但在那一刻，我就觉得它不过是一件恼人的麻烦事而已。船沉了。他们两天前急急忙忙驾船开往上游，经理也在船上，负责开船的船长是个志愿者。开出去不到三个小时，船底就被石头划开了，船在南岸附近沉没了。我不禁问自己：船都没了，我来这还能做什么？事实上，我要做很多事，以便把归我指挥的那条船捞上来。我必须第二天就出发去开工。把沉船捞上来，运回贸易站修理，要花好几个月的时间。

我和经理的第一次会面相当奇怪。当天早上，我走了二十英里的路才见到他，他却没有请我坐。他的表情、五官、仪态和声音都平淡无奇。他不高不矮，不胖不瘦。他那双蓝眼睛的颜色很普通，眼神却冷漠得过分，他盯着人看的时候，无疑能把这眼神变得跟沉重的利斧一样劈向人。但即使是在这些时候，他身体的其余部分却依然平淡如常。此外就只剩下他嘴唇上那种难以捉摸的表情，微乎其微，总有点鬼鬼祟祟，似笑非笑的，我到现在还记得清清楚楚，但解释不了。它不是故意的，这种微笑，尽管他每说完一次话，它又变明显一些。他一闭嘴，它就出现，就像拿封印把话封住一样，哪怕只是最平常的话，也弄得绝对不可理解似的。他是个普通的商人，从年轻时起就受聘在这些地区工作——从来没干过别的。大家都听他指挥，然而他没有令别人爱上他或是害怕他，大家对他甚至连尊敬都谈不上。他只能令人感到浑身不自在。就是这话！浑身不自在。也不是明确的不信任——只是浑身不自在——仅此而已。你们不知道这样一帮……一帮……职员的效率有多么低下。他没有组织能力、创新能力，甚至连好好发号施令都不会。他把这个可怜的贸易站搞得乌烟瘴气，就是最好的证明。他没有学问，智力低下。他居然被提拔为经理——怎么会这样？大概就是因为他从来不生病……他在那里熬过了三个三年的聘期……在人人都生病的地方，强健的体魄本身就是一种力量。他每次休假回家都会去大肆寻欢作乐一番。跟上了岸的水手似的——当然他不一样——只不过他的外表光鲜一些。这一点从他不经意的闲谈中也听得出来。他墨守成规，但能够保持日常工作的正常运转——他只有这点本事。但他是个了不起的人物。没人知道有什么可以控制得了这样一个人，光这一点就足以令他了不起。他从来不泄露个中秘密。也许他身体里空无一物。但这种怀疑永远无法证实——在那个地方没法做外科检查。有一次，多种热带疾病突然暴发，站里几乎所有‘代理人’都病倒了，却有人听到他说：‘出来这里的人就不应该有内脏。’他又用那种奇怪的笑容封印住这句话，仿佛那是一扇开往黑暗世界的大门，而他恰好是看门人。仿佛看到点儿什么——但门马上就关上了。那些白人吃饭的时候老是为了谁坐上座吵个不停，把他吵烦了，他就命令人做了一张巨大的圆桌，做好了没地方摆得下，就又另外盖了一间屋子。贸易站的食堂就是这么来的。他坐的地方就是首席——剩下的，坐哪里都一样。人们觉得他就是怀有这种信念，坚定不移的。他既不文雅也不粗野。他很安静。他允许他的‘跟班’——一个来自海岸地区的青年黑人，被养得肥头大耳的——就在他眼皮底下对那些白人粗暴无礼、兴风作浪。

他一见到我就说个不停。我走得太慢了。他等不起，只好先开船。上游的贸易站急需物资供应。已经耽搁得太久，他都不知道哪个死了，哪个还活着，他们情况如何——等等，等等。他完全不听我解释，摆弄着一根封口蜡棒，重复了好几次说形势‘非常严峻，非常严峻’。有流言说一个非常重要的贸易站情况危急，站长库尔茨先生也病倒了。希望不是真的。库尔茨先生是……我累坏了，烦躁得要命。让库尔茨去死吧，我想。我打断他说我在岸上对库尔茨先生有所听闻。‘啊！他们在下游地区也谈论他啊。’他嘟嘟囔囔地自言自语。然后他又开始说个没完，向我保证库尔茨先生是他手底下最好的代理人，非凡卓绝，公司决不能没有他，这样我应该理解他为什么这么焦虑了吧。他说自己真是‘非常，非常担忧’。确实，他在椅子上不停地扭来扭去，大声喊道：‘啊，库尔茨先生！’把封口蜡棒都掰断了，却又被这个意外事件吓住了。接下来他想知道‘需要花多长时间去’……我又打断他。我快饿死了，又站了那么久，丧失了耐性。‘你问我，我问谁去？’我说，‘我还没见到那条沉船呢——好几个月吧，短不了。’这场对话对我来说真是浪费时间。‘好几个月，’他说，‘好吧，那我们三个月后就可以出发了。好。这件工作三个月足够了。’我气呼呼地从他的小屋出来（他自己住一间小泥屋，屋外还带一条简陋的走廊），一边自己向自己咕哝着对他的看法。他是个唠唠叨叨的傻瓜。日后我收回了这句话，因为他对这件‘工作’需要的时间估计得一丝不差，真是惊人。

第二天我就开工了。可以说我把贸易站抛诸脑后。我觉得只有那样我才能紧紧抓住实实在在的生活，弥补这一段时间的空虚感。然而，人总是会开小差东张西望的。然后我看见了那个贸易站，那些男人在院子里的阳光底下漫无目的地逛来逛去。有时我问自己，他们这是在干什么。他们拿着滑稽的长棍子，魂不守舍地走来走去，就像很多变了节的朝圣者，被鬼勾了魂，在那个破篱笆里来回打转。‘象牙’这个词在空气中回荡，他们低声念叨着它，叹息里也全是它，真的像在向它祈祷似的。到处隐隐弥漫着一丝愚蠢而贪婪的气味，就像尸体发出的臭味。天啊！我从未见过如此不真实的景象。贸易站外，那片寂静无声的荒野紧紧包围着这一小块开拓出来的地方，在我看来是那么伟大而不容对抗，就像邪恶或真理一样。它不急不躁地，等待这一次疯狂的侵略自行结束。

哦，那几个月！好吧，别提了。后来又发生了很多事。一个晚上，一个装满白棉布、印花棉布、玻璃珠的草棚，不知道还有没有放别的，突然着火，仿佛地球突然裂开，放出一团复仇之火来，要把那些垃圾统统烧掉。我在那拆开了的汽船旁边安静地抽着烟斗，看见他们都在火光中跳来跳去，高举双臂，那个蓄着胡子的胖男人拿着水桶猛冲向河边，一边还不忘向我保证说每个人都‘值得表扬，值得表扬！’打起一夸脱左右的水又猛冲回去。我注意到他的桶底有个窟窿。

我慢慢走上前去。急也没用，那草棚像盒火柴一样烧得一发不可收拾。从一开始就毫无希望。火焰蹿得高高的，把所有人都挡了回去，照亮了一切——然后猛然熄灭了。草棚已经被烧成一堆灼热的灰烬。他们在一旁打一个黑人，据说这次失火都怪他。就算真的是他，他叫得也太凄惨了些。过后我看见他连续几天坐在一片小小的树荫下，奄奄一息的样子，努力挣扎着想康复；后来他站起来走了——荒野无声无息地把他吞了回去。我从黑暗走近那堆余烬的时候，发现前面有两个人在聊天。我听见他们提到库尔茨的名字，又听见什么‘利用这次不幸的事故’之类的话。其中一个是经理，我向他道了夜安。‘你之前有碰到过这样的事情吗——啊？真不敢相信。’他说，然后走开了。另一个男人留在原地。他是一个头等的代理人，年轻，彬彬有礼，略带矜持，蓄着八字胡，长着鹰钩鼻。他刻意和其他代理人保持距离，他们私下里说他是经理派来监视他们的密探。我呢，我之前没怎么跟他说过话。我们开始交谈，慢慢从发着嘶嘶声的废墟前走开去。他请我去他位于贸易站主楼内的房间。他划亮一根火柴，我注意到这个年轻的贵族不仅有一个镶银的化妆盒，还能一个人用一整根蜡烛——那时就只有经理有点蜡烛的权利。墙上覆着当地的草垫，还挂着许多战利品：长矛、非洲梭枪、盾牌和刀子。这位先生负责制砖的业务——别人是这么跟我说的，但站里连砖头的碎块都找不着，而他在那里都有一年多了——一直在等。似乎没有某些材料就不能制砖，我不知道是什么——说不定是麦秆。无论如何，那里是没有麦秆的，也不太可能从欧洲运来，所以我也弄不明白他到底在等什么。也许是某个奇迹吧。然而，他们全部人都一直在等——那十六个还是二十个朝圣者。说真的，从他们的工作态度来看，他们应该并不觉得这份工作有多么糟糕，尽管他们唯一要做的事好像就只是生病——据我所知。他们通过愚蠢地相互中伤和酝酿谋害同伴的计划来消磨时间。贸易站里总是疑云密布——当然没有哪个阴谋被付诸实践。这片疑云就像站里其他的一切那样不真实——与这个公司的慈善外衣、人们虚伪的谈话、公司的管理制度和人们在工作中的表现一样。唯一真实的，是被委派到贸易站当负责人的渴望。贸易站可能有象牙，他们可以通过买卖象牙获得分成。他们相互仇恨，相互设计陷害，相互中伤，都只是由于这个缘故——但如果你要叫他们动动手指头做点什么正经事——别做梦。天啊！世上毕竟有这么一样东西，允许一个人偷一匹马，却不许另一个人对缰绳产生非分之想。直接把马偷走吧。很好。他照做了。说不定他会骑马呢！但有时如果有人望一眼缰绳，也会惹得最慈悲为怀的大圣人勃然大怒。

我不知道他为什么要跟我说那么多话，但谈着谈着，我突然想到这家伙心怀鬼胎——实际上，在套我的话。他反复拐弯抹角地提到欧洲，提到我可能在那里认识的人——用问题引我说话，引我说起那个死城里的熟人之类的。他的小眼睛好像两片闪闪发亮的云母片——充满好奇——尽管他努力装出一副爱理不理的样子。刚开始我还挺惊讶的，但很快又感到很好奇，想看看他到底想打探什么消息。我完全想象不出自己藏了什么话，值得他花这么多心机去打探。看着他在费尽心思地让自己失望，真的很有趣。因为其实我肚子里只有一股寒气，我的脑子里也只有那条倒霉的汽船。很明显，他把我当成了恬不知耻的大骗子。最后他生气了，为了遮掩一个怒火中烧的举动，他打了个呵欠。我站起身。然后我注意到在房门的嵌板上钉着一幅小小的油画草图，画的是一个女人，披着布，蒙着眼，拿一个燃烧着的火把。背景一片灰暗——近乎漆黑。那女人的动作庄严神圣，火把的光芒映在她的脸上，很是邪恶凶险。

我被那幅画迷住了。他客客气气地站在一旁，手里托着一个空的半品脱香槟瓶（用于宁神静气），瓶口插着一根蜡烛。我向他问起这幅画，他说是库尔茨先生画的——在这个贸易站的时候，一年多之前——在等待合适的交通工具前往他的贸易站那会儿。‘告诉我，老兄，’我说，‘库尔茨先生是谁？’

‘内地贸易站的站长。’他简短地说，别过脸去。‘受教了，’我笑着说，‘而您是中央贸易站的制砖负责人。大家都知道。’他沉默了片刻。‘他是个天才，’他终于开口说道，‘他是慈悲、科学和进步的使者。鬼才知道他还是什么。我们想要的是，’他突然开始慷慨陈词，‘为了使欧洲那边委托给我们的事业能得到更好的指导，比方说，更高明的才智、广泛的同情心和团结一致的目标。’‘这是谁说的？’我问。‘他们很多人都这么说，’他回答，‘还有人把这些话写在文章里，于是他来了。他可是个特殊人物，这点您应该也是知道的吧。’‘我凭什么知道？’我打断他，惊讶极了。他没理我。‘是的，现在他掌管着最好的贸易站，明年就会变成副经理，再过两年……但我确定您知道两年后他会变成怎样。您属于新派——美德派。特意把他派来的人又推荐了您。哦，您别否认。我相信自己的眼睛。’我现在明白了。我那亲爱的姨妈果然有一些有权有势的朋友，现在这些朋友开始对这个年轻人产生了意料之外的效果。我差点哈哈大笑起来。‘您也看公司的内部通讯？’我问。他无话可说。太好玩了。‘等库尔茨先生，’我板起脸继续说道，‘当了总经理，您就没戏了。’

他冷不丁地吹灭了蜡烛，我们一同走出屋子。月亮已经升了起来。黑暗的人影无精打采地四处乱窜，把水泼在不断嘶嘶作响的余烬上。月光下升起缕缕蒸汽，那个遭毒打的黑人在某个地方呻吟着。‘这畜生真会捅乱子！’那个精力旺盛的八字胡先生边说边向我们走过来。‘打得好！犯法——惩罚——砰！不能心软，不能心软。只能这么办。这才能防止日后再发生严重的火灾。我刚才还跟经理说……’他看清了我的同伴，马上老实了，‘您还没睡呢，’他说，带着一种奴颜媚骨的热情，‘太正常了。哈！危险——焦虑。’连忙溜走了。我继续走向河边，我的同伴跟随着我。耳边隐隐传来一句刺耳的话：‘一群笨蛋——该死。’那些朝圣者们三五成群聚在一起，手舞足蹈地发表着议论，有几个还拿着他们的棍子。我真的相信他们睡觉都拿着棍子。在篱笆的外面，月光下的森林仿佛一群狰狞的鬼怪，大地的寂静穿透了昏暗中的骚动，穿透了这个可悲的院子里发出的轻响，直达人的心底——它的不可知，它的浩荡，它隐含的生命的惊人真相。受伤的黑人在我们身边某处微弱地呻吟着，又深深地叹了一口气，我听不下去，加快脚步走开去。我感到有一只手探到我的手臂底下。‘我亲爱的先生，’那个家伙说，‘我不想别人误解我，尤其是您，因为您很快就会有幸见到库尔茨先生，而我还要等很久。我不想让他错误地以为我另有所图……’

“我任由这个纸糊的靡菲斯特[20]滔滔不绝地讲下去，仿佛如果我使点劲儿就能用食指戳穿他，并很可能发现里面除了几点污垢之外什么都没有。这下你们明白了吧？这家伙一心想着好好巴结当时的经理，好慢慢爬上副经理的位置，但那个库尔茨半路杀了出来，打乱了他们的如意算盘。他仓促地说个不停，我也没想打断他。我把肩膀倚在汽船的残骸上。我们把它打捞上来，放在岸边的斜坡上，好像它是一只大河怪的尸体。扑鼻的泥土味——远古时期的泥土，天啊！高高的原始森林一动不动地立在眼前，黑色的小溪上泛起块块亮光。月亮把一层薄薄的银纱覆在万物之上——在杂草上，在泥上，在比庙墙还要高的乱林上，在那条大河上——那条河是如此宽广，静静流淌着，在一个幽暗的缺口之外闪烁生辉。一切都很美好，生机涌动，安然无声，而那个家伙竟一直在啰里啰唆地为自己解释。我在想，这片广袤无垠的荒野一脸沉静地望着我们二人，似是有所请求，又像在发出威胁。迷途至此的我们到底是什么？我们能够操控这个哑巴一样的庞然巨物吗？还是将臣服于它？这一个没有嘴巴，说不定连耳朵都没有的巨物，是如此庞大，庞大得深不见底。那里面究竟藏了什么？我可以看到一点象牙从深处流出，听说库尔茨先生就在那里。我实在听够库尔茨这个名字了——上天做证！然而不知怎的他还没有形成一个具体的形象——就好像我不过是听见说那里面有一个天使或者一个魔鬼。这种情况就像听到有人说火星上有居民一样，信不信由你。我认识一个苏格兰的修帆工，他拍胸脯保证说火星上有人，但如果你问他火星人长什么样，言谈举止如何，他会马上涨红了脸，含含糊糊地说什么‘用四条腿走路’。要是你敢笑，他就会——尽管都六十岁了——跟你打起来。我不会为了库尔茨跟人打架，但却是因为他，我差一点撒了谎。我是最恨别人撒谎的，太可恶了，我受不了。不是因为我比其他人正直，只是因为谎言使我恐惧。谎言总带着一丝死亡的阴影，说得人满嘴腐臭——这世上我最讨厌和最憎恨的莫过于此——我真想把它彻底忘掉。它让我痛苦、恶心，就像一口咬到腐烂的食物。我想这是一种天性。好吧，我放任那个年轻人天马行空地幻想我在欧洲的影响力，也差不多是在撒谎了。刹那间我也学会了虚张声势，就跟那些深受蛊惑的朝圣者一样。这仅仅是因为我突然产生了一个想法，这么做可能对于当时与我素未谋面的库尔茨多少有点好处——你们能理解吧。那时他对我而言只是一个名字。你们看得见他吗？你们看得见这个故事吗？你们看得见任何东西吗？我好像在对你们说一个梦——真是吃力不讨好，因为梦里的感受是无从通过语言传递的。挣扎着想反抗，浑身颤抖，铺天盖地的荒诞、惊奇和迷乱相互交织，总感觉要被一种超自然的力量抓住，这些感受才是梦的本质……”

他沉默了片刻。

“……不，那不可能。人生中某一段时期的感受是无法转述的，正是这种感受，构成了人生的真相和意义——人生的本质，微妙而贯穿始终。不可能的。人生如梦——一样的孤独……”

他又停下来，好像在思考，然后接下去说——

“当然，对于当时的情况，你们这些家伙比当时的我要看得清楚一些。你们很了解我的为人……”

天已经很暗了，我们这些听众几乎看不见彼此。已经有很长的一段时间，独自坐在一旁的他对我们而言只剩下一个声音。其他人都悄无声息，可能都已经昏昏睡去，我却还醒着。我还在听，一直在听，字字句句都留心着，寻求着蛛丝马迹，以求解释为什么这个故事引起了我隐约的不安。它似乎不是从双唇流出的，而是在这条沉重的河流上空，那稠滞的夜色中自行上演。

“……是的——我任他往下说，”马洛又开始了，随他想象我有什么靠山。管他呢！但其实我什么靠山都没有！除了身后那条又旧又可怜的破汽船。当他夸夸其谈着什么‘每一个人都必须努力升职’，‘人们不是，您也知道，来这儿看月亮的’。库尔茨先生是一个‘无所不能的天才’，但就算是天才，和‘合适的工具——聪明的人’一起工作也会轻松得多。他并没有制砖——为什么呢？因为有不可抗力——我应该很清楚才对。而说到他为经理做秘书做的工作，那是因为‘哪个理智的人会不知轻重地辜负上司的信任呢？’我明白了吗？明白了。我还想怎样？我想要铆钉，天啊！铆钉。我要继续我的工作——我要把船底的洞补上。我要铆钉。海岸那边有成箱成箱的铆钉——那么多箱——山一样堆着——箱子都要撑破了——简直要爆炸！在山腰上那个贸易站的院子里，走一步就能踢飞一个铆钉。铆钉都滚到那片死亡之林里去了。只要你不嫌弯腰麻烦，就能用铆钉装满口袋——而在需要铆钉的地方却一颗也找不到。我们有钢板，但没有东西固定它们。每周，那个形单影只的黑人信使都会扛起一个大邮袋，拿着一根棍子，从我们的贸易站出发去岸边。而岸边的大篷车每周几次载来各色贸易商品——暗无光泽的印花布，看一眼吓一跳，令人反感；一夸脱卖一便士左右的玻璃珠子；还有印着怪异圆点的棉手帕。没有铆钉。三个搬运工就可以把我需要的铆钉全部运来，让汽船再次浮起来。

他对我的态度越来越亲热，但我猜我那漠不关心的态度肯定终于触怒了他，因为他决定有必要让我知道，他连上帝或魔鬼都不怕，更何况区区一个普通人。我说我看得出来他是很勇敢的，但我想要的是一些铆钉——如果库尔茨先生知道这里的情况，他也会需要铆钉。现在每周都有人送信去岸边……‘我亲爱的先生，’他喊道，‘我的信完全是经理口授的。’我要求把铆钉送来。办法总比困难多——对于一个聪明人来讲。他的态度变得非常冷淡，突然间谈起一只河马的故事。他觉得很奇怪，为什么我能安心睡在船上（我一天到晚都守在船上）。有一只可恶的老河马，喜欢晚上爬上岸，在贸易站一带四处乱跑。那些朝圣者常常倾巢而出，把所有来复枪都找出来向它开火，直到弹药耗尽。甚至有人通宵埋伏等待它。可是他们都白费力气。‘那畜生好像受到魔法的保护，’他说，‘但在这里，只有畜生是受魔法保护的。人却没有——您理解我的意思吗？——这里的魔法是不保护人的。’他在月光下站了一阵子，把他那优美的鹰钩鼻稍稍偏过去，他那双云母片似的眼睛一直睁着，泛着光。然后，他匆匆说了声晚安，大步离去。我可以看出他动摇了，也很困惑，这些天我一直很压抑，现在终于看到了希望。甩掉那家伙后，我回到我那有权有势的靠山身旁，那条破破烂烂的、歪歪扭扭的、溃不成形的、一文不值的汽船。我吃力地爬上甲板，脚下哐啷作响，就像一个空的亨帕[21]饼干桶被人沿着下水道一路踢过去时发出的声音。她造得不够结实，外观也不够漂亮，但我在她身上付出了那么多艰辛的劳动，我无法不爱她。没哪个有权有势的朋友比她更派得上用场。她给了我一个机会，让我出去闯一闯——去发现我有什么能耐。不，我不喜欢工作。我情愿游手好闲，做做白日梦。我不喜欢工作——没人喜欢——但我喜欢藏在工作里的玄机——发现自我的机会。发现真实的自我——为自己，不为他人——其他人永远不会知道。他们只能看见肤浅的表面，永远说不清楚个中真谛。

我看见有人坐在船尾的甲板上，悬着两条腿在烂泥上方。我并不感到惊讶。你们瞧，我和站里仅有的几个技工称兄道弟，而其他朝圣者自然是不把他们放在眼里的——我想是因为他们举止不够得体。这一位是工头——负责制造锅炉的——非常称职。他个子高高的，骨瘦如柴，脸色蜡黄，一双大眼睛炯炯有神。他总是愁眉不展，头顶像我的手心一样秃，但他掉的头发好像粘在了下巴上，在新的地方开枝散叶，因为他的胡子一直垂到腰部。他是个鳏夫，有六个年幼的孩子（为了出来赚钱，他把孩子们留给一个亲妹妹照顾），他最喜欢飞鸽，那给了他生活的热情。他是飞鸽迷，也是行家，快要走火入魔了。下班后，他有时会从他的小屋走过来，和我聊他的孩子和鸽子。工作的时候，他不得不爬进汽船下面，弄得满身烂泥，他便用一块类似餐巾的白布把胡子扎起来。他特意把这块布带在身边，布的两头各有一个小环，可以套在耳朵上。晚上可以看到他蹲在岸边，在小溪里仔仔细细地把它冲洗干净，然后一本正经地摊在灌木丛上晾干。

我用力拍一下他的背部，大喊道：‘我们要有铆钉了！’他手忙脚乱地爬起来，喊道：‘不会吧！铆钉！’就像他不能相信自己的耳朵，又低声说，‘您不会……？’我不知道为什么我们俩好像得了精神病一样。我把手指放在鼻子上，神秘地点点头。‘恭喜你！’他大喊起来，在头顶上打响指，跷起一只脚。我拉他一起跳吉格舞[22]。我们在铁做的甲板上欢呼雀跃。船身发出恐怖的哐啷声，河对面的原始森林送来回声，像滚滚天雷一样，碾过沉睡的贸易站。它肯定把住在茅屋里的某些朝圣者吓得坐了起来。经理小屋的走廊亮着灯，一个黑影挡住光，又消失了，又过了一秒钟左右，走廊也消失了。我们停下来，被我们的踏脚声驱散了的宁静，又从大地深处汹涌回来。那堵草木巨墙，由无数树干、树枝、树叶和藤蔓纠缠而成，盘根错节，在月光中寂静不动，仿佛无声的生命发起了一场狂暴的侵略，一个植物的巨浪，翻得有天那么高，海啸般冲压下来，要横扫我们这些渺小的人，击碎我们渺小的存在。但它始终没有动。远方突然爆发出一阵滞闷的拍水声和鼻息声，我们听得清清楚楚，仿佛有一条鱼龙在水面嬉戏，掀起阵阵银光闪闪的浪花。‘说到底，’锅炉匠头脑清楚地说，‘怎么可能会不给我们铆钉呢？’怎么可能，的确！我也想不出为什么会不给我们铆钉。‘三周内运到。’我充满信心地说。

但并没有运到。取而代之的是一场侵略、人祸和天灾。这一切在接下来的三周里陆续袭来。每一次都是由一个骑着驴的白人带头，他穿着新衣服和黄皮靴，在高高的驴背上左一下右一下地向朝圣者们点头哈腰，让他们深受感动。一帮吵吵嚷嚷的黑人紧跟在驴子后面，他们走得腿酸脚疼，一脸阴沉，他们把一大堆帐篷、野营凳、铁皮箱、白箱子、棕色包裹扔在院子里，把贸易站弄得更加混乱，站上的神秘气氛也加深了一层。这样的商队一共来了五个，他们神色慌张，仿佛刚刚抢完无数服装店和粮食店，逃到这里来喘口气。看见他们那可笑的神情，人们当然会认为他们是要跑到没有人的荒野去安心分赃。因为商品太多而忙中生乱，实属正常，但这群蠢货却弄得这么鬼鬼祟祟，真不像样。

这帮爱岗敬业的人把自己称作埃尔多拉多探险队，我相信他们宣过誓，不能对外泄露机密的。然而，他们一开口就是下流肮脏的海盗腔：莽撞却软弱，贪婪却畏缩，残暴却胆小。他们这一大帮人都缺乏远大的目光和严肃的目标，而他们又似乎并没有意识到，要做出点成绩，这两者都是不可或缺的。他们一心只想着把财物从大地的肠子中掏出来，丝毫没有道德上的目标，跟强盗撬保险箱的行为差不多。我不知道是谁出钱资助了这一系列高尚的行动，但我们经理的叔父正好是这帮人的头目。

他的外表像贫民窟里的屠夫，眼里闪着一种昏昏欲睡的狡猾。他把大肚子架在一双短腿上，好像感到很自豪似的。在他那帮人把贸易站搞得乌七八糟期间，他只跟自己的侄子说话。叔侄两人不避嫌疑地整天四处游荡，两个脑袋紧紧靠在一起，没日没夜地密谈着。

“我已经把铆钉的事情抛开了。一个人对于那些蠢材的忍耐是有限度的。我说：去死吧！——就撒手不管了。这样一来，我获得了充足的时间来思考，时不时地，我会想到库尔茨。我也不是对他很感兴趣。并没有。但我很想知道，这个人怀揣着那些道德观念来到这里，是不是能最终爬上经理的位子，而他当上了经理之后，又会干出些什么事情来。”

第二章

有一晚，我正舒舒服服地平躺在汽船的甲板上，忽然听到有人在说话，声音越来越近——那对叔侄正在沿河散步。我重新把头枕在手臂上，正要昏昏入睡的时候，又突然听见有人在我耳边说话，说的大概是：‘我就跟个小孩儿一样天真无邪，但我不想被人指挥得团团转。我到底是不是经理？居然命令我把他送去那里。简直是疯了。’……我忽然意识到，那两人正站在船头边的河岸上，就在我脑袋下面。我没动。我压根没想过要动：我困得很。‘确实够可恶的。’叔叔咕哝着说。‘他主动向公司的领导们请求派他去那里，’另一个说，‘还不就是想要显摆一下自己的才能吗？然后他们就命令我送他去了。他们偏就这么信任他！太可怕了！’他们一致认定这非常可怕，又说了些古怪的话：‘要风得风，要雨得雨——就只他一个人——委员会——任他摆布’——这些杂乱无章的只言片语驱散了我的睡意。等我完全清醒过来，听见叔叔说：‘气候可以帮助你解决这个困难。那里只有他自己一个人？’‘是的，’经理回答，他派助手到下游来，捎给我一张纸条，上面居然写着：把这个可怜的魔鬼赶走，并且别再费事派给我这样的傻瓜了。我宁可孤身一人，也不愿意让那些听你指使的人来帮我！那是一年多以前的事情。真想不到他会这么蛮不讲理！‘’那之后还有他的消息吗？‘另一个粗声地问。’象牙，‘侄子结结巴巴地说，’很多象牙——头等的——很多——从他那里送来，真可恶。‘’和象牙一起送来的还有什么？‘粗哑的低音问。侄子好像放炮一般回答道：’发货清单。之后便是一片寂静。他们谈的，是库尔茨。

那时我已经非常清醒了，但放松躺着实在是太舒服，便一动不动，不想转换姿势。‘这么远的路，那些象牙是怎么送来的？’那个年长一些的人嘶吼着说，似乎非常苦恼。另一个解释道，是由库尔茨的贴身办事员，一个英国籍的混血儿领着一队独木舟运来的。显然库尔茨原本打算亲自把象牙运回来，贸易站那时已经既没有商品，也没有存粮，但走了三百英里后，他突然决定折回去，便自己一人坐上一条小独木舟，让四个人帮他划桨，并吩咐混血儿将象牙继续运往下游。竟然有人做出这样疯狂的举动，那两个家伙似乎大为震惊。他们无法猜测出一个合理的动机。对我而言，则仿佛第一次看见了库尔茨。那是一个如此鲜明的画面：独木舟，四个划桨的野蛮人，和那个突然之间义无反顾地把公司总部、安逸的生活和——也许——乡愁都抛在身后的白人，他是如此形单影只，执意要走入荒野深处，走向那凄荒的贸易站。我不知道他的动机。也许他不过是一个好人，他一心扑在工作上，纯粹是出于对工作本身的热爱。而他的名字，他们一次也没说出来。他是‘那个人’。而那个混血儿，据我所听到的，兢兢业业、奋不顾身地指挥了那次困难的旅程，他们却一直叫他‘那个无赖’。那个‘无赖’报告说那个‘人’有一次病得很严重——到现在也没有完全恢复……我下方的两个人随后走了开去，在不远处来回走动。我听到：‘军营——医生——两百英里——现在挺孤独的——不可避免的延误——九个月——没有消息——奇怪的谣言。’他们又走回来，经理一边说着：‘据我所知，除了那个游商之外——那个社会的害虫，只有他能从土人那里弄来象牙。’他们现在在谈论谁呢？通过这些零碎的话，我猜是库尔茨的某个手下，而且经理很讨厌他。‘如果不吊死一两个这样的家伙，以儆效尤，我们就只能一直当不公平竞争的受害者。’他说。‘当然了，’另一个咕哝道，‘吊死他！为什么不？任何事情——在这里你可以肆无忌惮地做任何事情。就是这样。你要明白，在这里，没有人可以威胁到你的职位。为什么？你受得了这里的气候——你活得比他们都要久。危险在欧洲，但在我离开那里之前，我已经尽量——’他们走了开去，交谈声变成一阵模糊的窃窃私语，然后又高起来。‘那意外的一再延误并不能怪我。我已经尽力了。’那个胖男人叹了一口气。‘很惨。’‘还有他那蛊惑人心的胡说八道，’另一个接着说，‘他在这里的时候真是烦死人了。他说，每个贸易站都应该是沿途的指路明灯，把人们引向光明。它们当然是贸易的中心，但也是开化、进步和教育的中心。真是荒唐——那个浑蛋！而且他想要当经理！不，真是——’他愤怒过度，嗓子被噎住了。我稍稍抬起头来。我惊讶地发现原来他们离我这么近——就在我下面。我都能向他们的帽子吐口水。他们盯着地面，陷入了沉思。经理用一根纤细的树枝轻轻鞭打着自己的腿，他那精明的亲戚抬起头来。‘你这次来这儿一直没生病吧？’他问。另一个吓了一跳。‘谁？我吗？哦，上天保佑——上天保佑。但剩下的人——哦，我的天！都生病了。而且他们死得太快，我都来不及把他们运走——太神奇了！’‘哼，就该这样。’叔叔咕哝道，‘啊！我的孩子，相信这个地方——我说，相信这个地方。’我看见他伸出一条粗短得像鱼鳍的手臂，挥舞着，划过眼前的森林、小溪、泥土和河流——夕阳照亮了这片土地的外表，他却似乎要凭着这样一个无耻的动作，煞有介事地向它的内心深处发出号召，想要召唤出那潜伏的死亡、隐藏的邪恶和深邃的黑暗。那情景实在太恐怖，我惊得跳起来，甩过头去看森林的边缘，好像想看看，对于他这种信赖的表示，森林会做出什么反应。面对这两个家伙，高高的森林一动也不动，报以狰狞的耐心，静待这一场狂乱的侵略自行消失。

他们不约而同地大骂起来——全然出于恐惧，我相信——然后假装不知道我在那里，转身回贸易站去。在低低的太阳下，他们肩并着肩，身子前倾，仿佛正在吃力地拖着两条可笑的影子爬坡。那两条影子，长短不一，被他们拖在身后，缓缓碾压过深深的草地，却没有压弯一片草叶。

几天后，埃尔多拉多探险队走进了那片耐心的荒野。荒野仿佛把他们吞了进去，就像大海吞掉一个潜水员一样。很久以后，我听见消息说所有的驴都死了。至于那些不及驴值钱的动物，我完全不知道他们命运如何。他们，毫无疑问，就像我们这些留下来的人那样，求得了自己应有的命运。我没有问。那时我即将要与库尔茨会面，正相当兴奋地憧憬着。我说‘即将’，是相对而言。从我们离开那条河算起，到抵达他那个贸易站下面的河边，又过了两个月。

“沿河驶往上游，就像驶回原始世界，那个草木席卷地球、大树称王的时代。空的河，无边的寂静，密不透风的森林。空气温暖、浓稠、沉重而迟滞。灿烂的阳光中，了无喜悦。长长的水道奔流向前，一路上杳无人迹，奔入远处阴惨的浓荫中。在银光闪闪的沙岸上，河马和短吻鳄并肩躺着晒太阳。水面越来越开阔，流过一个又一个绿树茂密的小岛。在那条河上，就像在沙漠里一样，极易迷路，一心想驶到水深处，却总是撞上沙洲。直到你觉得自己疯了，过去认识的一切永远也回不来了——它们在某个地方——很远——也许在另一个时空。有那么一些片刻，往事会涌上心头，就像当人完全没有时间独处的时候，会不时地想起过去的片段一样。但这些回忆像扰攘嘈杂的梦，在这个只有植物、水和寂静的世界里，在无法挣脱的现实底下，它们是如此不真实。这种生命的沉静，完全无法使人安宁。那是一股无法抗拒的力量所表现出来的沉静，笼罩着谜一样的意图。它盯着你，仿佛跟你仇深似海。后来我就习惯了，没有再看见它，因为没时间。我不得不一直摸索航道；我不得不几乎全靠直觉地去寻找河岸的蛛丝马迹；我小心翼翼地提防水底的石头；我学会了咬紧牙关，不让心脏跳出来，一个狡猾的老暗桩就能轻易划开这条破船，所有朝圣者都将掉进水里淹死；我不得不留心注意哪里有枯树，晚上去砍掉，第二天用来烧锅炉。当你不得不对付这些事情，用全副精神对付肉眼所能看见的无数琐事，现实——现实，我是说——就不见了。内在的真相总是看不见的——幸好，幸好。但我仍然能感受到它。我常常觉得它那神秘的沉静盯着我，看我在耍猴戏，就像它在盯着你们这些家伙，看你们踩在各自的钢丝上表演——表演什么来着？半克朗[23]翻一个跟头那种……”

“别说得那么难听，马洛！”一个声音咆哮道，这下我知道身边至少有一个听众还醒着。

抱歉。我忘了还要额外付一点钱，给你们拿去治心痛。其实价钱有什么要紧呢，只要把戏耍得好？你们耍得很好。我也没有耍得很糟糕，那可是我第一次指挥航行，我没让那条汽船沉掉。对我而言，这仍然是一个奇迹。试想一下，假如你们要驾驶小货车走过一条糟糕的路，却被蒙住眼睛的情景。不怕你们笑话，那趟航行着实让我大汗淋漓，浑身颤抖。毕竟，对一个海员来说，没能照顾好一个本应一直浮在水上的东西，把它的底刮穿了，简直是滔天大罪。可能没人怀疑到你身上去，但你永远忘不了那‘砰’的一声——是不是？简直就像撞在心上。你记得它，梦见它，半夜惊醒时想起它——很多年以后——浑身冷一阵热一阵的。我承认那条汽船也并没有一直浮在水上。她不止一次地蹭进了河底的烂泥里，只好请二十个食人族的生番把她团团围住，在水里噼里啪啦地往前推。这些家伙是我们沿路捎上的，给我们当水手。真不错——这些食人族——很称职。他们是工作上的好搭档，我对他们感激万分。况且，他们并没有在我们眼前你吃我我吃你：他们带了一批腐烂了的河马肉上船当食物，使得荒野的神秘气氛染上了阵阵扑鼻的恶臭。呜！我仿佛又闻到了。船上还有经理和三四个武装着棍子的朝圣者——全都安然无恙。有时我们经过岸边紧挨着未开发地区的贸易站，白人们从摇摇欲坠的小屋里狂奔而出，做着夸张的手势，表示他们是多么喜出望外以及多么盼望我们到来。他们看起来是如此的诡异——仿佛是被某个魔咒禁锢在那个地方。‘象牙’这个单词会在空中回旋那么一阵子——我们继续前进，回到寂静之中，行驶在荒凉的河道上，绕过死滞的河湾，曲曲折折地在两岸高耸的峭壁之间穿行，船尾明轮笨重地拍着水，那空洞的声音惹起阵阵回响。树，树，成千棵，成万棵，粗大的，巨大的，天一般高；在它们脚下，这一艘脏污的小汽船，紧贴着岸，逆流艰难前行，就像在巍峨的门廊下，一只迟缓的甲虫在地板上缓缓爬过。在那种情境下，人显得那么渺小和迷茫，然而那种感觉并不怎么压抑。毕竟，即使你很渺小，那只脏兮兮的小甲虫也还是向前爬着——这就是你对它的全部要求。在朝圣者的想象中，它会爬去哪里，我不知道。但我敢打赌，一定是一个有利可图的地方！对我而言，它爬向的是库尔茨——一心一意地。但后来蒸汽管开始漏水，我们爬得慢极了。一段又一段的河道在我们眼前展开，又渐渐消失于我们身后，仿佛森林不慌不忙地横穿水面，隔断了我们的后路。我们越走越深，探进了黑暗的心。那里异常安静。夜深的时候，帷幕一般的树林背后，沿河传来隆隆的鼓声，隐隐地彻夜作响，仿佛高高地在我们头顶上空盘桓不绝。这到底是战争、和平还是捕猎的鼓声，我们无从分辨。鼓声戛然而止，天地蓦然陷入一片寒冷的寂静之中——黎明即将来临。伐木工们还在沉睡，他们的篝火快要熄灭了，树枝折断的噼啪声也惊心动魄。我们是史前地球上的流浪者，流浪在一个未知的星球上，周围是全然陌生的风景。我们本可以把这片土地想象成一笔会给继承者带来厄运的遗产，而自己是第一批来接收它的人，想要征服它，必须以刻骨的痛苦和残酷的辛劳作为代价。但当我们艰难地转了一个弯，又会蓦然遇上许多草墙、尖削的茅草屋顶、一阵狂叫、许多乱挥乱甩的黑手臂、嘈杂的拍手声和跺脚声、摇摇晃晃的身躯、疯转的眼珠，在一大片低垂着，沉重得一动不动的枝叶底下。汽船就这样沿着那片阴暗而不可理喻的狂乱吃力前进。这些史前人类是在诅咒我们，在向我们祈祷，又还是在欢迎我们——谁能分辨？我们已经完全无法理解周围的环境，我们像幽灵一样飘过，充满好奇，却又暗暗恐惧着，就像神志正常的人一头撞进了疯人院里的一场暴乱。我们无法理解，因为我们已经走得太远，我们记不起来，因为我们是在原始时代的黑夜里航行，而那个时代已经一去不复返，不留下一丝痕迹——和记忆。

那片土地仿佛不属于地球。我们所习惯的地球，就像一个被制服了的怪物，被五花大绑，但那里——在那里你可以看到一个自由的怪物。那不属于地球，那里的人也——不，他们也是人。啊，你们看，那才是最糟糕的——怀疑他们也是人。渐渐地你总会怀疑起来。他们大吼大叫，乱蹦乱跳，疯狂地转圈，做出狰狞的表情，但真正令人不寒而栗的，是想到他们也有人性——跟你们一样的人性——让你们想到远古的亲属，和他们一样，狂野而暴躁，骚动不安。太丑陋。是的，丑陋极了。但如果你毕竟还是一个人，就会向自己承认，这种诚实得可怕的噪声，唤起了身体深处最隐秘的回响，令你产生模糊的怀疑，怀疑那声音包含着某种意义，某种你能够——即使离那些太初的夜晚如此遥远——能够理解的意义。为什么不？人的头脑无所不能——因为它包含了一切，包含了全部的过去以及将来。而那里面究竟有什么？喜悦，恐惧，忧伤，虔诚，勇气，愤怒——谁又知道？——除了真相——脱去了时间外衣的真相。就让那些愚蠢的人目瞪口呆、胆战心惊——真正的人自然会懂得，并一直冷眼旁观。但起码，他必须和这些岸上的人一样，也是人。他必须用真实的自己来拥抱那个真相——用他天生的力量。原则？原则不行。后天得来的一切，像衣服，不过是一块华丽的布——一扯就掉。不，你需要的是一个饱经风霜的信念。他们鬼哭神嚎，是想唤醒我吗——是不是？很好，我听见了，我也承认确实如此，但我也有想说的话，不论是好是坏，没有人能够阻止我说出来。当然了，那些战战兢兢而玉洁冰清的傻瓜是永远安全的。谁在那里嘟哝？你想知道我为什么不跳上岸，和他们一起咆哮，一起跳舞？好吧，不——我没有。你说什么？我玉洁冰清？胡说！我是没有时间。我不得不手忙脚乱地用白铅粉和羊毛毡包住漏水的蒸汽管——我忙坏了。我不得不看紧船舵，躲开暗桩，用尽一切办法让那条破烂的船往前开下去。这么明显的事情，不用比我更加聪明也看得出来。我还得时不时去盯一眼那个负责烧锅炉的野蛮人。他是一个经过改良的样本，懂得烧立式锅炉。我低头就能看见他，而且，一点不假，看着他就仿佛在看着一条狗，学人样穿着短裤，戴着羽毛帽子，用两条后腿走路，令人深受启发。这个很不错的伙计没有白受那几个月的培训。他明显是鼓足了勇气，才敢蹲在蒸汽计量仪和水位指示器前——他的牙齿被锉得尖尖的，这个可怜的魔鬼，头顶毛茸茸的鬈发剃成古怪的图案，双颊上各有三个用作装饰的疤痕。他本应在岸上拍手跺脚，但却埋头工作，仿佛被施了奇怪的魔法，满脑子都是进步的知识。他是个有用的人，因为受过训练，他只知道，如果那根玻璃管里面的水干了，住在锅炉里面的魔鬼就会因为口渴而大发雷霆，实施可怕的报复。所以他诚惶诚恐地盯着玻璃管，汗如雨下，仔细添火（他手臂上系着一个临时准备的护身符，是一块破布，另外还有一块磨得光亮的骨头，和手表一样大，打平穿过下嘴唇），而那密密丛丛的河岸慢慢从我们身边划过，岸上的吵闹声渐渐远去，又是无数英里的寂静——我们继续向前爬，爬向库尔茨。但到处都是暗桩，浅浅的河水极其凶险，锅炉里面好像真的有一个狂怒的魔鬼，所以锅炉工和我都忙得焦头烂额，没有时间仔细咀嚼心中那些恐怖的念头。

在离内地贸易站大概五十英里远的地方，我们路过一座用芦苇盖的小屋。屋子前面竖着一根歪歪斜斜的木杆，看得人心里难受，上面飞扬着碎布条，图案已经辨不清了，但依稀看得出曾经是一面旗。还有一堆码得整整齐齐的木头。真意外。我们上了岸，发现那堆木头上面有一块木板，写着褪了色的铅笔字。我们仔细反复辨认出写的是：‘木头给你们。尽快。小心靠近。’下面有签名，但看不清楚——不是库尔茨——比库尔茨的名字长得多。尽快。尽快去哪里？往上游去吗？‘小心靠近。’我们靠近时可没有小心。但这个警告说的不是这里，因为我们只有靠近了这里，才能看得见警告。上游肯定是出事了。但出了什么事——严重吗？这才是我们关心的啊！干吗写得像份电报一样啊，真够愚蠢的。周围的灌木丛默默地挡住了我们远望的视线。小屋门口挂着一张破破烂烂的红色斜纹布门帘，哀哀地打到我们脸上来。这座小屋已经荒废了，但看得出来，不久前这里曾经住过一位白人男士。屋里还放着一张简陋的桌子——用两条木棍支着一块木板，一个黑暗的角落里堆着垃圾。我在门的旁边捡到一本书。封面已经不见了，书页被翻得极脏极软，书脊却被人拿白棉线非常用心地重新装订过，那棉线还很干净。那是一个惊人的发现。这本书名叫《航海术探究》，作者是陶泽或陶森——大约是这么念的，是一位皇家海军的船长。我翻了一下，内容枯燥得要命，有许多说明性的图表和可恨的数字表格，已经出版六十年了。我极尽温柔地捧着这个神奇的古董，生怕它会在我的手里化成灰。在书中，陶森或者陶泽，热心地探讨了锚链和绞辘能承受的最大拉力和其他类似的问题。这本书并不好看，然而它那单纯的目的一目了然，是如此真心实意地在探寻工作的正确方法，使得这些卑微的书页，那么多年前的思想，不仅能给人以专业上的指导，还带来了其他启示。这位简单直率的老水手，在认认真真谈着锚链和绞辘，使我忘记了丛林和朝圣者，沉浸于一种美好的感受之中，仿佛终于找到了某些确凿不移的真实。在那里，光是这本书的存在就已经不可思议，而更令人震惊的是，页边竟然还有笔记，用铅笔做的，明显与正文相关。难道我在做梦！笔记全是用密码写的！确实，看起来跟密码似的。居然会有人费心把这么一本书带到这个荒无人烟的地方来，认真研读——还要做笔记——而且用密码！简直是天方夜谭。

有那么一阵子，我一直隐约听到一阵恼人的吵闹声。我抬起头，发现那堆木头不见了，经理和所有朝圣者都正在河边向我大喊大叫。我被迫匆匆把书塞进口袋。我发誓，当时的感觉，就仿佛被他们生生拽出了一个死党的家。

我发动破引擎，继续前行。‘肯定是这个倒霉的商人干的——这个小偷。’经理大声说，充满仇恨地回头看着我们刚刚离开的地方。‘他肯定是个英国人。’我说。‘那也不能肆意妄为，否则照样会遇上麻烦。’经理恶狠狠地说。我假装天真地评论说，人生在世，遇到些麻烦也是在所难免的。

水流越来越急，汽船似乎已经奄奄一息，船尾明轮疲倦地拍打着河面。我发现自己正踮着脚跟，全神贯注地等待下一次拍打声传来，因为我清醒地意识到，它会随时报废。那种感觉，就像看着最后的生命之光一点点消逝。但我们仍然在往前挪。有时候我会在前头不远的岸边挑出来一棵树，用来测量我们离库尔茨又近了多少，但总等不到赶上它，就忘记挑的是哪棵树了。人是不可能有耐性，做到那么长时间一直盯着同一件东西的。经理已经不失风度地退居幕后。我又苦恼又生气，开始和自己争辩，到底要不要坦诚地和库尔茨谈一次，但在我与自己达成共识之前，我就意识到，最终谈与不谈，实际上不论我做什么，都没有意义。知不知道内情又有什么关系呢？谁是经理又如何？人有时就是会这样顿然醒悟。这整件事情的关键，深藏于表面之下，我了解不到，也无从干涉。

到第二天黄昏，我们估计库尔茨的贸易站大约只在八英里开外。我想继续赶路，但经理板起脸来，告诉我继续航行太危险，太不明智，太阳快下山了，我们必须留在原地，等到第二天早上再出发。而且，他指出如果要遵从‘小心靠近’的警告，我们就应该在白天靠近——而不是在黄昏或夜里。他说得合情合理。开着这条破船，八英里要走差不多三个小时，而且前头河道上的波纹也非常可疑。然而，对于要再等一个夜晚，我莫名地感到生气。当然这很不理智，因为都等了好几个月了，再等一晚又算得了什么。既然有那么多木头，又有人警告我们要小心，我就在河中央把船停好。河道又窄又直，两岸高高地隆起来，像铁路的路堑。离太阳下山还早得很，这里就已经迫不及待地阴沉了下来。水流稳而急，但两岸一片死寂。被藤蔓绞在一起的大树尽管还活着，还有矮树丛里每一棵活着的灌木，都仿佛化作了石头，甚至连那最柔软的新枝，最轻盈的嫩叶，也冰冷僵硬。它们不是睡着了——诡异得仿佛灵魂出了窍。四周是一片全然的寂静，人害怕地睁大眼睛看着它们，渐渐怀疑自己聋了——然后黑夜突然降临，又把人砸瞎了。大约凌晨三点，一条大鱼纵身跃出水面，噼里啪啦的水声刺耳得像枪声，吓得我跳了起来。日出时，升起一团极暖极湿的白雾，比黑夜更浓稠，凝滞着，死死赖在那里，紧紧包围住你，牢不可破。等到大约八九点钟，它就像一扇百叶窗一样，渐渐上升消散。我们又能够看上一眼那些参天大树，缠成一片的乱林，太阳悬在上空，像一个炙热的小球——全部都纹丝不动——然后那扇白色的百叶窗又迅速地稳稳落下，好像滑下一个上满润滑油的滑槽。我命令把刚刚收上来一点的锚抛回去。锚链还在钝重地嘎嘎响着，突然传来一声惊叫，叫得山崩地裂，仿佛从无尽的凄凉里喊出来，在灰暗的空气中缓缓飞升。它停了，然后是一片哀怨的吵闹声，混在野蛮人古怪的喧哗里。仅仅是因为猝不及防，我帽子里的头发就全部倒竖起来。我不知道别人对此有何感想：这场凄惨凌乱的骚动是如此突然，而且明显从四面八方同时爆发出来，我觉得就像是那片迷雾本身在惊叫。这场骚动突然进入高潮，爆发出一声震耳欲聋的尖叫，戛然而止。我们惊讶得呆若木鸡，在原地保持着各种可笑的姿势，仍然固执地想要在可怕得过分的寂静里听出点什么声音来。‘善良的上帝啊！这是在干什么——’我身边一个朝圣者结结巴巴地说——他矮胖，黄发红须，穿着绑边靴子和粉红色的睡衣，裤腿塞进袜子里。另外两个朝圣者张着嘴巴发了整整一分钟的呆，然后冲进小小的船舱，又跌跌撞撞地跑出来，站定了，恐惧地左顾右盼，紧紧攥住‘上好膛’的温彻斯特步枪。我们能看见的只有汽船，她的轮廓模糊地淡进雾里，仿佛随时要融掉，还有她周围那雾茫茫的狭长水道，大约两英尺宽——就这么多。凭我们的耳目，无法感知到余下的世界。也许耳目之外根本就了无一物。逝去了，消失了；被吹散了，了无声息，了无踪影。

我跑向船头，命令立刻拉紧锚链，以便随时起锚开船。‘他们会袭击我们吗？’一个恐惧的声音轻轻地说。‘我们逃不出这片雾，他们会把我们全部杀掉。’另一个含糊不清地说。朝圣者们的脸因为紧张而抽搐，手微微战抖，眼睛一眨不眨。我饶有兴味地拿这些白人的表情和黑人水手做比较。对于这段河流，黑人水手和我们一样陌生，尽管它距离他们的家只有八百英里。这些白人当然是心乱如麻，还因为被一阵如此野蛮的吵闹声惊吓到而倍感痛苦，露出古怪的表情。黑人则带着警惕，自然流露出对事情表示关注的神情，但他们几乎都是一脸平静，甚至有那么一两个人在收锚链的时候竟然在笑。其中几个相互简短地嘟哝了几个词语，似乎这阵吵闹声就得到了妥善的解释。他们的头领是一个年轻健壮的黑人，郑重其事地披着用流苏镶边的深蓝色衣服，鼻孔大得吓人，头发全被熟练地编成油汪汪的发卷。他正好站在我身边。‘啊哈！’我点点头说，只是为了表示友好。‘抓住他！’他厉声说，睁圆发红的眼睛，锋利的牙齿寒光闪闪——‘抓住他。把他交给我们。’‘给你们干什么？’我问，‘你们要对他做什么？’‘吃了他！’他粗暴地说，把一只手肘抵在栏杆上，望进浓雾中，表情凝重，仿佛陷入了庄严而深邃的沉思。要不是突然想到他和同伴们肯定已经饥肠辘辘，我肯定会被吓个半死：至少在过去一个月里，他们的饥饿感一定与日俱增。他们的聘期是六个月（我想在他们这些人里，没有一个对时间有明确概念，正如无数个世纪前的我们一样。他们还生活在混沌的原始时代——可以说，没有继承到任何可供学习的经验。），当然了，在河的下游，有人制定了某项荒唐的法律，只要根据它签好合同，没人会费心过问这些黑人在这段时间里吃的是什么。他们确实是带了一些腐烂的河马肉，但就算那些朝圣者没有为此大吵大闹，把它们扔进河里，那么点肉也吃不了多久。朝圣者们这么做当然有点专横跋扈，但确实也可算作合法自卫。试问如果你不论是睡是醒，还是在吃饭，都要闻着死河马的气味，又怎么能够分出神来，在险境里保全性命？况且他们每周付给这些黑人三根铜丝，每根大概长九英寸。从理论上讲，黑人们可以用这些货币在河边的村庄购买食物。结果很明显。要不就没有村庄，要不就是村民极不友善，又或者是那个跟我们一样天天吃罐头，偶尔还能吃到公羊肉的经理，举出某个难以解释的理由拒绝停船。所以，除非他们直接把铜丝吃掉，或者做成环来捉鱼，我看不出这笔高得离谱的薪水有什么用。我不得不说，薪水按时支付，倒是大贸易公司的做派，极守信誉。剩下唯一能吃的东西——尽管看起来完全无法下咽——我只看见他们有几团紫色的脏东西，像半熟的面团，包在树叶里保存，不时拿出来吞一块。但每一次都吃得那么少，好像只是在做样子，根本达不到维持生命的目的。他们为什么没有借口说受不了饥饿魔鬼的折磨而袭击我们——他们是三十对五——并马上吃个痛快呢？我到现在也想不明白。他们高大强壮，不懂瞻前顾后，勇武有力，尽管那时他们的皮肤不再像原先那么光洁，肌肉也松弛了。我看出了某种东西在约束着他们，阻止了这个完全有可能发生的行为，那是人性的奥秘之一。我看着他们，兴趣暴增——不是因为我醒悟到随时会被他们吃掉，尽管我承认，在那一刻我忽然发现——可以说是以全新的目光——那些朝圣者看起来是多么倒胃口，而我希望，是的，我确实希望，自己看起来不是——怎么说才好呢？——那么——令人难以下咽：这小小的虚荣心，实在是异想天开，不过我当时整日都处在半梦半醒的状态，有这种想法也不奇怪。也许我还有点发烧。人不可能一直对自己的生活状态明察秋毫。我经常‘有点发烧’，或其他什么小毛病——荒野调皮地伸出爪子抓了人一下，虽然无关痛痒，却是空前浩劫的前奏。是的，我盯着他们，和盯着任何其他人类时一样，带着好奇心，想知道在遇到肉体无法承受的考验时，他们的冲动、动机、能力和软弱将如何表现。约束！有什么能约束得住他们？是迷信、厌恶、忍耐、恐惧——还是某种原始的道义？恐惧敌不过饥饿，忍耐拖不垮饥饿，厌恶在饥饿面前总是荡然无存，至于迷信、信仰，或是你们所说的原则，也不过是风里的浮尘。你们知道吗？无休无止的饥饿有多么残忍，把人折磨得怒火中烧，产生阴暗的念头，而它只是黑压压地盘旋不去，简直是丧心病狂。啊，我可是知道。它使人穷尽天生的力量去抗争。丧亲之痛、身败名裂之耻和灵魂之毁灭真的算不了什么——与这种没有尽头的饥饿相比。多么可悲，但事实就是如此。这些家伙也完全没有必要像俗世里的人一样感到良心不安。约束！我还不如在一条奔向战场撕吃尸体的鬣狗身上找自我约束。但我面前明摆着一个事实，看得人眼花缭乱，像深海上浮泛的泡沫，像谜团表面的蛛丝马迹——海一样深的谜团。那片野蛮的号叫声，从河边传来，隔着看不穿的白雾，叫得如此悲哀绝望、离奇古怪和不知所云，在我们身边席卷而过，其中含义已经足够神秘，但每当我想起这个事实，还是觉得它要比这种含义神秘得多。

有两个朝圣者着急地低声争辩着应该往哪边靠岸。‘左边。’‘不，不，你别乱来。右边，右边，毫无疑问！’‘情况严重，非常严重，’经理的声音从我身后传来，‘要是库尔茨先生在我们到达之前有什么闪失，剩我一个人孤零零的可怎么办？’我盯着他，对他的真心实意毫不怀疑。他就是那种力求保全大局的人。那是他自我约束的表现。但当他嘟嘟囔囔说什么必须马上开船的时候，我简直懒得理他。我知道，他也知道，那是不可能的。要是我们拉起锚，绝对会飘起来——飘上天，我们就不知道会飘去哪里——去上游还是下游，或是横着飘——直到我们在这边或者那边靠岸——并且一下子不知道是在左边还是右边靠的岸。我当然没有起锚。我不想撞船。没有比那里更不适合发生沉船事故的地方了。就算不马上淹死，也会眨眼间以某种方式死掉。‘我准许您冒一切风险开船。’他在片刻沉默之后说道。‘我拒绝冒任何风险。’我粗鲁地说。他早料到我会这么说，但可能我的语气还是吓到了他。‘既然如此，我必须尊重您的决定。您才是船长。’他客客气气地说。我转过身去背向他，以表感谢。我看着浓雾。它会持续多久？越看越绝望。库尔茨在这片凄凉的丛林里搜掠象牙，要找到他真是危险重重，就好像他是中了魔咒的公主，沉睡在一个童话的城堡里。‘他们会攻击我们吗，您觉得？’经理用信赖的语气问。

我觉得不会。有几个明显的原因。浓雾是一个。如果他们坐独木舟离岸，在雾里肯定找不着北，就像我们现在轻举妄动的结果一样。而且，据我判断，两岸的森林密不透风，他们走不出来——可树林里有许多双眼睛，早已看见了我们。河边的丛林一定异常稠密，但那些土人显然能够穿过丛林后面的灌木丛。然而，雾散那片刻，在这整条河道上都看不见独木舟——更别说在汽船两侧。但真正使我深信他们不会攻击的，是那片声音的本质——我们刚才听到的那片喊叫声。它不够凶猛，并没有传达出马上要发动进攻的意图。尽管它是如此突然、粗野和残暴，我却不得不承认，它给我的印象是哀伤的。那些土人一瞥见汽船，不知怎的，内心就充满了无法抑制的哀伤。危险，如果有的话，我解释说，那是由于我们接近了喷薄而出的人类激情。甚至极端的悲伤，最终也可能通过暴力发泄出来——但多数时候，它只是表现为死一般的冷漠……

真想让你们看看那些朝圣者瞠目结舌的表情！他们笑不出来，甚至也懒得骂我胡说，但我相信他们认为我疯了——也许是认为我被吓傻了吧。我煞有介事地对他们发表演讲。我亲爱的伙计们，担忧没有用。保持密切注意？好吧，你们能想象我当时有多么全神贯注地在寻找雾散的迹象，就像猫在伏击老鼠那样。但我们仿佛被深深埋在几英里厚的羊毛里一样，要眼睛来又有什么用！而且我也感觉像被埋在羊毛里一样——窒息，闷热，喘不过气来。再说了，我说的每一句话，尽管听起来有点荒诞不经，却丝毫不假。后来被我们称作攻击的那次行动，其实也只是想把我们赶走。那次行动远算不上攻击——甚至从一般意义上说，也不是防御性的：仅仅是绝望中本能的挣扎，本质上纯属自卫。

我想，雾散了之后，大约过了两三个小时，事态才有所进展。转机出现在距离库尔茨的贸易站大约一英里半的地方。我们刚刚费尽九牛二虎之力转过一个河湾，看见河流中央有一个小岛，或者说不过是一个小土丘，覆满了鲜亮的绿草。似乎是一个小孤岛，但当我们沿河深入，我发现原来有一条很长的沙洲，这个小岛是沙洲的起点。又或者说，它是一长串小浅滩的起点。这些小浅滩颜色暗淡，刚好被水没过，正像人的脊梁骨，在后背的皮肤底下隐约可见，直直地排下去。那时，根据我看见的情况，我可以选择在沙洲的左边或者右边行驶。两边的河道对我而言当然都是陌生的。河岸看起来根本没有区别，深度看起来也一样，但既然有人告诉过我贸易站在西边，我自然选择了西边的河道。

我们刚开进去，就发现这边的河道比预想中狭窄得多。我们左边是那条连绵不绝的沙洲，右边是又高又陡的河岸，灌木丛生。灌木丛上方是密密地排成一列列的大树。河道上空垂下厚密的枝叶，不时地，某棵树的大树枝横伸出来，冷冷地挡住前进的路。正午已经过去了好几小时，森林面目幽沉，向水面投下了一大片长长的阴影。我们在这片阴影里前行——你们也想象得到有多么举步维艰。我把她转向岸边，贴岸行驶——探测杆测出岸边的水最深。

我的一位朋友就在我脚下的船头处测量着水深，他虽然饥饿难耐，却也不急不怨。这条汽船恰像一艘安上了甲板的平底船。甲板上有两间带门窗的小柚木房子。锅炉在船头，引擎在船尾，几根柱子撑起一个轻而薄的顶棚，罩住整个甲板。烟囱伸出顶棚，烟囱跟前是用薄木板搭成的一个小船舱，用来做驾驶室。驾驶室里有一张沙发，两张轻便折凳，一杆装了弹药的马蒂尼-亨利步枪斜靠在角落里，此外还有一张极小的桌子，以及舵轮。正前方开了一扇大大的门，两侧各有一扇宽阔的百叶窗。当然了，门窗平时总是大开着。白天我高高地坐在驾驶室门前的顶棚边缘，晚上我睡在沙发上，或者说在沙发上努力入睡。一个黑人，体格健壮，行动敏捷，来自某个岸边的部落，由我那位可怜的前任培训过，现在当舵手。他戴着一副扎眼的黄铜耳环，一幅蓝布从腰一直裹到脚踝，总是摆出一副不可一世的样子。在我见过的傻瓜中，他最为反复无常。你在他身边的时候，他掌起舵来总是信心十足，昂首挺胸，但如果他看不见你，立刻变得手忙脚乱、无所适从，被那瘸子一样的汽船欺负得失魂落魄。

我低头盯着测深杆。每测一次，杆子便往上露出一些，让人心焦火燎。这时我看见我的测水工突然擅离职守，伸直了身子躺在甲板上，甚至连杆子都来不及拉上来。但他并没撒手，杆子垂在河水里，随波摇荡。与此同时，那位锅炉工，在我视线所及的下方，在他的锅炉前面猛然抱头坐下。我悚然一惊。接着我不得不火急万分地把目光转到河面上，因为前头有一个暗桩。棍子，小棍子，密密地飞来——铺天盖地：飕飕地飞过眼底，掉在我脚下，扎进我身后驾驶室的墙。而在这期间，这条河，河岸，森林，都一直非常安静——死一般的安静。我只听得见船尾明轮钝重的拍水声和这些棍子的噼啪声。我们狼狈地绕开了暗桩。箭，啊！有人在向我们放箭！我冲进去把朝岸的百叶窗关上。那个笨舵手，紧握轮辐，高抬双膝，狂暴地踏着脚，嘴里咯咯作响，仿佛一匹被勒疼的马。真可恶！船已经离岸不到十英尺，而且笨拙难行。我被迫马上探身出去拉上那扇笨重的百叶窗，蓦地看见在浓密的树叶里有一张脸，正好与我的脸一样高，在定定地盯着我，目露凶光。然后，突然间，好像垂在我眼前的薄纱猛然被掀开，我看到，在乱枝缠结的暗林里，涌动着赤裸的胸膛、手臂、腿和熊熊燃烧着的眼睛——丛林里密密麻麻地挤挨着乱扭乱动的人体，那青铜色的皮肤上，油光乱闪。树枝在摇，在晃，在沙沙作响，乱箭从里面疾飞而出，然后百叶窗合上了。‘直着往前开。’我对舵手说。他定定地昂着头，脸朝前，但不断转动眼睛。他一边继续掌舵，一边重复着抬起双脚又轻轻放下，嘴里微微冒着白泡。‘不许动来动去！’我怒火中烧地向他说。我还不如去命令风里的树不要摇来摇去。我冲出驾驶室。下方的铁甲板上传来人心惶惶的脚步声和惊慌失措的喊叫声。一个声音尖叫道：‘求你把船往回开！’我看见一个V字形的水纹，就在前头水面上。什么？又是暗桩！下层甲板上传来一阵枪声。朝圣者们用温彻斯特步枪开火了，但他们这样做毫无杀伤力，完全是浪费铅弹。霎时间一阵浓烟滚滚，缓缓前移。我对着烟骂了几声。现在水纹和暗桩都消失了。我在门边窥视着，箭蜂拥而至。它们可能淬了毒，但看起来连猫也杀不死。丛林开始咆哮，伐木工们仿佛上了战场一般大喊大叫起来。有人就在我身后开枪，把我的耳朵都要震聋了。我回过头去，发现驾驶室里仍然翻滚着浓烟和吵闹声，连忙向船舵冲过去。那个愚蠢的黑人什么都不管了，甩开百叶窗，举起马蒂尼-亨利步枪向窗外乱射。窗口就那么大开着，他站在那里双眼发红，我狂喊他回来，一边匆忙扭转船舵，让走歪了的船驶回来。即使我想掉转船头，空间也不够了，障碍物近在眼前，隐没在那阵迷乱的烟里。刻不容缓，所以我把船一头扎向岸边，我知道那里水深。

我们慌慌张张地紧贴着岸边的灌木丛走，把伸到河上的枝叶撞得四散纷飞。下方的枪声突然停了，就像我之前预计的一样，因为子弹很快就会射光。我猛然把头向后一甩，躲过一支嗖的一声闪过驾驶室的箭，看着它从一边窗口飞进来，又从另一边飞出去。那个舵手好像疯了，挥舞着空膛的来复枪，向岸边狂喊乱叫。越过他往窗外看，有许多模糊的人影，弓着身子奔跑着，跳跃着，滑行着，若隐若现。突然，百叶窗前飞来一个巨物，来复枪掉进了水里，舵手猝然后撤几步，扭过头来，用一种怪异、深邃又熟悉的表情看了我一眼，倒在我的脚上。他头的同一侧两次撞上舵轮，我看见一根不知道什么东西，仿佛是长棍的尾段，四处噼啪乱撞，还撞翻了一张小凳子。看起来就像他从岸上某人手里把这根棍子抢了过来，却因用力过猛失去了平衡。已变薄的烟散开了，我们躲开了暗桩。往前望，我预计再前进一百码左右就可以自由地驶离河岸。我忽然发觉双脚又湿又热，连忙低头看。这个男人翻过身来，脸朝上直直地盯着我，双手紧紧握住那根棍子。那是长矛的柄，那长矛也许是被扔进窗口，也许是直戳进来，正好插穿了他肋下的腰部。矛头撕开了一个骇人的裂口，深深插了进去，已经看不见了。我的鞋子里满是血，船舵下面也死寂地漫着一摊黑红色的血，隐隐闪着光。他的眼睛泛着奇异的光泽。新一轮的枪声又爆发了。他焦灼地望着我，紧紧抓住长矛，仿佛它价值连城，我要把它夺走似的。我花了很大力气才挣脱了他的目光，把注意力重新放到驾驶上来。我腾出一只手来，在头顶上摸到汽笛的绳子，匆忙地一次又一次拉响汽笛。那片愤怒的喧闹声和喊杀声骤然停止，紧接着从树林深处传来一阵哀号，如此悲恸震颤，如此幽怨不绝，透着凄切的恐惧和彻骨的绝望，仿佛要跟随大地上最后一丝希望杳然逝去。灌木丛里一片骚动。箭雨停了，几支余箭的声音尖锐刺耳——然后又是一片死寂。在寂静中，船尾明轮那无精打采的拍水声清晰可闻。我重重地把舵向右转过去，那个朝圣者，穿着粉红色睡衣，满脸通红，狂躁不安，来到驾驶室门前。‘经理让我来——’他拖着官腔，才开口便停住，‘老天爷！’他说，直直地注视着那个伤者。

我们两个白人在旁边俯视着他，他的眼睛闪闪发光，那探求的眼神紧紧包裹着我们。我敢肯定，那眼神看起来就像他立刻要用一种听不懂的语言向我们发问，但他一言不发地去世了，一动不动地，连肌肉的抽搐也没有。只有在最后一刻，好像要回应某个我们看不见的信号，或是某声我们听不见的低语，他深深地皱了一下眉头，使他那张死去的黑脸带着一种奇异的表情，忧郁，幽深，险恶。那双眼里隐含探求之意的光辉转瞬即逝，只留下荒凉的虚空。‘你会开船吗？’我急切地问这个传话人。他一脸迟疑不决，但我紧紧抓住他的手臂，他马上明白我是在命令他去开船，不管他会不会。实话告诉你们，我急得发疯，一定要马上换掉鞋袜。‘他死了。’那个家伙深感震惊，喃喃地说。‘用不着你说，’我说，狂乱地扯开鞋带，‘而且，我猜库尔茨先生现在也已经死了。’

一时间我满脑子只想着这件事。我感到绝望透顶，好像发现了自己一直为之奋斗的东西根本只是海市蜃楼。要是我走这么远的路，只是为了和库尔茨先生谈谈，此时此刻我自然应该气恼得无以复加。和他谈谈……我把一只鞋从甲板上扔下去，开始意识到那正是我想要的——和库尔茨先生谈一次话。很奇怪，我发现自己从没想象过他在做什么，我一直只是在想象他在说什么。我没有对自己说‘现在我永远见不到他了’，或者‘现在我永远无法和他握手了’，而是‘现在我永远听不见他说话了’。他只是作为一个声音而存在。当然，在我的脑海里，他并非无所作为。难道人们不是带着各种嫉妒或溢美的口吻对我说，他搜刮、拿货物换来、诈骗或是偷了很多象牙，比所有其他代理人找到的象牙加起来还要多吗？但这不是重点。重点是，在他各种过人的天分之中，尤其鹤立鸡群，让人无法视而不见的，是他说话的能力，他的如珠妙语——那天赋极高的字句，既蛊惑人心，又烛照人心，既极为冠冕堂皇，又极为下流可耻，宛若跃动的光流，又宛若一连串的谎言，从那片密不可破的黑暗的心中流淌而出。

“我死命地把另一只鞋子也扔进河里。我想，天啊！全完了。我们走得太慢，他已经消失了——连带着他的天赋，因为某根长矛、某支箭或某根大木棍。我到底还是永远听不到那个家伙说话了——我感到悲伤，悲伤得毫无节制，歇斯底里，跟这些在灌木丛里哀号的土人一样地情感失控。就算我的信仰崩溃，就算我忽然生无可恋，也不可能感到更加悲凉，更加孤寂……为什么这么粗鲁地叹气，是谁？觉得这很荒唐吗？荒唐就荒唐吧。我亲爱的上帝！难道人就不能——来，来点烟丝。”……

他沉默了，黑夜陷入深不见底的寂静之中。然后他划着一根火柴，火光映出他的脸，瘦削，苍老，凹陷，皱纹向下坠，眼睑也向下坠，带着一副凝神冥思的表情。他贪婪地吮吸着烟斗，那张脸在忽明忽灭的焰光里，在夜色中反复地出现、消失。火柴灭了。

“荒唐！”他喊道，“这种事，怎么讲你们都不会理解……你们，这里的每一个人，都有两个安稳的归宿，就像一艘有两个锚的船，街头有肉铺，巷尾有警察，你们食欲旺盛，体温正常——听好了——从年头正常到年尾。而你们说，荒唐！说我荒唐——简直是胡说八道！荒唐！我亲爱的孩子们，对于一个刚刚因为紧张过度而扔掉了一双新鞋的人，你们能指望他有什么样的表现？现在想起来，我真惊讶自己当时竟然没有哭出来。我，总的来说，为我的坚强倍感自豪。想到已经永远无法听到天赋过人的库尔茨向我侃侃而谈，错失了千载难逢的好机会，我感到痛彻心扉。我当然是伤心错了。那个机会仍然静候着我。是的，而且我后来都听厌了。我也知道了自己是对的，一个声音，他仅仅是一个声音而已。我也听到了——他——它——这个声音——其他的声音——所有的都只不过是声音——那段时间的记忆在我身边缠绕不去，难以捉摸，就像一片庞大的闲谈声渐渐低了下去，只剩死滞的余音，愚蠢，恶劣，卑鄙，野蛮，或者说是赤裸裸的下流，毫无任何意义可言。只是声音，声音——甚至连那个姑娘本身——啊——”

他沉默良久。

“最后，我撒了一个谎，超度了他那阴魂不散的天赋。”他突然又开始说起来，“姑娘！什么？我提到一个姑娘了吗？哦，她是局外人——完全是。她们——我是指女人们——是局外的——而且也不应该牵涉进来。我们必须帮助她们安心留在自己那个美好的世界里，以防她们把我们的世界变得更糟糕。哦，她不应该被牵涉进来。我们把库尔茨从地狱里拉上来的时候，他还在念念不忘着‘我的未婚妻’。这样你们就该知道她有多么清白。还有库尔茨那高耸的额头！他们说有时候头发会重新长出来，但这个——啊——样本，却秃得干净彻底。荒野轻拍过他的头，然后，瞧，它就变得像个球一样——一个象牙球；荒野轻抚过他，然后——看！——他就此凋谢。它攫住他，爱他，拥他入怀，潜入他的血管，吃净他的肉，通过某种邪恶得不可思议的入会仪式，把他的灵魂牢牢地据为己有。他被它宠坏了，成了它最娇纵的宠儿。象牙？我想确实如此，有成堆的象牙，堆成山的象牙，多得把那间老旧的泥棚屋都要挤爆，多得让人不禁觉得，不论是在那片土地的上面还是下面，都再也找不出一根象牙来了。‘都差不多要变成化石了。’经理曾经轻蔑地说过。那些象牙并不比我更枯朽，但只要是从地里挖出来的象牙，他们就称作化石。看来这些黑人的确会偶尔把象牙埋进地里——但明显他们埋得不够深，未能阻止天资过人的库尔茨先生身受此厄运。船舱装不下这么多象牙，我们只好把剩下的堆在甲板上。这样一来，只要他还能睁开眼睛，就可以继续含情脉脉地欣赏它们，他对这些珍宝的爱惜赞赏之情至死不休。你们真该听听他说的‘我的象牙’。哦，是的，我听见了。‘我的未婚妻，我的象牙，我的贸易站，我的河流，我的——’什么都属于他。听得我屏息静气，等着听到荒野爆发出天崩地裂的狂笑声，响亮得可以震落满天的星星。什么都是他的——但那是不要紧的，要紧的是他是谁的，又有多少股黑暗的力量宣称自己享有他的所有权。思考这个问题简直令人不寒而栗。答案是无法想象的，尝试去想象它也对人毫无好处。他在那片大地的众多魔鬼之中窃据高位——我并无夸张。你们理解不了。你们怎么能理解？——脚下踩着坚固的人行道，四周围着一群友好的邻居，时刻准备着给你们鼓劲儿，或是在背后议论你们，你们优雅地往返于肉铺和警察之间，对闲言碎语、绞刑架和精神病院心怀圣洁的恐惧——你们又怎么能够想象，一双没有枷锁的脚能把一个人带到属于太初时代的什么鬼地方去？这双脚走的是一条凄荒的路——彻底的凄荒，连警察的影子都看不到——这双脚走的是一条死寂的路——彻底的死寂，听不到任何一个善意的邻居低声地警告你们人言可畏。这些细节毫不起眼，却造成了天壤之别。当它们消失，人就必须求助于自身天生的力量，求助于自己坚持某种信念的能力。当然你们可能已经愚蠢到失去了犯错误的能力——甚至迟钝到意识不到自己正在被那些黑暗的力量攻击。我想，没有哪个傻瓜曾经拿自己的灵魂去和魔鬼讨价还价：是因为傻瓜太傻，还是魔鬼太坏——我不知道，又或者是因为，你们是圣洁得如此惊天地泣鬼神，以至于除了天国的景象和声音，你们都充耳不闻，熟视无睹，而地球对你们来说只是个立脚之处——做这样的人，对你们而言是得是失，我不想妄加评论。但绝大部分的人，既不属于前者，也不能归为后者。地球，是我们的家，我们不得不忍受这里的各种景象、声音，还有气味，天啊！——比如说，忍受死河马的气味——而又竭尽全力地独善其身。这时，难道你们还没有发现吗？你们的力量起作用了，你们坚信自己有能力挖出毫不起眼的洞穴，把这些不得不忍受的东西全都埋进去。那是一种驱使你们献身的力量——不是献给你们自己，而是献给某个说不清道不明，却又令人心力交瘁的事业。这已经够难了。注意，我不是在找借口，更不是在申辩——我只是在尝试让自己理解——理解——库尔茨先生——库尔茨先生的幽灵。这个幽灵，从虚空的深处浮现出来，接受过文明的熏陶，在它彻底消失前，竟对我产生了惊人的信赖，使我受宠若惊。这都是因为它能用英文跟我交流。未变质前的库尔茨，有一部分教育是在英国接受的，而且——他本人直白地说过——他从不曾滥用他的同情。他的母亲有一半英国血统，父亲则有一半法国血统。整个欧洲都为库尔茨的横空出世贡献了力量。我后来还慢慢了解到，破除野蛮传统国际协会还曾经委托他撰写一个报告，用作日后的工作指南，真是知人善任。而他也已经写好了。我看见过。我读过。这个报告雄辩滔滔，激动人心，但我觉得它未免有点杯弓蛇影。他竟然挤得出时间来写完一份十七页的报告，而且每页都密密麻麻地写满了字！但这肯定是在他——这么说吧——发疯之前写的，为此他还跑去主持一些午夜舞会，这些舞会的落幕仪式恶劣得令人不齿，它们——把我在不同时间听到的只言片语拼凑起来，我发现——是在祭祀他——明白吗？——祭祀库尔茨先生本人。但那个报告写得确实漂亮。然而，开篇第一段，鉴于我已然知悉后事如何，现在想起来，竟是谶语。他劈头就抛出一个论断，说我们白人，依照目前的发展水平，‘在其（野蛮人）眼前，须作为超自然之生物而存在——吾等身附神力，翩然下凡’，等等，等等。仅凭简单训练，吾等即可向其行使实无约束之有益特权”，等等，等等。以此为起点，他天马行空地写下去，把我也蛊惑住了。整篇报告写得雄壮艳丽，只是很难让人记住具体写的是什么。我觉得它散发着由神圣的慈悲生出的广博气度，看得我心潮澎湃。这就是滔滔雄辩那股脱缰野马一般的力量——华辞丽藻的力量——那些灼灼欲燃的辞藻，如此高尚，如此力量无穷！全篇报告一气呵成，其间并无任何务实的文字冒出来，截断行云流水一般的佳词妙句，除却写在末页页脚的一条注释。这条注释明显是在报告写成多时之后，由一只颤抖不已的手写上去的，不妨将它看作是对某个方法的说明。它异常简短，却在这篇感人得足以唤起人们利他主义情怀的报告末尾闪着强光，炫目，骇人，就像划破宁静天空的一道闪电：“斩绝土人！”令人不解的是，他显然把这条宝贵的附注忘得一干二净。因为，过后，当他略微恢复意识，便三番四次地恳求我要小心保管好‘我的小册子’（他这么叫它），好像未来它绝对能为他的事业增光添彩。我对所有这些事情了如指掌，并且，事实证明，后来我也不得不尽心尽力地捍卫他的身后美名。在这一点上，我已经仁至义尽，完全有权利决定它[24]的命运。只要我愿意，我就可以把它扔进人类发展进程的垃圾桶，让它永远安息在所有的牺牲品，以及人类文明中诸多湮没无闻的著作之间。但那时，唉，我身不由己。他已经被刻进了人们的记忆里。无论如何，他不是一个凡夫俗子。他有力量诱惑或恐吓蛮荒之民为了向他表示崇敬而发狂似的大跳巫舞，他也能够让朝圣者们为了他终日深锁愁眉。他至少拥有一个忠实的朋友，征服了这个人的灵魂，那既非原始野蛮，亦非见利忘义的灵魂。不，我忘不了他，尽管我并没有足够的证据来断言，为了把他找回来，我们牺牲了一条生命到底值不值得。我发疯一般地想念我那刚去世的舵手——甚至当他的尸体还躺在驾驶室里，我就已经在想念他了。也许你们会认为这不可理喻，我竟然会想念一个土人，他比撒哈拉沙漠里的沙子更不值一提。可是，请你们想想，他也做了点事情，他有掌舵。几个月来他一直陪在我身后——一个帮手——一件工具。他是我的伙伴！他帮我掌舵——我不得不时刻盯住他，我担心他因为能力不足而犯错，于是在我和他之间，生出了一种微妙的联系，而当它蓦然断裂，我才恍然大悟。在他受伤时投向我的目光里，有一种亲密的深邃，至今仍历历在目——仿佛在最重要的时刻，宣布了我们在久远的时代里，确曾血脉相连。

可怜的傻瓜！他为什么不离开那个百叶窗呢！他控制不住自己，控制不住——就像库尔茨一样——只是一棵任风摆布的树。我一换上一双干的拖鞋，就把他拖了出去。我当然是先把矛从他身侧拔了出来——我承认我在这么做的时候，紧紧闭着眼睛。过门槛时，他的两只脚后跟一起跳了一下，他的双肩死死压着我的前胸，我从背后拼命抱住他。天啊！他很沉，很沉，我觉得他比地球上任何一个人都要沉。然后我毫不迟疑地把他扔进河里。水流马上攫住他，就好像他是一缕水草。我看见尸体翻了两圈，便永远地消失了。那时所有朝圣者以及经理都团团围在驾驶室四周，像一群兴奋的喜鹊一般说个不停。我听见一阵窃窃私语，说我冷血，竟然毫不迟疑地把尸体扔掉。他们把尸体留下来有何用，我猜不着，也许是要对它做防腐处理吧。然而，我也听见从下面甲板传来的另一阵窃窃私语声，令我毛骨悚然。我的朋友，那些伐木工，对我的行为同样不满，而他们的理由更加充分——尽管我承认那个理由本身实在是超乎寻常。唉，实在是太过分！我横了心，如果我那刚去世的舵手一定要被吃掉，能吃他的也只有鱼。他生前是一个二流的舵手，现在他死了，却可能变成众人趋之若鹜的宝贝，说不定会引起一场轩然大波。而且，我正急于回去自己掌舵，因为那个穿着粉红睡衣的男人看起来笨拙得令人绝望。

那场简单的葬礼一完，我就马上回去掌舵。汽船稳稳地在河流的正中央半速前进，我可以分神去听他们在怎么说我。他们抛弃了库尔茨，他们抛弃了贸易站，库尔茨死了，贸易站被烧成灰烬——等等——等等。那个红毛的朝圣者，大概以为我们至少为库尔茨报了夺命之仇，竟发了疯一般狂喜不已。‘喂！我们肯定把丛林里的敌人杀了个落花流水，是不是？多么了不起！你们说是不是？是不是？’他竟真的跳起舞来，这个嗜血成性的小丑！这时候他倒活蹦乱跳的，刚才看见那个受伤的男人时，他却差点昏过去！我忍不住说：‘说真的，你们制造出来的那一大团烟雾还真够了不起的。’从灌木丛顶部的沙沙声和摇晃程度来看，我当时就知道几乎所有的子弹都打高了。要想击中目标，必须瞄得够准，并把枪架在肩上开火，这些家伙却把枪顶在了盆骨上，开枪的时候还要闭着眼！土人们之所以撤退，我坚持说——而且我是对的——是因为汽笛的尖叫声。一听见我这么说，他们马上把库尔茨抛开了，愤愤不平地冲着我大喊大叫以示抗议。

经理站在船舵旁，鬼鬼祟祟地在我耳边低声说，天黑前无论如何要远远地离开这里，逃到河流下游去。此时我看见远处河边有一小块空地，上面隐约有几座建筑物的轮廓。‘这是什么？’我问。他惊讶地拍拍手。‘就是那个贸易站！’他喊道。我保持半速，马上把船向岸边驶去。

我从望远镜里看到一个小山坡，坡上一株灌木也没有，只有零零落落的几棵树。坡顶有一座长条形的房子，破败暗淡，深埋在高高的乱草中。尖尖的屋顶上大洞满布，远远看去像是大张着一个个黑色的嘴巴。房子背后，是一片凌乱的丛林。四周没有围栏，也没有篱笆。但显然曾经有过类似的东西，因为在房子旁边，仍然立着一排细长的木柱，大约有一打左右，粗粗修剪过，顶端还装饰着雕花圆球。栏杆，或是木柱之间任何别的什么东西，已经杳然无踪了。当然，那一切都被森林簇拥着。河岸空旷开阔，我看见一个白人站在水边，戴着一顶车轮一般的帽子，使劲儿向我们挥胳膊。细察森林边缘的上下方，我几乎可以肯定里面有动静——有人在走来走去。我万分谨慎地驶过森林，熄灭引擎，让船自行顺水而下。水边的人开始朝我们大喊大叫，催我们上岸。‘刚才有人袭击我们！’经理向他喊道。‘我知道——我知道，不要紧的！’那个人回喊，欢乐得无与伦比。‘过来吧，没关系的！我太高兴了！’

看见他，我想起之前见过的某样东西——我在某处看见过，很滑稽的。我一边驾船靠岸，一边喃喃自语：‘这个家伙到底像什么呢？’我猛然记起来了。他像个戏剧里的丑角。他的衣服原来很可能是棕色的，用荷兰亚麻布制成，但现在满是补丁，夺目的补丁，蓝色的，红色的，黄色的——背后有，前面有，肘上有，连膝盖上也有，外套的镶边色彩斑斓，裤腿的流苏猩红鲜艳。沐浴在阳光下的他，看上去如此欢欣若狂，又如此惊人的光鲜整洁，因为你能清清楚楚地看见，这些补丁无一例外地缝得巧夺天工。一张白皙稚气的脸，胡子刮得干干净净，五官都很平淡，鼻子正在掉皮，一双蓝眼睛小小的。在这张率真的脸上，颦笑交相追逐，就像风吹过的平原上交替出现的阴影和阳光。‘小心，船长！’他喊道，‘这里昨晚打进去了一个暗桩。’什么？又有暗桩？我承认我骂了很难听的话。我差点就捅穿了这艘破船，立刻了结这趟令人走火入魔的旅程。岸上的丑角把他那个像哈巴狗一样的小鼻子抬起来冲着我。‘您是英国人吗？’他满面春风地问。‘那你是吗？’我站在船舵边向他喊道。他马上沉下脸，摇摇头，好像在对我的失望表示歉意。接着他重新快活起来。‘管他呢！’他欢欣鼓舞地喊道。‘我们没来晚吧？’我问。‘他在那上边。’他回答，头朝山上一甩，脸上瞬间堆满愁容。他的脸就像秋日的天空，阴晴不定。

那些全副武装的朝圣者前呼后拥着经理朝那座房子走去的时候，这个家伙跑到甲板上面来。‘听我说，我现在感到很不自在。丛林里藏着那么多土人！’我说。他热切地向我保证绝对不会出乱子。‘他们都很笨。’他又说，‘你们来了我真高兴，我一天到晚都要提防着，不让他们跑出来。’‘但你刚才说没关系！’我叫起来。‘是的，他们不会伤害人。’他说。我直直地盯着他，他改口说：‘也不完全是这样。’接着又快活地说，‘说真的，你们的驾驶室真该好好打扫打扫了！’紧接着，他建议我在锅炉里保存足够的蒸汽，万一遇到任何麻烦，可以马上拉响汽笛。‘汽笛尖叫一声，比你们所有的来复枪都见效。他们都很笨。’他重复道。他就这样喋喋不休地说个不停，简直不给我开口说话的机会。他似乎是太久不曾和别人说话了，现在要好好补偿一番。事实上，他也笑着暗示道，实际情况就是如此。‘你怎么不跟库尔茨先生说话？’我说。‘你不跟他说话——你只听他说，’他喊道，口吻带着庄重的赞叹，‘但现在——’他摆摆手，转眼间陷入了深不见底的沮丧中。过了一会儿，他忽然跳到我面前，抓住我双手使劲儿地晃，一边急促含混地说：‘水手兄弟……荣誉……愉悦……欢乐……自我介绍……俄国……大司祭的儿子……坦波夫[25]政府……什么？烟丝！英国烟丝！上好的英国烟丝！真是好兄弟！抽不抽烟？哪有不抽烟的水手？’

他抽了烟，平静下来。我渐渐了解到，他逃学出来，上一艘俄国船出了海，后来又逃走了，在英国船上工作过一段时间，现在已经跟他的大司祭父亲和好如初。他特别强调了这件事。‘但人年轻的时候，就是要去开开眼界，累积经验和想法，使自己更加见多识广嘛！’‘来这里开眼界？’我打断他。‘您是不知道！在这里，我遇到了库尔茨先生。’他郑重其事地责备我说，真是年少轻狂。此后我便闭口不言。似乎他在成功说服一个陆上的荷兰贸易公司为他提供补给品和货物之后，便毫无顾忌地深入荒野。他像个婴儿一样，根本不去想自己可能遭遇什么。他独自一人在那条河上流浪了差不多两年，与一切人和事断绝了联系。‘我并不像看上去那么年轻，我二十五岁了。’他说。‘开始的时候，老范·修登总是让我滚开，’他兴高采烈地叙述道，‘但我一直没放弃，缠着他谈啊谈啊，谈到后来，他害怕我真的能把死人说活了，就给我一些便宜货和几杆枪，让我永远不要再来见他。他是个老好人，那个荷兰人，范·修登。一年前，我托人给他送了一小批象牙，这样等我回去的时候，他就不好意思再叫我小偷了。希望他已经收到了吧。其他的事情我一点儿也不在乎。我给你们准备了一堆木头。那座是我从前住的房子，你们看到了吗？’

“我把陶森的书还给他。看他的样子，简直是要吻我，但他克制住了。‘我就剩下这么一本书了，还以为丢了呢。’他说，喜不自胜地盯着它，‘独自流浪的人总有旦夕祸福。有时候小船会翻掉——有时候惹怒了那些土人，就只好落荒而逃。’他翻开书。‘你用俄文做笔记？’我问。他点点头。‘我还以为是密码呢。’我说。他笑了，接着突然严肃起来。‘我费了很大劲儿才把这些人挡在外面。’他说。‘他们想要杀死你吗？’我问。‘不！’他喊道，然后紧闭双唇。‘他们为什么攻击我们？’我继续问。他迟疑片刻，然后羞怯地说：‘他们不想他走。’‘他们不想吗？’我惊诧地说。他讳莫如深地点点头。‘请您听好了，’他喊道，‘这个人让我豁然开朗！’他张开双臂，那双小小的蓝眼睛盯着我，睁得又大又圆。”

第三章

我两眼发直地盯着他，惊讶得茫然无措。我面前的这个人，穿着花团锦簇的衣服，好像刚刚从一个哑剧团里逃了出来，依然充溢着铺张的热情。他的存在虚幻、诡异，完全是莫名其妙的，没有道理可讲。你根本无法想象他的人生是怎么样的，他竟然能够成功穿越千山万水至此，而且活了下来——他竟然没有立刻烟消云散。‘我往前走几步，’他说，‘又再走几步——突然有一天，我发现已经走得太远，找不到回头的路了。管他呢。反正我还年轻。我能活下去。您赶紧把库尔茨带走——赶紧——听我的。’他浑身上下都散发着青春的光辉，包裹住他花枝招展的破衣服，他的贫困，他的孤独，以及那份与徒劳无功的流浪形影相随的寂寞，蚀骨的寂寞。月复一月——年复一年——朝不保夕的岁月。他之所以依然能够在那里无畏无惧地活着，从不思前想后，全因为他年轻气盛，不知深浅。我不禁有点欣赏起他来——甚至有点嫉妒他。正是这种青春的光辉在催促他前行，并护佑着他。他当然对荒野别无所求，他要的只是能够让他自由呼吸和一往无前的空间。他只想活下去，走下去，不惜身犯险境，不惜困蹇无依。如果一种纯洁无瑕、毫无心计而不求实利的冒险精神确曾支配过一个人，那一定是这个花衣青年。我禁不住要嫉妒他，他身上竟燃烧着一股如此谦逊而纯粹的精神。它仿佛耗尽了他所有能够用来关注自我的精力，如此彻底，甚至当他还在跟你说话的时候，你便已经忘记了，正是他——眼前这个人——经历了这一切。不过对于他无限景仰库尔茨一事，我一点儿也不觉得有什么好嫉妒的。他对此确实有欠深思熟虑。库尔茨闯入了他的生命，他便带着狂热的宿命感，为他倾倒。我真的觉得，那是他生平所有的遭遇中最凶险的事。

他们终于不可避免地相逢了，就像风止住后，两艘共同随水浮荡的船，终于擦碰在一起一样。我想，库尔茨先生一定是需要一个听众，因为当他们某次在森林里扎营的时候，曾经彻夜交谈，当然更可能的是库尔茨在说，他在听。‘我们无所不谈，’他说，谈起那个夜晚，依然满心激动，‘我都忘记了人还要睡觉。整个夜晚似乎还没有一个小时那么长。我们无所不谈，无所不谈！……还谈到了爱。’‘什么？他和你谈爱情！’我十分感兴趣地说。‘您别想歪了，’他血脉贲张地喊道，‘是那种笼统意义上的爱——他令我茅塞顿开——茅塞顿开。’

他高高地举起双臂。我们那时在甲板上，那个无所事事地坐在一旁的伐木工工头抬起头来看他，一双深邃的眼睛碎光流转。我环顾四周，不知怎的，但我向你们保证，这片土地，这条河，这片森林，这熊熊燃烧着的苍穹，在我看来如此绝望，如此黑暗，如此深不可测，对人类的弱点如此无情。‘这么说，你们从此当然是形影不离了？’我说。

事实正好相反。看来总有各种各样的原因中断他们的交往。他自豪地告诉我，库尔茨生过两次大病，都是在他的精心看护下才挺了过来（听他的口气，好像那是多么惊心动魄的丰功伟绩），但库尔茨行动的时候，照例是不带其他人的，总是孤身深入密林。‘想见他的时候，我就到这个贸易站来，但往往要等上很多很多天才能等到他。’他说，‘啊，但他值得等！——有的时候。’‘他去干什么了？探险吗？’我问。‘当然是了。’他发现了很多村庄，还有一个湖呢——其实他也说不清楚它们的确切方向。太好奇总是危险的——但他去探险，主要还是为了找象牙。‘但那时他手里已经没有货物了，拿什么换象牙呢？’我抗议道。‘但他还剩下很多弹药。’他回答道，转过脸去。‘你就把话说穿了吧，他就是在四处抢劫吧？’我说。他点点头。‘他肯定不是唯一一个这么干的人！’他吞吞吐吐地说了一些关于沿湖村庄的事情。‘库尔茨令那个部落对他唯命是从，是不是？’我暗示道。他有点窘迫。‘他们对他佩服得五体投地。’他说。他说这些话的声调奇怪得很，我不禁用锐利的目光看着他。他是如此热切地想要谈论库尔茨，却欲言又止，实在古怪之极。这个库尔茨，已经渗透他生命的每个角落，支配了他的思想，操控着他的感情。‘不然你想怎么样？’他爆发了，‘他带着雷鸣和闪电降临到他们面前——他们从来没有见过这种东西——真是太可怕了。他可以变得非常可怕。库尔茨不是普通人，不能用平常的标准来评判他。不，不，不！现在——我只是想让你知道——我不介意告诉你，他有一天连我都想射死——但我不会去评判他。’‘射死你！’我喊道，‘为什么？’‘因为，我有一点象牙，是我房子附近村子的首领给我的。我过去常常帮他们打猎的。他想据为己有，无论如何要据为己有。他正颜厉色地说，我必须把象牙给他，然后迅速离开那个地方，否则就要一枪杀了我，因为他可以这么做，并且也很想这么做，在这个地球上没有什么可以阻止他杀死任何想杀的人。他也说得没错。我把象牙给他了。有什么要紧！但我没有走。不，不，我离不开他。不过当然，我必须处处小心，直到时过境迁，我们重归于好。那时他再次病倒。等他好了，我只好避开他。但我毫不介意。他一般住在河边的村庄里，偶尔到河边来，有时候也会和我说说话，而有时候我还是谨慎一些比较好。这个人受了太多的苦。他也痛恨这一切，但不知怎的就是无法抽身。一有机会，我就恳求他尝试一下，赶在无可挽回之前离开。我还主动提出请他带我一起回去。他会说好，却依然我行我素，然后又出发去别的地方找象牙，一连消失好几个星期。他混在这些人中间，连自己是谁都忘掉了——忘掉了自己是谁——唉。’‘天啊！他这是疯了！’我说。他愤怒地否认。库尔茨先生是不会疯的。要是我听过他谈话，即使只是在两天前，也不敢这么随便地下判断……我们一边说着话，我已经拿起了望远镜朝岸边看，扫视楼房两边和背后的森林边缘。那片丛林，死一般沉默，死一般安静——沉默安静得就像山上那座黯败的房子一样，然而却有人潜藏在内——意识到这一点，我感到不寒而栗。这个骇人的故事并没有在这片荒野里留下丝毫痕迹，它的细节，也不曾被言明，我几乎完全是通过那一声声凄凉的呼喊，一次又一次的缩背耸肩，七零八落的字句，一遍遍伴随着长叹的闪烁其词，靠自己想象出来的。岿然不动的树林像一个面具——像紧闭的狱门一般，沉重得仿佛一直在往下坠——这些树木，仿佛无所不知，无限耐心，凛然难侵，静静地看着这一切。这个俄国人又向我说，库尔茨先生不久前刚来过河边，随身带着那个湖边部落的所有战士。他之前又消失了几个月——我想他是去显灵了吧——后来却突然回到这儿来，一副想要向河对岸或下游发动袭击的架势。显然，他对象牙的渴望压过了——怎么说呢——那些稍嫌不够务实的志向。然而他的身体突然垮掉了。‘听说他倒在这里，没人照顾，我就来了——想着趁机再劝他一次。’俄国人说，‘唉，他很不好，太不好了。’我把望远镜转向那座房子。它看起来已经完全荒废了，只有残败的屋顶，长长的泥墙从荒草堆里探出来，上面张着三个大小不同的正方形小窗洞：从望远镜里看去，仿佛这一切都触手可及。然后我猛地一转，望远镜里蓦然出现了一根木桩。篱笆朽坏了，木桩却残存了下来。你们还记得吗？我刚才说过，远远地望见这些木桩上的雕花圆饰时，我是多么的惊讶。在这片废墟里，竟然有人挣扎着要镂金描彩！现在它突然来到眼前，吓得我猛然把头向后一甩，就像要躲开迎面而来的一拳。然后我缓缓地一个木桩一个木桩看过去，发现之前我没看真切。这些圆球并不是装饰，而是饱含象征意义的，它们意味深长，却又莫名其妙，骇人又恶心——引人思考，也能引来正在空中鸟瞰觅食的秃鹫，但最终总不免被那些不畏辛劳地爬上木桩的蚂蚁享用。要不是脸朝那座房子，它们，那些木桩上的人头，本可以更加震撼人心。只有一个，我辨认出来的第一个，面朝着我。我并没有像你们所想的那么大惊失色。我之所以向后猛然甩头，完全是吃惊时的条件反射。我本来是想着会看到一个木球的嘛。我故意回头去看那第一个——就是它，又黑又干又皱，双眼紧闭——一个人头，仿佛在木桩上沉沉睡去了，而那干巴巴的嘴唇萎缩起来，窄窄地露出一线牙齿的白色，仿佛在笑，在止不住地笑，仿佛正在做着一个永不醒来的梦，一个令人忍俊不禁的梦。

我可没有泄露商业机密。事实上，后来经理说库尔茨先生所用的手段对那个地区而言是毁灭性的。对这个观点，我没有什么想法，但我真的希望你们能够理解，把那么多人头插在木桩上根本毫无益处。它们只能表明库尔茨先生对自己的各种欲念束手无策，表明他缺乏某件东西——不是什么了不起的东西，然而每当欲念冲昏了他的头脑，在他的滔滔雄辩里却无论如何找不到它。他本人是否意识到这个缺陷，我不知道。我想他最后肯定有所醒悟——只是大限已至。但荒野一早就看透了他，对他那异想天开的侵略，进行了残忍的报复。我想，荒野一定曾经向他耳语，告诉他他所不知道的事情，关于他自己的秘密，告诉他，在他受教于这片无边的凄凉荒野之前无从想象的事情——事实证明，这些低语对他有着致命的诱惑力。它们在他身体里放肆地回响着，因为他已然只是一个空空如也的躯壳……我放下望远镜，那个离我近得几乎可以和它喁喁私语的人头似乎立刻跳了开去，消失在遥不可及的远方。

库尔茨先生的这位信徒有点沮丧。他仓促含混地絮叨起来，想要让我相信他确实不敢把这些——嗯，标志——取下来。他不害怕本地的土人，库尔茨不点头，他们不敢胡来。他犹如天神下凡。这些土人密密麻麻地围绕在库尔茨的住处四周安营扎寨，首领们每天前去问安。他们会伏在地上……‘不要告诉我他们觐见库尔茨先生的时候要行什么礼。’我喊道。很奇怪地，我浑身上下毛发倒竖，感觉这个细节比库尔茨窗外那些在木桩上慢慢风干的人头更容易令人失控。毕竟，那只是一个野蛮的画面，然而我那时却仿佛觉得自己被送到一个一片漆黑的地区，到处弥漫着隐约的恐惧，在那里，坦白纯粹的野蛮本性对人而言是一种安慰，因为它有权利——理直气壮地——存在于光天化日之下。这个年轻人目瞪口呆地望着我。我猜他没有想到，我可一点儿也不崇拜库尔茨。他忘了，我从未听到过那些天花乱坠的演讲，那些关于，关于什么来着？关于爱，公正，为人之道——诸如此类——的演讲。如果让他伏在库尔茨脚边，他肯定顺服之极，一点也不输给那些最野蛮的人。我不知道当时发生了什么，他说那都是谋反者的人头。我忍不住狂笑起来，把他吓坏了。谋反者！下一次他们又会被叫作什么？我已经听到过敌人、罪犯、工人——而现在这些又成了谋反者。木桩上那些图谋不轨的人头，在我看来温柔和顺。‘你怎么能够想象，这样一种生活对像库尔茨先生这样的人来说有多么残酷！’库尔茨的最后一个信徒喊道。‘对你而言，也一样的残酷？’我说。‘我！我！我是个笨蛋。我只是井底之蛙。我对其他人一无所求。你怎么能拿我和……？’汹涌的感情把他噎住，忽然之间，他崩溃了。‘我真是不明白，’他痛苦地嘟哝道，‘我拼尽全力，只求他能活下去。对这一切，我一直置身事外。我无力插手。这么多个月了，这里连一滴药水，一口能给病人吃的食物都没有。他被抛弃了，多么可耻啊。把这样一个人抛弃了，这样一个满怀着高尚思想的人……可耻！可耻啊！我——我——我已经一连十天十夜无法合眼……’

在宁静的暮色里，他的声音渐渐飘散如烟。在我们说话的时候，森林那长长的影子早已泻下了山坡，漫过那堆断垣残壁，漫过那排充满着象征意义的木桩。那一切全笼罩在阴暗之中，但我们在下面，仍然是金阳如水。河边空地对着的河道流光溢彩，却又沉静宁谧，而上下游的河湾都已隐没在冥漠的暮色之中。岸上一个人也没有，那片丛林也没有沙沙作响。

突然，一群人从那座房子的边上簇拥而出，仿佛蓦地从地里钻了出来似的。他们紧紧挨在一起，穿过齐腰深的荒草，中间抬着一个临时草草做成的担架。在这片刚才仿佛空无一人的荒野中，平地响起一声尖叫，凄厉刺耳，就像一支利剑划破宁静的空气，直直刺进了这片土地的心脏。紧接着，跟变魔术似的，无数的人——裸体的——手执长矛、弓和盾，目露凶光，行为粗野，从那片阴郁凝重的森林里呼啸而出，涌进了河边的空地。丛林瑟瑟作抖，草丛也随之震颤，然而一切很快又复归平静，重新摆出一副凝神静思的姿态。

‘现在，要是他不发话救我们，我们就别想活了。’紧挨着我的俄国人说。这伙抬着担架的人本来朝着汽船走来，此刻也停下脚步，好像被石化了一样。我看见担架里的人坐起身，瘦骨嶙峋的他，举起一条细长的手臂，从抬着担架的那丛肩膀上，高高地探了出来。‘这个人能把笼统的爱谈得如此美妙动人，现在让我们看看他能不能举出个高明的理由来救活我们吧。’我说。我对这个令人困惑的险境有一种说不出的厌恶，好像我现在不得不向那个邪恶的幽灵摇尾乞怜似的，实在是有失身份。我什么都听不见，但通过望远镜，能看到那条干瘦的手臂在发号施令似的挥舞着，那个下巴在动，那个幽灵的眼睛透着寒光，深深陷在枯槁的头颅里，那个头一点一点的，仿佛正在抽搐，可笑之极。库尔茨——库尔茨——在德文里是‘短促’的意思——没错吧？名如其人，他生得匆忙——也死得急促。他看起来至少有七英尺高。盖在他身上的布已经滑了下来，露出身体，可怜，可怕，仿佛滑下来的是一块裹尸布。他那鸟笼一般的肋骨起伏着，他手臂的骨头涌动着。他多么像一个活了过来的死神雕像，用古老的象牙雕成的，正在向一群一动不动的青铜人偶，黑乎乎、亮闪闪的人偶，咄咄逼人地不停挥着手以示威胁。他张大了嘴——那副表情看起来古怪又贪婪，仿佛他想把眼前的一切全部吞进去，所有的空气，所有的泥土，所有的人。我隐约听到一个阴沉的声音，他肯定是在咆哮。突然他又倒了下去。那些人抬着担架继续蹒跚前行，担架在他们肩上摇来晃去。几乎与此同时，我注意到那一大群土人不动声色地撤回森林中去，仿佛那片突然把他们吐了出来的森林，现在长吸一口气，又把他们吞了回去。

担架后面跟着几个朝圣者，他们拿着他的武器——两杆猎枪，一杆沉重的来复枪，一把轻型左轮手枪——这些就是那个朱庇特的雷电，真够寒酸的。经理挨着他的头走着，向他弯下腰去耳语了几句话。他们把他安置在一个小小的船舱里——小得仅仅放得下一张床和几张小折脚凳那种。我们把那些未能按时送到他手里的信件带来了，现在他的床上散满撕破的信封和展开的信。他用虚弱的手在这些纸中间寻摸着。他那炙热的眼神仿佛正在燃烧，然而他疲倦的面容却沉静如冰，我不禁吃了一惊。他并不是因病萧索，看起来也并不痛苦。这个幽灵一脸满足安详，仿佛如今的它已经尝遍人间所有的酸甜苦辣、喜怒哀愁。

他沙沙地摩挲着其中一封信，直直地盯着我的脸说：‘很高兴见到您。’一直有人在给他写信，向他推荐我。又是那时流行的推荐信。他毫不费力就能声如洪钟地说出话来，几乎都不需要费事去动动嘴唇，真是太惊人了。一个声音！就是这个声音！低沉，深邃，震天动地，然而这个人看起来却已经如此有气无力。可是，他残存的力量仍然足以——当然已是强弩之末——把我们逼入绝境，我马上就会讲到。

经理悄无声息地出现在门廊里。我马上走出去，他一把拉上我身后的门帘。朝圣者们充满好奇地看着那个俄国人，他正凝视着岸边。我随着他的目光看过去。

远处，隐隐约约地有些灰黑的人影在森林昏暗的边缘晃来晃去，河边有两个青铜色皮肤的人，倚着高高的矛，站在阳光中，戴着用布满斑点的兽皮做成的奇异头饰，严阵以待，岿然不动，仿佛两座雕塑。在洒满了金色阳光的岸边，一个狂野豪放、艳光四射的女人，幽灵一般，沿河从右往左走着。

她稳稳迈着脚步，身披垂满流苏的彩纹布，昂然地踩在泥土上，一身蛮俗的饰物叮咚作响，灿然生辉。她高高地昂着头，头发盘成一个黑盔。她缠着及膝高的古铜色绑腿，手臂上套着金黄色的铜钏儿，黄褐的脸颊上描了一块猩红色，脖子上挂满了玻璃珠子项链。种种狰狞的物件，符咒，巫师的赠礼，垂在她身上，每走一步都光摇影颤。她这一身装束，肯定值好几根象牙。她野蛮却美艳绝伦，狂暴却辉煌富丽。她从容的步子，既含着不祥之感，也透着庄严之气。在忽从天降，笼罩住这片哀土的寂静里，无涯的荒野那肥沃而神秘的身躯，生灵涌动，仿佛正在凝视着她，沉吟不已，仿佛那就是它自己的灵魂，变幻莫测，却热情汹涌。

她走到汽船前面，面朝我们站定。她长长的影子拖进河里。她的表情忧伤而凶狠，原始的悲哀，滞闷的痛苦，以及由蠢蠢欲动却难以坚定的决心所带来的恐惧，一团乱麻般纠缠在一起。她纹丝不动地站在那里盯着我们，就像荒野的化身，那神态仿佛在筹划着某个险恶的阴谋。过了整整一分钟，她才向前迈了一步，浑身沙沙轻响，黄色的金属流光溢彩，缀满流苏的彩布飘拂摇漾。她没有再前进，仿佛心痛得无法动弹。我身旁的年轻人咆哮起来，朝圣者们在我背后嗡嗡地交头接耳。她盯着我们所有人，仿佛全靠这坚如磐石的目光，她才得以保全性命。忽然间，她张开裸露的双臂，高高举在头上，一动不动，好像被无法抑制的渴望攫住，歇斯底里地想要触碰天空。与此同时，阴影迅疾地包裹上来，遮暗了河面，把汽船也裹入怀中。牢不可破的寂静沉沉地笼罩下来。

她缓缓转身离去，沿着河岸继续走，走进左边的丛林里。只有一次，在她即将要融进昏冥的丛林时，回眸看了我们一眼。

‘要是她要上船，我恐怕要向她开枪。’那位浑身补丁的男士心惊肉跳地说，‘过去这两周，我拼了命才把她挡在屋外。可后来她还是进来了，大吵大闹，责怪我把储物间里那点子破布拿去补我的衣服。我也有点按捺不住。我肯定回击了，因为她发了疯一般对着库尔茨大喊大叫足足有一个小时，还不时狠狠地指着我。我听不懂这个部落的方言。好在那天库尔茨大概是病得太难受，没精神理她，不然真不知道怎么收场。我真不明白……不——真是够呛。唉，现在总算结束了。’

这时帘后传来库尔茨深沉的声音：‘救我！——你要救的是那些象牙吧。别跟我扯这个。救我！为什么？我之前不也被迫救过你一命吗？你这是在破坏我的计划。生病！生病！我还没像你们希望的病得那么重！不要紧，我不会放弃我的计划——我会东山再起。咱们走着瞧。你，还有你到处兜售的那些蠢主意——你这是要拆我的台。我会卷土重来的。我……’

“经理出来了。他纡尊降贵地挽着我的手臂，把我拉到一边，真是意外的荣宠。‘他情绪很低落，非常低落。’他说。他觉得有必要唉声叹气一番，但忘了同步地装出悲伤的样子。‘我们对他已经仁至义尽，不是吗？但不必讳言，库尔茨先生对公司而言已然弊大于利。他估计错误，现在动武，时机还不成熟。谨慎再谨慎——那是我的原则。我们还要继续谨慎下去。我们对这个地区暂时还无能为力。多么不幸！总体而言，公司的贸易利益必将受损。我不否认他获得的象牙数量惊人——但大部分都朽坏了。无论如何，我们必须把它们拯救出来——但您看，我们现在的处境是多么凶险——为什么？因为他使用了龌龊的手段。’‘你，’我望着河岸说，说那是”龌龊的手段？‘’还有什么疑问吗，‘他愤怒地高声说道，’难道您不认为是这样吗？……

‘那根本谈不上是什么手段。’过了一会儿，我低声说道。‘确实如此，’他兴高采烈地说。‘这种局面我早就预见到了。这充分说明他缺乏判断力。我有责任向有关方面汇报这一情况。’‘哼，’我说，‘那个家伙——他的名字是什么来着？——那个制砖商，会帮你把那份报告写得精彩绝伦的。’他惊讶得哑口无言了好一阵子。他简直是污染空气，我从来没有感到如此窒息过。我在精神上走投无路地倒向了库尔茨，但求解脱——确实是但求解脱。‘然而我认为库尔茨先生是一个卓绝不凡的人物。’我咬牙切齿地说。他吓了一跳，冰冷阴沉地白了我一眼，静静地说：‘他以前是。’便转过身去背对着我。我就这样失宠了。我发现自己转瞬之间变成了库尔茨的同党，盲目地赞成使用那个时机不成熟的手段：我是多么龌龊！啊！但起码我自己选择了要做的噩梦是哪一个。

事实上，我是倒向了荒野，而不是库尔茨先生。坦白讲，我觉得库尔茨等于已经被埋掉了。而有那么一会儿，我感觉自己也仿佛被埋在一个巨大的坟墓里，和许多令人不齿的秘密一起。好像有什么在压迫着我的胸膛，沉重得无法忍受，我闻到潮腐的泥土味，所向披靡的腐败无形无迹，却又阴魂不散，我能看见的，只有看不穿的暗夜，一片漆黑……俄国人拍拍我的肩膀。我听见他在口齿不清、结结巴巴地说着什么‘同行兄弟——纸是包不住火的——我知道一些会败坏库尔茨先生名声的事情’。我没有打断他。对他而言，库尔茨先生明显还没有被埋掉。我怀疑在他看来，库尔茨先生是长生不死的。‘说吧！’我最后说，‘没关系！正巧我也是库尔茨先生的朋友——从某种意义上说。’

他讲了一大堆冠冕堂皇的开场白，说什么要不是看在我们是‘同行’的分上，他将誓死对我守口如瓶。‘他怀疑这些白人对他不怀好意——’‘你说得没错。’我说，想起无意中听到的那次谈话。‘经理想绞死你。’乍一听到这个情报，我觉得还挺可笑的，但他却显得忧心忡忡。‘我最好不声不响地离开，’他郑重其事地说，‘我现在对库尔茨已经没有什么用处了，他们很快就会随便找个借口把我赶走。还有什么可以阻止他们呢？离这里三百英里就有一个军营。’‘既然如此，’我说，‘要是你在附近有土人朋友，也许你最好尽快去投奔他们。’‘有很多，’他说，‘他们都很单纯——反正我也无求于他们。’他咬着唇站着，又说：‘我不希望这里的白人受到任何伤害，但当然我更为关心的是库尔茨先生的名声——但您是我的同行兄弟，因此——’‘别担心，’我过了一会儿说，‘我会好好保全库尔茨先生的名声。’我自己也不知道，说这句话有几分是出于真心实意。

他压低声音对我说，正是库尔茨先生命令向汽船发动攻击的。‘有时他想到有人要把他赶走，就满心怨恨——那时就是……但我想不明白这些事情，我的头脑太简单。他以为那能把你们吓跑——你们会以为他已经死了，就知难而退。我阻止不了他。唉，最近这一个月真是太折磨人了。’‘现在好了，’我说，‘他没事了。’‘也许——是吧。’他咕哝道，明显还有几分怀疑。‘谢谢，’我说，‘我会小心注意的。’‘记得不要说出去——好吗？’他紧张地恳求我，‘要是这里有人——他可就身败名裂了。’我极其严肃地向他发誓，保证只字不提。‘有一只独木舟和三个黑人兄弟在等着我，就在这附近。我这就走。你能给我一些马蒂尼-亨利枪的子弹吗？’当然没问题，我赶紧偷偷给了他一些，没有人注意到。他向我眨眨眼，不问自取地从我那里抓了一把烟丝。‘咱们可是好兄弟——多么棒的英国烟丝。’他刚走到驾驶室的门口，又转过身来——‘喂，你有没有多余的鞋子？’他把一条腿抬起来。‘看。’他拿几根打满结的绳子把鞋底捆在光脚下面，跟穿着草鞋似的。我翻出一双旧鞋来，他美美地看了一眼，就把它塞进左边腋下。他许多口袋中的一个（红得发亮的）被子弹绷得鼓鼓的，另一个（暗蓝色）塞着《陶森格物录》，其他口袋也装满了东西。他似乎认为自己这身装备已经无懈可击，完全可以再去与荒野缠斗一番。‘啊，我将永远，永远不会再遇到这样一个人了。你真该听听他的诗朗诵——而且他告诉我那是他自己写的诗！他会写诗啊！’回想起这些快乐的时光，他的眼里泛起幸福的光彩。‘啊，他使我豁然开朗！’‘再会。’我说。他和我握握手，走进凄迷的夜色之中。有时候，我不禁问自己，我到底是否真的见过他——世间到底有没有这样一个奇人呢！……

刚过午夜，我猛然醒来，想起他的警告。这个夜晚繁星点点，那个警告里暗示的危险，越想越真实。我赶忙起身四处走动，看看有没有什么风吹草动。山上有一个大火堆，明明灭灭地照出贸易站大楼一个塌陷了的角落。一个代理人带着船上的几个黑人正在巡逻，手持武器，把守着那些象牙。而在森林深处，红光闪烁不定，仿佛躲在一堆漆黑的乱柱后面，忽而蹿出地面，忽而又逃回地底。库尔茨的信徒们就驻扎在那里，忐忑不安地彻夜守望着。满耳都是单调的鼓声，滞闷沉重，震颤不绝。树林像一堵漆黑平滑的墙，背后有很多男人绵绵不绝地自顾自念着某种怪异的咒语，那声音好像从蜂巢里传出来的嗡嗡声一样，听得半梦半醒的我昏昏欲睡。我想我一定是倚在汽船的栏杆上睡着了。一阵平地惊雷一般的嘶吼声，仿佛是某种诡异的愤怒之情在久遭压抑之后突然爆发，把我惊醒了，我在迷糊中有点手足无措。嘶吼声戛然而止，只剩下那低低的嗡嗡声，仿佛是听得见的寂静，让人心下安然。我下意识地朝小木屋扫了一眼。屋里点着一盏灯，但库尔茨先生不见了。

如果我当时相信了自己的眼睛，一定会当即尖叫一声。但我一开始真的无法相信它们——那种事实在是太离奇。实际上，我被吓坏了，这种恐惧毫无内容，纯粹是恐惧本身，与有形的切身危险一点关系也没有。这种感情之所以如此排山倒海——我该怎么说？——是因为我受到了精神上的震撼，好像有人把某种狰狞可怖的东西，不堪细思，令人本能地厌恶的，突如其来地塞进我的怀里。这当然只是转瞬即逝的感觉，紧接着涌上来的，是那种普通的危机感，也许致命的危险近在咫尺，突袭和大屠杀随时可能爆发，诸如此类的，都是燃眉之急。然而，这种感觉真的舒服得多。我迅速镇静了下来，实际上，它的效果是如此明显，以至于我没有高声发出警报。

有一个代理人，穿着一件阿尔斯特宽大衣，把扣子扣得严严实实，睡在甲板上一张椅子里，距离我不到三英尺。那阵喊叫声没有吵醒他，他鼾声细细。我没有扰他清梦，兀自跳上了岸。我没有出卖库尔茨先生——这是上天的命令——我选择了这个噩梦，这是我的命。我迫不及待地要与这个幽灵单打独斗——直到今天，我也不知道为什么我如此吝啬于与任何其他人分享那段极端邪恶的经历。

一上岸，我就看见一条刚刚被人踩出来的小路——穿过草丛，很宽。我记得自己高兴极了，对自己说：‘他走不了——他是用四肢在爬——他跑不掉的。’草叶湿湿的，沾满了露水。我握着拳头，大步流星地向前走。我一定是在模模糊糊地想，我要扑到他身上打他一顿。我记不清了。当时我的脑海里萌生出一些很蠢的念头。那个织毛线的老女人和那她膝上那只猫闯进了我的记忆，在这样一件壮举的另一端，竟然如此不合时宜地坐着那样一个人。我看见朝圣者们一字排开，把温彻斯特步枪抵在髋骨上，朝天开枪。我想，我永远也不要回到汽船上，我开始想象自己手无寸铁地孤身生活在森林中，直到白发苍苍，老态龙钟。就是诸如此类的蠢念头。我还记得自己把鼓声听成了心跳声，那平稳的节律让我心情愉悦。

尽管如此，我一直沿那条小路走着——不时停下脚步，凝神静听。夜色澄莹，四周一片玄青色，露珠和星星清辉点点，然而在这片夜色里，仿佛潜伏着许多黑影。我好像看到前头有什么东西在动。很奇怪地，那天晚上我在每一件事情上都毫无道理地充满了自信。我离开了那条小路，绕了一个大弯（我毫不怀疑，自己当时一定在暗暗发笑），以便绕到那些骚动不安的东西前头——如果我真的看见了什么东西的话。我要去截住库尔茨，好像正在玩小孩的追逐游戏一样。

我一头撞上了他。要不是他听到了我的脚步声，我肯定会摔到他身上去。他连忙颤颤巍巍地站了起来，细长，苍白，虚弱，好像从泥土里冒出来的一缕水蒸气，朦朦胧胧地在我面前袅袅升起，悄无声息。与此同时，在我身后，火光在树与树之间跳跃着，一片嗡嗡的低语声从森林里流淌而出。我敏捷地截住了他，而等我终于站在他的面前，我似乎猛然惊醒，一下子意识到情况的严峻。危机远未过去。他要喊起来怎么办？尽管他几乎连站都站不稳，他的声音依然浑厚有力。‘快走开——去躲起来。’他声音深沉地说，听得我毛骨悚然。我回头看了一眼。我们离最近的火堆还不到三十码。一个黑乎乎的人影站了起来，迈开又黑又长的双腿，摇摆着一双又黑又长的手臂，在火光中走来走去。这是个头上长着角的黑影——大概是羚羊角吧。他一定是个魔法师或巫师：简直像一个恶鬼。‘你知不知道自己在干什么？’我低声说。‘我很清楚。’他故意大声说出这几个字来，听起来是如此的遥远，却又如此响亮，好像是用扩音喇叭喊出来的。如果他嚷嚷起来，我们就遭殃了，我暗暗想道。此时此境并不适合动武，况且对这个幽灵——这个流离无依且饱受折磨的可怜虫，我也下不去手。‘你这是有去无回，’我说，‘你会彻底完蛋的。’人有时候就是会这样灵光一闪，是不是？我确实讲得没错，尽管实际上当时他已经一败涂地，不可能输得更惨。而也正是在那一刻，我们建立起了坚实的友谊，变得亲密无间——并将一直——一直亲密下去——直到世界末日——甚至更久。

‘我有许多宏伟的计划。’他吞吞吐吐地嘟囔道。‘我知道，’我说，‘但要是你敢喊出来，我就立马砸碎你的脑袋，用——’附近一根棍子、一块石头也看不见，‘我就立马掐死你，一了百了。’我改口说。‘我正准备干一番惊天动地的大事业，’他用充满热望的声音和满怀憧憬的语气哀求道，听得我心都凉了，‘现在却因为这个愚蠢的混账家伙——’‘你放心，回到欧洲，人们一定还会把你当成英雄。’我坚定地断言道。我不想掐死他——那样做没有半点实际的好处。我是想破除施在他身上的魔咒——荒野施在他身上的魔咒，无声无息，却犹如千钧重负，似乎是想通过唤醒遗失于记忆深处的兽性本能，唤醒扭曲的欲望和畸形的热情得到满足时的回忆，把他拉入自己那冷酷无情的怀抱。我相信，正是这个魔咒牵引着他，把他引到这片森林的边缘，引入丛林里，引他飞蛾扑火一般扑向那熊熊火光，那隆隆鼓声和那诵念诡异咒语的嗡嗡声。正是这个魔咒，蛊惑了他不安分的灵魂，使他犯下了人神共愤的罪行。而且，你们还不明白吗，那时的危险并不在于被人一棍打破脑袋——尽管我非常强烈地感到那随时可能发生——而在于我不得不与这个人周旋，不论我对他讲最崇高的话，或使用最下流的手段，他都无动于衷。我甚至不得不像那些黑人一样乞求他的庇佑——求助于他本人——求助于他引以为傲，却令人难以置信的堕落无耻。没有比他更崇高的事物，也没有比他更下流的事物，对此我心知肚明。他已经一脚把地球踢开了。这个魔鬼！他还把这个地球踢得支离破碎。他超然绝世，在他面前，我不知道自己是站在地上还是悬在空中。我一直在跟你们讲我们谈话的内容——重复一字一句——但那又有什么意义呢？它们只是再平常不过的日常用语——熟悉而模糊的声音，我们在生命中每一个清醒的日子里跟别人聊天时都会用到。尽管如此，我却觉得在这些字句背后，隐藏着梦里听到的话语，做噩梦时的梦呓，暗含骇人的启示。灵魂！如果曾经有人与一个灵魂苦苦缠斗过，这个人就是我。而且这个与我争论的人并不是一个疯子。你们相信也罢，不信也罢，他绝对神志清醒——他的确把全副精神只放在了自己身上，专注得可怖，但他的思维纹丝不乱。意识到这一点，我看到了一线生机——我当然不能在彼时彼地杀死他，因为他一定会大喊大叫，那我就完了。但他的灵魂已经疯掉了。在荒野中，它是如此孤独，它看透了自己，天啊！它怎么能不发疯。我也被迫——我想我也算是罪有应得——亲身经受把它看透的痛苦。他临终倾吐的由衷之言，令人对人类彻底寒心，与之相比，一切滔滔雄辩都显得苍白无力。他也在与自己苦苦搏斗，我看得出来——我听得出来。我看到了这个灵魂里难以想象的奥秘，它天不怕地不怕，不信神不信鬼，无畏无惧，只知道盲目地和自己过不去。我的头脑一直很清醒，但当我终于把他放进沙发，帮他平躺好，我已经满头大汗，两条腿直打战，好像我是背了半吨重的东西下山。可实际上我不过是搀着他走，他也只是把一条瘦骨嶙峋的手臂紧紧扣在我的脖子上——而且，他并不比一个孩子重多少。

第二天中午我们开船的时候，一直躲在树幕背后的那群人又从森林里汹涌而出，挤满了空地，占满了山坡，到处是青铜色的身体，裸露着，呼吸着，颤抖着。其实我早就敏锐地察觉到他们躲在那里了。我往上游驶了一段，然后掉头向下游开去。两千双眼睛盯着这个狂怒的河中巨魔，看着它嘭嘭咚咚地前进，溅起阵阵水花，一边用一条可怕的尾巴拍着水，向天空呼出滚滚黑烟。在沿河第一排土人的面前，有三个从头到脚涂满鲜红色泥土的人，焦急地来回踱着步。我们再次经过时，他们面朝河流不断跺脚，使劲儿点着戴着犄角装饰的头，猩红色的身体左摇右摆。他们冲狂怒的河魔晃动一捆黑色的羽毛，一张拖着尾巴的斑纹兽皮——那兽皮看起来像个干葫芦。他们隔一会儿就喊出一连串古怪的话，不像是人类的语言。而那片突然被打断的嗡嗡声，低沉深邃，仿佛是对某种邪恶祷文的回应。

我们把库尔茨抬进了驾驶室：那里空气更充足。他躺在沙发上，百叶窗没有放下来，他总是望出窗外。岸上人潮涌动。那个把头发盘成黑盔的黄褐色皮肤女人从人群中冲出来，跑到河边。她伸出双手喊了一句不知道什么话，那群狂暴的土人马上齐声怒号起来。那片怒号，清晰，急促，声嘶力竭。

‘您听得懂他们在喊什么吗？’我问。

他越过我看过去，怒火熊熊的目光里充满渴望，脸上交织着惆怅和憎恨的表情。他没有答话，但我看见，他那苍白的嘴唇露出一丝微笑，一丝耐人寻味的微笑。片刻之后，它抽搐了一下。‘我怎么会听不懂？’他缓缓地说，喘着气，好像这句话是一个超自然的力量从他身上撕下来的。

“我拉响了汽笛。我这么做是因为我看到甲板上的朝圣者们都兴冲冲地跑去拿来复枪，看他们的神情，好像对这个快乐的游戏期待万分。听到突如其来的汽笛尖叫声，一种无助的恐惧席卷了那个楔形的人群。”停手！别吓跑他们！甲板上有人恼火地喊道。我拉了一下又一下，土人们四散奔走，有的跳来跳去，有的蹲下身，有的团团打转，竭力想避开随着汽笛声飞过去的恐怖灾难。那三个猩红色的家伙吓得贴着地趴在河边，好像被射死了一样。唯独那个野蛮却艳丽的女人毫不畏缩，在我们后面，隔着那条波光粼粼却森冷阴郁的河流，哀伤地张开了裸露的双臂。

接着，下面甲板上那群蠢材开始玩他们的小游戏，一阵浓烟挡住了我的视线。

褐色的河水迅疾地从黑暗深处奔腾而下，把我们送往大海，速度是我们沿河上溯时的两倍。库尔茨的生命也在急促流逝，退潮一般，从他内心涌退，退入无情的时间之海里。经理一副安详的样子，现在他再不必为致命的危险担惊受怕了。他偷偷用深远而满足的眼神瞥了我们两人一眼：这个‘事件’的收场，不能再美满了。我看得出，很快我就会变成‘龌龊的手段’的唯一拥护者。朝圣者们都对我嗤之以鼻。这么说吧，我和这个濒死的人是一丘之貉。在那片横遭这帮刻薄贪婪的恶鬼入侵的神秘土地上，我竟然在毫无准备的情况下，心甘情愿地跟库尔茨站在了一边，并且义无反顾地接受了这个强加在我身上的噩梦，说起来也真是够奇怪的。

库尔茨又开腔了。一个声音！一个声音！直到最后一刻，它依然是如此的深沉浑厚。在生龙活虎的时候，库尔茨能用那些雄奇瑰丽的言辞掩盖住内心那片空虚的黑暗，直到现在，即使他已经油尽灯枯，那声音依然萦绕不散。啊，他也斗争过！他斗争过！现在，他的精神已经疲倦不堪，只剩一片废墟坏址，那些阴暗的鬼影却徘徊不去——名和利的鬼影，众星捧月一般，低眉顺眼地围着他卓绝高贵的不朽辩才团团转。我的未婚妻，我的象牙，我的贸易站，我的事业，我的思想——都是偶然会泄露出说话者高尚情怀的话题。从前那个库尔茨的幽灵常常在这个空洞的躯壳旁边出没，这个躯壳只是一个赝品，注定马上就要被埋进这片原始土地的一个土丘里。这个赝品曾彻悟到谜一样的人生里包含的残忍的爱和超脱的恨，而这爱和恨，你争我夺，都想把这个浸满原始感情的灵魂，这个汲汲于镜花水月般的功名利禄的灵魂据为己有。

他有时幼稚得令人生厌。他满心憧憬着，当有朝一日他从某个蛮荒之地成就了丰功伟业之后，衣锦还乡之时，会看到许多国王在火车站恭迎他。‘只要你能向他们展示出赚钱的本领，他们就会无限度地认可你的能力。’他会这么说，‘当然你不能为非作歹——动机一定要冠冕堂皇——谨记。’汽船在一成不变的漫长河道上前行着，驶过如出一辙的河湾，那些葱茏的原始大树，耐心地目送着它，这来自另一个世界的肮脏碎片，变革、征服、贸易、屠杀和幸福生活的先驱。我头也不回——我在驾船。‘关掉百叶窗，’一天库尔茨突然说，‘这景色令我发狂。’我照做了。驾驶室陷入一片寂静之中。‘啊！我还会回来把你折磨得肝肠寸断的！’他对着看不见的荒野大喊。

汽船坏掉了——不出我所料——我们只好在一个小岛的一角停船维修。这次耽搁破天荒地动摇了库尔茨的自信心。一天早晨他交给我一包文件和照片——用一根鞋带捆在一起的。‘请帮我保存好它。’他说，‘这个可恶的笨蛋（指经理）一趁我注意不到，就会把我的箱子翻个底朝天，他真做得出来。’下午我去看他时，他仰躺着，双目紧闭，我便安静地离开，但忽然听见他模糊不清地说：‘光明磊落地活着，死，死……’我侧耳倾听。他没有再说话。他是在梦中排练着某次演讲，还是在斟酌着某篇报文的字句？他一直有给报纸写文章，并打算继续写下去：‘为了传播我的思想。这是一个义务。’

他是一片密不透风的黑暗。我看着他，就好像在俯瞰一个躺在悬崖底的男人，阳光永远无法到达的悬崖底。但我能用来照顾他的时间并不多，因为我要帮轮机师拆开漏水的气缸，掰直弯掉的连杆，还有其他诸如此类的事情。我每天都生活在一大堆混乱的锈铁、锉刀、螺母、螺丝、扳手、锤子和曲柄钻之中，恍如置身地狱——我恨透了它们，因为它们非常不听使唤。我不得不频繁地跑到那个小小的打铁房里去，谢天谢地我们船上有一个打铁房。我在这堆废铜烂铁中没日没夜地拼命工作着——直到两条腿颤得站不住才去休息。

一天晚上，我点着一根蜡烛走进驾驶室，听见他在微微颤抖着说：‘我这是躺在黑暗中等死。’把我吓了一跳。我把蜡烛凑近他的脸，离他的眼睛不到一英尺，勉强低声说道：‘唉，别胡说！’我呆若木鸡地站在他身旁，低头看着他。

他的容貌扭曲了，我从没见过这种变化，哪怕是近似的变化也没有见过，也不想再见到。啊，我不是悲伤难抑，而是被迷住了。仿佛有人撕碎了他的面纱，那张象牙色的脸上，交织着阴森的骄傲、冷酷的威雄、懦弱的恐惧——一种激烈而彻底的绝望表情。在这个超凡的时刻，在他即将要大彻大悟之际，他是否在重温他的人生，抽丝剥茧地反思每一个欲望、每一种诱惑和每一次堕落？他轻轻地喊出声来，也许是对某个人影，也许是对某个场景——他喊了两声，轻得像是在喘气——

‘好可怕！好可怕！’

我吹熄蜡烛，离开了驾驶室。朝圣者们正在食堂吃饭，我在经理对面坐下，他抬起头，向我投来一瞥询问的眼光，我不露痕迹地假装没有看见。他向后靠到椅背上，一脸安宁，带着他特有的微笑，把他那深不见底的卑鄙轻轻藏起。无数小小的苍蝇不断地扑到油灯上，桌布上，我们的手上和脸上。经理的跟班突然从门外把那个傲慢无礼的黑脑袋伸进来，用尖厉的轻蔑口吻说——

‘库尔茨先生——死了。’

所有的朝圣者都冲出去看热闹。我一动不动，继续吃饭。他们肯定认为我铁石心肠。但我不太吃得下。食堂里有一盏油灯——有一点光——而食堂外面是如此的黑暗，黑暗得狰狞凶残。我再也没有回到那个卓越的男人身旁，他对于自己的灵魂在这个地球上的冒险之旅，已经宣布了最终定论。那个声音消逝了。那里可曾有过什么东西？可我当然知道，第二天朝圣者们把一个什么东西埋进了一个脏污的泥洞里。

而他们差点连我也埋掉了。

但是，你们也看见了，我没有当即随库尔茨而去。我没有。我要留下来把这个噩梦做完，并再次表达我对库尔茨的忠诚。命，这都是命！人生真令人哭笑不得——寡情少义的逻辑做出了种种神秘的安排，为的竟是让人白辛苦一场！它能给你的，至多也不过是你对自己的一点点认识——却又总是来得太迟——只是一腔令人死不瞑目的余恨。我曾不顾一切地与死神搏斗。你们想象不出那有多无聊。身处一片混沌的灰色之中，脚下空无一物，四周空无一物，没有观众，无人喝彩，毫不光荣，人既不无限渴望胜利，也不极度害怕失败，那种气氛温温吞吞、犹犹豫豫，令人作呕，使你怀疑自己的权利，更加怀疑对手的权利。如果最高的智慧表现出来就是这副模样，那人生必定是一个更大的谜，比某些人所想象的更为神秘。我当时差点就有机会说出我对人生的定论，但我很羞耻地发现，即使我真的要说，也一个字都说不出来。这就是我敢确定库尔茨很了不起的原因。他有话讲。他讲了出来。正因为我窥视到那条边界另一边的景象，我能更深刻地理解他的凝视，他看不到烛光，但那凝视是如此壮阔，足以容下整个宇宙，又是如此锐利，足以看透所有在黑暗中跳动着的心。他做出了总结——他下了定论。‘好可怕！’他是个了不起的人。毕竟，他表达了某种信念，内里有坦率，有坚定，他颤抖着轻声喊出了反抗的意念，让我瞥见了人生真相的狰狞画面——欲望和憎恨离奇地相互纠缠着。最令我刻骨铭心的，不是我当时面临的困境——而是一个无形的灰色场景，里面充满了肉身的痛苦，以及对一切事物的幻灭都漠不关心的轻蔑——甚至包括这些痛苦本身的幻灭。不！我经历的仿佛是他的困境。没错，在我获准撤回犹疑的脚步之时，他迈出了那最后的一步，越过了边界。也许正是这造成了天壤之别，也许所有的智慧，所有的真相，所有的诚意，全都压缩在了那个惊鸿一瞥的时刻之中，在我们迈过门槛，步入看不见的世界那一刻。也许是吧！我真希望自己对人生的总结不会是一句冷漠而轻蔑的话。他的喊声要好得多——好得多。那是一个断言，一个道德上的胜利，用无数的失败、可憎的恐惧和可憎的满足作为代价换来的。但它是一个胜利！正因为如此，我直到最终，甚至更长久地，都会对库尔茨忠心耿耿。直到很久之后，当我又一次听见，不是他本人的声音，而是他那滔滔雄辩的回响，仿佛从一个像水晶悬崖般透亮的灵魂向我发出来的，我对他的忠诚依然如故。

不，他们没有把我埋掉。尽管我模糊地记得，有一段时间，我好像走在一条通道里，那通道穿过某个不可思议的世界，那里既没有希望，也没有欲望。每次想起来都有点毛骨悚然。我发现自己又回到了那个阴森的城市，无比憎恶地看着人们匆匆忙忙地穿过街道，赶着去从彼此身上占点小便宜，去风卷残云般吃掉恶心的饭食，去开怀畅饮肮脏的啤酒，去做无聊又愚蠢的梦。他们践踏了我的思想。他们是入侵者，在我眼里，他们只不过是自欺欺人地装作很了解人生，简直令人生气，因为我能感觉到，他们绝对不可能知道我所知道的事情。他们的神态举止，纵使平凡得无可厚非，是平民百姓在高枕无忧、安居乐业时的平常表现，我却越看越恼火，仿佛看到的是一群蠢材，危险已逼近眼前，他们不仅无法理解，浑然不觉，还要在那里大肆炫耀自己的愚蠢。我们没有冲动要去唤醒他们，但我不太克制得住自己当面嘲笑他们有多么愚蠢，多么自以为是。我想我那时不太舒服。我在街上踉跄乱撞——有各种事要办——向可敬之极的人勉强挤出笑容。我承认我的所作所为简直荒谬，但在那段日子里，我的体温几乎没有正常过。我亲爱的姨妈绞尽脑汁地想帮我‘固本培元’，但那么做完全是南辕北辙。我不需要保养身体恢复元气，我是胡思乱想过甚，心灵需要抚慰。我留着库尔茨给我的那捆信，想不出到底应该怎么处理它。他母亲不久前过世了，听说逝前一直是他的未婚妻在侍汤奉药。一天有人来拜访我，他把胡子刮得干干净净，戴着金边眼镜，摆出一副公事公办的样子，提出许多问题，开始的时候还算委婉，后来就彬彬有礼地逼问我，要我说出那些他很乐意称之为‘文件’的东西到底在哪里。我并不惊讶，还没回来的时候，我就已经为此和经理吵过两架。我对经理说，我一张纸也不会给他，对这个戴眼镜的男人我也采取了相同的态度。最后他阴沉着脸，摆出一副威胁的样子，面红耳赤地争辩说公司有权利收回关于其‘领地’的一切信息。然后他说：‘鉴于库尔茨先生的伟大才能，以及他所处环境之恶劣，他对这片未开发地区的知识，肯定尤为全面独到，因此——’我向他申明，库尔茨的知识，不论多么全面，都与贸易或者公司行政方面的问题没有直接关系。接着他把科学搬了出来。‘如果……将会造成不可估量之损失’云云。我把那份‘破除野蛮传统’的报告交给他，不过注释已经被我事先撕掉了。他急不可耐地一把接了过去，看完后却轻蔑地对它嗤之以鼻。‘我们有权期望获得的并非这份文件。’他说。‘那就不要再白费心机了，’我说，‘剩下的全是私人信件。’他威胁要走法律途径，然后灰溜溜地走了，我再也没见过他。但两天后，另一个家伙来了，自称是库尔茨的表亲，急切地想知道他亲爱的亲戚临终时的全部细节。他不经意地向我透露，其实库尔茨本来是一个了不起的音乐家。‘差不多就要扬名四海了。’那人说，我相信他是一个风琴手，他灰白的长发瀑布般披在油汪汪的大衣衣领上。我没有理由怀疑他的话，但直到今天，我依然说不清楚库尔茨究竟所司何职，他又是否有过固定的职业——有什么职业能让他施展他最了不起的才华呢？我曾把他看成是会给报纸写文章的画家，或者是擅长绘画的记者——但就连这个表亲（在拜访期间一直吸鼻烟吸个不停）都说不上来他曾经是做什么职业的——准确地。他是个全面的天才——在这一点上，我同意这个老家伙的意见。他马上拿出一方巨大的棉布手帕，震耳欲聋地擤了擤鼻子，老气横秋、激动不已地与我告别，卷走了一些无关紧要的家庭信件和备忘录。最后拜访我的，是一个急于知道他‘亲爱的同事’命运如何的记者。这位来客告诉我，库尔茨的真正职业应该是‘站在大众的一边’的政客。他有一双毛茸茸的剑眉，一头硬挺挺的短发，眼镜上穿着黑色的粗带子。他突然说得兴起，承认他认为库尔茨根本不会写文章——‘但是，天啊！他太能说了！他能震慑住整个会场。他信念坚定——明白吗？——他有坚定的信念。他能让自己相信任何事情——任何事情。他要是参加极端的党派，一定能成为了不起的领袖。’‘什么党派？’我问。‘随便一个党派，’对方回答，‘他是个——一个——极端主义者。’我不也是这样想的吗？我表示赞成。他忽然好奇地问我知不知道‘到底是什么诱使他到那里去的？’‘我知道。’我说，立刻把那份著名的报告交给他，并请他出版，如果他认为合适的话。他草草扫了一眼，一边不停地喃喃自语，断言它‘会卖座的’，就把它顺走了。

就这样，我终于只剩下一小包信和那个姑娘的画像。我惊讶于她的美——我要说的是，她的表情很美。我知道阳光有时也会被迫撒谎，但我不禁感到，她脸上那种柔和而真挚的神情，不是靠操控光线和姿势能制造出来的。她看起来随时准备好在精神上毫无保留地倾听，不带丝毫的怀疑，完全把自身置之度外。我决定亲自去拜访她，把她的画像和那些信件还给她。出于好奇？没错，也许还出于其他心情。所有曾经属于库尔茨的一切，都从我的手上交了出去：他的灵魂，他的身体，他的贸易站，他的宏图大计，他的象牙，他的事业。只剩下他的回忆和他的未婚妻——我也想交出去了，从某种意义上讲，交给过去——我要亲手将他留给我的一切，全部交给那两个字：遗忘。所有人最终都免不了要遗忘。我没有在为自己辩护。我也不知道自己真正需要的到底是什么。也许那只是一时的心血来潮，由潜意识里的忠诚引起的，也许只是想要完成某个荒唐的任务，人生在世，不就是为了完成种种说不清道不明的任务么？我不知道。我无法分辨。但我去了。

我原本以为，对他的记忆与对其他死者的毫无二致，在每个人的一生中，这种记忆都会慢慢地越积越多——只是一个模糊的印象，影子一般掠过脑海，转瞬即逝。但当我来到那扇又高又沉的门前，站在街上高高的楼房中间，我却觉得那些楼房犹如一个精心维护的墓地里死寂却富丽的两排墓碑，我仿佛看到了他坐在担架上的幻象，贪婪地张大嘴巴，好像要吞掉整个地球和所有的人类。那一刻，他又在我面前活了过来，跟过去一样栩栩如生——一个影子，不知餍足地追求着外表的辉煌，追求着狰狞的现实，比黑夜的影子还要黑暗，披着卓绝辩才的高贵外衣。这个幻象似乎和我一起进入了房子——那个担架，抬担架的鬼影，他那群狂热却顺从的崇拜者，那群土人，森林的幽暗，烟水迷茫的河湾之间，河面的寒光，那鼓声，滞闷而规律的，宛如心跳声——那片被征服了的黑暗的心跳声。那是荒野的胜利时刻，一次狂暴的侵略和复仇，而我，要独自抵挡它，以拯救另一个灵魂。我又想起了他在那个远方说过的话，在我背后的火光中，在那片耐心的森林里，顶着羚羊角的人影在扭动着，我又听到了那些破碎的字句，简单得凶险，简单得令人惊颤。我记得他卑怯的央求，卑怯的威胁，卑怯而巨大的邪恶欲念，他灵魂里的卑鄙、苦恼，以及暴风雨般的痛苦。后来，我有一天去看他的时候，他似乎已经镇定下来，但样子十分憔悴。他说：‘此时此刻，这批象牙完全属于我所有，公司还没有为它们出过一分钱。是我自己一个人出生入死收集来的。但我担心他们将来一定会宣称那为公司所有。哼，真是棘手。你认为我应该怎么做呢——反抗？是吗？我只想他们还我一个公道。’……他想要的只是一个公道——只是公道。我上了二层，在一扇桃花心木门前按了按门铃。在我等候之时，他似乎躲在玻璃嵌板后面盯着我——用那个广阔无际的凝视，那个拥抱着、谴责着、憎恶着整个宇宙的凝视。我仿佛听到他在低声喊着：‘好可怕！好可怕！’

暮色渐浓。我必须在高高的客厅里等候。客厅里有三扇长长的落地窗，从天花板一直拖到地面，仿佛三根包裹着彩幔的大圆柱，隐隐生光。家具的弯腿和靠背镀了金，璀璨生辉，映照成模糊的曲线。高高的大理石壁炉是苍白色的，白得冰冷、哀伤。一个角落里摆着一架沉重的大钢琴，平滑的琴面泛着黑暗的光芒，整个地像一口暗淡而磨光的石棺。一扇高高的门开了——关了。我站起来。

她走上前来，一身黑衣，脸色苍白，在暮色中仿佛是在朝我飘来。她正在服丧。距离他去世之日已经有一年多了，距离死讯传来之日也已经有一年多了，可是，看她的样子，她永远会记得那一天，永远为他服丧。她握起我的双手，喃喃道：‘我早就听说您要来。’我注意到她并不是很年轻——我是说，她并不天真烂漫。她已经足够成熟，有能力驾驭忠诚、信仰与苦难。房间似乎越来越暗了，好像在那个浓云密布的黄昏，所有忧伤的光线都避祸一般聚集到她的额头上。那淡金的头发，苍白的面容，精致的蛾眉，似乎围绕在一个灰蒙蒙的光环里，那双黑色的眼睛，望穿了光环，定定地看着我。这目光诚实，深邃，自信，深信不疑。她高高地昂着悲伤的头，仿佛对这份悲伤倍感自豪，好像她要说：‘我——只有我懂得怎样得体地为他服丧。’但当我们还在握手的时候，她脸上浮现出一种凄荒得可怕的表情，我便察觉到，她属于绝不甘于沦为时间之神的玩物那类人。对她而言，库尔茨仿佛昨日才去世。而且，天啊！那个表情太动人心魄了，竟然使我也觉得，库尔茨是昨天刚去世的——不，库尔茨刚刚才去世。刹那间，我看见库尔茨和她同在——库尔茨的死和她的悲伤——我看见在库尔茨死去那一刻，她眼里的悲伤。你们能理解吗？我看见他们同在——我听见他们同在。她深深叹了一口气，哽咽着说：‘我活了下来。’然而我那紧绷的耳朵似乎无限清晰地听到，与她那绝望悔恨的声调交融在一起的，是库尔茨那个低喊，库尔茨下的那个定论，那个永恒的谴责。我问自己，我在那里做什么，心中万分惊恐，仿佛我不慎闯进了一个人类看不得的地方，里面满是残忍而怪诞的谜。她示意我坐到一张椅子上，我们坐下来。我把那个小小的包裹轻轻地放到一张小桌子上，她把手放在上面……‘您一定非常了解他。’悲痛地沉默了片刻之后，她喃喃说道。

‘在那种地方，人和人很容易变得亲密起来。’我说，‘我对他的了解，深入得可谓无以复加。’

‘而且您也很欣赏他吧，’她说，‘了解他的人不可能不欣赏他，是吗？’

‘他是个非凡卓绝的人。’我迟疑地说。她若有所求地定定看着我，似乎满心期待我说下去。我又说：‘了解他的人，不可能不——’

‘爱他。’她迫不及待地替我把话说完，把我吓得哑口无言，‘说得真对！说得真对！但请您知道，没人比我更了解他！他把自己所有高贵的信赖，都毫无保留地交给了我。我最懂他。’

‘您最懂他。’我重复道。而也许她确实最懂他。但我们每说一句话，房间似乎就变得更暗一些，只有她细滑而白皙的额头，仍然被信仰和爱的永恒光芒映照得光亮如雪。

‘您是他的朋友，’她继续说，‘他的朋友。’她重复道，稍微提高了一点声音，‘您当然是他的朋友，因为他把这个包裹交了给您，并请您来见我。我感觉我可以和您推心置腹地谈一谈——啊！我一定要说出来。我希望您能——您这个听到了他临终遗言的人——您能明白我对他是多么重要……我并不是要以此为豪……没错，我确实很自豪地认为，我比地球上任何人都更加了解他——他也曾亲口对我这么说过。但自从他母亲过世之后，我就找不到人——没有人——来——来——’

我静静听着。暮色越来越浓了。我甚至不确定库尔茨是不是把对的那个包裹交给了我。我相当地怀疑，他想交给我保管的，是另一包信件，他死后经理在灯下细细检查的那包。这位姑娘不停地说着话，她深信我在同情她，希望能从我身上得到安慰。她如饥似渴地倾诉着。她说她的家人十分反对这桩婚事，仿佛是因为库尔茨不够富有。实际上，我也不知道库尔茨是否自始至终都是一个穷小子。通过与他的接触，我绝对有理由推断，正是由于厌倦了自己不够富有，他才义无反顾地跑到了那个地方去。

‘……只要有幸一闻其声，有谁能不为他倾倒呢？’她在说着，‘他能唤起人们内心最美好的情感，使人们归心于他。’她神色庄重地看着我，‘这是伟人的天赋。’她继续说道，她的声音，似乎淹没在缭乱的伴奏声中，那伴奏里，满是谜样的神秘、孤寂的凄凉和愁肠百结的悲伤，我曾在哪里听到过的——河水潺潺，风中的绿树飒飒，野人群的怪语嗡嗡，从远处传来的回响细细，如此的深邃难解，还有一个微弱的低语声，越过那个永恒的黑暗世界的门槛，幽幽传来。‘但您听见他说的话了！您听见了！’她叫了起来。

‘是的，没错，我听见了。’我怀着某种近似绝望的情绪说，在她心中坚定的信仰面前，在那伟大得足以救赎一切罪孽的幻象面前，我看见那幻象在黑暗中闪耀着天堂的光彩，我屈服了。在那片不可一世的黑暗中，我没有能力保护她——我甚至没有办法保护我自己。

‘对我而言，这是一个多么大的损失——不，应该是对我们而言！’她非常有风度地改口道，真是慷慨。然后又低声补充道：‘对于整个世界而言。’在黄昏最后一丝光线里，我看得见她闪着光的眼里饱含泪水——她一直强忍着的泪水。

‘我曾经是多么高兴——多么幸运——多么自豪，’她继续说道，‘太幸运了。有那么一阵子，我实在是太快乐了。而现在，我是如此不幸——抱恨终身。’

她站起来，淡金色的头发仿佛聚拢了所有黄昏的余光，熠熠生辉。我也站起身来。

‘而所有的这一切，’她继续摧心剖肝地说道，‘他所有的承诺，所有的伟大，所有的宏伟思想，他高贵的心灵，都荡然无存了——逝去了，只剩下回忆。您和我——’

‘我们会永远缅怀他。’我连忙说。

‘不！’她叫道，‘这一切不可能就这样灰飞烟灭——这样一个人牺牲之后，怎么可能不留下只鳞片羽——除去不尽的悲伤之外？您知道他胸中的宏图伟业，我也知道——也许我无能力去理解——但有其他人听闻过。一定有什么东西留存了下来。至少，他的高谈阔论仍然充满了生命力。’

‘他的高谈阔论是不朽的。’我说。

‘而且他也树立起了一个榜样，’她轻声自语道，‘人们会景仰他——他的一言一行，都闪耀着美德的光辉。他是一个绝佳的榜样——’

‘是的，’我说，‘他还树立起了一个榜样。是的，榜样。我给忘了。’

‘但我没有。我不能——我不能够相信——还是不能。我不能相信永远都见不到他了，没有任何人会再见到他了，永远，永远，永远！’

她伸开双臂，仿佛在目送一个面朝着她渐行渐远的人，她把手深入黑暗之中，在窗户逐渐暗淡下去的狭窄光亮之中，轻轻扣住一双苍白的手。再也看不见他！我那个时候已经清清楚楚地看见了他。终我一生，我将一直看得见这个雄辩滔滔的幽灵，而我也会看见她，一个哀伤而熟悉的阴影。她现在的姿势，跟另一个人如出一辙，那个同样哀伤的阴影，浑身挂满了无能为力的符咒，在那条黑暗之河上，张开了裸露的棕色手臂。她突然非常低沉地说：‘他虽死犹生。’

‘这个结局，’我说，闷在心中的愤怒翻江倒海，‘完全对得起他的人生。’

‘但我没能陪伴他到最后。’她低声道。我突然对她生出无限的怜悯，不生气了。

‘我们尽力了——’我嘟囔道。

‘啊，但我对他的信仰之深，超过了地球上任何一个人——比他自己的母亲还要多，比——他自己还要多。他离不开我！我！他的每声叹息，每句话，每个手势，每个眼神，我都将无比珍重爱惜。’

我感到一阵寒气冰住了我的心。‘别这样。’我强压着声音说。

‘对不起。我——我——服丧了这么久，如此孤寂——如此孤寂……您和他在一起——您在他临终时陪伴在旁？我常常想，他是多么孤独啊！身边没有如我一般了解他的人，也许连听他说话的人都没有……’

‘我一直陪伴在他身旁，’我颤抖着说，‘我听见了他的临终遗言……’我害怕得不敢往下说。

‘请您重复一次好吗，’她肝肠寸断地低声说，‘我想要——想要——某些东西——某些东西——来——来支撑我活下去。’

我简直马上就要向她咆哮道：‘您不是听见了吗？’那句话在暮色中低声回荡着，一声紧似一声，仿佛风刚起时的轻响，咄咄逼人地越刮越烈。‘好可怕！好可怕！’

‘他的临终遗言——支撑我活下去，’她低声道，‘难道您不明白我爱他——我爱他——我爱他！’

我用尽浑身气力，缓缓地说了一句话。

‘他最后说的是——您的名字。’

“我听见一声轻微的叹息，我的心脏仿佛被冻住了。一声狂喜却凄厉的尖叫，充满胜利的神秘喜悦，无可言说的痛苦，把我的心完全石化了。‘我就知道——我从未怀疑过！’……她知道，她从未怀疑过。我听见她哭得梨花带雨，她把脸深深地埋在手里。我似乎感到，我还来不及逃走，这座房子就会塌掉，天也会塌下来砸死我。但一切如故。天才不会为了这样一件小事就塌掉。我真想知道，如果我能替库尔茨争取到他想要的公道，天会塌下来吗？他不是说了，他想要的只是公道吗？但我帮不了他。我不能告诉这个姑娘。那实在是太黑暗了——黑暗得太凶残了……”

马洛讲完了。他坐在一边，朦胧，寂静，那姿势仿佛一座正在修行悟道的佛像。有那么一阵子，众人一动不动。“我们错过了第一次退潮。”主任突然说。我把头抬起来。海面上横遮着一堆乌云，那条通向天涯海角的河道，在阴沉的天空下，忧伤地流淌着——仿佛头也不回地，要流入一片庞大的黑暗的心中。

[1]英国古镇，在泰晤士河南岸，距离伦敦市中心21英里。

[2]指伦敦。

[3]意为以水手为职业。

[4]英国著名航海家，继麦哲伦后第二位完成环球航海的壮举。

[5]英国著名探险家。

[6]弗朗西斯·德雷克曾乘坐。

[7]流行于古罗马时代的一种葡萄酒，常常出现在古罗马文学作品中。

[8]意大利东北部港口城市。

[9]舰队街曾是英国新闻和出版事业的中心，现在仍然是英国媒体的代名词。

[10]一种多泡沫的淡啤酒，原产德国。

[11]原文为法语。

[12]原文为拉丁文。教徒对圣母玛利亚欢呼时使用。

[13]原文为拉丁文。公元52年，在罗马皇帝克劳迪斯面前，俘虏和罪犯在模拟海战中说的一句话。这些俘虏和罪犯都必须在模拟战争中战死。

[14]使用茴芹、茴香和苦艾等制成的高度酒。

[15]原文为法语。

[16]原文为法语。

[17]原文为法语。

[18]迪尔和格雷夫森德均为英国地名。

[19]重量单位，一英石等于6.35公斤。

[20]歌德名著《浮士德》中的魔鬼，常诱人淫乱作恶。

[21]英国的饼干公司，曾经是世界上最大的饼干公司。

[22]爱尔兰传统舞蹈，有点像踢踏舞。

[23]旧时英国货币，1克朗等于5先令。

[24]指代库尔茨写的报告。

[25]位于俄罗斯东部。

译者序

十九世纪末，美国阿拉斯加发现金矿，这不啻在沉闷的下层社会响起一声震雷，消息一传十、十传百，很快传遍了全美国。在社会底层苦苦挣扎的人们，心里重新燃起了生活的希望，尽管这种希望对他们来说无异于海市蜃楼之于沙漠中的求生者。于是，破产的农民、失业的工人、城市的流民，这些形形色色、做着各式各样发财梦的人们为着共同的目的聚到一起，化作大小、长短、粗细不同的人流，朝着遥远的北方蠕动着。

年仅二十岁的杰克·伦敦也夹裹在人流中。谁也不知道这个青年是怎样上路的。时至今日，他阿拉斯加之行的真正意图早已随着时间的流逝而湮没了，我们只能凭借遗留在历史上的雪泥鸿爪进行揣测。首先，他此行的目的不能判断为淘金，似乎应该认定为探险或者猎奇。从史料中我们得知，杰克·伦敦出身贫困家庭，小小年纪便开始做童工。他曾在美国各地流浪，目睹了各种社会怪状，对当时的社会本质有着深刻的认识。他二十岁之前结束了流浪生活，以惊人的毅力发奋读书，同时接受马克思及尼采的思想，接受了人类一种全新的理想——社会主义的熏陶。他毕竟是读书之人了，有修养、有志向。他要用自己手中的笔，描绘今后美好的生活，而不愿成为一夜发财的暴发户，他的这种理想主义的思想，在其代表作《马丁·伊登》中有所流露。在杰克·伦敦的心目中，暴发户除却散发铜臭，还与粗俗、贪婪同名。因此，一个有理想、有抱负的文学青年，断不会像其他淘金者那样，千里迢迢来到阿拉斯加，乞求《天方夜谭》中阿里巴巴再现，口诵咒语，黄金洞现。如果说杰克·伦敦是在作家的好奇心理驱使下踏上阿拉斯加行程，虽然听上去有些浪漫，却是令人信服的。阿拉斯加之行，艰辛万状，险象环生。一路上，山峦叠嶂，河谷相连。他穿过荒原，翻过雪山，风餐露宿，啼饥号寒，以生命为代价完成了一次艰难的生活体验。

打阿拉斯加归来，杰克·伦敦创作出了《野性的呼唤》《白牙》等描写狼与犬的小说。前者描写一只有着狼血统的犬，这只犬为了生存与其他的犬进行了殊死的搏斗，最后在狼群的召唤下恢复了野性，逃进原始森林变成了狼。而《白牙》则是描写狼变犬的故事。一只狼崽被人相救并被养大，它克服了野性逐渐驯化。最后，在主人危难之时它舍身相救并咬死了主人的宿敌。这些小说惊险离奇，有时显现拟人化特征，作者自己称之为“北方故事”。当时，“北方故事”深受广大读者喜爱，杰克·伦敦由此获得文学事业上的成功。但他并不以此为荣耀，就像当年他不会企盼成为一夜发财的暴发户一样，今天他同样不会把“北方故事”当作自己的文学成就。他要创作出系统的、理想化的、有传奇性的、近乎完美类型的、经历了人世间的痛苦和幸福并受人崇拜的文学形象，以实现自己多年的夙愿，他把这一夙愿交由《马丁·伊登》付诸实现。

杰克·伦敦的代表作《马丁·伊登》，取材于作者早年的生活经历和个人的奋斗过程。前半部分有明显的自传体例，后半部分以及主要情节有虚拟之嫌。书中讲述的是青年水手马丁的文学生涯及其爱情经历。马丁出身社会下层，自选择了水手这一职业后只能与船随伴，长年在海上漂泊。特殊的职业和丰富的生活经历造就了他豪爽、开朗的性格和强壮的体魄。他才智过人，有进取心。自从与富家小姐露丝邂逅，两人相互产生爱慕之心。马丁在露丝小姐鼓励下，劳作之余刻苦学习，以求言谈举止文雅风趣，博得小姐的芳心。一个偶然的机会，促使马丁走上文学道路，从此他从自己丰富的生活经历中汲取素材，刻苦写作。久而久之，他撰写的故事既生动感人，又有文采。自己每每读罢，觉得十分满意，遂向报社、杂志社投稿。可是，杂志社的编辑们对马丁的文章不屑一顾，经常连看也不看便随手退稿。马丁不顾一切地忘情写作，稿件却屡屡被退回，导致他生活拮据，经常靠典当衣物来填饱肚子。房东催要房租，食品商拒绝赊账，正当他焦头烂额的时候，女友露丝又迫于家庭的压力要同他分手。他绝望到了极点，心中的五彩人生瞬间变得丑恶无比。马丁精神即将崩溃了，完全心灰意冷了。谁知此时此刻，幸运之神突然降临了——他的书稿和文章被多家杂志社选用出版了，他的境遇发生了翻天覆地的变化。房东对他笑脸相迎，食品商对他毕恭毕敬，原先瞧不起他的人们纷纷表示祝贺，露丝也前来要求和好。马丁经过一阵热闹的周旋后，冷静了下来，这才发觉全是金钱在作祟，一切都是虚伪的。这次，他的精神真的崩溃了。他用投海这一简单而古老的方式结束了自己的一生。

小说以生动感人的形象揭露二十世纪初美国社会金钱至上的腐朽、虚伪的社会现实，马丁经过自己超乎寻常的努力取得文学事业上的成功后，才发觉一切都如同幻化的梦境。当他撩开上流社会表面那层温情的面纱，才发觉里面竟然充斥着奸诈和冷漠，他实在经受不起这等精神上的打击。作者借此流露出对社会悲观失望的情绪。而马丁艰难而辉煌的经历，是杰克·伦敦竭力推崇和刻意营造的，从中不难看出尼采哲学对作者有着深刻的影响。甚至，尼采“个人奋斗”的思想可以说是作者的精神支柱。

第一章

那人用钥匙打开门，走了进去，身后跟着一位小伙子。小伙子笨拙地摘下帽子。他穿着粗布衣裳，浑身散发出海洋的腥味，与眼前这宽敞的大厅格格不入。他不知把帽子往哪里放才好，于是便要朝衣袋里塞，可对方却伸手接了过去。那人做得不动声色和从容不迫，真是叫这位尴尬的小伙子欣赏得很。小伙子心想：“他能体谅人，会对我照应到底的。”

他走在那人的身后，肩膀一摇一摆，深一脚浅一脚的，就好像平坦的地板正随着大海的波动而起伏。他的步态摇摇晃晃，使原本宽敞的厅堂显得异常狭小。他忧心忡忡，生怕宽厚的肩膀会撞上门框，或者把低矮的壁炉架上的古玩给碰下来。在各种各样的陈设之间，他东躲西闪，结果使实际上仅存在于他脑海中的危险感愈加强烈。在一架大钢琴和厅堂中央一张堆着一厚摞书的桌子之间，空着好大的地方，足够六七个人并肩穿行，可他走过时仍是胆战心惊。他粗壮的胳膊松松地垂吊在身体两旁，真不知怎样处置自己的手脚。他忐忑不安，眼看一条胳膊快要碰上桌子上的书本了，便如受惊的马儿一般跳到一旁，结果差点把钢琴前的凳子撞倒。看到前面的那人走路不慌不忙，他平生第一次意识到自己走路的样子与其他人不一样。想想自己野里野气的步态，内心不由顿感羞愧，脑门上沁出了细细的汗珠。他停下来，用手帕擦了擦紫红的脸颊。

“等一等，阿瑟老兄。”他说道，想用开玩笑的语气掩饰心里的不安，“来得太突然，叫我措手不及。给我一点时间定定神。你清楚，我本来是不愿来的，再说你家里的人也不一定愿见我。”

“没关系，”对方安慰道，“在我们家你不必感到惊慌。我们可是平平常常的人家——哈，这儿有我一封信。”

他走到桌子跟前，拆开信看了起来，这就给新来的客人一个稳定情绪的机会。客人心领神会，十分感激。他天生富于同情及理解之心，所以这当儿尽管外表惊慌，仍能体会到别人的好意。他揩干额头上的汗水，控制住脸上的表情打量着四周，不过眼睛里却露出一种惊慌的神情，像是野兽害怕掉进陷阱一样。他置身于一个陌生的环境，唯恐会发生不测，对自己该干些什么心里没底，只知道自己的走路和举止都非常笨拙，生怕自己的一言一行均会同样叫人尴尬。他极端敏感，同时自惭形秽到了无可挽救的地步。所以，对方在看信时偷偷向他投来的好奇的目光，像匕首一样深深扎入他的心坎。他瞧见了那目光，然而却声色不动，因为在他所学到的本领中有一项就是控制自己。那只匕首也刺伤了他的尊严。他怪自己不该到这儿来，不过在同一时间又做出决定：既然来了，不管情况怎样，都应该坚持到最后。他脸上的线条开始绷紧，双目投射出战斗的光芒。于是，他比较轻松地将目光扫向四周，注意观察着，把美丽的大厅内每一个细小的物品都刻入脑海之中。他的两眼间距很宽，任何东西都逃不出他的视野；当这双眼睛欣赏面前的美景时，战斗的光芒逐渐消失，取而代之的是一种温和的亮光。他对美是敏感的，而这里正有能引起他共鸣的东西。

一幅油画吸引住了他，使他留住了脚步。惊浪拍天，冲上高矗的石岩；低垂的雨云遮盖住苍天；大浪的旁边有一只领航帆船被风儿吹得东倒西歪，甲板上的每一个物件都清晰可见，行驶在落日的余晖下，头顶风雨欲来的天空。画中的美景对他产生了无法抗拒的吸引力。他忘掉了自己走路时的笨拙相，来到油画的跟前，凑得很近很近。可是，画面上的美消失了。他露出困惑的神情，呆视着这幅看起来像是随意涂抹的画作，后来走到了一旁。但所有的美顷刻间又回到了画面上。“这幅画会变戏法。”他暗忖。油画给他留下了杂乱的印象，同时又令他不胜愤慨，因为他觉得不该为了变一个戏法就牺牲这么多的美。他不懂油画，从小看惯的只有五彩石印画和石版画，而这些画无论是近瞧还是远看，总是线条清晰、轮廓分明。以前在商店的橱窗里，他的确看到过油画，但橱窗玻璃挡住了好奇的他，使他不能把眼睛凑到跟前欣赏。

他回头去望正在读信的朋友，却瞥见了桌子上的那些书。他的眼睛里闪出期望和向往的神情，像是一个饿着肚子的人看到了食物一般。于是，他不由自主地一个箭步，膀子左右摇晃了一下，来到桌子前，开始爱不释手地翻阅那些书。他浏览书名和作者的姓名，读上几段文字，手和眼都忙个不停，而且发现了一本他以前看过的书。至于其他的书和作者，对他来说都是陌生的。他偶然翻到斯温伯恩[1]的一部诗集，便一直看了下去，忘记了自己身在何处，脸上散发出红光。他两次用食指按在看到的地方，把书合上去看作者的名字。斯温伯恩！他要记住这个名字。这家伙有眼光，一定体验过五彩缤纷的生活。可斯温伯恩是谁呢？是不是和大多数诗人一样，死了已有百年之久了呢？或者现在还活着，仍在写作？他翻到了书名页……不错，这人还写过别的书；就这样，明天早晨第一件事就是到公共图书馆找几本斯温伯恩的书看。接着，他又翻回到原来的地方，出神地读了起来。他没留意一位年轻女子走了进来。直到听见阿瑟的声音，他才转过神来。阿瑟介绍说：

“露丝，这位是伊登先生。”

伊登按住书页，将书合起。还未扭过身来，他便被一种全新的感觉弄得心潮激荡，这种感觉不是由那女子引起，而是由她弟弟的言辞所导发。在他那肌肉发达的外壳里，裹着一团跳动着的敏感神经。外界对他的心灵哪怕是稍加触动，他的思想、情绪和感情都会活跃起来，如火焰般燃烧。他异常聪颖和出奇地敏感，丰富的想象力每时每刻都在区分相同之处以及不同的地方。令他激动不已的是“伊登先生”这个称呼——在他的一生中，人们一直称他“伊登”，“马丁·伊登”，或者仅仅把他叫作“马丁”。而这一次竟有人称他为“先生”！他从内心觉得这是了不起的称呼。他的大脑好像一下子变成了一个巨大的照相机暗盒，他看到在自己的意识周围排列着无数生活中的情景——锅炉房、船甲板、营地、沙滩、监狱、酒馆、传染病院和贫民窟的街道。在各种场合中，人们对他的称呼犹如一根线，把这些情景串联在一起。

接着，他转过身，看到了那女子。一见她，他脑海中的幻象便一齐消失了。她面孔白皙、身段轻盈，有一双灵秀的蓝色大眼睛和一头浓密的金发。他说不出她的穿戴究竟怎样，只知道她的服饰和她本人一样美。在他的眼里，她宛若一朵结在细嫩枝条上的苍白色金花。不，她是一个精灵，一个天仙，一个女神，因为这样圣洁的美在人世间是找不到的。要不，书本上的话也许是对的，在上流社会她这样的人儿比比皆是。她应该得到那位诗人斯温伯恩的歌颂。诗人在刻画桌子上那本书中的姑娘伊索尔特时，脑子里或许想的正是她这样的人。刹那间，他眼花缭乱、感情复杂、思绪万千，周围的现实一刻不停地变换着。他看到她向他伸出手来，一边直视着他的眼睛，一边大大方方地像男士一样同他握手。他所认识的女人可不这样握手，其实，她们大多就不跟人握手。种种联想，以及种种他和女人结识的情景一齐涌入了他的脑海，大有淹没一切的可能。但他把所有的念头都抛至一旁，把眼光投向她。这样的女人从未见过。他以前的女相识不能与之相提并论！立刻，那些女相识在她的两旁排列成行。在这永恒的一瞬间，他仿佛置身于一个画像陈列馆里，许多女人的画像如众星捧月般将她围在中间，等待他用巡视的目光去测量和估价，而她就是测量和估价的标准。他看到了脸色憔悴、病容满面的工厂女工，看到了市场街南端的那些叽叽嘎嘎地又笑又闹的姑娘，看到了牧区的姑娘们，还看到了皮肤黝黑、抽着烟卷的墨西哥女郎。随后，这些女人的形象消失了，取而代之的是穿着木屐、走路扭捏作态、长得似洋娃娃一般的日本女人；眉清目秀，但打着堕落烙印的欧亚混血儿；身材丰满、头戴花冠、棕褐色皮肤的南部海岛国女郎。这些幻影渐渐变得模糊了，而接着出现的是一类奇形怪状、噩梦一般的女人——其中有在白色教堂区的街道上徜徉的邋遢婆娘，有喝得醉醺醺的卖春妇，也有满口脏话、横行霸道、令人作呕的母夜叉，她们都具有女人的躯壳，可怕地猎取着水手、港口的下等人以及人类社会的渣滓。

“你请坐，伊登先生，”姑娘说道，“阿瑟把你的事告诉给我们后，我一直盼着能见到你呢。你可真勇敢——”

他不以为然地摆了摆手，喃喃不清地说他所做的事根本算不上什么，碰上任何人都会那样干的。她发现他的那只摆动的手上有几处新划破的尚未愈合的伤口，再瞧瞧另一只垂吊在一旁的手，也是一副同样的情形。她飞眼又仔细打量了一下，看到他的腮帮子上留着一道伤疤，还有一条疤遮在前额的头发下，而第三道伤疤顺颈而下，消失在了硬领里。一看到他紫铜色的脖子上那条被硬领磨出的红痕，她就忍不住想笑。显而易见，他不习惯穿硬领衣服。而且，她还用女人的眼光审视了一遍他的穿着，发现他的衣服缺乏美观，属于廉价品，隆起的二头肌把肩部顶出一道横向皱褶，而袖子也因此显得皱皱巴巴。

他一边摆着手，喃喃地说自己什么也没干，一边则听从她的吩咐，想坐到椅子上去。他羡慕地望着她从容落座，然后跌跌绊绊地向她对面的座位走去，心里为自己的笨拙相感到无地自容。这对他是一种新的体验。以前，他从不知道自己的举止是优雅还是笨拙，因为他从未思考过这类事情。他谨小慎微地在椅子边坐下，被自己的双手搅得心烦意乱。不管把手放在哪里，都觉得碍事。此时，阿瑟走了出去，而马丁·伊登只好用遗憾的目光送他离开。和这位白皙的仙女单独待在房间里，他感到手足无措。这儿没有侍者端酒，也没有小厮到街角为他买酒，所以不能靠这种社交场上的饮料交流友谊。

“你脖子上的伤疤真怕人，伊登先生，”姑娘说道，“是怎么落下的？我想其中必有一段惊险的经历。”

“让一个墨西哥人扎了一刀。”他抿了抿干枯的嘴唇，清清嗓子说，“我们不过是打了一架。我夺过了他的刀，而他恨不得一口咬下我的鼻子。”

他虽然说得轻描淡写，但眼前却闪现出一幕热闹的场景——那是萨利那·克鲁兹[2]的一个布满星光的闷热的夜晚，在白色的海滩上，停泊在港湾里的蔗糖运载船上闪出点点灯火，远处传来酩酊大醉的水手喧闹的声音，周围的码头工人挤作一团，那位墨西哥人的脸上怒火燃烧，用钢刀扎入他的脖子，顿时血如泉涌，人群里爆发出呐喊声，墨西哥人的躯体与他的紧紧扭在一起，滚来滚去，扬起一阵白沙，而远处的某个地方却传来令人陶醉的吉他弹奏声。当时就是这样一种情景，至今回想起来他还觉得激动不已，心想如果那个把领港船绘制在墙上的画家能把这样的场景表现出来就好了。他以为，那白色的海滩、闪烁的星光、蔗糖船上的灯火，以及在沙滩中央把两位打架的人团团围住的黑压压的人群，可以构成一幅壮丽的画面。他觉得，将那把刀展现在画面上，在星光下刀光闪闪，看起来一定精彩。不过，这样的想法一丝一毫都没有掺入他的言谈之中。“他还想一口把我的鼻子咬掉呢。”他最后说道。

“啊！”姑娘失声叫道，声音既微弱又遥远。他注意到她那表情丰富的脸上露出一丝吃惊的神色。

他自己也感到有些吃惊，被太阳晒黑的脸颊上微微泛出困窘的红晕，腮帮子火辣辣地发烫，就好像在锅炉房里面对着敞开的炉门似的。像持刀斗殴这一类乌七八糟的事，显然不适于作跟小姐交谈的话题。书中的人物，以及她生活圈子里的人是不谈这种事的——这种事也许他们闻所未闻。

在他们刚刚开始的谈话中出现了短暂的停顿。随即，她以试探性的口吻问起了他腮帮子上那道疤的来由。一听她的问话，他就明白她在竭力谈他所熟悉的事情，于是便决定把话题引开，转向她的领域。

“那是在一次事故中落下的。”他用手摸着腮帮子说，“一天夜间，虽然没起风，但海浪汹涌，把主帆桅吊索打断了，紧跟着索具也掉了下来。吊索是用钢丝拧成的，呼呼地飞舞，像条蛇一样。值班的人都想抓住它，我也冲上前去，结果给拍了一下。”

“噢。”她这次说话时用的是一种会意的语气，可实际上她对他的解释有许多地方都听不懂，弄不清什么是“吊索”，也不知道“拍一下”意味着什么。

“斯万伯恩这个人……”他开始实施自己的决定，然而却把“温”拖得过长，发成了“万”字。

“谁呀？”

“斯万伯恩，”他又重复了一遍，但还是没有把音发对，“就是那位诗人。”

“他叫斯温伯恩。”她纠正说。

“不错，正是那伙计。”他期期艾艾地说，同时脸上又发起烧来，“他去世有多长时间啦？”

“哦，我没听人说起过他已不在人世了。”她以惊奇的目光望着他，“你是在哪儿和他认识的？”

“我从来就没见过他，”他答道，“不过，就在你进来之前，我在桌子上的那本书里看到了他的几首诗。你觉得他的诗写得怎么样？”这个话题一经提出，她便口若悬河地讲了起来，他感觉好了些，把身子从椅子边朝后稍微挪了一下，但两手却紧紧抓住椅子扶手，仿佛椅子会从他的屁股下溜掉，将他摔到地板上似的。总算使她扯上了自己熟悉的话题。当她滔滔不绝往下讲时，他竭尽全力地侧耳倾听，陶醉地望着她那张如花似玉的白皙面孔，不知她那颗漂亮的脑袋里怎么装着这许多学问。她虽然流利地说出一些陌生的字眼，使用一些他不知道的绝词佳句和思维方式，使他感到困惑，但他仍然能听懂她的意思，觉得那些词句和思想刺激着他的大脑，令他兴奋不已。他暗忖，这就是美，热烈而奇妙，是他以前做梦都想象不到的。他忘掉了自我，以饥渴的目光呆视着她。他要为了她而生活和奋争，努力赢得她的青睐。书本上说得对，世界上果真有这样的女性，而她就是其中的一个。她给他的想象插上了翅膀，于是一幅幅场面恢宏、绚丽多彩的画卷展现在他眼前，上面描绘的是一些朦朦胧胧、充满爱情和浪漫色彩的巨人，他们为了一个女性——一个白皙的女人或金色的花朵创造着英雄业绩。透过这种摇晃和颤抖的幻象，犹如透过神奇的仙境一般，他呆呆地望着这位坐在他跟前高谈阔论文学艺术的有血有肉的女人。他也在倾听，但他紧紧盯着对方，全然不知自己目光逼人，不知自己本质里的男性全都聚在眼睛里闪闪发光。她对男人的世界知之甚微，但作为女人，她却强烈地感觉到了他火辣辣的目光。从没有男人这般凝视过她，这令她发窘，使她说话结巴，思维失去了连贯性。她害怕那目光，但同时又莫名其妙地喜欢这样被人盯着瞧。她的教养在向她发出警告：有危险，要出错，但那是一种微妙、神秘和诱人的错误。她的本能却吹响了传遍她全身的号角，怂恿她越过等级、身份和利益去接近这个来自于另一世界的旅人；接近这个手上带着伤、脖子上因不习惯穿硬领衣服而被磨出一道红痕的粗鲁小伙子；接近这个显而易见在粗俗的生活中沾染了满身污点的年轻人。她喜欢洁净，这种天性使她萌生了厌恶感；可她是女人，而且刚刚开始懂得女性的矛盾心理。

“正如我所说——我刚才说什么来着？”她突然收住话头，想到了自己如此困窘，不由得大笑起来。

“你刚才说，斯温伯恩不能成为伟大的诗人，因为——哦，你刚才就说到这里，小姐。”他提醒道。与此同时，他似乎突然产生了一种渴望，随着她的笑声，一股股微微的电流在他的脊梁骨爬上爬下，给他以甜美的感觉。他心想，那笑声宛若叮当的银铃声，顿时把他带到了一个遥远的地方；他坐在那儿的粉红色樱花下，吸着烟卷倾听尖顶塔上传来的钟声，那钟声召唤着足蹬草鞋的信徒们去做礼拜。

“不错，谢谢你，”她说，“斯温伯恩之所以不能成为伟大的诗人，是因为他有些粗俗，他的许多诗作根本就不值得一读。真正伟大的诗人所写的每一行诗都包含着美好的真理，能唤起人性中一切崇高和圣洁的品质。伟大的诗作，每删掉一行，世界就蒙受一份损失。”

“我只看了几句，还以为他了不起呢，”他迟疑地说，“没想到他竟然是一个——一个卑鄙的人。我猜想，他在别的诗作中就原形毕露了。”

“你刚才看过的那本书中就有不少诗句可以删掉。”她说，语气郑重、坚决和武断。

“我八成是把那些诗句漏掉了。”他声称，“我所读到的都是真正的地道诗，都是闪闪发光的诗句，犹如太阳或探照灯，把我的心里照得亮堂堂。我的感受就是如此，不过，我想我对诗歌是缺乏鉴赏力的，小姐。”

他有气无力地住了口。他被弄糊涂了，痛苦地感觉到自己说话有些语无伦次。他觉得自己刚才读过的作品蕴含着伟大和辉煌的生命力，然而他的话却说得很不恰当。他无法表达内心的感受。他暗自把自己比作一个水手，在一条陌生的船上，于茫茫的黑夜里，在不熟悉的活动桅杆间摸索。他心想，现在完全得靠自己了解这个新的世界。以前，他无论想掌握任何事情，都一定能称心如意。而现在，他必须设法学会表达心里的思想，让她能够听得懂。她在他心目中所占的位置愈来愈大。

“再谈谈朗费罗[3]吧——”她说道。

“嗨，我读过他的作品，”他冲动地插话说，急于展示和卖弄他那一星半点的书本知识，想让她知道他不完全是一个草包，“如《赞美生活》、《精益求精》，还有……哦，我想就是这些。”

她嫣然一笑，点了点头。不知怎么，他觉得她的笑隐含着宽容，而且是怜悯性的宽容，他真是太愚蠢了。不该不懂装懂。朗费罗那伙计撰写的诗集恐怕多得数不胜数。

“请原谅我这么打岔，小姐。其实，我对这类事情了解不多。这不是我的专长，不过我一定会把它变为我的专长。”

他的话让人听起来像是恫吓。他声音果断，两只眼睛里燃烧着火焰，脸上的线条绷得紧紧的。她觉得他的下巴都扭得变了形，给人以好斗和咄咄逼人的印象。他的体内迸发出强烈的男子气质，如海浪般冲击着她。

“我认为你能够做得到——把它变为你的专长，”她笑了笑说，“因为你非常强壮。”

她的目光在他肌肉发达的脖子上逗留了一会儿。他的脖子肉筋隆起，粗得和公牛脖子一样，被太阳晒成了紫铜色，溢涌出旺盛的精力和强健的力量。尽管他红着脸傻坐在那儿，一副没出息的样子，但她又一次感到自己被吸引了过去。此时，她产生了一个荒唐的念头，这使她大为吃惊。在她看来，如果她把两手放在这脖子上，脖子里蕴含的力量和精力便会一股脑儿流入她的体内。她被这个念头吓坏了。这念头似乎揭示出：她的本性里有一种意想不到的堕落品质。再说，力量对她意味着粗俗和野蛮。她理想中的男性美历来都是纤弱和文雅的美。可是，这个念头怎么也摆脱不掉。她感到困惑不解的是，自己竟然渴望把手放在那太阳晒黑的脖子上。其实，她根本算不上健壮，她的肉体和精神需要的就是力量，可她当时不明白这一点。她只知道，从来没有一个男人像这个人一样对她产生这么大的作用，他的言谈不合文法，时时叫她吃惊。

“我并非一个弱不禁风的病人，”他说，“遇到难解的问题，就是生铜烂铁我也消化得了。可这次我却患了消化不良症，你说的话我大半都消化不了。你知道，我从未受过这方面的训练。我喜欢看书和读诗，一有空就阅读，但从来没有像你那样思考过问题。因此，我讲不出个所以然来。我就像一个航海者漂流在陌生的海域，既无航海图也无罗盘。我想弄清自己的方位，也许你可以为我指点迷津。你所谈到的这些，都是从哪儿学来的？”

“我想是从学校以及通过自修学来的。”她回答道。

“我小时候也上过学呀。”他反驳说。

“不错，可我指的是中学、讲座和大学。”

“你上过大学？”他问道，丝毫不掩饰自己诧异的心情。他觉得他们之间的距离更加遥远，起码又远了一百万英里。

“我现在正念大学，修的是专科英语。”

他不知道什么叫“专科英语”，但在心里记下了这一点空白，随后又继续进行谈话。

“得念多长时间的书，我才能够上大学？”他问道。

看到他有这样的求知欲，她笑了笑以示鼓励，然后说道：“这要取决于你已经念了多长时间的书。你上过中学吗？不用说，你没上过。那么，你小学毕业了吗？”

“我离开校门的时候，还差两年毕业，”他回答道，“但我上学的时候，学习成绩一直都是优秀。”

一转眼，他就生起自己的气来，怪自己不该自我吹嘘，于是便狂烈地牢牢抓住椅子扶手，把每个指尖都弄得发痛。此刻，他发现一位妇女走进房间来。只见姑娘离开座椅，脚步轻盈地迎了上去。两人相互吻了一下，接着便用胳膊勾着对方的腰，朝他走过来。他心想，来人一定是姑娘的母亲，她身材细长，一头金发，显得端庄美丽。她的服饰在他看来十分适合于这样的人家，优美的线条令他觉得赏心悦目。她以及她的装束，使他想起戏台上的女人。随后，他回忆起往事来——他见过这等高贵的女士穿着这等华美的服装步入伦敦剧院看戏，而站在一旁观看的他却被警察推入遮篷外的雨幕之中。接着，他的思绪又飞向了横滨的大饭店，他站在人行道上，曾看到过华贵的夫人小姐出入于饭店。随即，横滨市区和港口化为一千幅画面，一幕幕开始从他的眼前闪过。但由于当下有紧急事情要办，他就不得不把记忆中千变万化的情景迅速推至一旁。他知道自己必须站起来等待人介绍，于是便艰难地挣扎起身来。他伫立在那儿，裤子的膝盖处鼓起两个大包，可笑地垂着两条臂膀，绷紧面孔准备迎接即将来到的考验。

[1]　19世纪英国著名诗人，作品为广大青年所喜爱。

[2]　墨西哥东南部一海港。

[3]　19世纪美国著名诗人。

第二章

走进餐厅的一路，像是经历了一场噩梦。他忽而停步，忽而绊跌，忽而猛冲，忽而蹒跚，有时似乎寸步难行。不过，他最后还是抵达了目的地，而且在她身旁坐了下来。一排排的刀叉充满了不可知的危机，吓得他胆战心惊。他出神地望着这些刀叉，后来刀叉发出的耀眼光芒转变成一种背景，衬托出一幅幅轮船上的场面——他和伙伴们坐在一起，用出鞘的刀子和手指头吃腌制的牛肉，或者用烂铁匙从小锅里舀稠稠的豌豆汤喝。他鼻子里闻到的是牛肉发腐的臭味，耳朵里听到的是船板的吱嘎声、舱壁的呻吟以及吃东西的人响亮的咀嚼声。他望着伙伴们吃东西时的样子，觉得他们和猪相差无几。如今到了这里，他可得当心点，千万别弄出声响，时时都得留意才对。

他把餐桌旁的人扫视了一圈，看到对面坐的是阿瑟以及阿瑟的弟弟诺曼。他们是她的亲弟弟，他提醒自己，于是心里对他们产生了一股温情。这个家里的人是多么相亲相爱啊！他的脑海里闪现出她母亲的形象，闪现出母女俩相互亲吻并相互挽着对方的胳膊向他走来的情景。在他的生活圈子里，父母和子女之间缺乏这种亲昵的表现。这说明，上流社会的人过的是一种崇高的生活。而在这个上流社会的小小一隅，他所看到的最美好的东西就是这种爱。他为这种爱深受感动，心里产生了亲切的共鸣。他一生都渴望得到爱，因为对爱的追求是他的天性，是他生活中一个必不可少的部分。可是他始终未能获得爱，从而逐渐变得冷酷和麻木。他以前不知道自己需要爱，现在也不知道。他只是看到了爱的表露，并为之兴奋，觉得爱是美好的、崇高的和圣洁的。

令他感到高兴的是，摩斯先生不在座。他跟阿瑟虽说已经有点熟了，可是和她、她的母亲以及她的弟弟诺曼交往绝非轻而易举之事。他觉得，做父亲的要是也在场，一定会叫他难以招架。他认为，自己一辈子都没这般劳累过，连最繁重的工作与这相比也只能算是儿戏。一下子要干这许多自己所不习惯的事情，累得他心力交瘁，额头上沁出细细的汗珠，衬衣都被汗水湿透了。以前他可从未这样吃过饭：得使用陌生的餐具，得偷眼四瞧，学着别人的样做每一桩新的事情，得接受潮水般涌来的种种印象，还得在心里对这些印象进行注释和分类；他感受到自己对她产生了一种欲望，而这种欲望搅得他心神不宁，令他迟钝和痛苦；他觉得自己渴望进入她的生活圈子，并耽于沉思，朦朦胧胧制定了接近她的计划，可他得不时地敦促自己不要去胡思乱想。还有，当他偷眼看对面的诺曼或其他人，想弄清在哪种情况下使用何种刀或叉时，他会记住对方的相貌特征，不由自主地对他们进行评估，以此推断他们是哪一类人——这一切都和她联系在一起。另外，他还得讲话，倾听别人对他说的话以及大家的言谈，还得在必要时回答提问，时时约束他那个惯于信口开河的舌头。乱中加乱的是那个不断对他造成威胁的仆人，此人无声无息地出现在他的身旁，活似提出谜语和难题，要人马上解答的可怕的司芬克斯[1]。这顿晚餐从头到尾他总是想到洗指盆，搅得他心烦意乱。他的思绪支离破碎，但持续不断，有好几十次他都在思量着洗指盆何时会端上来以及它们是什么样子。他听人说起过这种东西，现在迟早不出几分钟他就可以亲眼看到，可以和这些高贵的人坐在一起，观看他们洗指——啊，他自己也要用用那洗指盆。而最为重要的是：在这些人面前，应该怎样表现自己，这个问题埋藏在他的心底，但总是浮现在他的脑海里。自己应该采取什么样的态度呢？为此他绞尽脑汁、苦思冥想。怯懦的想法是装模作样，扮演一个戏中人物；而更怯懦的想法是：这样做会一败涂地，因为他的天性与这样的行为格格不入，结果只能见笑于人。

晚餐的前一半时间，他苦苦琢磨应采取什么样的态度，所以沉默寡言。谁料想他的沉默却驳斥了阿瑟在前一天所说的话——她的这位弟弟曾宣布要把一个野蛮人带回家吃饭，并让家里人不必惊慌，因为他们会发现这位野蛮人相当风趣。马丁·伊登毫无察觉，压根没想到她弟弟会如此忘恩负义——要知道，正是由于他帮忙，这位弟弟才得以摆脱一场令人不快的争斗。他就是这样坐在餐桌旁，为自己的格格不入感到不安，同时又对周围发生的一切感到心醉神迷。他生平第一次意识到，吃饭的作用不仅仅局限于实用的目的。他不知自己都吃了些什么，反正全是食物。在这张餐桌旁，吃是一种艺术活动，他对美的热爱在此处得到了满足。而且，吃饭也是精神活动，使他的心里难以平静。他听到了自己所不懂的话以及在书本上才能看得到的话，他以前认识的男男女女都愚昧无知，讲不出这样的话来。他听到这些话从这个了不起的家庭——她的家庭成员的口里随随便便地讲出来，高兴得心花怒放。书本里描绘的传奇故事、美，以及充满生气的场面，在此处变成了现实。他欣喜若狂——这是一种少有的心情，是一个人看到自己的梦步出幻想的裂缝而转变成现实时所产生的心情。

他从未遇到过如此崇高的生活气氛，于是退居幕后，默默地聆听、观察和欣赏，答话时只使用单音节词，对她说“是，小姐”或“不，小姐”，对她母亲说“是，夫人”或“不，夫人”。他克制住冲动，没有按船上训练的那一套，对她的弟弟们说“是，先生”或“不，先生”。他觉得这样说话不得体，等于承认自己低人一等——如欲赢得她的芳心，就绝对不能这样做。再说，这也是他的自尊心所不允许的。他曾在心里喊叫过一句：“上帝啊，我和他们是同样的人，如果他们的确懂得一些我不懂的东西，那么，我也有一些东西可以教给他们！”一转眼的工夫，她或她的母亲叫他一声“伊登先生”，他就会把他那咄咄逼人的自尊抛到九霄云外，心里感到乐悠悠、暖烘烘。他是一个文明人，事情原来就是如此，正和自己在书本上看到的人物们坐在一起共进晚餐。他本人也是书中的人物，游历于书本的字里行间。

他的形象与阿瑟的描绘是不相符的，因为他不是野蛮人，倒像一只温顺的小羊。但与此同时，他正在挖空心思寻找一条行动的方案。他不是温顺的小羊，他那争强好胜的个性绝不容许他充当配角。只有在万不得已的情况下，他才开口讲话，而他的话语和他来餐厅时的步态一样，忽而急促，忽而停顿。他在自己杂乱的词汇库里搜索字眼——有些词他明知很恰当，可又害怕发不准音，于是便斟酌再三；有些词怕别人听不懂，或者过于粗俗、刺耳，他便舍弃不用。同时，他始终有这样一种感觉：这般斟词酌句只会把他变成一个呆子，使他无法表达内心的感受。再说，他喜欢无拘无束，这就跟条条框框起了摩擦，情况非常类似他的脖子和硬邦邦的浆领所起的摩擦。而且，他敢肯定，这样的做法不能持久。他天生富于思想和情感，心里骚动和冲撞着创造精神。心中的想法和感触在经历分娩的痛苦，急于寻找表达的方式，这时他很快会失去控制，忘掉自我，忘掉自己身在何处，于是，那些古老的词语——他所熟悉的语言工具，便悄然溜出口来。

一次，那个缠在他身边、给他带来干扰的仆人递过来一些东西，他拒绝不要，便简短而重重地说了声：“波奥！”

席上的人一下子都支棱起耳朵，期待着解释。仆人暗自得意，而他却羞愧得无地自容。不过，他很快就稳定住了情绪。

“这是卡拿加[2]语，意思是‘吃完了’，”他解释道，“就那么自然而然说了出来。这个单词的拼法是P-a-u。”

他注意到她在以好奇和疑问的目光紧紧盯着他的手，而他解释得正带劲，于是便又说道：

“前不久我在一艘太平洋邮轮上工作，沿海岸线行驶。轮船误了点，在普吉特海峡那一带的口岸上，我们拼命地干活，往船上装货——那是些杂货，也许你知道这是什么意思。结果，手上被碰掉了点皮。”

“哦，我不是指这个。”她连忙解释说，“根据你的身材，你的手似乎显得太小了些。”

他觉得脸上发烧，认为她的话揭出了他的又一个缺陷。

“是的，”他自卑地说，“这双手是不够大，经不起磨炼。我的胳膊和肩胛健壮有力，撞起人来像骡子一样有劲，可是用拳头揍人家的腭骨，手也会被弄破的。”

他对自己的这一席话并不满意，不由恼恨起自己来。他放松了对舌头的控制，讲出一些难登大雅之堂的事情来。

“你和阿瑟素不相识，然而却那样帮助他，真是见义勇为啊！”她看出他有些狼狈，但不知是什么原因，于是便非常体贴地说。

他体会到了她的好意，心里油然升起一股温暖的感激之情，也就忘掉了自己信口开河的舌头所带来的苦恼。

“那根本算不了什么，”他说，“任何人都会那样做的。那几个流氓是在找麻烦，因为阿瑟并没有惹他们。他们推搡他，而我也推搡他们，并打了他们几拳头。我手上的皮掉了一些，但那帮家伙的牙齿却让我打掉了几颗。不管怎样，我不能放过他们。当我看到——”

他讲到半截，却觉得自己过于庸俗，实在不配和她相处，于是便停了下来，嘴巴还张得大大的。阿瑟接过话头，把自己在渡轮上和那帮喝醉了酒的流氓如何发生冲突，以及马丁·伊登如何冲上前搭救他的经过又讲了一遍（这件事他已讲了足有二十遍）。这时的马丁紧皱眉头，思量着自己简直是当众出丑，同时更加绞尽脑汁地考虑起在这些人面前应该有怎样的行为和举止。当然，截至目前他做得并不成功。他自认为不属于他们的阶层，讲不了他们的语言，而且伪装不了他们的同类。弄虚作假是会露馅的，再说，这也不符合于他的天性。他心里根本容不下欺骗和诡计。不管发生什么样的情况，他都必须保持本质。现在还讲不了他们的那种话，但最终他一定能学会，这就是他的决心。可此时此刻，他得讲话，得讲自己的话，当然措辞要缓和些，好让他们听得懂，同时不至于使他们过分吃惊。另外，对不熟悉的事情他绝不会硬说自己熟悉，甚至连默认都不会。根据这项决定，待那兄弟俩谈起大学经、三番五次提到“三角”这个名词的时候，马丁·伊登便问道：

“‘三角’是什么？”

“即三角学，”诺曼说，“是一门高等数理学。”

“什么叫数理学？”这第二句提问不知怎么使大伙儿都笑起诺曼来。

“即数学、算术。”诺曼说。

马丁·伊登点了点头。他瞥到了一眼显然是无边无际的知识领域。他所看到的都是可以摸到的实物。在他非凡的眼光里，抽象的概念拥有具体的形态。他的大脑可以点石成金，把三角学、数学以及它们所代表的整个知识领域转变成辽阔的景色。于是，他看到了绿叶和林间通道，一景一物都散发着柔和的光泽，或闪烁出耀眼的光芒。远处的紫色雾霭遮住了视线，使一切都显得模模糊糊，可他知道，就在那片紫色的雾霭之后有着未知数和浪漫的故事，这些在吸引和诱惑着他。对他来说，这就宛若美酒一般。他要去冒险，靠头脑和双手干一番事业，去征服一个世界——他的意识深处涌出一个念头：征服和赢得这个坐在他身旁的白皙的百合仙女。

这幅朦胧的幻景由于阿瑟的插话破碎了，随即便消失了。阿瑟整整一个晚上都在处心积虑地想使他露出野蛮人的本质。马丁·伊登记起刚做的决定，第一次恢复了自我。起初还是左思右想，但很快便陶醉于畅所欲言的喜悦之中，把他的生活经历一五一十展现在周围的人眼前。当走私船翠鸟号被缉私艇扣住时，他是船上的一名水手，目睹了所发生的事情，因而可以把自己看到的讲给他们听，他给他们描绘了汹涌澎湃的大海，描绘了海上的人们及船只。他把自己观察事物的能力赋予对方，使他们能够以他的眼光看待他目睹过的情景。他采用艺术家的手法从大量的素材中筛选出细节，描绘出一幅幅五光十色的生活画面，而且讲得活灵活现，以粗犷的语言、热情和力量感染听众，令他们随他一道沉浮。有时，他的生动叙述以及他的言辞会叫他们震惊，但暴烈的场面之后旋踵而至的往往是一种美感，悲剧之中总是穿插着幽默，穿插着他对水手们离奇古怪心理活动的形容。

当他侃侃而谈时，姑娘向他投来惊诧的目光。他的激情使她感到温暖。她不由想到，她以前的岁月都是在冰冷中度过的。她渴望紧偎这个熊熊烈火般的男子，这个像火山口一样喷发出力量、野性和勃勃生气的男子。她觉得她必须向他靠拢，费了很大的劲才克制住了自己。同时，她也感受到一阵相反的冲动，想躲开他。他的双手伤痕累累，皮肤里深嵌着辛勤劳作的生活留下的斑斑污垢，肌肉高高隆起，这些都激起了她反感的心理。他的粗野吓坏了她，他每一句粗野的话都是对她耳朵的侮辱，每一个粗野的生活片断都是对她灵魂的亵渎。可他一次又一次地吸引着她，使她觉得他肯定掌握着控制她的邪恶的力量。她头脑中根深蒂固的观念正在全面瓦解。他的传奇经历和冒险生涯在冲击着传统的惯例。他把冒险视为家常便饭，而且动不动就开怀大笑，这样看来，生活不再是严肃认真的事情，不再需要自我克制，而变成了一件任你玩来玩去的玩具，待你轻轻松松玩够了、娱乐够了，可以随随便便将它扔到一边去。“因此，尽情玩吧！”这种声音在她的心里鸣响，“只要有这个愿望，就靠上前去，把双手放在他的脖子上！”这种轻率的念头一经出现，她真想大喊出声，她考虑到了自己清白的生活和教养，权衡了她和他在地位上的悬殊，可这些都无济于事。她四周瞧瞧，发现大伙儿都在着了迷似的望着他；要不是看到母亲的目光中含着恐惧，她一定会绝望的。不错，那是一种陶醉般的恐惧，但不管怎么说也是一种恐惧。这个来自于黑暗的外部世界的男人是个恶人。母亲看出了这一点，而且绝不会看错。平时她事事都依着母亲，这一次她也相信母亲的判断。于是，他的激情对她不再散发出暖意，而她对他也不再感到那般胆战心惊。

后来，她坐到钢琴前为他弹奏，同时也是对他的一种蔑视，因为她有个朦胧的意图，想以此强调他们之间横着一条不可逾越的鸿沟。她弹奏的乐曲犹如当头狠狠一棒，打得他头晕目眩，栽倒在地，但同时他又为之感到兴奋，他敬畏地凝视着她，他心里的鸿沟和她心里的一样，变得愈来愈宽，而他逾越这道鸿沟的野心却以更快的速度膨胀。他过于敏感，情感过于复杂，不可能望着一条鸿沟整晚上呆坐在那里，特别是在有音乐的时候。他对音乐有着异乎寻常的感受力。音乐犹如烈性酒一般，使他热血沸腾，感情奔放；音乐又似麻醉剂，操纵着他的想象，令其腾云驾雾，直刺青天。它驱散了污秽的现实，把美感和浪漫的想象注入他的心房，给他的思想插上飞翔的翅膀。他听不懂她弹奏的乐曲，因为那曲调与他以前在舞厅里听到的呼呼响的钢琴声及呜啦呜啦的铜管乐迥然有异。然而，他在书本上看到过一星半点有关于这种音乐的知识，于是主要靠着一种信念去领会她的弹奏。起初，他耐心期待着轻松活泼、朴素明快的旋律，可过不了多久，这种旋律便会中止，使他陷入迷惘之中。一旦他抓住旋律的起伏，感到心情激动，任想象展翅高飞之时，这种旋律总会在一阵听不懂的杂乱无章的声音中消失，把他的想象和内心的情感抛回到大地上。

他一度闪出一个念头，认为这是在有意嘲弄他。他觉得她怀有抵触情绪，于是便努力分析她的双手按琴键时所表达的含义。后来，他却觉得自己的想法既卑鄙又荒唐，便打消了这种念头，更加陶醉于音乐之中，重新沉湎于刚才的那种欢快的心境。他的双脚脱离了大地，血肉之躯化为灵气，眼前和身后都闪耀着灿烂的光芒；随即，面前的场景骤然消失，他开始游历于一个对他说来十分亲切的世界。他所看到的是梦幻般的壮丽景色，熟悉的事物和陌生的事物交融在一起。他来到阳光普照的奇特港埠，混身于闻所未闻的野蛮人中间在市场上溜达。香料岛的香味扑鼻而来，他航海时曾在温暖无风的夜晚嗅到过这种香味；或者，他迎着东南贸易风行驶，在热带海域度过了一个又一个漫长的日子，身后碧绿色的海洋上棕榈丛生的珊瑚岛逐渐隐去，而前方的碧绿色大海上又涌现出座座长满了棕榈树的珊瑚小岛。一幕幕情景飞快地交替闪现。他忽儿骑着野马，疾驰在具有神话色彩的五彩沙漠[3]上，忽而透过颤抖的热浪垂首俯视白色坟墓般的死亡之谷[4]；或者在结冰的海洋上划船，那儿耸立着巨大的冰山群，于阳光下闪闪发光。他躺在珊瑚海滩上，那儿的椰子林一直延伸至柔声细语的海浪跟前。一艘古老船只的残骸在熊熊燃烧，发出蓝色的火焰，火光中有一群人在跳草裙舞，而伴唱的歌手却和着叮咚的四弦琴和隆隆的锣鼓声高唱野蛮的情歌。那是一个充满诗情画意的热带的夜晚。一座火山口于星光映衬下呈现出黑色的轮廓，组成了背景，头顶上飘浮着一弯苍白的新月，南十字星座[5]低悬在天边，发出燃烧的光焰。

他犹如一架竖琴，而他所体验和感受到的全部生活则是琴弦；阵阵乐声宛如清风，拨动着琴弦，带来回忆和梦幻。他不仅仅是在感觉。他的感觉已经有了具体的形式、色彩和光芒，把他想到的景物以神奇和升华的方式展现出来。过去、现在和未来交织在一起；他在这个温暖而辽阔的世界上不断地闯荡，历经艰险，屡建功勋，终于来到了她身旁——啊，他赢得了她的青睐，用胳膊搂着她，带她一道在他的心灵王国里飞翔。

她侧首望了望，从他的脸上看出了几分他的心思。那张面孔改变了形状，闪亮的大眼睛穿破声音帷幕，看到幕后有跳跃、搏动的生活以及巨大的精神幻影。她不由吃了一惊。那个野蛮和笨手笨脚的粗人不见了。不合体的衣服、伤痕累累的手以及太阳晒黑的面孔虽然犹在，但这些却像是监狱里的铁栅栏，透过栅栏她看见一个伟大的灵魂在张望，那个灵魂寡言少语，因为它拙嘴笨舌，说不出话来。这仅仅是短瞬间的一瞥，随即她又看到了那个粗人，于是不由为自己的胡思乱想哑然失笑。不过，那短暂的一瞥却留下了久久不散的印象。待他起身告辞，跌跌绊绊朝外走时，她把斯温伯恩的那册诗集借给了他，另外还借给他一本勃朗宁[6]的书——她所上的英语课程正在研究勃朗宁的作品。他看上去活像一个小男孩，红着脸站在那里，结结巴巴地向她道谢。她心里油然涌起一股母性的怜悯之情，忘掉了那个粗人和那个被囚禁的灵魂，忘掉了那个以男子气十足的目光凝视着她，既给她带来喜悦又使她感到恐惧的男人。她眼前所看到的只是一个小男孩。这孩子在跟她握手，手上的老茧像是豆蔻擦子，折磨着她的皮肤，口里还在语无伦次地说着：

“这是我一生中最伟大的时刻。你知道，我不习惯这里的……”他不知所措地望了望四周，“……不习惯这里的人和房子。一切对我都是新奇的，叫我喜欢。”

“希望你下次再来。”当他跟她的弟弟们道晚安时，她这样说道。他戴上帽子，深一脚浅一脚地、狼狈地出了大门，接着就不见了。“喂，你觉得他怎么样？”阿瑟问。

“他非常有意思，像是一缕新鲜的空气，”她说，“他有多大啦？”

“二十——快满二十一啦，今天下午我才问过他，我当时没想到他会这么年轻。”

她跟弟弟们亲吻道晚安时，心里则暗忖，我比他大三岁。

[1]　希腊神话中的狮身人面怪兽，给路人出谜语，要求解答。凡是答不上来的，就被它杀掉。

[2]　夏威夷群岛上的土著人。

[3]　在著名的大峡谷以东，沙土呈红、白、紫、棕等色，故得名。

[4]　加州东部一盆地，气温颇高，寸草不生。

[5]　由四颗明星组成，在南半球可以看得见。

[6]　19世纪英国著名诗人。

第三章

马丁·伊登走下台阶，把手插进上衣口袋，掏出一片棕色卷烟纸和一撮墨西哥烟草，然后熟练地卷了一支纸烟。他将第一口烟深深吸入肺部，再徐徐吐出。“上帝保佑！”他出声地说道，声音里带着敬畏和惊异的成分。“上帝保佑！”他又说了一遍。这还不算完，他最后又咕哝了一句：“上帝保佑！”接着，他伸手把领子从衬衫上撕下来，塞进衣袋里。天空中飘着冷冰冰的蒙蒙细雨，但他摘下帽子，光着脑袋淋雨，还解开背心上的扣子，摇摇晃晃地走着，一副满不在乎的样子。他沉浸在狂喜之中，只迷迷糊糊觉得天在下雨，心里做着一个一个的美梦，构想着刚才发生过的情景。

他终于遇上了这个女人——他不喜欢老去想女人，所以很少想到这样的女性，但他隐约觉得自己总有一天会碰上。吃饭时，他就坐在她的身旁。他曾感觉到自己握住了她的手，曾望过她的那双眼睛，看到了一颗美丽的灵魂——而充当灵魂窗口的眼睛以及表达和体现灵魂的肉体也是同样的美丽。他没有把她的肉体视为肉体——这是一种新鲜的思维，因为对于以前结识的女人，他只是把她们看作一具具肉体。她的肉体则有所不同。在他的心目中，她的血肉之躯不再是肉体，因为肉体会有种种疾病和弱点。她的肉体不仅仅是灵魂的外装，也是灵魂的延伸，是她那神圣本质的纯洁和奇妙的结晶。这种关于神圣性的感觉吓了他一跳。他从梦境中惊醒，开始冷静地思考。以前他未受过这方面的影响，哪怕是片言只语或任何启迪和暗示他都没往心上放过。他一直都不相信有什么神圣性，也不信仰宗教。他曾经毫无恶意地嘲笑过牧师以及他们关于灵魂不朽性的说教。他认为根本就没有什么来世，生命只存在于现世，而后便是永恒的黑暗。然而，他在她的眼里却看到了灵魂——永不消亡的不朽的灵魂。在他以前结识的人当中，无论是男是女，没有一个人给过他关于这种不朽性的启示，而她却给了他。她向他投来目光的第一个瞬间，就同时把这一点悄然无声地告诉了他。他走着路，眼前浮现出了她的面容——白皙、严肃、甜美、敏感，挂着一丝只有灵魂才具有的怜悯和温柔的微笑，其纯洁性是他以前做梦都难以想到的。她的纯洁对他犹如当头棒喝，使他大吃一惊。他辨得清善恶，但纯洁作为人生的一种美德，却从没有进入他的脑海。而现在从她身上，他看到纯洁是善良和清白的最高境界，二者的总和便构成了永恒的生命。

顿然，他野心勃发，企图赢得永恒的生命。他连为她打水都不配——这一点他很清楚；今晚他之所以能够见到她、接近她以及跟她交谈，全靠的是神奇的命运和美妙的侥幸。事情是出自于偶然，不包含有人为的因素。他不配交这样的好运。论思想本质，他是诚实的。他谦卑和恭顺，怯生生的，打心眼里瞧不起自己，罪人们到忏悔室去的时候就是怀着他这样的心情。他也是罪人。不同的是，那些唯唯诺诺、恭恭敬敬的罪人在忏悔室看到的是未来高尚生活的美景，而他看到的则是占有她后他将要抵达的辉煌境界。可是，这种对她的占有是虚无缥缈的，完全不同于他以前的占有。野心鼓起疯狂的翅膀，直冲九霄；他看到自己跟她一道攀登高峰，一道思考问题，一道追求美妙和高尚的理想。这就是他梦寐以求的那种灵魂的占有，纯净得不夹杂丝毫粗俗的成分，属于一种他无法具体想象的无拘无束的精神友谊。他没有苦思冥想，其实他压根就没动脑筋去想。感情代替了理智；他浑身颤抖，产生了一种前所未有过的激动情绪，陶醉地漂浮在情感的海洋上，那里，感情得到升华和神圣化，超越了生命的顶点。

他步履蹒跚，活像个醉汉，口里狂热地一个劲低声喊：“上帝保佑！上帝保佑！”

街拐角有个警察怀疑地打量着他，注意到了他那一摇一晃的水手步态。

“怎么喝成了这样？”警察问。

马丁·伊登又回到了现实中来。他好比流动的有机体，能够迅速地适应环境，不管是凹角还是缝隙都能够流得进和充得满。听到警察的吆喝，他立刻恢复了平时的样子，清楚了是怎么回事。

“这很奇怪，是吗？”他哈哈笑了声说，“我没留意到自己竟然把这话讲出了声。”

“你还会喝出声呢。”警察断言道。

“不，这倒不会。劳驾，借个火，我要搭辆车回家去。”

他点着烟。道过晚安，然后继续朝前走去。“你说这事让人糊涂不？”他低声叫了起来，“那警察还以为我喝醉了呢。”他暗自一笑，不由乱想起来，“我想我是真的醉了，”他又说，“没料到一个女人的脸蛋竟能让人如醉如痴。”

在电报大街，他搭上了一辆开往伯克利的电车。车上挤满了年轻人，他们唱着歌，而且一遍又一遍喊着大学啦啦队的口号。他好奇地打量起他们来。这些年轻人都是大学生，和她上的是同一所学校，社会地位与她相等，可以同她结识，只要愿意，每天都可以见到她。他不理解，这些人为什么晚上不愿意待在她身旁，崇拜和爱慕地围她而坐，和她一起聊天，而是自己跑出来寻欢作乐。他的大脑不停地胡思乱想。他注意到有个小伙子眯缝着眼、耷拉着嘴唇，便断定他是个恶人。那家伙要是到船上干活，肯定会行窃、发牢骚和搬弄是非。而他马丁·伊登却比那家伙强。这一念头使他感到振奋，似乎把他和她之间的距离缩短了。他开始将自己和那群学生作比较。他觉得自己身体强健、肌肉发达，坚信在体格上他要胜那些学生一筹。但一想到学生们的脑袋瓜里装着知识，能够和她有共同语言，他就泄了气。他在心里情绪激动地问：一个人的头脑是派什么用场呢？他们干的事情，他也会干。他们从书本上了解生活的时候，他则在忙于生活。和他们一样，他的脑袋瓜里也装满了知识，只不过他的知识属于另一种类罢了。他们当中有多少人会打绳结，有多少人会操纵舵轮或充当瞭望员呢？他的一生以一幅幅惊心动魄、英勇壮烈、艰苦卓绝和辛勤劳作的画面展现在他眼前。他仍记得自己在学习生活的过程中所遇到的困难以及所遭受的失败。起码，在这方面他是强者。总有一天，那些大学生也得置身于生活，像他一样经受磨炼。好啊！待他们忙于生活时，他可以从书本上了解生活的另一侧面。

电车穿过奥克兰和伯克利之间那片疏落散布的居民住房时，他留意寻找一幢熟悉的二层楼房，楼房的门面上挂着一块招眼的牌记：希金波森零售店。马丁·伊登就是在这个角落下了车。他抬头先把那块牌记瞅了一会儿，因为牌记上的字对他有更深的含义，似乎有一个卑鄙、自私和狡诈的人从那些字眼里跳了出来。伯纳德·希金波森娶了他的姐姐，所以他对这个人非常了解。他用钥匙打开前门，爬到了二楼。他的姐夫住在这一层，而楼下开着食物杂货店，空气中都弥漫着蔬菜腐烂的气味。为数众多的外甥和外甥女，不知是哪个把一辆童车丢到了过道里，使他在摸路时绊了一跤，“砰”的一声撞到了一扇门上。“这个守财奴，”他心想，“真是吝啬到家啦，连破费两分钱点盏煤气灯都不肯，非得把房客的脖子摔断不可。”

他摸到门把手，推门走进一间亮着灯的屋子，看到姐姐和伯纳德·希金波森正坐在那里。姐姐在为他补裤子，而姐夫把骨瘦如柴的身体横在两把椅子上，两只脚穿着破旧的便鞋，悬在第二把椅子的边沿上。他正在看报，此时从报纸上端露出他那双阴森、奸诈和咄咄逼人的眼睛，瞧了瞧马丁。马丁·伊登一看到他，总会产生一种厌恶的感觉。他不理解姐姐究竟看上了这个人的哪一点。他觉得这个人简直是条害虫，总是让人忍不住想踩死他。“总有一天，我会把他的脸揍得稀巴烂。”他常用这样的话安慰自己，以容忍这个人的存在。那双黄鼠狼似的恶毒的眼睛，此时正用抱怨的目光观望着他。

“有话就讲吧。”马丁说。

“那扇门是上个星期才漆的，”希金波森先生半埋怨半威吓地说，“工会规定的工钱你是知道的，所以应该小心点才是。”

马丁原想还嘴，可又觉得那样只会白费口舌。他的目光越过这个狰狞、卑鄙的人，落在了挂在墙上的一幅五彩石印画上。他一直都很喜欢这幅画，然而此刻却像是第一次见到似的，心里感到惊奇。他觉得这幅画庸俗不堪，和这幢房屋里所有其他的东西一样。他又回想起自己刚离开的那户人家，先想到的是那些油画，接着便想到了她，想到她同他握手告别是怎样用柔媚动人的目光注视着他。他忘掉了自己身处何地，忘掉了伯纳德·希金波森的存在，直至听到后者的吆喝声。

“见到鬼了吧？”对方厉声问。

马丁醒过神来，望了望那双含着轻蔑、恶毒和怯懦的贼亮的小眼睛，脑海里突然像映电影一样浮现出这个人在楼下卖东西时的情形——还是这双眼睛，然而却带着谄媚、自满、世故和巴结人的神情。

“不错，我的确见到了一个鬼，”马丁答道，“再见吧。晚安，葛特露。”

他挪步朝外走时，被那肮脏的地毯上裂开的一条缝绊了一下。

“别把门关得山响。”希金波森先生警告他说。

他觉得血管里的血直朝上冲，但他还是克制住了自己，随手轻轻地带上了门。

希金波森乐滋滋地瞅了瞅自己的妻子。

“他喝酒了。”他压低嗓门，嘶哑着声音说，“我告诉过你，他会喝醉的。”

她无奈地点了点头。

“他的眼睛闪着亮光”，她承认说，“出去时他穿的是硬领衬衫，回来却不见了领子。不过，他也可能只喝了一两杯。”

“他站都站不稳了，”她丈夫宣称，“他走路时我瞧着呢，一跌一绊的。你自个儿也听到了，他在过道里差点摔跟头。”

“我想那是让爱丽丝的车子绊了一下，”她说，“黑灯瞎火的，他一时看不清。”

希金波森先生怒火冲胸，提高了嗓门。白天在店里营业，他抹杀了自己的个性，而晚上和家里人在一起，他便原形毕露。

“告诉你，你那个宝贝弟弟喝醉啦。”

他的声音冷酷、尖刻和不容置辩，两片嘴唇恰似机器上的印模，给每个字都盖上一个印。他妻子叹了口气，没作声。她是个肥大的妇人，衣着老是邋里邋遢。笨重的躯体、繁忙的家务以及丈夫的折磨，把她弄得总是疲惫不堪。

“告诉你，酗酒是他父亲遗传给他的，”希金波森先生不住口地数落着，“将来他也得死在街上的水沟里。这你知道。”

她点点头，叹了口气，接着便继续缝补。他们俩都认为，马丁是喝醉酒后回家的。他们压根就不懂得美，否则，就一定能看得出，那闪闪发亮的眼睛以及投射着异彩的面孔都说明小伙子第一次对爱情产生了憧憬。

“瞧瞧他给孩子们做的好榜样吧。”希金波森先生突然怨恨起妻子的沉默态度，哼了声鼻子说道。有时，他真希望她多跟他顶顶嘴。“他要是再酗酒，就让他滚蛋。明白吗？我可不愿听凭他胡作非为，喝得酩酊大醉，毒害天真无邪的孩子。”希金波森先生很喜欢这个字眼，这是他词汇库里的一个新词，还是最近阅报时从新闻栏目中搜集来的。“不错，就是‘毒害’，再没有别的说法了。”

他的妻子又叹了口气，伤心地摇摇头，继续缝补着。希金波森先生又开始埋头看报。

“他把上个星期的食宿费交了没有？”他把报纸略微朝下放放，突然问道。

她点了点头，然后说道：“他还有些钱呢。”

“他什么时候再出海去？”

“我想，得待他花完工钱吧，”她回答说，“昨天他到旧金山去找过活。不过，他口袋里还有钱，所以比较挑剔，不轻易和哪条船签合同。”“他那样的末等水手还摆什么臭架子，”希金波森先生哼了声鼻子说，“还挑三拣四呢！他配吗？”

“听他说，有一只船要到一个遥远的地方寻找宝藏；如果他的钱能用到那时候，他就随着一块去。”

“他要是打算安顿下来，我倒可以给他一个赶马车的活。”她丈夫这样说道，然而声音里听不出丝毫的善意，“汤姆不干了。”

他妻子露出一副惊愕和狐疑的神情。

“汤姆今晚就走，为卡鲁塞家干活去。那一家出的工钱比我的高。”

“我说过你会失去他的，”她嚷嚷起来，“他的价值不止你给他的那一点点钱。”

“听着，老婆子，”希金波森恐吓道，“我已经讲过有一千遍了，叫你别多管闲事。下次我可不客气啦。”

“我才不怕呢。”她轻蔑地说，“汤姆是个好小伙子。”

她丈夫对她瞪起了眼睛，因为她的话简直是一种反抗。

“你的那个弟弟要是真有本事，可以把马车接过来嘛。”他说着哼了哼鼻子。

“不管怎样，他又没短你食宿费。”她反驳道，“再说，他是我弟弟，只要不欠你的钱，你就没权利整天找他的茬儿。就算这七年来我是你家的人，可我也有做姐姐的感情呀。”

“如果他再在床上看书，就得收他灯油钱，这一点你对他说过吗？”他责问道。

希金波森夫人一声也没吭。她的反抗情绪消退了，精神萎缩进了疲倦的肉体里。她丈夫战胜了她，一副得意扬扬的样子，眼睛里冒着凶光，兴高采烈地用耳朵倾听她那咝咝的鼻息声。他压服了她，并从中得到极大的快感。这些年月，压服她是很容易的，但在他们刚结婚的头几年情况却不是这样。后来是因为生了一大群孩子，再加上丈夫无休无止的唠叨，她的精力才削弱了下来。

“好吧，你明天就告诉他吧。”他说，“另外，趁我没忘记之前，我想告诉你，明天最好把玛丽安叫来照料孩子。汤姆一走，我就得赶大车去，而你考虑一下，到楼底下站柜台吧。”

“可明天是洗衣服的日子呀。”她怯声怯气地抗议说。

“那就早点起床，先把衣服洗完。我要到十点钟才出门呢。”

他恶狠狠地把报纸揉搓得沙啦沙啦响，接下来又看他的报了。

第四章

马丁·伊登离开了他的姐夫之后，仍感到热血在体内蠕动。他在没一线光亮的后半截过道里摸索着，来到了自己的房间——一个小得像鸽子笼一样的房间，只够放一张床、一个脸盆架和一把椅子。希金波森先生很会精打细算，不肯雇用人，因为他妻子就可以干用人的活。再说，腾出用人的房间可以多招一个房客。马丁把斯温伯恩和勃朗宁的诗集放在椅子上，脱下外套，一屁股坐到了床上。他身体的重量一压上去，弹簧床垫便像患了气喘病一样吱吱发响，然而他却没加留意。他动手去脱鞋，可眼光却落到了对面的那堵白粉墙上——那儿斑痕点点，被房顶渗下的雨水冲出一道道又长又脏的棕褐色条纹。在这脏污的背景上，一幕幕幻景开始闪动和放射光彩。他忘掉了脱鞋，久久凝视着，最后嘴唇开始蠕动，喃喃地叫了一声：“露丝！”

“露丝！”他没料到一个简单的音节竟会如此动听、如此悦耳。他一遍又一遍地叫着，逐渐陶醉了。“露丝！”这个名字就是一件奇宝，是一个能够带来奇迹的充满魔力的字眼。他每叫一声，都会看见她的面孔在眼前晃动，使肮脏的墙壁蒙上一道金光。这道金光不是停留在墙壁上，而是向无穷无尽的空间延伸。他的灵魂穿过金光的深处，去寻觅她的灵魂。他心中最美好的东西，似壮丽的浪潮奔涌而出。想到她，他就变得高尚、纯洁和完美，或者希望变得完美。这是一种新的感觉。以前所认识的女人，没有一个使他变得完美，而总是起着相反的作用——使他变得卑鄙下流。他不知道，虽然结果是一团糟，但她们当中有许多人都曾不遗余力。他向来缺乏自我意识，所以不知道自己的身上具有一种能够赢得女性青睐的东西，一种能够使女人们垂涎于他的青春的东西。那些女人倒是常来骚扰他，可他却从不为之动心。他也永远想象不到，竟会有些女人因为他的缘故而循规蹈矩。他一直都是浑浑噩噩地度日，直到现在才觉得她们老是伸出邪恶的手拖拽他。这对她们无益，对他也无益。可他现在平生第一次开始产生自我意识，觉得自己没有权利指责别人。望着反映自己出乖露丑的幻象，他羞愧得满脸发烧。

他霍地立起身，想在脸盆架上方的镜子里看看自己的面容。他用毛巾抹了抹镜面，又看了看，仔仔细细打量了好半晌。他算是第一次真正看到了自己。他的眼睛擅长于观察，然而在这之前，它们却忙于观察千变万化的大千世界，从未有过闲暇顾及他本人。他看到了一个二十岁小伙子的头和脸，可由于不习惯评头论足之类的事情，故不知做怎样的评价。在方方正正的高额头上方，他看到的是一簇棕色的头发——那头发是深棕色的，呈波浪式，微微打着卷儿，让任何女人见了都会喜欢，都会手发痒和手指头发颠，忍不住上去捋摩和抚弄。然而他只是匆匆扫了一眼，觉得这头发在她眼里没有任何价值，却长久地、若有所思地端详着那高高隆起的四方额头，拼命想看穿它，弄清里面的脑子是聪颖还是愚笨。那儿到底藏着什么样的脑子呢？他一再这样问自己。它有什么样的本事呢？能给他带来多大好处？可以帮助他接近她吗？

他想知道，是否有一颗灵魂潜伏在那双铁灰色的眼睛里——那眼睛常常湛蓝湛蓝，在阳光普照的海洋上被带着咸味的海风锻炼得非常锐利。他还想知道，他的这双眼睛对她会产生怎样的效果。他努力把自己想象成她，盯着他的这双眼睛瞧，可这种想象一无所获。他可以成功地钻进别人心里，但他必须熟悉对方的生活方式。对于她的生活方式，他却一无所知。她是一个奇妙的谜，所以他怎能猜透她的心思呢？不管怎样，他认为自己的眼睛是诚实的，既不显得小气也不显得卑鄙。他那张被太阳晒成棕色的面孔却叫他感到意外，他料想不到自己竟然这么黑。他卷起衬衫袖子，把胳膊下边的白皮肤和自己的脸色做比较。是呀，他毕竟是个白种人！可是，就连他的胳膊也被太阳曝晒过。他把胳膊扭过来，用另一只手将二头肌推开，仔细瞧了瞧胳膊下边阳光极少光顾的地方，那儿显得十分白。他望着镜子里的紫色脸膛，想到这张脸曾经跟他胳膊下边的皮肤一样白，便不由笑了起来。他想象不来，世界上只有极少数女人——苍白得似幽灵般的女人可以称得上皮肤比他白细，即比他身上未遭阳光蹂躏的部位白细。

他那两片富于美感的厚嘴唇遇到情绪紧张时便抿起来，牢牢贴在牙齿上，要不是由于这一点，他的嘴巴完全可以说是天使的嘴巴。有时候，由于唇片贴得太紧，使他的嘴显得严峻和冷酷，甚至给人以禁欲主义的印象。他的嘴唇是战士的嘴唇，又是恋人的嘴唇，可以津津有味地品尝生活的甘甜，也可以将甘甜抛至一旁，去支配生活。他的下巴和颚部，坚实而略带一些赤裸裸的挑衅性，协助嘴唇征服生活。力量和美感达到平衡，由此而产生良好的效果，鼓舞他热爱健康的美，促使他对美好的情感发出共鸣。在两片嘴唇之间，是一副从没有得到过牙科医生的医治也不需要医治的牙齿。他看了看那两排牙齿，觉得它们既洁白又生得结实和整齐。可是他看着看着，心里却起了烦恼。他搜索了一下大脑的某个角落，模模糊糊记起一种印象——有些人每天都刷牙。那些人属于上流社会，是她那个阶级的人。她肯定也是天天刷牙。要是了解到他这一辈子从没刷过一次牙，她会怎么想呢？他打定主意先买一把牙刷，养成刷牙的习惯。他要立即行动起来，明日就开始。不能指望单靠成就赢得她，还必须对自己进行彻头彻尾的改造，甚至包括刷牙和戴硬领，尽管硬邦邦的领子会使他产生浑身不自在的感觉。

他抬起手，用拇指球揉了揉结满了老茧的手掌，呆望着深嵌在皮肉里的污垢——用任何刷子都无法擦掉的污垢。这和她的手有着天壤之别！一回忆起她的手，他的心里就有一种甜美的情感在跳动。他认为那手宛若玫瑰花瓣；凉丝丝、软绵绵的，又似雪花。他万万想不到一个女人的手竟会如此美妙和柔软。他发觉自己在想象由这样的一只手抚摸而产生的奇妙感觉，于是不由惭愧得红了脸。这样去想她，未免太粗俗了，从某些方面而言，似乎亵渎了她崇高的灵魂。她白皙而纤弱，是一个远远超脱了世俗的仙女。可尽管如此，他仍然念念难忘她那柔软的小手。工厂女工和劳动妇女那结着硬茧的手，在他已司空见惯。他非常清楚她们的手为什么变得粗糙；然而，她的小手……她的手之所以柔软，是因为她从不用手去干活。想到一个人不必为生计而干活，他便肃然起敬，同时觉得他和她之间的鸿沟愈裂愈大。蓦然，他看到一群不劳动的贵族形象耸立在对面的墙壁上，那是铜铸的塑像，高傲而威风。他自己终生劳作，最初的记忆似乎就和劳动密不可分，而且，他的家庭就是劳动之家。拿葛特露来说吧，她的手由于不停地干家务而变得粗硬，由于洗衣服而红肿，就像煮熟的牛肉一样。还有玛丽安妹妹，她去年夏天到罐头厂上班，一双漂亮的小手让番茄刀割得伤痕累累；去年冬天在纸箱厂干活，又叫切削机削掉了两个指头尖。他还记得自己的母亲是怎样带着粗硬的手掌躺在棺材里。他父亲也干了一辈子活，直到咽下最后一口气；父亲死时，手上结的硬茧一定有半英寸厚。可是，她的手是柔软的，她母亲以及她弟弟的手也是柔软的。最后这一点使他感到吃惊；这充分说明他们的社会地位高高在上，而她和他之间横着一段极大的距离。

他苦笑一声，又坐回到床上，把鞋脱了下来。他真蠢，竟让一个女人的脸蛋儿和柔软、白皙的手搅得神魂颠倒。这时，他眼前的那堵肮脏的粉墙上又出现了一幅幻景。那是夜晚时分，他站在伦敦东区[1]的一幢灰蒙蒙的廉价公寓房前，而对面立着一位叫玛吉的十五岁的工厂小女工。他们刚刚参加过厂里举办的宴会，他这是送她回家来。她就住在这幢猪圈不如的灰蒙蒙的公寓房里。他边道晚安，边伸出手去和她握手。她却扬起嘴唇等待亲吻，不过，他不愿吻她，因为他有些怕她。后来，她拉起他的手，异常激动地紧紧握着。他觉得她手上的硬茧摩擦着他的老茧，心里涌起一股强烈的怜悯感。他望了望她那双期待和渴望的眼睛，望了望那匆匆从童年时代步入可怕和残酷的成熟期的营养不良的女儿身段。最后，他极不情愿地用胳膊搂住她，低头吻了她的嘴唇。她快活的叫喊声在他的耳边回荡；他感到她就像猫一样紧偎在他身上。她真是个可怜的小瘦猫！对于这幅很久以前发生过的场景，他不住眼地盯着瞧。此时此刻，他仍感到浑身起鸡皮疙瘩，就跟那天晚上她紧紧贴在他身上时一样，同时，他心里也温丝丝的有几分怜悯之情。这幅场景昏暗而油腻，连落在人行道石板上的蒙蒙细雨也给人以油腻腻的感觉。突然，一道灿烂的光芒照射到了墙壁上；她的那张白皙的面孔，头顶皇冠似的金发，横贯那幅昏暗的幻景，并取而代之，闪闪烁烁，如远不可及的朗星。

他从椅子上拿起勃朗宁和斯温伯恩的诗集，放在嘴上吻了吻，暗忖：好在她发过话，让我再到她家去。他又照了照镜子，然后极其严肃地对自己出声说道：

“马丁·伊登，你明天要干的第一件事就是到公共图书馆去查阅有关礼节的书籍。明白吗？”

他熄掉煤气灯，躺倒在床上，使弹簧床垫吱吱扭扭乱响了一通。“你不能再说脏话啦，马丁老伙计；你必须停止讲脏话。”他这样出声地念叨着。

最后，他沉沉入睡，并做起梦来；就这些梦的疯狂和大胆程度而言，与大烟鬼的幻想不差上下。

[1]　贫民窟。

第五章

次日早晨，他从玫瑰色的梦境中醒来，回到弥漫着水蒸气的环境里，这儿散发着肥皂水和脏衣服的气味，回响着杂乱的生活所具有的刺耳噪音。走出房间时，他听到了哗啦哗啦的搅水声、尖厉的叫喊声和响亮的掴耳光的声音，那是他姐姐在拿众多儿女中的一个出气。孩子的哭叫声像刀子一样扎在他的心头。他觉得周围的一切，包括他所呼吸的空气，都叫人感到厌恶和不舒服。他心想，这与露丝家的那种美好和宁静的气氛有着多么大的差异。那儿的一切都属于精神世界，而这里的一切却如此现实，现实得令人作呕。

“到这里来，阿尔弗雷德。”他对那个哭哭啼啼的孩子叫道，同时把手伸进了裤袋里。他的钱就放在那儿，随随便便的，和他平日自由散漫的生活方式一样。他把一张二角五分的钞票放在孩子的手里，然后将孩子搂在怀里，哄着他，叫他不要再哭。“去吧，去买点糖果吃，别忘了分给弟弟妹妹一些。记住，要买最经吃的那种。”

他姐姐从洗衣盆上抬起涨红的脸，望了他一眼。

“五分钱就够了，”她说，“瞧你这个样子，一点也不知道珍惜钱。让孩子吃那么多，会把他吃出病的。”

“没什么，姐姐，”他乐呵呵地说，“我会节省着花钱的。要不是你这么忙，我会亲亲你，向你道个早安。”

他很想对他的这个姐姐表示自己的一片温情，因为她是个好人；他知道，她在以她的方式爱着他。可是，不知怎么，随着时光一年年地流逝，她变得愈来愈不像过去的她，愈来愈难以叫人捉摸。他觉得，全是由于繁重的家务、成群的孩子以及丈夫的唠叨，她才变了样。他突生异想，认为她的天性似乎遭到了腐烂的蔬菜和难闻的肥皂水的污染，遭到了她在零售店的柜台上收下的一角一分钱币的污染。

“去吃你的早饭吧！”她尽管心里很高兴，但说话的语调却粗声粗气。在分布各地的所有的兄弟中，她一直最疼爱的就是这个。“我真想吻吻你啊。”她说，心里突然感到一阵激动。

她用拇指和食指抹去一条胳膊上滴下来的肥皂水，接着又去抹另一条胳膊。他把两条臂膀搂在她粗大的腰肢上，吻了吻她那湿漉漉、水汽蒙蒙的嘴唇。泪水在她的眼眶里打转转——这可不全是因为感情冲动，多是由于过度疲劳，身体虚弱的缘故。她一把将他从身边推开，可他还是瞧见了她那泪水模糊的眼睛。

“你的早饭在炉子上热着，”她慌忙说道，“吉姆这个时候也该起来了。我今天起了个大早，因为要把衣服洗出来。汤姆不干了，找不到人手，伯纳德只好亲自去赶大车，今天绝不会有好脸。”

马丁怀着沉重的心情走进了厨房。姐姐红涨的面孔和邋遢的身段像硫酸一样蚀入了他的大脑。他敢肯定，她如果能有点闲暇，会好好疼他的，可惜她干起活辛苦得要命，因为伯纳德·希金波森是个畜生，把她逼得太狠。但话又说回来，他总觉得她的吻里没有一丝一毫美好的成分。不错，这是一个不同寻常的吻，因为多年来，只有当他航海归来或出海时，她才吻他。不过，这个吻带着肥皂水味，而且他还注意到她的嘴唇松弛无力，缺乏亲吻时应该具有的热情和活力。她的吻是精疲力竭的吻，因为她长期以来辛苦劳作，已忘掉了该怎样亲吻。记得她结婚之前当姑娘的时候，在洗衣坊辛苦了一天，还要和最出色的男孩通宵达旦地跳舞，丝毫不理会自己跳完舞后还要干一天重活。接着，他又想到了露丝，想到她的芳唇一定有一种凉丝丝、甜蜜蜜的味儿，因为她浑身上下都散发出这种芳香。她的吻一定像她的握手或打量人的眼神，坚定而坦率。他放大胆幻想着她的芳唇印在了他的嘴唇上，而且这一想象异常逼真，使得他飘飘欲仙，仿佛穿行在玫瑰花瓣组成的云彩之间，闻到的净是芬芳的花香。

在厨房里，他看到另一个房客吉姆正在慢吞吞地喝麦片粥，眼睛里露出一种病态的恍惚神情。吉姆给一个管道工当学徒，尖尖的下巴，乐呵呵的性格，有点神经质和傻里傻气的，一看就知道在人生的角逐场上是个没出息的人。

“怎么不吃呢？”他见马丁郁郁寡欢地用羹勺一个劲搅动冷冰冰的煮得半生不熟的麦片粥，便问道，“昨天晚上又喝酒啦？”

马丁摇了摇头。他心情沉重，因为他觉得所有的一切都是那样庸俗。露丝·摩斯似乎离他更加遥远了。

“我倒是喝了酒，一直都灌到了嗓子眼儿。”吉姆吹嘘道，同时神经质地哧哧一笑，“啊，她真是个美人儿。还是比利把我送回家的呢。”

马丁点点头，表示自己在听着——他生来就有这样一种习惯，不管是任何人跟他讲话，他都侧耳倾听——然后斟了一杯温吞吞的咖啡。

“今晚一块到莲花俱乐部跳舞吧？”吉姆问，“那儿可以喝到啤酒。台美斯加尔那帮人如果也去，准会闹个天翻地覆。不过，我不在乎，照样带女朋友去。见鬼，我嘴里怎么有一股味儿！”

他扮了个鬼脸，喝了口咖啡，想把嘴里的异味除掉。

“你认识朱莉亚吧？”

马丁摇了摇头。

“她是我的女朋友，长得可漂亮啦，”吉姆解释道，“我把她引见给你，只是你别将她抢走。不知姑娘们看上了你哪一点，这我的确弄不懂。你抢别人女朋友的手段实在叫人厌恶。”

“我可从未抢过你的女朋友。”马丁丝毫不感兴趣地说，心里巴不得赶快把这顿饭吃完。

“不对，我的女朋友你也抢过，”对方激动了起来，口气坚定地说，“就拿玛吉来说吧。”

“我与她没任何关系，那天晚上除外，从来没跟她跳过舞。”

“对啊，问题就出在那天晚上。”吉姆嚷嚷道，“你和她跳了跳舞，瞧了她几眼，一切就都完了。当然，你是无心的，可是却永远断送了我。她再没正眼看过我，老是问到你。如果你当时有那个意思，她会迫不及待地和你幽会。”

“可我当时并没那个意思。”

“反正都一样，我受到了冷落。”吉姆羡慕地望着他，问道，“你是怎么得手的，马特[1]？”

“靠的是对她们不理不睬。”马丁答道。

“你是说装着不理睬她们？”吉姆急切地问。

马丁考虑了片刻，然后回答说：“那样也许可以成功，可我觉得我的情况略有不同。我从来就不管那回事——不太管那回事。倘若你能够装得像，也可以，很可能会得手。”

“昨天晚上你要是到赖利家参加谷仓舞会就好啦，”吉姆前言不对后语地宣称，“在场的人都大打出手。西奥克兰来了个顶呱呱的家伙，人称‘耗子’，身手矫健敏捷，谁也近身不得。我们当时都希望你能在那儿。你到底上哪里去了？”

“上奥克兰去了。”马丁说。

“去看演出？”

马丁将餐盘推开，立起了身。

“今晚一块去跳舞吧？”对方冲着他的背影问。

“不去，我不想去。”他回答说。

他下了楼，来到街上，大口地呼吸着空气。刚才的气氛实在沉闷，那位学徒的唠叨逼得他要发疯。有时候，他得全力克制自己，才不至于伸手把吉姆的那张脸按到粥盘上。吉姆愈唠叨，他就觉得露丝离他愈远。和这样的人为伍，他怎么能配得上她呢？摆在面前的问题令他失去了胆量，而他的劳动阶级身份压得他直不起腰。他的姐姐、姐姐的住房和家庭、学徒工吉姆以及他所认识的每一个人、生活中每一层关系——所有的一切都在拖他的后腿。他所品尝到的生活并不美好。在这之前，他和周围的人们一样埋头生活，把生活当作一种美好的东西。对于生活，除非是在看书的时候，否则他从不提出疑问；可书毕竟是书，神话故事毕竟是神话故事，描绘的是奇妙和不可能存在的世界。不过，他现在亲眼看到了那个世界，明显而真实，最中央有一位叫露丝的如花似玉的女人；从今往后，他难免会品尝到辛酸和剧烈的痛苦，产生强烈的渴望和绝望心情——这种绝望会给他一些满足，因为它建立在希望之上。

起初他举棋不定，不知是到伯克利公共图书馆还是奥克兰公共图书馆好，结果选择了后一个，因为露丝就住在奥克兰。图书馆是她最可能去的地方，也许在那儿能见到她。这谁说得准呢？他不了解图书馆的布局，在一排排小说书架之间转个没完，后来，一位五官小巧玲珑、看起来像是负责人的法国人模样的姑娘告诉他说参考书都在楼上。他也不知道问一声桌旁的管理员，就钻进哲学书室瞎闯起来。他听说过哲学这门科学，但没想到竟有如此之多的哲学书籍。大部分的著作充斥了高高的书架，使他自叹才疏学浅，同时又令他兴奋不已，因为这些书可以为他那充满活力的大脑提供用武之地。在数学书库，他拿起几本有关三角学的书，边翻阅，边望着那些看也看不懂的公式和图形发呆。他认得英语，但书上看到的却是一种陌生的语言。诺曼和阿瑟懂得这种语言，因为他听到他们讲过，那两人可是她的弟弟呀。走出书库时，他陷入了绝望之中。那些书似乎从四面八方向他压来，像是要把他压死。想不到人类积累的知识竟如此浩瀚，他一下子给唬住了，他的大脑怎么能够消化得完呢？过了一会儿，他记起有些人，或不少人，已经掌握了这些知识。于是，他怀着激昂的心情低声发了一个冲天大誓：凡是别人的大脑能够办得到的事，他的大脑也能办得到。

他就这么到处游荡，望着那些满载着智慧的书架，忽儿沮丧忽儿高兴，心情变化个不停。在一个杂类书库，他找到了一本《诺利氏备要》，便恭敬地翻阅起来。从某个方面来说，这本书和他用的是同一类语言，都属于海洋语言。随后，他又找到一部鲍迪奇[2]的著作，以及几本莱基和马歇尔的作品。这下可好啦，他可以自学航海术，把酒戒掉，一步一步朝上努力，当一名船长。刹那间，他觉得露丝离他近在咫尺。当上船长，他就可以娶她（如果她愿意嫁他的话）。假如她不愿嫁他，他也会为了她好好做人，把酒戒掉。接着，他突然想起来，作为船长就得为水险商及船主效劳，而这两种主子利益截然相反，弄不好就可以并且准会毁掉他。他将眼光四下扫了扫，看到那成千上万册的书，不由合上了眼帘。不，不能再航海了。这浩瀚的书海里蕴藏着极大的力量。要想建立丰功伟业，就得在陆地上干。再说，船长是不允许携带妻子一道出海的。

时间到了中午，接着就是下午。他忘记了吃饭，继续寻找有关礼节的书籍。因为，除了事业，他还在苦苦思考一个非常具体的简单问题：如果你结识了一位小姐，她请你去看她，那么，应该何时登门造访呢？他就是这样在询问自己。可是，等他找到了那个书架，却白忙活一场，怎么也寻觅不到答案。关于礼节的讲究竟如此之大，吓得他目瞪口呆。上流社会那一套传递名片的礼仪错综复杂，使他感到困惑迷惘。他放弃了努力。他没有找到要找的东西，只发现了一点：要想讲究礼仪，就得花一生的时间去研究；他必须先活上一辈子，才能学得礼致彬彬。

“你需要的书找到了吗？”他朝外走时，桌旁的管理员这样问他。

“找到了，先生，”他答道，“你们的图书馆真好。”

那人点了点头。“欢迎你常来。你是水手吧？”

“嘿，他是怎么知道的？”马丁下楼时，不由问自己。

在穿过第一个街段时，他的步子迈得呆板和笨拙，后来他陷入沉思，忘掉了自我，才恢复了雄壮、优美的步态。

[1]　马丁的爱称。

[2]　18世纪美国著名航海家兼数学家。

第六章

一种近乎饥饿感的不安情绪在折磨着马丁·伊登。他渴望见到那位以纤巧的手有力控制着他生活的姑娘，但他鼓不起勇气登门看望她，生怕操之过急会犯下错误，触犯那种被称为“礼节”的可怕东西。在奥克兰图书馆及伯克利图书馆，他花去了大量的时间，为他自己、他姐姐葛特露、妹妹玛丽安和吉姆填写领取借书证的申请表格。他请吉姆喝了几杯啤酒，才征得了他的同意。用四张借书证把书借来，他就在用人的房间里挑灯夜读，为此希金波森先生每星期收他五角钱的灯油费。

书读得愈多，他心情便愈加不安。每一页书都是一个窥视孔，从中可以看得到知识王国。书中的内容滋养着他的求知欲，使之逐渐膨胀。不过，他不知从何处入手，常常为自己的基础浅薄而苦恼。一些最一般性的知识——显而易见，每位读者均应该掌握的知识——他都一无所知。至于他所读到的那些令他高兴得发狂的诗篇，也是同样一种情形。他不但读了露丝借给他的那册斯温伯恩诗集，还读了斯温伯恩的另外一些作品，其中，他理解比较深的是《陶洛兰丝》。他认为，露丝肯定理解不透这首诗。她过的是温文尔雅的生活，怎么能理解得透呢？后来，他偶然看到了吉卜林的诗，看到吉卜林对熟悉景物的描绘那般富有韵律、节奏和魅力，于是不由给迷住了。诗人对生活的共鸣以及深刻的心理描写，使他大感惊讶。“心理”作为一个新词，贮存进了马丁的词汇库。他买了一部词典，这项开支减少了他的积蓄，使他不得不出海挣钱的日期有所提前。而且，这件事令希金波森先生也大为光火，因为希金波森先生巴不得他能用这笔钱支付膳宿费。

白天，他不敢走近露丝的家，可到了夜里他就像小偷一样埋伏在摩斯府邸的周围，偷偷观望那一扇扇的窗口，用爱的目光打量那为她遮风挡雨的屋墙。有几回，他险些让她的弟弟们撞上；一次，他尾随摩斯先生进了闹市区，在灯火通明的街上端详着后者的面孔，心里一直盼着她的父亲突然会遇上死亡的威胁，这样他便可以跳出来舍身相救。另外有一天晚上，他总算没有白辛苦，透过二楼的一扇窗口瞧见了露丝的倩影。他只看到了她的头部和肩膀，当她对着镜子梳头时又看到了她扬起的胳脾。那仅仅是一瞬间的事情，可对他来说却是长长的一瞬间——在这一瞬间，他的热血化成了美酒，欢快地在他的血管里沸腾。后来，她拉下了窗帘。但他已经发现，那儿就是她的房间。此后，他常常到那儿去，躲在街对面黑魆魆的树影里，没完没了地抽烟。一天下午，他看到她的母亲从一家银行走了出来，这件事又一次证明他和露丝之间存在着巨大的距离。只有她的那个阶层和银行打交道，而他一辈子都没进过银行，认为到那种地方去的仅仅是有财有势的人。

从某方面而言，他经历了一场思想上的革命。她干净的外表和纯洁的品性对他产生了影响，于是他觉得自己的体内迸发出一种强烈的愿望，想把自己洗得干干净净。他必须这样做，否则他就不配和她相处。他又是刷牙，又是用厨房里的板刷洗手，后来在一家杂货店的橱窗里看到指甲刷子，便立刻联想到了它的用途。买刷子时，店员瞧了瞧他的指甲，建议他买一把指甲锉，这样一来他又多了一件梳洗用具。在图书馆，他看了一本有关保养身体的书，便立刻开始培养每天早晨洗冷水浴的习惯。吉姆见了又惊又奇，而希金波森先生大为困惑，他看不惯这种赶时髦的举措，于是便认真地考虑起是否应该对马丁加收水费。还有一项行动与裤子的折缝有关。马丁既然对这类事情发生了兴趣，他很快便注意到：工人阶级的裤子，膝部总是鼓囊囊的，而高居工人阶级之上的那些人所穿的裤子，从膝部到脚面都是笔挺的。而且他还找出了原因，于是便潜入姐姐的厨房寻找熨斗和烫衣板。一开始他就出了乱子，笨手笨脚地熨糊了一条裤子，只好再买一条，而这笔花销又把出海的日期提前了许多。

这样的自我改造不仅局限于外表。他虽然还是抽烟，但却把酒戒掉了。在此之前，他一直认为喝酒是男人的体面，并以自己的海量感到骄傲，因为大多数男人都不是他的对手。旧金山有许多他的水手朋友；每每碰上这些人，他都要照老规矩宴请一顿，对方也回请他；可他给自己要的不是淡啤酒就是姜汁酒，听到伙伴们的嘲笑，他也毫不动气。待他们发起酒疯，他便静静观察，看着他们丑态百出和失去理性，心里暗暗庆幸自己已不再和他们是同一类人。他们借酒消愁，一旦喝醉，头脑便变得模糊和迟钝，感到飘飘欲仙，陶醉于天堂幻境之中。而马丁对烈性酒的渴望已经消失。他以新的更美好的方式得到陶醉——追求露丝，因为是露丝使他燃起了爱情的火焰，使他看到了高尚和永恒的生活；博览群书，因为是书籍在他心中激起了强烈的求知欲；渴望搞好个人卫生，因为这样可以使他更加强健，令他通体舒泰，在体质上达到完美。

一天晚上他到剧院去瞎碰运气，期望在那儿看到她；他从二号楼厅望去，果然看到了她。他见她同阿瑟以及一个陌生的年轻人沿过道走了过来，那人蓬松着一头足球状的乱发，还戴着一副眼镜，一看见他，马丁便顿生忧虑和忌妒之心。只见她在乐池前坐了下来，而他在这个晚上除了她之外，任什么都视而不见——只顾看她那纤美、雪白的膀子以及她淡黄色的秀发，不过由于距离太远，这些只能看个模模糊糊。可是看他的却大有人在；他不时要扫一眼周围的人，结果发现前排有两个姑娘，隔着十几个座位，眼睛里带着大胆的神情冲着他微笑。他向来都比较随和，天性不愿给人难堪。要是在过去，他会回以微笑，而且不仅如此，还会鼓励对方的笑容。可现在情况发生了变化。他虽然冲姑娘们笑了笑，但随后便把目光掉开，再没有着意去观望她们。他忘却了这两个姑娘的存在，可是有好几次，他的目光都撞上了她们的笑脸。他不可能在一天之内便脱胎换骨，也不可能违背自己固有的善良天性；于是，在这种时刻，他便冲姑娘们发出了温和、友好及通情达理的微笑。这档子事儿对他并不陌生，他知道她们在向他伸出女性的手。可眼下的情况有所不同，他的心全在远处乐池前的那个世界上独一无二的女人身上——那女人和他自己阶层中的这两位姑娘天差地别，是如此不同，使他由不得对这两位姑娘产生了怜悯和悲哀的心情。他衷心希望她们能有几分她的典雅和高贵，不过，他绝不会因为她们做得太过分而伤害她们的自尊心。他的内心并不高兴，甚至觉得有些羞愧，因为正是由于他出身卑贱才引出了这种现象。他知道，自己如果属于露丝的阶层，这两位姑娘就不会对他含情脉脉了；她们每冲他瞟一眼，他就觉得自己的阶层在用手把他朝低处拉。

演到最后一个剧情，未等落幕，他便离开了座位，指望着能在她朝出口走时，一睹其芳姿。门外的人行道上总是站立着许多人，他可以把帽檐拉低遮住眼睛，躲到别人的身后，让她看不到他。他随着第一股人流出了剧院，可是在人行道边沿处立足未稳，就见那两位姑娘跟了来。她们是来找他的。当时他恨不得把自己臭骂一顿，怪自己具有吸引女人的魅力。她们穿过人行道向这边漫不经心地徐徐走来，愈靠愈近，眼看就要发现他了。她们把步子放得越加缓慢，裹在人群里来到了他跟前，其中的一个用身子碰了碰他，样子像是刚刚看到他。这姑娘身材苗条、皮肤黝黑，生着一双乌黑高傲的眼睛。但这双眼睛在冲他微笑，于是他也笑了笑。

“你好。”他说。

他说话不假思索，因为以前在和别人初次见面的同样的情况下，他不知把这话都说过多少遍了。再说，他只能这样做。他天性宽宏厚道、富于同情心，容不得他怠慢他人。黑眼睛姑娘喜滋滋地笑了笑，给他打了声招呼，露出了想站住的样子，而挽着她胳膊的那个同伴咯咯一笑，也显出了止步的意图。他飞快地转动着大脑，心想绝不能让她出来时看到他在和她们聊天。于是，他非常自然，一点也不做作地靠到黑眼睛姑娘身旁，和她一道朝前走。他丝毫不觉得尴尬，舌头根也不打绊了。他如鱼得水，说出串串俚语和警句，同姑娘打情骂俏，而这在过眼烟云般的恋情中通常是相互了解的前奏。到了街拐角，人流继续向前行进，而他想挤出人群，到横街上去。可黑眼睛姑娘拽住他的胳膊，紧跟着他，而且把女友也拖着一起走，嘴里叫喊着：

“等等，比尔！急什么呢？就这么一下子想把我们甩掉？”

他哈哈一笑收住了脚步，朝她们转过身来。越过她们的肩头，他可以看到人群在路灯下川流不息地移动。他站的地方光线不太亮，如果她从此处走过，他可以看见她，而对方却瞅不到他。她一定会经过的，因为这条道路通向她的家。

“她叫什么名字？”他问那个咯咯笑的姑娘，同时冲着黑眼睛姑娘点了点头。

“你问她自己好啦。”对方说着，笑得前仰后合。

“喂，你叫什么？”他把脸转过来对着那个不知名的姑娘，问道。

“你还没把你的名字告诉我呢。”她针锋相对地说。

“你可从来没问过呀，”他笑了笑说，“再说，你刚才一下子就猜出来了呀。我叫比尔，没错，就是这样。”

“啧，见你的鬼吧。”她紧盯住他的眼睛，而她自己的眼睛含情脉脉，勾人魂魄，“老实讲，到底叫什么！”

接着，她又投来一个飞眼。自打人类产生了情欲，世世代代沿袭下来的女性魅力在她的眼中清晰可辨。他大大咧咧地打量着她，胆气也壮了，因为他知道自己一旦步步进逼，她便会羞怯和巧妙地撤退；可如果他畏缩不前，她势必将局面颠倒过来。不过，他毕竟是个男人，感觉得到她的吸引力，内心由不得对她那讨人喜欢的美意产生了好感。是啊，他了解这类事情，也十分了解她们，理解她们的一言一行。用她们的那个阶层的标准来衡量，她们可以说是好女人，为了微薄的工资辛勤劳作，不愿为了追求舒适的生活出卖自己，一心一意希求能在生活的荒漠里得到一丁点幸福；她们所面临的前途犹如一场赌博，一边是没完没了的可怕苦役，而另一边则是更为可怕的凄惨的火坑——走这条路虽然报酬较为丰厚，但长久不了。

“我叫比尔，”他点着头回答道，“这是真的，我的确叫比尔。”

“不是在哄人吧？”她问道。

“他根本不叫比尔！”另一位姑娘插嘴说。

“你怎么知道？”他责问道，“你以前可从没见过我呀。”

“没这个必要，反正我知道你在撒谎。”对方反驳说。

“直说吧，比尔，你到底叫什么？”第一个姑娘问。

“就是叫比尔呀。”他语气肯定地说。

她伸手抓住他的胳膊，淘气地摇晃着说：“明明知道你在撒谎，可我还是觉得你相当不错。”

他握住了那只多情的手，在掌心摸到了他所熟悉的疤痕以及变了形的骨头。

“你是什么时候离开罐头厂的？”他问。

“你怎么知道？”“好样的，你可真是洞察秋毫啊！”两个姑娘异口同声地说。

他一边和她们瞎扯些傻里傻气的闲淡话，一边浮想联翩，想到了图书馆里那满载着千秋万代智慧的一架子一架子的书。想到这前后的差异，他不由苦笑起来，心中产生了种种疑问。可尽管他内心苦思冥想、嘴上谈笑风生，他还是留意观看着从他身旁经过的看完戏的人流。最后他终于在路灯下瞧见了她，看见她夹在她弟弟以及那个戴眼镜的陌生小伙子中间，顿时，他的心脏似乎停止了跳动。这一时刻他已等了许久。他注意到她那高贵的头上裹着一条毛茸茸、薄薄的头巾，注意到她那穿着衣服的身躯仍显出典雅的线条，还注意到了她那雍容的举止以及提起裙边的优美的手。转眼之间，她就不见了踪影，撇下他一人望着跟前的这两位罐头厂的姑娘发呆。这两位姑娘既庸俗又可悲，拼命想把自己打扮得漂亮些，穿得整齐干净些，可无论是身上的衣料、头上的丝带还是手上的戒指，都是廉价品。他感到胳膊被人拉了一下，接着听到一个声音说道：

“醒醒，比尔！你这是怎么啦？”

“你说什么？”他问道。

“噢，没什么，”黑眼睛姑娘甩了甩脑袋，答道，“我只是说——”

“说什么？”

“我说，如果你能为她（此处指她的女友）物色一位男朋友，那就太棒了。这样，咱们可以找个地方喝冰淇淋苏打水，或者咖啡什么的。”他心里突然感到一阵厌恶。从露丝那儿转换到这个场景，显得过于急剧。跟前的这个姑娘一双大胆、高傲的眼睛，在这双眼睛的旁边他看到了露丝那清澈明亮的眼睛，像圣女的眼睛一样无比纯洁，正紧紧盯着他。不知怎么，他感到体内有一种力量在涌动。他有一种优越感，觉得他的生活意义要高于这两位姑娘，因为她们的思想总是围着冰淇淋和男朋友兜圈子。他记得自己在内心始终过着一种秘密的生活。他曾经试图把心里的想法和别人分享，却怎么也找不到能够理解他的女人或男人。他屡次尝试，但只会让听者迷惘困惑。这时他心想，既然他的思想已经超越了他们，那他本人也必须与众不同。他攥紧拳头，觉得力量在体内运动。假如生活对他有较大的意义，他就应该向生活索取更多，但索取也不能从这类伙伴身上索取。这双大胆的黑眼睛没有什么可以提供给他。他知道，这双眼睛的背后隐藏的无非是冰淇淋之类的念头。而旁边的那双圣女的眼睛却能够提供他所知道的一切以及他连想也想不到的东西；可以提供书本和绘画的知识，提供美和安宁，以及上流社会所有高贵和典雅。那双黑眼睛背后的每一个思维过程他都了如指掌，因为那种思维似钟表般有规律，可以看得到每个齿轮的转动。它们要求的是低级享受，和墓坑一样狭窄，叫人心生厌恶，到头来等待它们的正是这种墓坑。而这双圣女的眼睛要求的则是生活之谜、不可思议的奇迹和永生。他在这双眼睛里看到了她的灵魂，也看到了他自己的灵魂。

“麻烦就麻烦在一件事情上，”他出声地说，“我已经有约会了。”

姑娘的眼睛里露出了失望的神情。

“我想，是陪生病的朋友吧？”她讥讽道。

“不对，是一个真正的约会——”他停顿了一下，“是跟一位姑娘。”

“你不是在骗我吧？”她认真地问。

他望着她的眼睛，说道：“不骗你，这是实话。咱们可以改个时间再见面嘛，你还没把你的名字告诉我呢。还有，你住在哪儿？”

“我叫丽茜，”她说着，态度软了下来，拉住他的胳膊，用身子贴紧他，“丽茜·康诺莱，家住第五大街和市场街之间。”

他又聊了几分钟，然后便和她们分了手。他没有立即回家去，而是来到了那棵他夜夜守望的树下，抬头望着一扇窗口，喃喃地说：“那个约会就是跟你呀，露丝，我把它留给了你。”

第七章

那天晚上和露丝·摩斯初次见面之后，他闷着头苦读了一个星期的书，可还是不敢登门去看望她。他屡次三番鼓起勇气，但由于疑虑重重，决心便随之垮台。他不知何时去才算得体，也无人为他指点迷津；他真怕自己会犯下无法挽回的错误。他摆脱了昔日的伙伴以及旧的生活方式，又没有结下新的朋友，于是便无事可做，唯有读书。他看书一看便是老半天，换上普通人的眼睛，十几双也会被毁掉的。可他的眼睛十分结实，由异常强健的体魄做后盾。再者，他的大脑一直闲着，至于书本上的那些抽象的概念，他一辈子连想也未想过。而今，一切准备就绪，只盼着播种收获了。他的大脑从未因学习而疲倦不堪，现在以利齿咬住书本上的知识，死也不肯松。

一个星期下来，他觉得像过了几个世纪，把昔日的生活和观点远远抛到了身后。但由于缺乏准备，他遇到了挫折。有些书需要多年的专门研究才能看得懂，他也跃跃欲试地想读一读。一天，他会拿起一本过了时的哲学书，而第二天又涉猎于超时代的著作，于是大脑被相互冲突和矛盾的观念搅得昏昏沉沉。在经济学方面也是同样一种情形。在图书馆的同一个书架上，他会找到卡尔·马克思、李嘉图、亚当·斯密和密尔的著作，而这些人的经济法则极其深奥，也不知谁的理论已是陈词滥调。他被弄得糊里糊涂，然而他渴望搞明白。一日之间，他就对经济、工业和政治产生了兴趣。一次，在穿过市政厅公园时，他注意到那儿聚着一群人，中间的五六个人涨红着脸，高喉咙大嗓门地在认真辩论着。他站到旁听的人群里，从那些人民哲学家的嘴里倾听着新鲜和陌生的语言。那些人其中的一个是流浪汉，另一个是劳工鼓动家，还有一个是法学院的学生，其余的则是口若悬河的工人。他第一次听到了社会主义、无政府主义和单一税[1]这样的理论，从而得知各类社会哲学之间相互征战不息。他听到了数百个陌生的专门术语，而这些术语出自他那浅薄的书本知识尚未涉及的思想领域。由于这一层原因，他无法完全听懂辩论的内容，只能猜测和推想这些生僻词汇里所包含的思想。参加辩论的还有一个信仰神智学[2]的黑眼睛餐馆侍者，一个提倡不可知论的工会面包师，和一个以奇怪的哲学理论“自然即公理”[3]令众人困惑的老者；另外还有一个老者，滔滔不绝地议论着宇宙、阳原子及阴原子。

马丁·伊登一连听了几个小时，走开时头昏脑涨。他急匆匆赶到图书馆，因为有十几个古里古怪的词需要查阅。离开图书馆时，他腋下夹着四部书：勃拉伐茨基夫人的《秘密教义》[4]、《进步与贫困》、《社会主义精义》和《宗教与科学之战》。不幸的是，他一开始就拿起了《秘密教义》阅读，每一行都遇到许多看不懂的多音节词。他坐在床上看书，花在词典上的时间比花在书上的时间还多。由于查的生词过多，等到这些词再出现时，他已忘记了词的含义，只好再查。后来他想了个办法，把词义写在笔记本上，一页一页写得满满的。可他还是看不懂，一直到凌晨三点钟，脑子都成了一盆糨糊，书中的一条基本思想也没抓住。他抬头望去，觉得整个房间像大海上的船只一样，又是起伏又是左右摇摆。他把《秘密教义》扔到墙角那儿，连连骂了许多声，然后熄掉煤气灯，稳定好情绪入睡。看另外三部书时，运气也没好到哪儿去。这倒不是因为他无能或智力低下；如若不是缺乏思维方面的训练以及缺乏思维方式，他完全可以领会书中的观点。他看出了这一点，于是想出了个主意：什么书也不看，光看词典，直至彻底掌握词典里的每一个词。

真正给他带来欢乐的是诗歌。他读了许多的诗，觉得自己最喜欢的还是那些比较容易理解的普通诗行。他热爱美，而在诗里面他发现了美。诗歌如同音乐一样，深深打动了他；于不知不觉之中，他的大脑已在准备迎接即将来到的繁重工作了。他的大脑犹如白纸，不费力气便一节节地印上了诸多他所读到和喜欢的诗篇；这样一来，他很快便能够把自己看过的壮丽优美的诗行低吟或高歌，从中获取巨大的喜悦。一次，他在图书馆的一个书架上偶然发现并排放着盖莱[5]的《古典神话》和勃尔芬区[6]的《寓音时代》。在他那无知的黑暗当中亮起一盏灯，投射出灿烂的光芒，于是他更加如饥似渴地读起诗来。

桌旁的那个图书馆馆员见马丁经常出入，逐渐变得对他十分和气，总是以微笑迎接他，看到他进来便频频点头。正是由于这一点，有一次，马丁做了一件大胆的事情。他取了几本书来到桌旁，待那人在借书证上盖印时，他脱口说道：

“劳驾，有点事情想问问你。”

那人笑笑，注意听着。

“如果你结识了一位年轻小姐，她请你到她家去，那么你该何时登门拜访呢？”

马丁吃力得汗都冒了出来，觉得衬衫紧紧贴到了肩头上。

“让我说，任何时候都可以，”那人答道。

“不错，可我的情况不同，”马丁不同意地说，“她——我——你瞧，事情是这样的：也许她不在家，到大学里上课去了。”

“那就再去一次呀。”

“我的话没有把我的意思表达出来。”马丁支支吾吾地说，同时，他打定主意要把情况向对方和盘托出，“我不过是个粗人，没见过社交界的场面。那姑娘和我全然不同，而我与她也无丝毫相同之处。你不会觉得我在冒傻气吧？”他猛不愣丁问道。

“不，不，一点也不，这你放心好啦。”对方断然声明，“你的问题原本不是参考书库分内的事，不过我倒很乐意助你一臂之力。”

马丁感激地望了望他。

“如果我能那般洒脱，就好啦。”他说。

“你说什么？”

“我是说，但愿我能把话讲得自如和礼貌，举止得体。”

“噢。”对方理解地这么说了一声。

“最好什么时候去看她？下午？——不要离吃饭时间太近？或是晚上？星期天？”

“我来告诉你吧，”管理员脸上放着光彩说，“你可以先给她打个电话，约个时间。”

“好，就这么办。”他说着，拿起书来，转身要走。

可他又把身子扭了回来，问道：

“如果你对一位年轻小姐讲话——譬如说，对丽茜·史密斯小姐讲话，你称她‘丽茜小姐’还是‘史密斯小姐’？”

“称她‘史密斯小姐’。”管理员以权威的口气说，“一定要称她‘史密斯小姐’，直至你和她混熟。”

就这样，马丁·伊登解决了自己的问题。

他在电话上结结巴巴地问露丝他什么时候可以去还借来的书，而露丝的回答是：“什么时候都可以，我整个下午都在家。”

她亲自来门口迎接他，以女性的目光立刻发现他的裤子烫了缝，并隐约觉得他身上起了细微的变化，那是朝好的方面转变。同时，她被他的那张面孔所深深打动。他的虎虎生气似乎从体内奔涌而出，滚滚向她冲来。她又一次感到一阵冲动，直想靠到他身上去摄取温暖；又一次觉得惊奇，不知他为什么会对自己产生如此大的影响。而他接触到她那只迎接他的手，也又一次飘飘欲仙，感到无比喜悦。两人之间的区别在于：她冷静和沉着，而他的脸都红到了头发根处。他步履蹒跚，笨拙地跟在她身后，膀子左右摇晃，东倒西歪的走路姿势叫人替他捏一把汗。

来到客厅里坐下，他才开始觉得自如了些，而且自如得出乎他的意料。她的举止令他感到轻松；而她的那种体贴人的善良心肠使得他对她的爱更加疯狂。他们先从他借去的那两本书谈起，接着谈到了深受他爱戴的斯温伯恩以及令他费解的勃朗宁。她把谈话从一个话题引向另一个话题，同时在心里考虑着如何帮助他。自从他们初次相逢，她就常常思考这个问题，因为她很想对他有所帮助。他引起了她的怜悯和一片柔情，而这在以前是从来没有过的；不过，她的怜悯并非看低对方，而是一种母性般的感情。她的怜悯绝非普普通通的怜悯，因为激起她怜悯的是一个男子气概十足的人，这个人令她震惊，给她带来种种恐惧，使她心惊肉跳、脉搏扑扑颤动，叫她生出怪诞的念头和感情。他的脖子还是那样诱人，使她甜蜜蜜地思想着要把手放到上面去。这仍旧像是一种荒唐的冲动，但她已经习以为常。她想不到新生的爱会以这种形式表现出来，也想不到他在她心中激起的那份感情竟然是爱。她以为自己对他感兴趣只是因为他是一个具有种种潜在优点的不同寻常的人罢了，所以，她甚至觉得自己在行慈善之事。

她不知道自己渴望得到他，可情况对他就不同了。他清楚他爱她，对她的欲望比以往在生活中对任何东西的欲望都要强烈。他过去爱好诗歌，只是为了欣赏到美，可自从和她结识以后，通往爱情诗广阔原野的那扇门便大大敞开了。她帮助他理解到的东西，甚至比盖莱的勃尔芬区还要多。“狂热的恋人愿为一吻而死”——这样的诗行，要在一个星期前，他恐怕连想也不愿多想，可现在却始终萦绕在他心间。诗的奇妙及真实性令他惊叹不已，因为当他以目光注视着她的时候，他知道自己心甘情愿为一吻而死。他觉得自己就是一个狂热的恋人，并感到无比自豪，不管授给他什么样的骑士爵位都不会使他产生这样的感觉。他终于懂得了生活的真谛，知道了自己为什么诞生于人世。

他注视着她，倾听着她讲话，心里生出一个个大胆的念头。他回味着刚才在大门口同她握手时，自己的那一番欣喜若狂的感觉，渴望着再来那么一次。他的目光不时都会移到她的芳唇上；他多么希望能吻吻那两个唇片啊。不过，这种愿望当中不包含有一丝一毫低级下流的东西。她说话时，望着她那两片嘴唇的一翕一动，他感到兴奋异常。那嘴唇不是一般男女的那种普通嘴唇，不单纯是血肉的组合。它们是纯精神性质的嘴唇，所以他对这两个唇片的欲望迥然不同于那种诱惑他去亲吻其他女人的欲望。他渴望亲吻她的芳唇，把自己的吻印在上面，但他所怀的是一种高尚和庄严的感情，就像一个人去亲吻上帝的圣袍。他没觉察到自己的内心产生了这样的价值观，也不知道他望着她的时候，眼睛里闪射出的正是所有的男人在爱欲中烧时眼神里所带有的那种光芒。他意想不到他的目光是那样炽烈和富于男性气概，也意想不到自己的目光中那热情的火焰会影响到她的心灵。她那晶莹清澈的纯洁性装点了他的感情，使其升华，令他的思想如寒星般高雅；他要是知道自己眼里射出的光芒变成了股股热潮涌遍她的全身，激起同样的热情，一定会大吃一惊。他的目光一次又一次微妙地影响着她，不知为什么，总是甜丝丝地打断她的思路，随后又督促她去寻找尚未表达完的观点。她平素讲话一向轻松自如，所以，她如若不是觉得他绝非平庸之辈才这般使她心乱神移，一定会感到困惑不解。她对外界印象十分敏感，难怪一个来自于另一世界的旅人竟会对她产生如此大的影响。

她的意识深处在斟酌着如何帮助他，所以她把谈话引向那个方向；可首先提出这个问题的还是马丁自己。

“不知你能不能给我提些建议？”他这样问道，看到对方表示默许，心里便不由扑扑乱跳，“上次我来这儿时，曾说过我谈论不了书本一类的东西，因为我不知怎样谈才好，这些你还记得吗？回去后，我想了很多，而且到图书馆去了许多趟。书倒是看了不少，但大半都读不懂意思。也许，我应该从头开始。我从未享受过优越的条件，自小便苦苦干活。自打和图书馆结下了缘分，开始以新的眼光去看书——也包括看新书——，我得出了这样的结论：自己以前看的书不对劲。举个例子来说，牧场和轮船上的那类书与你们家的书就不一样。唉，我所习惯的就是看那一类书。还有——我可不是吹牛，我和我的那伙人是不同的。这倒不是说，我比那帮子和我一道走南闯北的水手及牛倌强到哪里去——要知道，我自己也放过一段时间的牛——，不过，我一直都喜欢看书，搞到什么书就看什么书。所以嘛——，我觉得自己跟他们大多数人的想法就不一样。

“啧，让我谈谈心里话吧。我从来都没进过这样的房子。一个星期前我到这里来，看到这一切，看到你、你的母亲以及你的两个弟弟，还有一什一物，我都打心眼里喜欢。以前听说过这种生活，在有些书上也看到过，当时我环顾了一下你们家，觉得书本上的东西变成了现实。我想说的是，我喜欢这种生活，希望能得到它，现在就想得到。我希望能呼吸上你们家里这样的空气——这种气氛里到处都是书画以及漂亮的东西，人们低声讲话、穿戴干净、思想纯洁。平时我所呼吸的空气中弥漫着饭菜、房租、垃圾和黄汤的气息，人们谈论的也全是这些。上次当你走上前去吻你的母亲时，我心想那是我所见到的最美好的景象。我见过不少世面，从某种程度而言，我比我们那伙大多数人见的世面要多得多。我喜欢见世面，见更多的世面，而且要见不同的世面。

“瞧，我还没扯到正题上呢。是这样的：我想过上你们家的这种生活，因为生活不仅仅是灌黄汤、苦干和四处流浪。可是，怎么样才能如愿以偿呢？从何处入手呢？我愿靠自己的努力去争取；要知道，若论苦干，一般人都不是我的对手。只要干起活，我可以昼夜连轴转。我竟然向你请教这些，也许让你觉得可笑。我知道，这个世界上最不该问的就是你，可我不晓得还有谁可以讨教——除了阿瑟。也许，我该去问他。如果我——”

他的话音消失了。一想到他去向阿瑟请教很可能会导致可怕的后果，弄得他自己丢乖露丑，他决心要讲出的话便戛然而止了。露丝并未马上开口，因为她正在全神贯注地想把他结结巴巴、粗声粗气的话语及其简单的思想内容与他脸上的表情联系到一起。她从未见过，人的眼睛竟能显示出如此大的力量。她从这个人的眼里看得出，他什么事情都能够办到，这与他拙嘴笨舌的表达力极不相符。她本人的头脑过于复杂和敏锐，以至于她无法公正地评价简单的头脑。可她发现对方的头脑在探索中显示出了力量。她似乎看到一个巨人在痛苦地扭动身躯，试图挣脱束缚着他的镣铐。待她开口说话时，脸上布满了怜悯的表情。

“你自己也意识得到，你所需要的是接受教育。应该回过头把小学上完，然后念中学和大学。”

“可是那得花钱呀。”他插话说。

“嗨！”她叫出了声，“这我可没考虑到。不过，你总有亲戚或什么人资助你吧？”

他摇了摇头。

“我父母已经去世。我有一个姐姐，已嫁了人，还有一个妹妹，大概马上也会嫁人。我在弟兄中最小，有一长串哥哥，可他们谁的忙也不帮。他们自顾自，浪迹天涯海角。老大亡身于印度，有两个哥哥现在南非，另外一个在海上捕鲸，还有一个在马戏团里演空中飞人，随团周游世界。我想，我跟他们是一个样。我十一岁时母亲去世，我就开始自己照料自己。我看，我非得自学不可；我想知道的是从何处入手。”

“让我说，当务之急是搞一本语法书来。你的语法真是——”她原本要说“糟糕”，但却改口说成了“不十分好”。

他飞红了脸，汗水直冒。

“我知道，我一定是用了许多俚语以及你不理解的词。可是，我只会用这类语言，只会这样说话。我脑子里倒装了些从书中学来的词，只是不会发音，所以就用不成。”

“问题不在于你说什么，而在于怎么说。我的话直了些，你不会介意吧？我并不想刺伤你的自尊心。”

“不介意，不介意，”他嚷嚷道，心中暗暗感激她的好意，“尽管说吧。我反正非得搞清不可，与其从旁人口中听到，倒不如向你讨教。”“那好吧。你说You was，其实应该说You were。你把I saw，说成了I seen。再者，你还用了双重否定——”

“双重否定是怎么回事？”他问。接着，他又自卑地说：“你瞧，我甚至连你的解释都听不懂。”

“恐怕我还没解释呢，”她笑了笑说，“双重否定即——让我想想——比如，你说Never helped nobody。Never是否定词，而nobody也是否定词。根据语法规则，双重否定等于肯定。Never helped nobody的意思是‘从不帮无人的忙’，那就是说一定帮了某人的忙。”“解释得非常清楚，”他说道，“我以前可从没想到过。但这并不表示着他们就一定帮了某人的忙吧？我觉得，Never helped nobody说明不了他们是否帮了某人的忙。以前我从未朝这方面想过，往后再不这样说了。”

他头脑敏捷、思维准确，叫她又高兴又惊讶。一旦理出头绪，他不仅能理解她的话，而且可以纠正她的错误。

“这些在语法书上都能找得到。”她继续说，“你说话时，我还注意到一个问题。你把don’t用得也不得当。Don’t是个缩略形式，代表着两个词。知道是哪两个词吗？”

他略加思忖，然后答道：“Do和not。”

她点了点头，接着说：“你在该用does not的地方，却用了don’t。”他感到困惑不解，没立刻弄明白。

“给我举个例子吧。”他请求道。

“这个——”她边思考，边皱起眉头和噘起小嘴，而他在一旁观察着她，觉得她的表情可爱极了，“例如，It don’t do to be hasty.把don’t换成do not，全句就该读It do not do to be hasty，而这听起来荒唐透顶。”

他把这个问题在心里琢磨和思考着。

“你不觉得刺耳吗？”她问。

“说不上刺耳（Can’t say that it does）。”他慎重地回答。

“你为什么不说Can’t say that it do呢？”她问。

“那样让人听起来不对头。”他慢吞吞地说，“至于刚才的那一句，我还是拿不准是对是错。大概是因为我的耳朵和你的不一样，未经过训练吧（ain’t had the trainin）。”

“根本就没有ain’t这个词。”她一字一板地强调说。

马丁又红了脸。

“还有，你把been说成ben，”她继续指教着，“把I came说成I come；另外，你总是将词尾砍掉，真是太糟糕了。”

“怎么解释呢？”他把身子前倾，恨不得跪倒在这位智力超群的才女面前，“我怎么砍词尾了？”

“你不把词尾念出来。And的拼写是a-n-d，你却把它念成an；ing的拼写是i-n-g，你有时念ing，而有时却将g砍掉。还有，你惯于砍掉词首的字母和双元音，发出的音模模糊糊。Them的拼写是t-h-e-m，而你却念成——嗨，算啦，没必要一一列举。你需要的是学语法。我去给你找本书，告诉你如何入手。”

当她立起身时，他脑海里闪过了自己在礼节书上看过的一段话，于是也笨拙地站了起来，可他心里却又顾虑重重，生怕这样做不合适，让对方误以为他要告辞。

“顺便问一声，伊登先生，”她走出房间时，回过头来高声发问，“什么是‘黄汤’？这个词你说过好几遍。”

“噢，黄汤，”他笑了起来，“那是俚语，意思是指威士忌和啤酒——反正是能让你喝醉的饮料。”

“瞧，又出问题啦。”她也笑了起来，“当不涉及个人的时候，不要用‘你’字。‘你’字完全是涉及个人的，你刚才的用法未能精确地表达你的意思。”

“这我可不懂了。”

“你刚才对我说：‘威士忌和啤酒——反正是能让你喝醉的饮料。’让我喝醉？这你还不明白吗？”

“是能让你喝醉，不对吗？”

“对当然是对，”她笑了笑说，“不过最好别把我扯进去。如果用‘人’替代‘你’字，听起来就会好得多。”

她把语法书取来，将一把椅子拖到他跟前——他思量着是否应该帮她搬一下椅子——在他身旁坐了下来。她翻动着书页，而两人的头凑在一起。她讲述着他必须做的工作，可他硬是听不进去，因为她近在身旁，叫他又惊又喜。可是，待她开始讲解动词变位的重要性时，他忘掉了她的诱惑。他以前从没听说过什么动词变位，而今聆听到一些有关语言构造的指教，便一下子着了迷。他把脸凑近书本，觉得她的秀发轻拂在他的面颊上。他一辈子只昏倒过一次，而现在感到自己又快要昏过去了。他简直有些透不过气来了，因为心脏把血液输送到喉管处，使他感到窒息。她似乎从来没有像现在这样容易接近过。刹那间，横在他们之间的那道宽阔的鸿沟上架起了桥梁。可是，他对她的感情还是那般圣洁。她并未降格屈就他，而是他攀上祥云，赶到了她身旁。在这一瞬间，他对她的崇敬简直跟教徒的敬畏和狂热不差上下。在他看来，他好像闯入了神界仙境，于是，他小心翼翼地慢慢把头移开，免得再触到她那似电流般令他震颤的秀发，而她对这一切却毫无察觉。

[1]　以一物为课税对象，废除其他捐税。

[2]　一种神秘学派，提倡轮回学说，研究人神媾通。

[3]　自然主义伦理学派的主张，认为“天理”即道德标准。

[4]　勃拉伐茨基夫人（1831—1891）是俄国神智学者，生平足迹遍及欧美两洲，先在纽约成立神智学会，后把总会迁往印度，去世时，信徒达十万之众。《秘密教义》是她的重要著作。

[5]　19世纪末美国教育家兼作家。

[6]　19世纪美国著名作家。

第八章

几个星期的时光过去了。在这段时间里，马丁·伊登一方面钻研语法和温习关于礼节的书籍，一方面还大量阅读自己所喜欢的书。对于他那个阶层的人，他一个都不见。莲花俱乐部的姑娘们不知他出了什么事，缠住吉姆问这问那；而在赖利家寻衅闹事的那群家伙中，有几个对马丁不再露面感到很高兴。另外，他在图书馆又发现了一本宝贵的书。语法书向他揭示的是语言结构的奥秘，而这本书揭示的则是诗歌的结构。于是，他开始研究诗的韵律、结构和格式，因为他不仅喜欢美，还喜欢弄清为什么美。他还发现了一部现代作品，这部作品把诗歌作为一种描写性艺术详加论述，选用了优秀文学作品中的大量例子。以前看小说时，他可从没有像研读这些书一样怀着如此高涨的热情。他头脑清新，因为这副头脑二十年来未负过重荷，而现在受到强烈欲望的驱动，便牢牢抓住他所读到的东西，其充沛的精力是学生的头脑不常有的。

站在今天的高度朝回看，他觉得自己所熟悉的那个旧世界，那个由陆地、海洋、船只、水手和恶女人组成的世界，显得十分渺小；可是，那个世界与眼前的新世界交织在一起，就会变成广阔的天地。他的心向往着两者的统一；当他最初看到两个世界的接触点时，他感到十分惊讶。他在书中看到了高雅的思想和美，而他自己也因此而变得崇高起来。这使他比过去更加坚定地相信，在他的上面，在露丝一家的那个社会里，无论男女都怀着这种思想和体现着这种思想。而在他的那个下层社会里则生活着一些卑贱的人，他渴望脱胎换骨，把污染了他一生的卑贱品质清洗干净，跻身于上流阶层的那个高雅的王国。他的整个童年时代及青年时期都笼罩着一种朦胧的不安情绪；他一直弄不明白自己到底想得到什么，但他的确有所渴望，并进行过徒劳无益的追求，直至遇到露丝。而今，他的不安情绪更加强烈，给他带来更大的痛苦，因为他终于确切、清晰地了解到，自己执着追求的是美、才智和爱情。

这几个星期里，他见过露丝五六面，每次见面都给他以新的鼓舞。她帮他学英语，为他纠正发音，并着手教给他算术。不过，他们的交往并不局限于基础性的学习。他生活阅历广、思想成熟，所以绝不会仅仅满足于学习分数、立方根、研究和分析词句；有时，他们的谈话会转到别的题目上去——讨论他刚刚读到的诗歌以及她新近研究过的诗人。当她把自己喜爱的诗章朗诵给他听时，他便喜不自禁，像到了天堂一样。他听过女人们讲话，但没有一个有她这样动听的声音。她的声音，不管有多么低，都会激起他的爱，而她吐出的一词一字都会叫他兴奋和心跳。她的音色、和谐的结构以及悦耳的抑扬顿挫，是修养和一颗高雅灵魂的结晶，既柔和华美，又令人难以捉摸。他聆听着她讲话，回忆起往事来，耳边响起那些野蛮泼妇刺耳的吼声，响起那些女工及他那个阶层中年轻姑娘的虽不很刺耳但却十分尖厉的喊叫声。随后，幻象开始出现，她们鱼贯掠过他的脑海，每一个人和露丝作一比较，都会给露丝的形象增添一份光辉。他的喜悦心情也在逐渐升级，因为他发现她不仅能理解所读书中的思想，而且在欣赏到优美的词句时还激动得发抖。她常给他读《公主》一书，而他常见她热泪盈眶，因为她天生的审美感就是这么敏锐。在这种时刻，她的感情使他也得到升华，把他变成一个超凡的人；他注视着她，倾听着她的话语，就像是在观察生活的本来面目和发掘生活最深奥的秘密。他意识到自己的感情已上升到微妙的高度，断定这就是爱情，而爱情是世界上最伟大的东西。回首以往，他过去所经历过的惊险和火热的场面——醇酒的陶醉、女人的爱抚、打架闹事以及生与死的搏斗——会从他的记忆长廊里一一通过；可是，跟他现在正体味的崇高热情相比较，过去的经历便显得微不足道和庸俗无聊。

这种情况露丝是注意不到的。她从未有过爱情的体验，而她在这方面的知识全都源自书本，书的作者根据幻想，把日常的生活片断引入非现实的童话王国；她不知道，这位粗鲁的水手正在潜入她的心房，在那儿积聚力量，总有一天这力量会爆发出来，似团团烈火燃遍她的全身。她不懂得真正的爱情之火是什么，因为她对爱情的理解仅局限在理论上。她把爱情看作闪烁的光焰，轻柔有如露水的滴落或静水中的涟漪，静谧有如黑色天鹅绒似的夏季夜空。在她的心目中，爱是一种比较温柔的感情，向心爱的人献上一片温馨，周围的气氛是花香馥郁、光影迷离和幽雅宁静。她想象不到会有火山爆发似的爱，想象不到爱情会释放出高温，将周围的一切化为焦土。她既不了解她自己，也不了解这个世界；生活对她来说犹如梦幻的海洋。父母的伉俪之情就是她心目中理想的爱情模式；她盼望着有那么一天，自己能够安宁、和谐地同一位心上人一道步入这种静谧和甜蜜的生活。

所以，她把马丁·伊登看作一个新奇和陌生的人，就连他对她产生的影响，她也觉得新奇和陌生。这是再自然不过的了。同样，她看到动物园里的野兽，听到狂风的怒吼，或者看到令人颤抖的道道闪电，也会产生非同寻常的感觉。这类现象有一种广泛性的因素，而他的身上也有一种广泛性的因素。他来到她身边，吐露着浩瀚天空和广阔原野的气息。他脸上带着热带太阳的熊熊烈火，那高高隆起、富有弹性的肌肉里充满了原始的生命力。他的那个神秘世界遥远得超出了她的想象，那是一个充斥着粗鲁人和暴力事件的世界，所以他才遍体鳞伤。他桀骜不驯、粗暴狂野，可是对她却俯首帖耳，这无形中满足了她的虚荣心。同时，她产生了一般人都具有的想驯服野兽的冲动。这是一种不知不觉的冲动，是她根本想象不到的；她的愿望是按父亲的形象重新塑造他，因为她认为父亲的形象是世界上最完美的。由于缺乏经验，她无法知道，她从他身上感觉到的广泛性因素最广泛地存在于万物之中；爱情可以把男人和女人从天南地北吸引到一处，可以驱使处于发情期的公鹿自相残杀，甚至还可以使元素跟元素不可抗拒地化合。

他神速的进步既叫人感到惊讶，又使人产生浓厚的兴趣。她在他身上发现了意想不到的优秀品质，而这些优秀品质似鲜花一样，栽在适宜的泥土里，便一天天茁壮成长。她给他朗读勃朗宁的作品，而他常对属于争论性的章节做上些古怪的解释，叫她如坠五里雾中。她压根想不到，他无论是对男人、女人还是生活都有着丰富的经验，所以他的解释常常比她的正确。他的观点在她看来是幼稚的，可是她又常常为他那大胆狂放的理解而兴奋不已；他的理解以星空为轨道，范围无比辽阔，叫她跟也跟不上，只好坐在那里，在捉摸不定的力量冲击下战栗。后来她弹琴给他听——这回不是刺激他，而是想用音乐试探他，因为音乐能达到她本人所无法达到的深度。他天生向往音乐，就像花朵向往阳光。他过去听的是工人阶级的拉格泰姆乐曲和小调，现在听的则是她弹得差不多滚瓜烂熟的古典乐曲，这是一个急剧的变化。然而，他跟一般的听众一样，流露出对瓦格纳[1]乐曲的喜爱；当她解释了《汤豪叟》[2]的序曲时，一下就让他着了迷，而她弹奏的其他曲子从未赢得他如此青睐。这阕曲子直接反映出了他的生活。他的过去就是“维纳丝堡”主题曲，而他则把她视为一阕“朝圣者合唱曲”；他被合唱曲带入一个崇高的境界，然后继续凌空飞翔，前往广阔、朦胧的精神王国，那儿善与恶之间进行着永久的战争。

有时候，他的提问会使她心中产生疑窦，一时怀疑自己对音乐的解释和观点是否正确。可是在听她唱歌时，他却从不提问题，因为她的歌完全表现的是她自己。她那纯正的女高音唱出的回肠荡气的曲子，每一次都使他心醉神迷。他会不由自主地把她的歌声与营养不良、缺乏训练的女工那难听的尖嗓门及刺耳的颤音作比较，与沿海口岸那些被烈性酒烧坏了嗓子的娘们所发出的沙哑叫声作比较。她喜欢为他唱歌和弹琴。说实话，她这是第一次同一个人的灵魂打交道，而改变他那可塑的灵魂会给人带来欢乐。她认为自己正在重新塑造他的灵魂，而且她的意图是好的。再说，和他在一起使她感到快乐。他并未引起她的厌恶之心。最初的那种反感其实只是她对隐秘的自我的一种恐惧，而今这种恐惧已烟消云散。她虽然并不知道，但她已经感到自己对他具有控制权。再说，他对她产生的是良好的影响。她在大学里刻苦学习，可一旦钻出无聊的书堆，他的出现便如清新的海风拂面吹来，似乎使她力量倍增。力量！她需要力量，而他把力量慷慨地奉送给她。和他同处一间房屋，或者到门口迎接他，就是获取生命的动力。他走后，她会带着更大的热忱和新补充的精力回到书本上。

她熟悉勃朗宁的作品，然而却从未想到过和灵魂打交道是件棘手的事情。她对马丁的兴趣愈来愈浓厚，而重新塑造他的生活成了她的强烈愿望。

“有个勃特勒先生，”一天下午，等到把语法书、算术书及诗集都搁置一旁时，她这样说道，“起初，相对而言，他的条件一点也不好。他父亲是个银行出纳员，后来染上痨病，拖了好几年，死在了亚利桑那州。他这一死，勃特勒先生（他叫查尔斯·勃特勒）在这个世界上就成了孤零零一个人。要知道，他父亲来自澳洲，所以他在加利福尼亚举目无亲。我听他多次提起，他一开始进一家印刷所打工，每星期挣三块钱。而现在，他的年薪至少有三万块钱。他老实、忠厚、勤奋和节俭，对大多数年轻人所醉心的享受娱乐从不问津。他立志每星期都要攒一笔钱，不管做出什么样的牺牲他都愿意。当然，他每星期的收入很快就超过了三块钱，而随着工资的提高，他积攒的钱数也愈来愈大。

“他白天干活，晚间上夜校，总是着眼于未来。后来，他进了夜晚中学。他当时年仅十七，就有一笔可观的固定收入，但他是个有抱负的人，渴望的是事业，而不是糊口的生计，所以情愿为了远大目标牺牲眼前的利益。他选中了法律，来到我父亲的事务所当勤务员——你想想吧！每个星期的工资只有四块钱。但他已学会了精打细算，就是这四块钱里他还要省出些钱来。”

她停下来想喘口气，同时注意着马丁的反应。他对勃特勒先生年轻时代的奋斗史很感兴趣，脸上闪着亮光，但也皱起了眉头。

“让我说，这对一个年轻人可真够艰苦的。”他评论道，“啧，一星期只有四块钱！他可怎么活呀？我敢肯定，他任何讲究都不会有。我现在每星期就要交五块钱的膳宿费，而且这还是极普通的。他的日子一定过得猪狗不如，他吃的东西——”

“他用一个小煤油炉子自己做饭吃。”她打岔道。

“比远洋轮船上水手的伙食更糟的不会多，可他吃的东西一定还不如轮船上最差的饭菜。”

“可是你想想他现在的情况吧！”她激动地叫喊道，“想想他现在的收入能给他提供多大的方便，早年的牺牲而今得到了一千倍的补偿。”马丁用犀利的目光望着她。

“有一点我可以和你打赌，”他说，“那就是勃特勒先生现在虽然富裕了，但绝不会享受。他当时年纪还小，多年来却吃得那么差，我敢说他现在的肠胃不会好到哪里去。”

在他那疑问的目光注视下，她垂下了眼睑。

“我敢打赌他如今落下了消化不良症！”马丁步步紧逼地说。

“不错，是这样，”她承认道，“不过——”

“我打赌，”马丁一口气说了下去，“他严肃和古板得像一只老猫头鹰，尽管年收入有三万块钱，却不懂得吃喝玩乐。我还敢打赌，看到别人享受生活，他不一定会感到高兴。我说得对吗？”

她点头表示同意，然后却急忙解释说：

“他不属于那类人，因为他天性沉稳和严肃。他一贯都是这个样子。”“你可以这样说他，”马丁言称，“每星期挣三块钱，后来又挣四块钱，一个小孩子家为了攒钱竟用煤油炉子自己煮饭吃，白天劳动一天，晚上还学习，光是埋头干活，从不玩耍，从不享乐，也不知道怎样享乐——他的三万块钱的确来得太迟了。”

他那丰富的想象力飞快地运转，脑海里马上闪现出了成千上万种情景，概括了那孩子的生活，概括了那个心地狭窄的孩子成长为年收入三万块钱的富翁之过程。通过这一番敏捷、广泛和繁杂的思索，查尔斯·勃特勒的一生全都集中到了他的眼前。

“你知道吗？”他继续说道，“我为勃特勒先生感到难过。他当时年少不更事，放弃了生活中的乐趣，全都是为了这三万块钱的年收入，而现在有了这笔钱却于事无补。三万块钱是个大数目，可是却抵不上他小时候用攒下的一角钱就能买到的东西——水果糖、花生或者一张楼厅上的戏票。”

这些独特的观点令露丝感到吃惊，不仅因为这是一些新颖的观点，与她的信仰背道而驰，也因为连她自己也觉得他的看法里包含着点点滴滴的真理，很可能会推翻或改变她的见解。如果她的年龄不是二十四岁，而是十四岁，她也许会改变主张；可她已二十四岁，无论在天性上还是教养上都是保守的，已经被夹在了那条她出生和成长的生活狭缝里。他那古怪的见解刚一出口，的确扰乱了她的心，可她把这归结为他是个奇特的人、过的是奇特生活的缘故，很快便淡忘了。不过，她虽然不同意他的观点，但他说话时表现出的力量、闪闪发光的眼睛以及认真的表情，却令她激动不已，时时在吸引着她。她永远也不会想到，这个来自于她那个世界以外的人，此时此刻所产生的观念比她的世界更辽阔、更深邃。她的眼光受到她那个世界的限制；而鼠目寸光的人只会觉得别人身上有局限性。所以，她认为自己的视野非常广阔，认为他和她的观点上的冲突标志着他的思想局限性。她想帮助他像她一样看问题，扩大他的视野，使他的眼光与她的一样。

“我还没有讲完呢。”她说道，“他工作起来，据父亲说，没有一个勤杂员能比得上。勃特勒先生总是怀着一股工作热情，从不迟到，通常提前十分钟就赶到办公室。可是他对自己的时间却非常吝啬，业余时间分分秒秒都用到学习上。他学习簿记和打字，晚上则给一位法院记者口述稿件，帮他练习速记，挣点钱交付自己的速记课程学费。他很快就当上了办事员，并成为一个不可多得的人才。父亲很赏识他，看出他定会平步青云。他接受父亲的建议，到法学院读书，后来当上了律师。他刚一回到事务所，父亲就拉他当了年轻的合伙人。他是个栋梁之材。国家参议员屡次请他，均遭到他的拒绝。父亲说，只要他愿意，最高法院的法官席位一有空缺，他就可以就职。这样的人生经历对我们大家都是一种勉励，它告诉我们，一个有志向的人可以从逆境中崛起。”

“他是个了不起的人物。”马丁诚恳地说。

然而他却觉得，这段故事里有些东西和他的审美观以及对人生的看法格格不入。在勃特勒先生那节俭和艰苦的生活中，他无法找到恰当的动机。如果他那样做是为了爱一个女人或者为了追求美，马丁是能够理解的。疯狂的恋人可以万死不辞嘛，但那是为了一吻，而不是为了三万块钱的年收入。所以，他对勃特勒先生的经历不以为然，觉得其中有不足为训的因素。一年挣三万块钱固然是件好事，但落下消化不良症，又加之不会享受人间乐趣，便把这笔可观收入的全部价值一笔勾销。

他把这种看法大体向露丝讲了讲，结果让她感到震惊，使她明白还需要做更多的改造工作。她所具有的是一种普遍的褊狭思想；这种思想使人们确信只有他们自己的肤色、信念和政见才是优秀和正确的，而散布在世界其他地方的人却不如他们幸运。正是这种褊狭的思想，使古代的犹太男人感谢上帝没有让他们投做女胎，使现代传教士以上帝代言人的身份跑遍天涯海角；也正是这种思想，使露丝渴望改变这个来自生活另一条狭缝的人，把他塑造得和她那条狭缝里的人一模一样。

[1]　瓦格纳（1813—1883），德国歌剧大师。

[2]　歌剧《汤豪叟》为瓦格纳的早期杰作，描写主人公汤豪叟被妖女所惑，在维纳丝堡过着声色犬马的生活，后来觉悟了，遂以朝圣者的身份到罗马去请求教皇赦免，而教皇说，除非他手里的手杖开花，才能赦免他的罪过。汤豪叟失望之余，想回维纳丝堡去，恰逢一队出殡的行列从身旁经过，方才知道他的爱人已为他忧愁而死。汤豪叟扑倒在爱人的棺材上，当场死去。一队朝圣者自罗马返回，带来汤豪叟的手杖，上面开着花，说明他的罪过已被赦免。该剧序曲以“朝圣者合唱曲”开始，接着是“维纳丝堡”主题的迷人曲调，最后仍以“合唱曲”作结尾。

第九章

马丁·伊登从海上归来，怀着一种恋人的欲望回到加利福尼亚。他曾在积攒的钱花完之后，登上了那条寻宝的帆船当水手；探险队用了八个月的时间也没找到财宝，于是便在所罗门群岛散了摊。大家在澳洲领了报酬后，马丁立刻搭了一条远洋轮回旧金山。这八个月里挣的钱，不仅够他在陆地上住许多日子，还可以助他从事大量的学习和阅读。

他具有学者的头脑，而他在学习方面的才智却是以他不屈不挠的天性以及他对露丝的爱作为后盾。他随身带着语法书，一遍一遍地复习，直到他那精力充沛的大脑掌握为止。他留意到同船的伙伴们讲起话来不顾语法，于是便在心里对他们的粗糙语言进行矫正和修改。他异常惊喜地发现他的耳朵愈来愈敏锐，正在形成对语法的感觉。双重否定结构像噪音一样让他听起来刺耳，可由于缺乏实践，这种刺耳的话往往从他自己的嘴里漏出。他的舌头硬是不肯一下子就用上新学到的技巧。

他把语法书反复看过之后，就开始阅读词典，每天给自己的词汇库增加二十个单词。他发现这可不是件轻松的工作，于是在掌舵和值班守望时，便一遍遍地温习那越来越长的注音和词义表，每次睡觉都是在默记中进入梦乡。他把never did anything、if I were以及those things这些短语和诸多的词尾变化，反复地默念，为的是使自己的舌头适应露丝讲的那种语言。他把and和ing念了不知有几千遍，反复重读d和g这两个音；他惊奇地注意到，他讲的英语已经逐渐比高级船员以及客舱里那些资助探险的绅士冒险家的英语还要纯正、还要精确。

船长是个目光呆滞的挪威人，他不知从何处搞到一部莎士比亚全集，然而却从没看过。马丁为他洗衣服，获得了他的允许，才能够阅读到这部珍贵的书卷。一时间，他陶醉在剧情中，陶醉在许多他所喜爱的诗章中，而这些几乎毫不费事地就印在了他的脑海里；他觉得好像整个世界都改变了形状，变成了莎士比亚的悲喜剧，他的思想则成为自由诗。他的鉴别力由此而受到训练，使他能够敏锐地欣赏高雅的英语；但同时，这样的阅读又把大量的古旧词和废弃词灌进了他的大脑。

这八个月得到了很好的利用，他不仅学会了讲正确的语言和思考高深的问题，还充分地了解了自己。以前他因孤陋寡闻而自惭形秽，如今却对自己的力量产生了信心。他觉得自己和同船的伙伴之间存在着极大的差异，并且明智地看出这种差异是在潜力上，而非成就上。他能做的事情他们也能做；然而，他感到心里有一团混沌的酵母在活动，这团酵母告诉他：他身上有潜力，能干出更多的事情来。这个世界那精彩的美景撩拨着他的心，他多么希望露丝能和他一道分享这一切。他决心把南海的旖旎风光好好地向她描绘一番。想到这里，创作的欲望在他心里熊熊燃烧，怂恿他把这种美展现给比露丝更广大的民众。于是，一个伟大的念头闪着金光披着异彩诞生了。他要写作，成为全世界的人用来观看的眼睛，用来倾听的耳朵以及用来感受的心脏。他要写——什么都写——诗歌、散文、小说、描写文，还有莎士比亚的那种剧本。这就是事业，就是赢得露丝的道路。文学家是这个世界的巨人，他认为他们要比一年挣三万块钱、只要愿意就能当最高法院法官的勃特勒先生之流优秀得多。

这种思想萌发后，便主宰了他，使他在返回旧金山的路上像做梦一样。他为自己身上意想不到的力量而陶醉，感到自己无所不能。在辽阔和荒凉的大海上，他获得了正确观察事物的能力。他算是第一次看清了露丝以及她的世界。她的世界似一件具体的东西出现在他的脑海里，他可以捧在手中，翻来覆去看个仔细。这个世界虽有多处模糊和朦胧的地方，可他看的是整体而非局部，他还看到了征服这个世界的途径。写作！这念头令他遍体发热。他一回去就动笔，第一篇就写这次寻宝之行。他要把文章卖给旧金山的某家报馆。这事先不告诉露丝，要让她看到他的大名登在报上时，感到惊讶和喜悦。写作的同时，他还可以继续学习，每天都有二十四个小时哩。他是战无不胜的，知道怎样去工作，一切堡垒都会在他的面前崩塌。他再也不用作为水手游历大海了；刹那间，他产生了幻觉，似乎看到了一艘蒸汽游艇。别的有些作家不就是拥有自己的游艇嘛。当然啰，他告诫自己，一开始不能急于求成，能靠写作挣点钱维持学习就该满足了。过一段时间之后——很难说得清得过多长时间——待到学好本事、准备停当，他就会写出伟大的作品，而他的名字将受到万人称颂。但意义更重大、无限重大和最最重大的是，他将以此证明自己能配得上露丝。成名固然是件好事，但他是为了露丝才勾画出了如此瑰丽的梦境。他并非一个追名逐利的人，而仅仅是一个狂热的恋人。

他口袋里装着工钱，回到奥克兰，仍旧住在伯纳德·希金伯森家他的那个房间，接着便动手写作。他甚至没通知露丝他已经回来，因为他想待写完“寻宝记”再去看望她。要克制住自己不去见她并不困难，因为狂热的创作热情正在他心里燃烧。再说，他写的这篇文章会把她带到他身旁。他不知这篇文章该写多长，但他数了数《旧金山考察家报》星期日增刊以两个版面登载的一篇文章，以此作为标准。经三天白热化的苦干，他完成了初稿；但当他以容易辨认的大字体把文章仔细誊写完，却在一本由书馆借来的修辞书里发现了段落划分和引号这类讲究。这些他以前从没想到过；于是，他立即动手重写这篇文章，并时不时参考修辞书，一天内学到的作文知识比普通学生一年学的还多。他把写好的文章又誊了一遍，小心翼翼地卷起来，可看报时在一则初学写作者须知中发现了这样一种铁的规定：手稿不能卷，而且只能写在一面纸上。在这两方面他都违反了规定。他还从这则须知中了解到，第一流报纸的稿酬至少十块钱一个栏目。于是，在第三次誊稿时，他用十块钱乘以十个栏目，以此安慰自己，而得数算来算去都等于一百，他认为这比出海强。如果没出现错误，他三天便可以完稿。三天就是一百块钱呀！在海上挣这笔钱，得花三个月或更长的时间。他认为，一个人尽管不重视金钱，但如果会写作还出海，那才是傻瓜呢。钱的价值在于能给他带来自由，可以为他买到像样的衣服，而这一切使他更接近、迅速地接近那个改变了他的生活、赋予他灵感的苗条和白皙的姑娘。

他把手稿装入一个平平展展的信封里邮出，信封上写着“《旧金山考察家报》编辑收”。他以为凡是报馆收到的稿件，立刻就予以刊登，而他的手稿是星期五寄出，所以星期天大概就能够见报。他心想，露丝读到文章就会知道他已返回，那该有多妙啊。待到星期天下午，他便登门去看望她。与此同时，他在琢磨着另外一种想法，他自豪地觉得这是一个特别明智、谨慎和谦虚的想法。他打算为小朋友们写篇探险故事，卖给《少年之友》杂志。他到公共阅览室查阅了一下《少年之友》的合订本，发现这份周刊的系列故事通常分为五期登载，每期约三千字。他还发现有几篇系列故事分七期连载，于是就决定写篇同样长短的文章。

他参加过一次赴北冰洋的捕鲸航行——那次航行预计历时三年，但由于船只失事，半年就宣告结束了。他的想象力丰富，有时甚至离奇古怪，但他基本上还是热爱现实的，这一点就迫使他只写自己知道的事情。他熟悉捕鲸生活，于是根据自己掌握的真实材料，以两个男孩为主人公，开始写一篇虚构的历险记。待到星期六晚上，他觉得写作并非难事，因为他当天就为第一期的连载写了三千字。吉姆见了感到十分有趣，而希金伯森先生却公然冷嘲热讽，吃饭时不住嘴地嘲笑家里出现了一个“文化人”。

马丁自我安慰，想象着他姐夫星期天早晨打开《考察家报》，看到“寻宝记”时脸上所露出的惊奇表情。这天一大早，他亲自跑到大门口，心情激动地把那份多页报纸翻阅了一遍，接着又异常仔细地翻第二遍，最后将报纸折起，放回了原处。他暗自庆幸没向任何人讲起过这篇文章。他想了想，觉得自己以前的判断是错误的，文章不会这么快就登到报纸栏目中。另外，他的文章缺乏新闻价值，很可能编辑会写封信先向他挑明这一点。

早饭后，他继续写系列故事。字句从笔端涌出，但他也常常停下来查词典或参考修辞书。趁着这种间歇，他就一口气把文章通读一遍或两遍；令他聊以自慰的是，他表现的虽然并非心里所感受到的伟大事物，但不管怎样，他在训练自己如何构思和抒发情感。写到天黑时分，他跑到阅览室去查阅杂志和周刊，一直待到阅览室十点钟关门。这就是他一个星期来的安排：白天写三千字，而晚上则苦苦研读杂志，特别注意那些在编辑看来适宜登载的故事、杂文和诗歌，天天如此。有一点是肯定的：芸芸众作家们能写的，他也能写，而且只要给他时间，他还能拿出那些作家写不出的文章。一次，在《新书消息》上看到一段有关杂志撰稿人报酬问题的文章，内容讲的不是罗德雅德·吉卜林的稿酬每字一块钱，而是一流杂志每字最少出二分钱的稿费，他为此感到振奋。《少年之友》当然是一流杂志，以此算来，他当天写的三千字就可以给他带来六十块钱——相当于海上两个月的工钱！

星期五晚上，他完成了这篇长达两万一千字的系列故事。按每字二分钱计算，他将得到四百二十块钱。这一星期干得真不赖。他手头从未有过这许多钱，真不知怎样才能够花得光。他挖到了一个金矿，这儿有取之不尽的财宝源。他打算添几身衣服，多订点杂志，再买几十本参考书，因为眼下他不得不跑到图书馆查参考。可这四百二十块钱里还有一大部分花不出去。他绞尽脑汁，后来想出了一个解决的办法：为葛特露雇个用人，再为玛丽安买辆自行车。

他把这份厚厚的手稿邮寄给了《少年之友》。星期六下午，他构思了一篇关于潜水采珠的文章，然后前去看望露丝。露丝接到他的电话，亲自来到大门口迎接他。他身上散发出的勃勃生气是那样熟悉、那样火辣辣，猛烈地冲击着她。这股生气似乎钻入她体内，似暖流在她的血管里奔腾，散发出的力量令她颤抖不已。他握住她的手，望着她那蓝色的眼睛，不由兴奋得红了脸，幸好八个月的阳光晒出一片紫铜色，遮住了脸上的红潮。然而，这紫铜色却遮不住他的脖子上被硬领磨出的伤痕。她注意到了那红痕，心里觉得好笑。但瞧了瞧他的衣服，这种感觉很快便消失了。这是他第一次定做服装，穿上去的确合体，使他看起来身材更修长、模样更英俊。另外，原来的便帽被一顶礼帽所替代。此时，她吩咐他把礼帽戴上，然后夸他外表潇洒。根据她的记忆，她从未如此高兴过。他的变化是她一手造成的，她以此而自豪，同时心里燃起强烈愿望，想进一步帮助他。

但最彻底的变化、最让她高兴的变化，则发生在他的谈吐上。他说话不仅比以前准确，也比以前自如，增加了许多新词。可心情激动和热情高涨的时候，他又会犯老毛病，发含混不清的音以及吞掉词尾的辅音。而且，在试用学来的新词时，他常常迟疑不定，让人觉得别扭。另一方面，他除了说话自如，还表达出轻松、幽默的思想，让她听了感到高兴。过去他插科打诨和谈笑风生，在他那个阶层中很受宠，可到了她面前，由于缺乏词汇和训练，却发挥不出这种风度。现在他刚刚开始适应，开始感觉到自己并不完全是个闯入者。但他十分拘谨，拘谨得有些过了头，让露丝掌握谈话的火候和观点，自己只是随着，绝不敢越雷池一步。

他把他近来所做的事情讲给她听，说他打算靠写作谋生，同时也不放弃自己的学习。可她并没把他的蓝图当回事，连句赞成的话也没说，这叫他大失所望。

“要知道，”她坦率地说，“写作跟干别的事一样，是一种行业。当然，这倒不是说我懂写作，我仅仅根据普遍现象泛泛而论。要想当一名铁匠，非得学个三年五载不可！而作家的收入比铁匠高得多。所以人们趋之若鹜，喜欢写作和试着写作的也会多得多。”

“但如果我对写作有特别的素质，那会怎样呢？”他这样问道，同时，心里为自己的措辞感到得意；他那敏捷的想象力把眼前的场景、气氛以及一千幅自己生活中粗俗下流、野蛮凶残的场景一起投射到了一面庞大的银幕上。

这种混合的幻景像一道光样一闪而过。没有岔断他们的谈话，也没有干扰他冷静的思路。在想象的银幕上，他看到自己跟这位甜蜜、美丽的姑娘待在一个满是书籍和油画、充溢着高雅情调和文化气息的房间里，他们面对面以纯正的英语促膝交谈，而周围的一切都沐浴在永恒的灿烂光辉中；在这幕场景的四周，在银幕的最边缘处，则模糊地现出幅幅截然相反的场景，每幅场景都是一张图画，由他这个旁观者随心所欲地观看。这些场景透过飘浮的烟云以及缕缕在鲜亮夺目的红光照射下逐渐消失的惨雾，展现在他眼前。他看到一些牛仔在酒吧间喝烈性威士忌，嘴里不干不净地说着粗俗下流的话；他看到自己也和他们在一起，边喝酒边粗野地骂人，或者在冒着烟的油灯下跟他们一道围坐于桌旁斗牌，把赌博的筹码抛得咔嗒咔嗒山响。他还看到自己精光着上半身，赤手空拳跟利物浦红鬼在萨斯奎哈纳号的水手舱里打得不可开交；他还看到了约翰·罗吉斯号那血淋淋的甲板——在发生暴乱的那个灰蒙蒙的上午，大副躺在主舱舱盖上痛苦地垂死挣扎，而船长手里的左轮枪喷着火舌、冒着青烟，周围的那些气歪了脸、粗野地叫骂着的暴徒一个个倒下。接着，马丁把目光移回中央的那幅场景上——那儿沐浴着永恒的光，安静和清洁，他和露丝在书籍及油画的氛围里坐着交谈；他看到了那架大钢琴，而她将用那架钢琴为他弹奏；随后，他听到了自己那经过斟酌的正确词句在耳边回响：“但如果我对写作有特别的素质，那会怎样呢？”

“一个人不管具有怎样的当铁匠的特别素质，”她大笑着说，“我还从没听说过有哪个人未经学徒就能当铁匠。”

“那你的意见呢？”他问，“可别忘了，我觉得自己有这种写作的能力——我解释不清，但我知道自己有这样的才能。”

“你必须接受全面的教育，”她回答说，“不管你最终是否当作家。任你选择什么样的职业，这种教育是必不可少的，而且来不得半点马虎或粗糙。你应该进高中学习。”

“不错——”他刚要说话，就被她打断了，因为她又想出了这样一个建议：

“当然，你还可以同时搞搞写作嘛。”

“我不得不写下去。”他坚定地说。

“为什么？”她不理解地问，她不太喜欢他的这种一意孤行的顽固劲。

“因为不写作就上不成高中。要知道，我必须生活，还要买书和衣服。”

“这我倒忘了。”她笑着说，“你为什么不生下来就有一笔收入呢？”

“我情愿有健康的身体和丰富的想象力。”他回答道，“钱我可以挣得来，但在其他方面也得发达，这全是为了——”他差一点儿把“你”字说出来，可后来却改口说成“为了一个人而发达”。

“别说‘发达’，”她嚷嚷道，可爱地发了点小脾气，“这是俚语，听起来就让人反感。”

他红了脸，结巴着嘴说：“对，对，希望你时时纠正我。”

“我——我很乐意帮你，”她吞吞吐吐地说，“你身上有很多优点，我希望你能成为一个十全十美的人。”

他一下子变成了她手中的黏土，热烈地渴望由她来塑造自己，而她也渴望把他塑造成她理想中的人物形象。当她指出下个星期一正巧要举行高中入学考试时，他立刻表示自己一定去投考。

随后，她弹琴和唱歌给他听，而他带着如饥似渴般的欲望盯着她瞧，为她那可爱的表情而陶醉。他暗自思忖，她的身后应该有上百个追求者，像他这样听她弹唱和渴望得到她。

第十章

他当天晚上留下来吃饭，而且给露丝的父亲留下了良好的印象，这叫她十分满意。他们谈起了航海业——一个马丁十分熟悉的话题，摩斯先生事后说他看上去像是个头脑清晰的年轻人。为了避免使用俚语、寻找合适的字眼，马丁说话时只得慢条斯理，这一来使他能够发掘内心最优秀的思想。他比近一年前头一次来吃饭时自如了一些，他的腼腆和谦恭的态度甚至博得了摩斯夫人的欢心，后者为他显著的进步感到高兴。

“他是第一个能让露丝多瞧几眼的男人。”她对丈夫说，“她对男人老是无动于衷，真叫我为她担心。”

摩斯先生诧异地望了望妻子。

“你的意思是想利用这个年轻的水手把她唤醒？”他问。

“我的意思是，只要有办法补救，就不能让她老死闺中。”夫人答道，“如果这位年轻的伊登可以引起她对人们的普遍兴趣，倒真是件好事。”

“而且是件非常好的事情。”他评价道，“可是，假设——有的时候我们必须假设，亲爱的——假设他引起了她的特别兴趣呢？”

“不可能，”摩斯夫人大笑着说，“她比他大三岁，另外，这没一点可能性。不会出什么事的，请相信我好啦。”

马丁的角色就这样定了下来，而他本人此时正受到阿瑟和诺曼的怂恿，考虑着要干一件奢侈的事情。他们打算星期天上午骑自行车进山玩。马丁对这个计划原来并不太经意，后来听说露丝也会骑车子，而且要跟着去，这才产生了兴趣。他既不会骑车子也没有车子，可是，露丝既然会骑，那么他就应该学会——这便是他的决定；辞别了摩斯一家，回去的路上他拐进自行车店，花四十块钱买了一辆。这笔花销比他一个月辛辛苦苦挣的工钱还要多，大大减少了他的积蓄；然而，《考察家报》将付给他一百块钱的稿酬，而《少年之友》的稿费不少于四百二十块钱，这两笔钱加起来一算，他就觉得额外的开支所引起的苦恼消退了几分。回家时，他一路学骑车子，把衣服都挂破了，他也毫不在乎。当夜他就从希金波森先生的店里打电话给裁缝，重新定做了一套衣服。接着，他扛着自行车攀上像太平梯杆紧贴着后墙的窄楼梯；待到把床从墙根挪开，他发现自己的房间小得刚能容下他本人和那辆自行车。

他本来打算星期天复习功课，准备参加高中考试，可是那篇关于潜水采珠的文章在诱惑着他，于是他整整一天都似发高烧一般挥毫描绘在他心里翻腾的美感以及浪漫的情调。这天早晨，《考察家报》没有刊登他的“寻宝记”，但他并未因此而泄气。他已经攀上了高峰，是不会轻易认输的。别人唤了他两次，他都没听见，于是便错过了丰盛的星期日晚餐——希金波森先生每个星期都要用这样的晚餐为他的饭桌增光添彩。在希金波森先生看来，这样的一顿晚餐反映出他的成就和富裕；为了表示庆祝，他针对美国制度发表了一通陈腐的言论，说这样的制度为每个勤奋的人都提供了飞黄腾达的机会，他没有忘记指出他本人就是由食品店的伙计干起，最后当上了希金波森零售店的老板。

星期一上午，马丁·伊登望着那篇尚未完稿的“潜水采珠”，叹了口气，然后就搭电车到奥克兰的那家高中去了。数天之后，他去问考试结果，方知自己除了语法课，别的课程全部不及格。

“你的语法学得很好，”希尔顿老师透过厚厚的眼镜片注视着他，告诉他说，“但对别的课程就不熟悉了，简直是一无所知；你的美国史糟糕透顶——没有别的词可以形容，只能说糟糕透顶。我建议你——”希尔顿老师打住了话头，用眼睛紧盯着他，既冷漠无情又缺乏想象力，活似他自己的试管。他在高中教物理，家里人口众多，薪金却少得可怜，满脑子装的都是机械地学来的知识。

“是，先生。”马丁毕恭毕敬地说。不知怎么，他真希望希尔顿老师的位子上坐的是图书馆桌旁的那个馆员。

“我劝你回到初中去，至少再学两年。再见吧。”

这次名落孙山并没给马丁造成多大影响，但他把希尔顿老师的话讲给露丝听时，对方却显出震惊的表情，这倒叫他感到意外。她的失望表现得如此明显，真让他为自己的失败觉得惋惜，然而他的惋惜主要是为了她的缘故。

“瞧，我的看法是对的吧，”她说，“你比那些考进高中的学生知识渊博得多，却未能通过考试，全因为你学的东西太零乱、太肤浅。你需要的是严格的教育，而这些只有懂行的老师可以提供给你。你必须具备扎实的基础。希尔顿老师的话是对的，我要是你，我会到夜校里进修。在那儿学一年半能赶得上学两年的水平。另外，白天你还可以搞写作；假如你无法靠写文章维持生计，那么白天就找个工作干。”如果我白天工作，晚上上课，那么，什么时候来看望你呢？——这是马丁闪过的第一个念头，但他忍了忍没说出来。只听他这样说道：

“我到夜校上课，似乎显得太孩子气了。要是真的划得来，那我倒不在乎，可我觉得这样做划不来。我自己学比他们教的要快。上夜校是浪费时间——”他想到了她以及自己对她的欲望——“我可浪费不起时间，说实话，我匀不出时间来。”

“有许多课程都是必须学的。”她说着，向他投来柔情的目光，让他觉得自己和她作对简直太残忍了，“拿物理和化学来讲——不做实验是学不成的；你还会发现，没人辅导，简直没指望能学得好代数和几何。你需要的是懂行的教师以及善于传授知识的专家。”

他一时没言声，挖空心思地寻找最谦虚的词句表达自己的意思。

“请别以为我在吹牛，”他启口说道，“我没有一点吹牛的意思。但我有一个感觉，我可以称得上一个天生的学者。我可以自学，因为我喜欢学习就像鸭子喜欢水一样。你自己也看得到我学习语法所取得的成绩，我还学了许多其他的知识——多得让你想也想不到。我还只是刚开了个头，等到我——”他犹豫了一下，弄准了发音后才继续说道，“待我攒足了力量吧。我现在总算第一次对事物产生了真正的感受，刚刚开始掌握（size up）情况——”

“别用‘size up’这个词。”她插话说。

“那就是估摸（get a line on）形势。”他急忙更正道。

“地道的英语里根本没这一说。”她仍不同意。

他慌乱地想重新再来一句。

“我的意思是说，我现在刚刚开始触摸到（get the lay of）情况。”

出于怜悯，她没再插嘴，由着他说了下去：

“知识对我就像一间海图室。一走进图书馆，我就有这种印象。教师扮演的角色是系统地向学生讲解海图室里的东西。其实，教师只是海图室的向导，他们自己的大脑不生产知识，既不杜撰也不创造。知识全在海图室里，他们不过熟悉入室的路径罢了。他们的任务是为外行引路，否则那些外行就会迷失方向。我可不会轻易迷路，因为我有辨别方位的能力。我一般都清楚自己在何处（where I’m at）——这次又错了吗？”

“别说‘where I’m at’。”

“对，”他感激地说，“是where I am。可是，where am I at——我是说where am I呢？噢，明白啦，该说在海图室里。至于有些人（people）——”

“应用persons。”她纠正道。

“有些人（persons）需要向导，大多数人都是如此；可我觉得自己没有向导也能前行。我在海图室里已待久了，快能摸清里面的路径了，到时候我就可以知道查阅什么样的海图以及踏勘什么样的海岸。依我看来，我自己朝前走反而快得多。要知道，一个舰队的速度是其中最慢的船只的速度，而教师的速度也会受到类似的影响。他们授课的速度绝对不能超过落后的学生。这样，我的速度就可以高于他们为全班学生规定的速度。”

“独行者最速。”她冲着他引用了一句格言。

他真想脱口喊出：“我和你一道前行，照样可以比别人快。”此时此刻，他看到了一幅阳光普照、晴空万里的幻景，他携带着她游历于天地之间，用胳膊搂着她，而她那淡金色的秀发轻拂着他的脸颊。就在这一瞬间，他意识到自己的语言贫乏得可怜。上帝啊！要是能想出绝词佳句，把他看到的奇景展现给她就好啦！他感到内心一阵激动，那是一种折磨人的强烈愿望——他渴望把那些突如其来闪现在他大脑镜面上的幻景描绘出来。啊，原来如此！他总算接触到了谜底。这就是那些大作家、大诗人成功的诀窍，这就是他们之所以伟大的原因，他们懂得怎样表达自己想到、感受到以及看到的事物。在阳光下昏睡的狗常常哀鸣和狂吠，然而却说不出它们究竟看见了什么，才会哀鸣及狂吠，他经常对这种现象感到纳闷。按说，他自己就和在阳光下昏睡的狗是一样的。他看到了高雅和壮丽的景色，然而却只会冲着露丝哀鸣和狂吠。不过，他再也不想昏睡在阳光之下了。他要站起来，睁开眼睛，不断奋争、苦干和学习，直至变得耳聪目明和伶牙俐齿，那时才能和她一道分享他所看到的美景。有些人发现了表达思想的诀窍，能够把文字变为顺从的奴隶，能够把字字词词联在一起，表达出单独的词字所表达不了的含义。他感到异常振奋，因为他瞥见了这一秘密；他的眼前又出现了那幅阳光普照、晴空万里的幻景——后来，他回到了现实中，觉得周围十分宁静，瞧见露丝眼里含着笑，正兴趣盎然地打量着他。

“我目睹了一幕壮丽的幻景。”他说。听到自己的话音在耳边回响，他感到怦然心跳。这些词是从哪里蹦出来的？它们恰当地形容了他在谈话中穿插的幻景。简直是奇迹！他从未用如此高雅的词句表达过高雅的思想，但那是因为他从未尝试过用语言形容高雅的思想。正是这样，这就清楚了。他从未尝试过，而斯温伯恩、丁尼生、吉卜林以及所有其他的诗人都做过尝试。他的心里仍在翻江倒海，继而想到了他的那篇“潜水采珠”。对于壮观的事物，对于在他心中燃烧的美感，他从来都不敢试笔。待到这篇文章完稿时，就会变成另外一种模样。文章应该表现波澜壮阔的美，想到这里他油然产生了敬畏感。接着，他又一闪念头，继续大胆地遐想。他责问自己：为什么不能像那些大诗人一样，用高雅的诗句歌颂美呢？他对露丝的爱既神秘又欢快，是精神上的奇迹。他为什么就不能像那些诗人，也讴歌这种爱呢？他们歌颂过爱情，而他也要歌颂爱。上帝啊！——

他耳边听到自己的一声呼叫，不由吃了一惊。他刚才精神迷乱，才喊出了声来。热血一阵阵涌上脸来，淹没了脸上的紫铜色，直至这股羞愧的红潮从硬领的边缘漫到头发根。

“我——我——请你原谅，”他口吃地说，“我想问题走了神。”

“听上去你像是在祈祷。”她嘴上虽这么说，但内心感到的却是失望和消沉，她这是第一次听到一个她所认识的男人说诅咒的话。她感到震惊，这不仅仅是原则和教养的问题，也是因为在生活中刮来的这股狂风侵入了她那隐蔽的处女园地，震撼了她的心灵。

不过，她原谅了他，而且为自己就这么轻易原谅人觉得意外。不知为什么，原谅他的任何过失不是件特别困难的事。他没有机会能像其他的人那样，他在竭力改造自己，同时正在走向成功。她怎么也想不到，自己对他如此宽宏大量或许还有别的原因。她对他柔情种种，然而她自己却意识不到，也没法意识到。二十四年的生活平静如水，未发生过一起恋爱事件，所以她对她自己的感情也缺乏敏锐的感觉；她从未对爱燃起过热情，此时也就觉察不到自己已动了情。

第十一章

马丁回过头又写他那篇关于潜水采珠的文章。要不是他屡次三番停下来尝试着去写诗歌，这篇文章早该完稿了。他的诗都是以露丝为灵感的爱情诗，但没有一首写完过。是啊，他怎能在一天之内就学会以高雅的诗句讴歌爱情呢！韵律、音步和结构本身就够呛，可除此之外，还有一种无形无体、虚无缥缈的东西。在所有伟大的诗歌中他都可以感觉得到这种东西，然而他却捕捉不到，将其放入自己的诗章。

这就是飘忽不定的诗歌的精神——一种他能够领悟并刻意追求，但抓不到手的精神。他觉得这精神宛如一团火焰、一股暖烘烘悠荡的气体，让他够不着捞不到，但有的时候他捕捉到这种精神的片鳞只爪，将它们编织成词句，在他的头脑中经久不息地回响，或者似美丽无比的云雾从他的眼前飘过。说来让人困惑，他怀着强烈的愿望想抒发感情，但写出的东西却枯燥乏味，像普通人那样胡诌一通。他把自己一篇篇未写完的诗歌朗读起来，发现这些诗里音步十全十美，韵脚朗朗上口，节奏也无懈可击，可就是缺乏他心里感觉到的那团火焰和高昂的激情。他搞不清这是怎么回事，于是时常感到绝望、气馁和沮丧，拐回头写他的那篇文章。散文当然是一种比较容易写的体裁。

继《潜水采珠记》之后，他又写了三篇文章：第一篇描绘航海生涯，第二篇刻画的是捉乌龟，而第二篇讲的是东北贸易风。接着，他开始写短篇故事，原只是作为试笔，不料写了六篇才住手，并把它们分别寄给各杂志社。他大量而紧张地创作，从早写到晚，夜深时仍然在写，除非上阅览室、到图书馆借书或者去看望露丝，才停下笔来。他过得非常快活，生活的调子十分紧张，像是害了没完没了的热病。据说创造的欢乐只属于非凡的人，而今他也品尝到了这种欢乐。周围的种种事物——烂菜和肥皂水的气味、姐姐邋遢的身段以及希金波森先生那带着嘲笑的面孔——都成了梦幻。真实的世界存在于他的心中，而他写的故事则是他心中的那个现实世界的斑斓片断。

白天实在太短，而他想学的东西又如此之多。他把睡眠时间缩减到五个小时，并发现这样做是完全可以的。他又试着只睡四个半小时，但马上就后悔地恢复到五个小时。要干的事情着实不少，他恨不得把所有醒着的时间都用在自己的追求上。每次停止写作转向学习，每次停止念书到图书馆去，每次硬着头皮离开知识的海图室，或放下阅览室里那满载着作家出售稿件秘密的杂志，他都怀着依依难舍的心情。和露丝在一起时，每次他起身离开，都心如刀绞；但一走上漆黑的街道，他便健步如飞，为的是路上尽量少花时间，好赶回家看书。最难办到的是合上代数课本或物理课本，推开笔记本和铅笔，闭上疲倦的眼睛睡觉。一想到要停止生活，即便只停短短的一段时间，他也感到难过。此时他唯一的安慰是：闹钟被上到了五个钟点后的位置。不管怎样，他只损失五个钟点，到时候丁零零的闹钟声就会把他从无知无觉的境况中惊醒，将又一个由十九个小时组成的辉煌日子呈现在他面前。

时光一星期一星期地流逝，他的钱愈用愈少，可进项却一个子儿也没有。那篇写给小朋友看的系列冒险故事邮出一个月之后，便被《少年之友》退了回来。退稿单上的措辞写得很委婉，使他对那位编辑产生了好感。然而对《旧金山考察家报》的编辑，他就没有这种感觉了。足足等了两个星期后，马丁给那人写了封信。过了一个星期，他又写了一封。待到月底，他亲自到旧金山拜访那位编辑。可是由于一位年轻的红头发勤杂员像狗一样把守着大门，他没能见到那位贵人。第五个星期结束时，他的稿件被邮寄了回来，上面连一条意见都没有附。没有退稿单和解释的话，什么都没写。寄给旧金山其他几家大报馆的文章，也遭到了同样的冷遇。他收到退稿，就邮寄给东部的几家杂志社，而那些杂志社退稿更快，每次都附着铅印的退稿单。

那些短篇故事也以同样的方式退回。他把文章看了一遍又一遍，觉得它们都是佳作，猜想不出为什么会被退回，直到有一天，他在报上看到凡是稿件都应由打字机打出，心里才明白了过来。当然，编辑工作太忙，没时间也没精力看手写的稿件。于是，马丁租来一台打字机，花了一天的时间掌握技巧。每天他都把写好的文章打出，而且以前的稿件一经退回，他也即刻打出。当这些稿件也开始被退回时，他感到非常惊讶。他的颌骨看上去更加倔强，下巴也更加咄咄逼人。他把稿件包起来，又寄给另外的一些编辑。

这时他产生了一个念头，觉得他不适合于判断自己作品的优劣。于是他找来葛特露，试着把故事念给她听。只见她眼放异彩，高兴地望着他说：

“你能写出这样的东西，真是了不起。”

“是啊，是啊，”他不耐烦地说，“可是——你觉得这篇故事怎么样？”

“太棒啦，”她答道，“简直棒极啦，而且动人心弦。真是让我感到太激动了。”

他看得到她的大脑已经混乱，和善的脸上明显地露出困惑的表情。于是，他等待着。

“可是，马特，”对方隔了好一段时间才说，“故事是怎么结尾的呢？那个说大话的年轻人最后得到她了吗？”

从艺术的角度来看，故事的结尾已经交代清楚了，然而他还是解释了一遍。听完之后，她说道：

“这正是我想知道的。你为什么不写进故事里呢？”

给她念了许多篇故事之后，他了解到一点：她喜欢幸福的结局。“故事写得太感人了。”她说着，在洗衣盆旁边直起腰来，疲乏地叹口气，用红红的、冒着热气的手抹一把额头上的汗珠，“可是，也让我感到悲伤。我真想哭一场。世界上的伤心事实在太多了。多想想高兴的事，才会叫我感到高兴。假如他和她结下百年之好，假如——这样说你不介意吧，马特？”她担心地问，“这只是我一时的感觉，大概是由于疲倦的缘故吧。不管怎么说，故事写得很好，简直棒极啦。你准备把它卖到哪里呢？”

“那可是另一码子事。”他哈哈大笑起来。

“如果东西出了手，你认为能拿到多少钱？”

“哦，一百块钱吧。照现在的价格，至少得这个数目。”

“好家伙！但愿你能把稿子卖出去！”

“钱来得容易吧？”随后他补充说，“我两天就写完了，平均每天挣五十块钱。”

他渴望把自己写的故事念给露丝听，可就是缺乏这份胆量。他决定等到刊登出几篇后再说，那时她就会明白他的工作价值了。在这段时间里，他继续勤奋耕耘。这是一次思想领域的惊人探险，冒险精神从未像现在这样强烈地诱引着他。除了原有的代数书，他还买来了物理课本和化学课本，又是解题又是论证。他对实验室得出的结果确信无疑；由于想象力强，他对化学反应比实验室里普通的学生还理解得透彻。他孜孜不倦地翻阅厚厚的书本，最后兴奋地发现自己正步步接近事物的本质。以前他只是从表面现象看待世界，而现在他开始理解这个世界的构造，理解力与物质的作用及相互作用。他的脑海中不断涌出过去所看到的事物，并自然而然地对其进行解释。杠杆和起重装置令他着了迷，这使他回想起海船上的木梃、滑车和辘轳。他现在明白了航海原理，明白了轮船为什么能在荒海上准确无误地沿着自己的航线行走。暴风、雨和潮汐的秘密暴露了出来，而贸易风的成因使他想到自己的那篇关于东北贸易风的文章未免动笔过早。他觉得，他现在可以把文章写得更好。一天下午，他跟着阿瑟到了加利福尼亚大学，屏住呼吸，怀着教徒般的敬畏感，参观实验室、观看示范、旁听一位物理学教授为几个班的学生举办的讲座。

然而，他对写作并未掉以轻心。短篇小说在他的笔下泉涌而出；他还扩大范围，创作了一些格式简单的诗——即他在杂志上看到的那种——遗憾的是，他竟然昏了头，浪费掉两个星期用自由体创作出一首悲剧诗，直至遭到六七家杂志社的当即退稿，他这才如梦方醒。后来他发现了亨莱[1]的作品，便模仿《病院素描》的格式写了一组海洋系列诗。这组诗风格朴素，描写的是光与色、浪漫与冒险。他为其题名为《海洋抒情诗》，觉得这是他迄今为止最优秀的作品。这组诗共分三十首，计一个月完稿。每天完成了写小说的工作量之后，他便赋诗一首——他这一天的工作量相当于一般成名作家的一个星期。辛勤的劳动对他来说算不了什么。那根本不是劳动。他的语言日臻完善：多少年来，由于笨嘴笨舌，他把美感和妙语都积压在胸中，而今这些都似狂涛巨浪奔涌而出。

这组《海洋抒情诗》他谁都没让看，甚至包括那些编辑。他对编辑产生了怀疑，但这也不是他不愿拿出《抒情诗》的原因。他觉得这组诗美丽无比，于是便不由自主地要把它们留下来，等到那遥远的灿烂时刻垂降，等到他敢于把自己写的东西念给露丝听的时候，他要和露丝一道分享。为了那一时刻，他将诗珍存在身边，并一遍遍朗读，直至倒背如流。

醒着的时候，他分分秒秒都勤作不息，在睡梦中他也不安宁；在安歇的五个小时里，他的主观意识始终在运转，把白天想到的问题和经历的事情编织成奇特的、不可思议的画面。实际上，他一刻也没休息过；如果换上一个身体较差、意志较薄弱的人，定会筋疲力尽地垮下去。傍晚去看望露丝的次数愈来愈少，因为六月正姗姗而至，那时她将获得学位，结束大学生活。文学学士！——每当想到她的学位，他就觉得她离他飞奔而去，快得使他追赶莫及。

每星期她都分出一个下午给他；由于去得晚，他经常留下来吃饭，然后听音乐。这种日子是他的大喜日子。摩斯府内的气氛与他生活的条件形成巨大反差，再加上有她相伴于身旁，这一切每一次都使他向上奋进的决心更加坚定。固然不错，他胸中怀着美感以及强烈的创作欲，但他奋斗的原因却是为了她。他首先追求的是爱情，也永远追求爱情。所有的一切都是为爱情服务，所以爱情冒险要高于思想领域的冒险。世界本身并不奇妙，因为它是在不可抗拒的力量作用下，由原子和分子所组成；真正使这个世界散发出奇妙魅力的是露丝生活在其中。她是他所知道、想得到或料得着的最奇妙的东西。

可她是那么遥远，这一直使他感到苦恼。她和他距离太远，叫他不知怎样接近她才好。和同阶层的姑娘及妇女在一起时，他曾经春风得意；可是，他从未爱过她们当中的任何一个，而今，他爱上了她，这不仅仅因为她属于另一个阶层。他的爱把她捧上了云霄，使她高于所有的阶层。她是个远不可及的生物，他不知怎样才能像普通恋人那样亲近她。不错，他获得了知识、完善了语言，正在步步接近她，按她的模式谈吐、寻找共同思想及乐趣；但这些满足不了他爱情的热望。他用恋人的想象力使她神圣化，而且是过于神圣化和理想化，觉得她已非凡身肉胎，和他毫无相似之处。正是他自己的爱情将她从他的身边推开，使她显得可望而不可即。爱情本身令他无法得到自己朝思暮想的尤物。

有一天，他们之间的鸿沟上突然架起了一座桥；自那以后，鸿沟虽然依旧是鸿沟，但比以前却要窄了些。那天，他们在一起吃樱桃——那是些香甜可口的黑樱桃，汁液的颜色似黑色的葡萄酒。之后，她为他朗读《公主》里的诗句，此时他不经意地发现她的芳唇上沾着樱桃渍。顷刻间，她的神圣性土崩瓦解了。原来她也是血肉之躯，和他以及所有其他的人一样，也是凡身俗体。她的嘴唇和他的一样，都是由血肉构成，樱桃染黑了他的嘴唇，也同样染黑了她的。如果她的嘴唇是这样，那么她所有的一切都不会例外。她是个女人，一个地道的女人，和别的女人一模一样。他恍然大悟，被这一发现惊得目瞪口呆。就好像他看到了太阳从天上坠落，或者看到了人们顶礼膜拜的圣物遭到了玷污。

随后，他意识到了这一发现的重大意义，于是，他的心儿怦怦跳动，怂恿着他去充当这个女人的情侣，因为她并非来自天外的仙女，只不过是个普通女人，双唇照常可以被樱桃染上颜色。这一放肆的念头使他浑身颤抖；然而，他的灵魂却在欢唱，理智得意扬扬地称赞他，说他的这种想法是正确的。她一定觉察到了几分他的这种变化，只见她停止了朗读，笑盈盈地抬起头望着他。他的目光从她的蓝眼睛移向她的嘴唇，一看到那儿的樱桃渍，他就要发疯。他差点伸出臂膀去拥抱她，像昔日生活放荡不羁的时候一样。她似乎身子向他倾斜，期待着，而他用全部的意志才克制住了自己。

“你连一个字也没听进去。”她噘着嘴说。

随后她冲着他大笑起来，因为她看到他那副慌乱的表情，觉得十分有趣。他望着她那双坦诚的眼睛，知道她丝毫没有猜透他的心思，不禁羞愧得无地自容。他的思想的确太狂妄了。除她之外，他所认识的女人，没有一个猜不出他的这种念头。可她没有猜出来，这就是区别。她与众不同。他对自己的庸俗下流感到震惊，对她的纯洁无邪肃然起敬，于是，那架桥梁垮了下来，他又隔着鸿沟向她瞭望。

不过，这件事到底还是使他朝她靠近了些。它萦绕于他的记忆之中，每当他极度消沉的时刻，他便热切地追忆这段往事。他们之间的鸿沟再也不会似从前那样宽了。他跨过了一段距离，这远远胜过获得一个文学学士学位，或十来个学士学位。她是纯洁的，固然不错，而且纯洁得超过了他的想象；可是，樱桃染黑了她的芳唇。她和他一样，也得严格地受宇宙法则的制约。她必须吃饭才能维持生命，弄湿了脚，也会着凉。但这并不是问题的所在。如果她能够感到饥、渴、冷、热，那么她也能感觉到爱情——对一个男人的爱情。他就是男人，为什么不能成为那个男人呢？“这得由我自己争取，”他常常这样热烈地对自己说，“我一定要成为那个男人，一定要把自己造就成那个男人。我一定能办得到。”

[1]　亨莱（1849—1903），英国诗人，代表作是《病院素描》。

第十二章

一天黄昏时分，天色尚早，马丁费尽心思在写一首十四行诗，但写出的诗句歪曲了似火焰和云雾盘绕在他脑海里的美感及思想。正在这时，他被叫去接电话。

“是一位小姐的声音，一位高贵的小姐。”来喊他的希金波森先生嘲讽地说。

马丁来到屋角的电话机旁，一听到是露丝的声音，就感到一股热流涌遍全身。刚才苦苦作诗时，他忘掉了她的存在，而此刻听到她的声音，他就像挨了棒击一样，燃起了对她的爱。多么美的声音啊！——轻柔和甜蜜，似远处传来的隐隐乐声，或更贴切地说，像一串银铃，音色纯正，清澈似水晶。凡俗的女人发不出这样的声音。这声音含有仙界的成分，因为它来自天外。他神魂颠倒，简直连对方说的话都听不进去了，然而他却控制着脸上的表情，他知道希金波森先生正用雪貂样的眼睛紧盯着他。

露丝没有许多话要说——她仅仅说，诺曼原打算晚上陪她去听讲座，但由于头痛不能前往，她感到非常失望，因为票已搞到手；她问他有没有别的约会，愿意不愿意陪她一道去。

哪能不愿意！他说话时竭力按捺住急切的心情。真是让人感到意外。他总是到她家去看望她，从不敢请她同他一起上任何地方。此刻在电话上和她交谈着，他心里却胡思乱想，产生了一种愿为她一死的强烈欲望，于是，一幕幕英勇献身的场面在他那眩晕的大脑里形成又消失。他非常爱她，爱得情深意切，爱得不可自拔。她竟然想和他一道出去，一道去听讲座——和他，马丁·伊登。这是一个让人高兴得发疯的时刻，顿然，她凌空而起，离他是那样遥远，使他觉得无路可以企及，只有为她一死。唯有这样，才能恰当地表达出他对她所怀有的深沉和崇高的感情。这种庄严的献身精神就是真正的爱情，是所有的恋人都具备的，而此刻在电话机旁，这种精神似火与光的旋风袭上他的心头；他觉得为她而死就意味着曾经活得有价值、爱得深沉。他年仅二十一岁，以前从未坠入过爱河。

他用颤抖的手放下了听筒；刚才她的声音深深打动了他，令他筋酥骨麻。他的眼睛闪闪发光，就像天使的眼睛一样，他的面容焕然一新，一扫凡尘间的庸俗，变得既纯洁又神圣。

“到外边吊膀子去吗？”他姐夫冷言冷语地说，“要知道这会导致什么样的结果，你会被警察抓去审讯的。”

可马丁高居云端一时下不来，即便这样恶毒的话语也无法使他重返大地。他感觉不到愤怒，也感觉不到自尊心受到伤害。他目睹了一幕伟大的幻景，不由飘然若仙；对这个蛆虫样的小人，他只感到非常非常可怜。他不用眼睛去看他，即使目光掠过他的身上，也视而不见；犹如在梦里，他恍恍惚惚走出大厅去换衣服。直至来到自己的房间，在打领带的时候，他才感觉到一种叫人不舒服的声音在耳边回荡。辨别了一下，他断定这是伯纳德·希金波森最后哼的那声鼻子，不知怎么，他刚才竟然没把这哼鼻声往心上放。

露丝家的大门在他们身后关上了。和露丝一道步下台阶时，他感到十分慌乱。陪她去听讲座，可不是一种轻松的幸福。他不知应该怎样做才好。他曾在街上看到过，她那个阶层的人走路时，女人挽着男人的胳膊，但有时他也看到过女人不挽男人的胳膊。他弄不清是否只有在晚上才挽胳膊，或者只有夫妻和亲属之间才挽胳膊。

快走到人行道跟前时，他想起了明妮。明妮总喜欢拘泥于形式，第二次陪他逛大街时，曾责骂过他，怪他靠内侧行走。她为他订了条规则：上等人和女士上大街，总是靠外行走。每次从街道的一侧走到另一侧，明妮就踢他的脚后跟，提醒他绕过去靠外边走。他感到纳闷，不知她的这种礼节是从哪里学来的，不知这是否从上流社会渗漏下来的，也不知它到底对不对。

待他们踏上人行道时，他心想试试看总不会有什么坏处；于是，他从露丝的背后绕过去，走到了她的外侧。接着，又出现了另一个问题：是不是应该把胳膊伸给她呢？他一辈子都没伸过胳膊给别人。他认识的那些姑娘从不挽男人的胳膊。头几次逛马路，男女挨在一起各走各的，之后，女的就用胳膊搂住男的腰，在没有灯光的街面还把头靠在男的肩膀上。可这次不一样，她不是那种姑娘。他必须有所行动。

他把靠近她的那条胳膊弯了弯——只是微微一弯，这并非邀请，却暗中带点试探性，显得漫不经心，就好像他习惯于这样走路。此时，奇妙的事情发生了。他感觉到她的手搭上了他的胳膊。这一接触，使一股股欢快的电流传遍了他的全身。短瞬间，他感到非常幸福，仿佛他离开了坚实的大地，随她一道凌空翱翔。可是，他马上又返回到地面上，被一个新的问题搅得心神不宁。他们正在穿过马路。到了那边，他的位置就会换到内侧，而他应该走在外侧。那么，他是不是应该放下她的胳膊，把位置再调回去呢？如果这次调换了，下一次是否还得重复一遍呢？还有下下一次呢？这里边有不对劲的地方。于是，他决定不蹦来跳去地出洋相。可他对自己的这个决定并不满意，当走到内侧的时候，他就快言快语、热烈地讲话，显出一副入神的样子，这样，万一没调换位置是件错事，也会让她觉得他是因为过于专心致志才导致了疏忽大意。

横过百老汇大街时，他又迎面遇到了个新问题。在刺眼的电灯光下，他看到了丽茜·康诺莱和她的那个爱咯咯笑的女伴。他仅仅犹豫了片刻，就抬手摘下了帽子。对待自己的同类人，他可不能耍阴谋诡计，再说，他摘帽子并不是单单向丽茜·康诺莱致意。她点点头，向他射来大胆的目光，她的眼睛不似露丝的那般温柔、和顺，而是俊俏中带点严厉，只见她的目光从他身上转向露丝，端详她的面孔、衣着和揣测她的身份。他觉察到，露丝也在飞眼打量对方。露丝的眼睛和鸽子的一样既胆怯又柔顺，但她疾眼一瞥就看到那个工人阶层的姑娘身裹廉价的俗丽衣服、头戴当时在年轻女工中十分流行的怪模怪样的帽子。

“多么漂亮的姑娘！”过了一会儿，露丝赞叹道。

马丁对她感激万分，然而嘴上却这样说道：“这我倒不清楚。我想这纯粹是个人口味的问题吧，依我看她并不特别漂亮。”

“什么？像她那样端正的容貌，一万个女人当中恐怕都挑不出一个来，可以说是如花似玉。她的脸庞轮廓清晰得像雕像一般，眼睛也长得非常美。”

“你真的这么想？”马丁问话时心不在焉，因为对他而言世界上只有一个美丽的女人，她现在就在他身旁，手搭在他的胳膊上。

“我真的这么想？如果那姑娘能够穿上一身得体的衣服，伊登先生，如果她能学会高雅的举止，就会让你眼花缭乱，令所有的男人为之倾倒。”

“她还得学学怎样说话呢，”他评价道，“否则大多数男人都听不懂她的话。我敢说，要是照平素那样讲话，她的话你恐怕连四分之一都听不明白。”

“一派胡言！你一旦攻击起人来，就变得和阿瑟一样坏。”

“你忘了咱们第一次见面时，我是怎样讲话的。自那以后，我学会了一种新的语言。而在那个时候之前，我说起话跟这姑娘一个样。如今，我总算能让你听明白我的话了，能用你的语言向你解释你不了解这位姑娘的语言。你知道她的一举一动为什么是那个样吗？过去对这种事情我从不问津，现在却想得较多，而且开始明白——明白许多事情。”

“到底是为什么呢？”

“因为她长年累月在机器旁劳动。一个人在年轻的时候，身体非常柔韧，而艰苦的劳动可根据其性质把人体像对待油灰一样进行塑造。在街上遇到的工人中，有许多我搭眼一瞧就知道他们是干什么行当的。你瞧瞧我。我走路为什么摇摇摆摆呢？因为我在海洋上度过了许多年头。我年纪轻、身体可塑性强，如果把这些年头用来当牛仔，那我现在就不会一摇一摆了，而会变成弓形腿。那位姑娘的情况也是这样。你也留意到了，她的眼睛可以说是很严厉的。从来没有人保护她，所以她只好自己照料自己。一个姑娘家，如果目光温柔、和顺，譬如像你的一样，就保护不了自己。”

“我想你的话是对的，”露丝低声说，“真是太不幸啦，她是个多么漂亮的姑娘呀。”

他望了望她，看到她的眼睛里闪烁着怜悯的光。这时，他想起自己在爱恋着她，并为自己交的好运感到惊讶，因为正是这股运气给他带来了爱情，使他能够用自己的胳膊引着她去听讲座。

你是谁，马丁·伊登？当夜回到自己的房间时，他冲着镜子里他自己的影子这样问道。他好奇地久久凝视着那个影子。你是谁？你是干什么的？你的根在哪里？你只配爱丽茜·康诺莱那样的姑娘。你应该待在劳力阶层，跟卑贱、粗俗及丑陋的人在一起厮混。你只配与牛马及苦力为伍，居身于臭气熏天、肮脏不堪的环境里。现在就能闻到烂菜的气味，那些土豆正在腐烂。闻呀，该死的，闻呀。你竟敢翻动书本、倾听优美的音乐、学习欣赏美丽的油画、讲地道的英语、思考你的同类绝对想不到的问题；你竟敢离开牛群以及丽茜·康诺莱那些姑娘去爱一个距你一百万英里、生活在局局星空上的白皙的仙女！你算老几？你是干什么的？去你的吧！癞蛤蟆还想吃天鹅肉？

他冲着镜子里的自己晃晃拳头，然后坐到床沿上，睁着眼做了一会儿梦。接着，他取出笔记本和代数书，全神贯注演算起二次方程题，不觉时光流逝，星辰黯淡，灰蒙蒙的晨曦泻照在窗户上。

第十四章

最后他终于不顾露丝，不顾自己对她的爱，决定不学拉丁语了，但这也不是由于奥尔奈的缘故。他的时间就等于金钱。比拉丁语重要的东西多着呢，有那么多学科在用急切的声音呼唤着他。他必须挣钱，可他的稿子没有一篇被采用。四十篇稿件在各杂志社之间没完没了地兜圈子。别人是怎样投稿呢？他在公共图书馆用去大量时间仔细琢磨别人写的东西，以批评的眼光研究他们的作品，拿他们的作品跟自己的稿子作比较。他心里觉得纳闷，想不通他们到底发现了什么诀窍，才卖出了自己的作品。

大批刊载出的作品都死气沉沉，真令人不胜惊讶。那些文章缺乏五光十色的生活，没有一丝生气，然而却卖了出去，一个字两分钱，一千字二十块钱——这是报刊剪辑上公布的价格。不知有多少篇短篇小说都使他感到困惑，他承认那些作品笔调轻松、措辞巧妙，可是却没有生气或不真实。生活是如此奇异和精彩，充满了斑斓的色彩、梦幻和英雄事迹，而那些小说却偏偏只描写它平庸的一面。他感觉得到生活中的压力、紧张、狂热、烦恼和剧烈的冲击——要写就写这些！他渴望讴歌进行最后拼搏的杰出人物，疯狂的恋人，以及那些在重重压力下、于恐怖和灾难中奋斗不息、以自己的努力使生活冒出火花的伟人。而杂志上的短篇小说似乎一味吹捧勃特勒先生那种利欲熏心的人，渲染平庸男女的无聊风流韵事。莫非全是由于杂志社的编辑都是些庸俗的人？他这样问自己。要不，就是因为那些作者、编辑和读者都害怕生活？

不过，他的主要问题在于他连一个编辑或作者都不认识。不仅不认识作者，就是尝试过写作的人他也不认识一个。没有人指点他、暗示他，没有人给他提哪怕是一个字的建议。他开始怀疑那些编辑不是活生生的人。他们像是一台机器里的齿轮。正是这回事，一台机器。他在短篇小说、杂文和诗歌中倾注了自己的心血，把它们交给这台机器，他把稿件折好，将回信所需的邮票和稿件一道放入长信封，然后封上信封，外面再贴上邮票，最后投进邮筒。稿件横穿大陆，过上一段时间就会被邮递员再拿回来，外面又换了个长信封，上面贴着他附去的邮票。那一头的编辑绝非人类，而是一些安排巧妙的齿轮，它们把稿件从信封中取出，塞入另一个信封，外面贴上邮票。这就像自动售货机，一旦投入硬币，机器就会咔嚓咔嚓运转，吐出一块口香糖或巧克力。到底能拿到巧克力还是口香糖，得取决于选择哪个投币口。编辑机器也是这种情况，一个口出支票，另一个口出的是退稿单。迄今，他只找到了后一个口。

正是退稿单使这种事情十足地像是可怕的机器运转过程。那种印刷得千篇一律的退稿单他已经收到了数百张——早期的稿件每一份都换来十几张。如果这些退稿单上哪怕附有一句话，一句私人的话，也会使他感到振奋。可是没有一个编辑显露出生命的迹象。这只能叫他觉得，那一端根本没有富于同情心的人，只有润滑得当、在机器上平稳运转的齿轮。

他是个出色的战士，一个不屈不挠、顽强执着的战士，情愿继续喂养这台机器，一年一年地喂下去；然而，他失血太多，生命垂危，因此用不了几年，只消几个星期这场战斗便会决出胜负。每过一个星期，他的食宿费都会使他向毁灭的深渊跨近一步，而四十份稿件所需的邮资，也在同样严重地吮吸着他的血汗。他不再购买书籍，在小的地方精打细算，力求使无法避免的末日迟一天到来。可是，他不懂怎样理财，竟然给了他妹妹玛丽安五块钱让她买件衣服穿，一下就使末日的降临提前了一个星期。

他在黑暗中苦苦挣扎，得不到忠告和鼓励，净遇到些叫人沮丧的事。甚至连葛特露也开始以不满的眼光看待他。起初，她怀着姐姐的爱心一味容忍他那在她看来十分愚蠢的行为；可现在出于姐姐的关心，她感到十分焦虑，她觉得他的愚蠢正在发展成为疯狂。马丁明白她的心情，这比伯纳德·希金波森当面唠叨的奚落更叫他难过。马丁对自己有信心，但持有这种信念的毕竟只他一人，连露丝也不相信他。她想让他全力以赴学习，虽然没公开反对过他写作，但也没表示过赞同。

他从没提出过要把自己的作品拿给她看，一种复杂微妙的心理阻止他那样做。再说，她在大学里的功课很重，他不愿剥夺她的时间。可是，她在获得了学位之后，却主动提出要瞧瞧他写的东西。马丁既高兴又胆怯。这下有裁判员啦！她是文学学士，曾在行家的指导下研究过文学。也许，那些编辑也是有能力的裁判，但她却有所不同。她不会递给他一张铅印的退稿单，也不会通知他的作品未被采用并不一定意味着他的作品没有价值。她是个富于同情心的人，会把看法干脆、明了地讲出来；更为重要的是，她可以借此了解他马丁·伊登的真实情况。从他的作品中，她可以了解他的心胸和灵魂，了解到一些关于他的梦想和能力的情况。

马丁把几份短篇小说的复写本集中到一块儿，后来略加思忖，又把《海洋抒情诗》也补充了进去。那是六月底的一个下午，他们骑上车子向山里进发。他们俩单独外出，这已是第二次。原本暖烘烘的空气在海风的吹拂下刚刚转凉，送来阵阵爽意。当两人骑车前行时，他深深感受到这个世界是如此得美和井然有序，生活和爱情充满了乐趣。他们将自行车放到路旁，爬上一座开阔的褐色山丘，那儿的野草遭到阳光的曝晒，散发出浓郁的、干燥的香气，令人心旷神怡。

“这些草儿已完成了使命，”两人朝下坐时，马丁这样说道。她坐到了他的外套上，而他伸开四肢贴紧温暖的大地。他嗅黄褐色的草散发出的香气，那香气钻进他的大脑，使他浮想联翩，由一株草想到所有的草。“它们实现了生存的目的，”他亲切地用手拍拍枯草，继续说道，“去年冬天的那场瓢泼大雨唤起它们的勃勃生气，于是它们战胜早春料峭、开鲜花、引蜂蝶、散播种子，无愧于自己的职责，无愧于这个世界——”

“你看待事物为什么老用这种实际透顶的眼光？”她打断他的话，问道。

“我想，是因为我在研究进化论的缘故吧。说实话，最近我才算开了眼界。”

“可我觉得，你这么实际就会失去美感，就会毁掉美，正像孩子们捉住蝴蝶后，把花粉从它们美丽的翅膀上抹掉一样。”

他摇了摇头。

“美有着深切的含义，遗憾的是，以前我并不了解这一点。我只是把美看作一样无意义的东西，认为美就是美，没有规律或原因可言。那时我对美一点也不懂，而现在才明白过来，或者不如说，才开始明白过来。我知道了草为什么能成为草，知道了正是由于阳光、雨水和土壤的隐秘化学作用它们才变成了草，所以它们在我的眼里就格外美。每一株草的生活史都充满传奇色彩，而且也富于冒险的情调。想到这些，我就激动不已。每当想到力与物质的作用，想到其中所发生的艰苦卓绝的斗争，我就觉得简直可以为那些草儿写一部史诗。”

“你讲得真是太好了。”她心不在焉地说。他发现她正在用灼人的目光打量着他。

他顿时慌乱起来，感到困窘不堪，脖颈和脸上都涌起了红潮。

“但愿我正在学会怎样讲话，”他口吃地说，“我心里似乎有千言万语要说，但要表达的东西却大得要命，让人不知怎样才能说得清心里究竟都有些什么。有时候，我觉得好像整个世界、整个生活以及所有的事物都聚集在我的心里，呼唤我去充当它们的发言人。我感到——嗨，这种感觉难以形容——我感到它们是那样伟大，可我一旦说话，却如小孩子家咿呀学语。把感情和感觉转变成书面或口头的语言，并且还要让别人读到或听到后产生同样的感情和感觉，这实在是件了不起的任务，也是崇高的工作。瞧，我把脸埋在草里，鼻孔里吸进的气息使我产生千百种思想和幻觉，令我激动得浑身颤抖。我所呼吸到的是宇宙的气息。我听到了欢歌笑语，看到了成功与痛苦、奋争与死亡；野草的芳香使我的大脑产生了种种幻觉，我真想讲给你、讲给世人听。可是，怎么讲呢？我的舌头打了结。刚才我努力想把草香对我产生的影响描绘给你听，然而却未能如愿，只说出了些在我看来简直是胡言乱语的拙劣词句。我的心里感到窒息，真想一吐为快。啊！——”他绝望地举起了双手——“让人不可思议、无法理解，又难以言喻！”

“可你讲得很好呀，”她仍坚持说，“你可以想一想，在我认识你后的这么短时间里，你就取得了如此的进步。勃特勒先生是个著名的演说家，每次大选时都被州委会请去演讲，但那天吃晚饭时你的那一通言辞也不次于他，只不过他比较善于控制自己罢了。你太容易激动；不过，多练练，你会克服这个缺点的。你完全可以成为一名优秀的演说家，只要肯干就大有前途。你是出类拔萃的，可以成为佼佼者。我相信，你无论干任何事情都没有理由不成功，就像你学语法那样。你可以成为出色的律师，也可以在政界崭露头角。你能够战胜一切困难，像勃特勒先生一样取得巨大成就。就是不要患他那样的消化不良症。”她微笑着补充说。

谈话在继续进行。她说话温和，但却很固执，一个劲地强调全面基础教育的必要性，强调把拉丁语作为事业基础的好处。她所刻画的理想中的成功男性，主要以她父亲为楷模，同时也无可置疑地带有勃特勒先生的特点和色彩。他侧耳认真倾听，仰面躺着，观望和欣赏着她那在讲话时一翕一动的唇片。不过，他的大脑却没有在倾听。她所描绘的图画中没有一处引人入胜，他感到的只有叫人隐隐作痛的失望以及对她的满腔爱情。她的话里始终没提他的写作，而他带来念给她听的那些手稿放在地上，没人予以理睬。

最后，趁着谈话间歇的一会儿工夫，他望望太阳，估摸了一下它在地平线上方的高度，提醒似的把手稿捡了起来。

“唉，我全忘了，”她赶忙说，“我很想听你念念。”

他给她念了篇故事，那是他自以为写得最好的作品之一。他给这篇作品题名为《生活的美酒》，那酒的醇香在写作时就曾钻进他的大脑，而现在朗读时又悄然在他的脑海里飘荡。故事的原始构思就具有一种魔力，后来他又以富于魔力的词句和笔触加以点缀。创作时火焰般的激情重新在他心中燃烧，使他陶然若醉，对作品里的缺点不闻不见。而露丝却不一样。她那训练有素的耳朵听出了用笔的不足和夸张，听出了新手那过分强调的语气；语句的节奏一出错、一打绊，她就能立刻察觉。她很少指出作品里的节奏错误，除了在过于浮华的地方——这时她会感到不舒服，觉得作品里的外行味太浓。外行——这就是她对整篇故事的最后评价，只不过她没把这话讲给他听。当他念完时，她仅仅指出了些小错误，然后说自己喜欢这篇故事。

可是，他却感到失望。她的批评是公正的，这他承认，然而他把作品念给她听并非为了几句课堂式的纠正话。细节问题无关紧要，不必小题大做，他自己可以修改，也能够学会怎样去修改。他从生活中捕捉到伟大的现象，力图展现在故事里，而他读给她听的正是这种伟大的东西，并非什么句子结构及分号。他想让她和自己一道感受这属于他的伟大东西——这种东西他亲眼看见，经过思考，亲手将其打印在稿纸上。是啊，他失败了，他心里暗自这样思忖。也许，那些编辑并没有错。他感受到了伟大的事物，可是却没能够表达出来。他掩饰住内心的失望，表面轻松地聆听她的批评，所以她全然不知他的心底深处正有一股抵触的湍流在涌动。

“还有一篇文章，题目叫《罐子》，”他摊开手稿说，“四五家杂志社都退了稿，可我仍认为它是篇佳作。其实，我也不知道怎样评价它，只是觉得里面有一种力量。也许，你不会和我有同感。文章很短——只有两三千字。”

“真是太可怕啦！”她听他念完后，失声喊叫起来，“太可怕了，简直可怕极啦！”

他看到她脸色苍白，两只眼睛睁得大大的，紧张得双手牢牢握在一起，于是心中暗暗感到高兴。他成功了。他把自己的幻想以及内心的情感转达给了别人，而且效果显著。不管她喜欢不喜欢，这篇文章感染了她、控制了她，使她只顾坐在那儿倾听，忘掉了挑出细节问题。

“这是生活，”他说，“生活并不总是美好的。也许我生来与别人不同，所以，我觉得这里存在着一种美的东西。在我看来，这种美增加了十倍，因为——”

“但是那个可怜的女人为什么不能——”她以断断续续的声音插话说。接着，她把后半截话又咽了回去，大声喊道：“天呀！真是一种堕落，那样肮脏和下流！”

刹那间，他觉得自己的心脏好像停止了跳动。下流！这他可没想到过，他的本意也不是要写这种东西。整篇短文摆在面前，字字都是燃烧的火团，他在这样通明的火光中查找，但找来找去都找不到下流的地方。于是，他的心脏又开始了跳动，因为他没有错。

“为什么不选个美好的题材呢？”只听见她在说，“我们知道世界上有下流的事情，但不能因此就——”

她用愤怒的声调滔滔不绝地朝下说，可是他却没有留心听。他只顾醉心地望着她那张纯洁的面孔——那面孔如此天真，又是那般出奇地无邪，其圣洁性好像无时无刻不在冲击着他，涤荡着他心里的污泥浊物，使他沐浴在一种清凉、柔和，一如星光的灿烂辉照中。“我们知道世界上有下流的事情！”一想到她那种老于世故的腔调，他就暗自发笑，觉得她的话既可爱又可笑。紧接着，一幅包罗万象的幻景闪现出来，他过去所熟悉和经历过的下流事情如海洋一般展现在他面前，于是，他原谅了她没理解那篇故事。她没有过错，因为她理解不了那种事情。感谢上帝，她一生下来就受到保护，才如此天真无邪。可是，他了解生活，了解生活中的美与丑，知道生活中虽然污痕斑斑，却也有它伟大的一面，对上天起誓，他要把自己对生活的看法讲给世人听。天堂里的圣徒——他们怎么可能不高雅和纯洁呢？而污泥里的圣徒——啊，那才是千古奇迹！生活的价值就在于此。他看到邪恶的泥潭里闪出道德之光；他爬出泥潭，眼梢上挂着泥浆，第一次瞥见了美，朦胧而遥远；他看到了怯懦、脆弱、邪恶、种种暴虐、新生的力量、真理以及崇高的精神品质——

此时，她说的几句话飘进了他的耳中。

“文章的整个格调有点低，格调高的作品比比皆是，《纪念》[1]就是一例。”

他忍不住想提出《洛克斯莱堂》[2]为例，要不是由于自己再次沉湎于幻景，他真会说出口；只见他呆呆望着她，看见这位与他同类的女性爬出洪荒时代的混沌，沿着巨大的生命阶梯向上攀登，历经百万年之久，终于出现在最高的一级上，演变成一个露丝，纯洁、美丽和神圣，使他懂得了爱，使他向往纯洁和渴望神圣——他，马丁·伊登，也是在绵绵不尽的生活中体验了无数失误和挫折才奇迹般爬出了沼泽泥潭。这就是浪漫、奇妙和光荣的事迹。这就是写作的素材，他要做的是寻找到表达的语言。天堂里的圣徒！——他们仅仅是圣徒而已，也是身不由己啊。然而，他是个人啊。

“你有力量，”他可以听到她在说，“但那是一股蛮力。”

“我像是瓷器店里的一头公牛，动辄闯祸。”他主动提出，赢得对方嫣然一笑。

“你必须培养鉴别力，必须考虑到趣味性、高雅性和格调。”

“我的确太冒失了。”他喃喃不清地说。

她赞许地笑了笑，然后静下心准备听另一篇故事。

“这一篇不知你会怎么想，”他带着歉意说，“文章有些古怪，恐怕我在写作时过于自不量力，但我的本意是好的。不要理睬里面的细小情节，且试试看是否能理解其中伟大的含义。也可能我表达不清楚，但文章的主题是伟大的、真实的。”

他开始读了起来，边读边观察着她，心想自己最后总算打动了她。她纹丝不动坐在那儿，眼睛直勾勾盯着他，几乎停止了呼吸，他认为是被他作品中的魔力迷得神魂颠倒了。本篇题为《冒险》，是对冒险生活的礼赞——它描写的不是故事书里的那种冒险，而是真正的冒险精神。它好比一个野蛮的监工，赏罚分明、奸诈成性、反复无常，要求手下人具有极大的忍耐性，逼迫他们不分昼夜地辛苦劳作，给他们的酬劳不是灿烂如阳光的荣誉就是由饥渴导致的黑色死亡，或者是一种由长期患热病，神志昏迷而导致的死亡；他带领着人们经历血与汗的洗礼和蚊虫的叮咬，沿着由低级、卑鄙的事件组成的长链向光辉的顶点攀登，最后取得崇高的成就。

他写进文章里的就是这种精神，一无遗漏，而且还超出了这个范围。他坚信正是这种精神温暖了她，使她坐在那儿静静倾听。她睁大了眼睛，苍白的脸上泛出红晕，他还没念完就觉得她已经气喘吁吁了。的确，她得到了温暖，但这种温暖不是来自于故事中，而是源自他的身上。对于这篇文章她倒没有多高的评价；但马丁体内的那种强大的力量，那种一向过剩的力量，却似乎奔流而出，覆盖和淹没了她。奇妙的是，凝聚着他的力量的文章，此刻成了他向她输送力量的通道。她感觉到的只有这股力量，却感觉不到通道的作用。她表面看起来像是对他的作品着了迷，但实际上却陶醉于另外一种完全无关的东西——一种突如其来在她的脑海中形成的危险、可怕的念头。她发现自己在思量婚姻到底是怎么一个样；这是个多么任性和狂妄的念头呵，一意识到这一点她便吓得心惊肉跳。这不是姑娘家该有的念头，与平时的她格格不入。她可从未为终身大事牵过肠挂过肚，因为她一直生活在丁尼生诗歌里的梦幻之乡，甚至对那位大师含蓄提及的女王和骑士间的暧昧关系也一知半解。她一直在沉睡，而今生活却猛烈叩响了她的重重大门。她心里一片恐慌，直想锁上插销，上好门闩，可是她任性的本能却怂恿她敞开大门，请进这位诱人的陌生人。

马丁得意地等待着她的裁决。他毫不怀疑那将是什么样的评价，所以她的话一旦出口，叫他格外吃惊。

“写得很美。”

“写得很美。”她停了一下，又强调地重复了一遍。

文章当然是美的；但除了美之外，还有一种别的特点，那特点灿烂绚丽，使美只能成为它的陪衬。他默默地躺在地上，眼看着一个形状可怕的偌大疑团在他的面前形成。他失败了，这是因为他不善于表达自己的思想。他明明看到了天底下最伟大的一件事情，却没能把它表现出来。

“你认为这个——”他迟疑起来，这是他第一次想用个生词，不禁有点羞怯，“你认为这个主题怎么样？”他问道。

“模糊不清，”她答道，“从大的方面讲，我只能这样评价。内容我倒是听得明白，但里面夹带的东西太多，显得太啰唆。你写了那么多题外话，妨碍了情节的发展。”

“那才是重要的主题呢，”他连忙解释说，“这是埋在下边的大主题，是一种宇宙性、世界性的东西。我尽量使它和只是作为表层的故事本身保持一致，这种路子没有错，可就是写得差了些，没能讲清心里要说的话。不过，我终究会学会的。”

她没能听懂他的话。她虽然是位文学学士，但这席话却超出了她的理解范围。她听不懂，却把自己不懂的原因归结为他的文章太松散。

“你未免过于善辩了，”她说，“不过，文章有些地方的确写得很美。”他觉得她的声音仿佛来自远方，因为此刻他正考虑着是否把《海洋抒情诗》念给她听。他怀着失望感郁郁不乐地躺在那儿，而她仔细打量着他，心里又突然涌出了关于结婚的任性念头。

“你想当名人？”她猛不愣丁问道。

“是的，有点想，”他承认说，“这是冒险的一个组成部分。当不当名人倒不重要，重要的是为之奋斗的过程。对我来说，成名只是达到某种目的的途径。为了这个目的，为了这个缘故，我强烈地渴望成名。”“全都是为了你。”他很想这样声明。她要是对他念的文章表现出浓厚的兴趣，他会把这话说出口的。

此时的她正忙于思考，想为他寻找一种至少能行得通的道路，所以没问他所指的最终目的究竟是什么。他在文学方面无前途可言，这一点她深信不疑。他今天念的那些幼稚、肤浅的作品就是证明。他可以讲出精彩的话，却不能够以文学的方式表达自己的思想。她拿丁尼生、勃朗宁以及一些她所推崇的散文大师与他相比，结果把他比得一无是处。不过，她没把心里的想法全告诉他。造成这种妥协的原因是她对他所产生的莫名其妙的兴趣。他的写作欲望毕竟是小小的遗憾，随着时间的推移会逐渐消失。那时候，他将全力以赴干些正经事儿，而且会取得成功。这她是知道的。他是那样强壮，绝不会失败——只要他肯放弃写作。

“希望你能把你写的东西都拿给我看看，伊登先生。”她说。

他高兴得红了脸。她产生了兴趣，这一点是肯定的。起码，她没有递给他退稿单。她曾说他的作品中有些段落写得很美，这可是他第一次从别人口中听到鼓励的话。

“我会的，”他激动地说，“我向你保证，摩斯小姐，我一定要干出些名堂。我知道，自己已走了很远的路；前边的道路依然很长，即便用双手和膝盖爬着走，我也要走到头。”他拿起了一叠手稿，“这是《海洋抒情诗》。回到家，我把它交给你，有空的时候看看。你可一定要把你的看法告诉我。你知道，我最需要的就是别人的批评。请你务必坦率直言。”

“我一定会十分坦率。”她嘴里答应着，而心里却有些不安，认为自己刚才对他就不坦率，并且怀疑自己下一次在他面前是否就能做到直言不讳。

[1]　丁尼生为悼念亡友而作的著名长诗。

[2]　也是丁尼生的名诗。

第十五章

“第一场战斗结束了，”十天之后，马丁冲着镜子这样说，“但还会有第二场战争和第三场战争，一仗仗地打到最后，除非——”

他没把话说完，而是扫视了一圈简陋的小屋，最后将忧郁的目光落在了一堆退回的稿件上，那些稿件仍然装在长信封里，放在屋角的地板上。他没有邮票再把它们寄出去了，所以一个星期来它们堆积成了山。明天、后天和大后天还会有稿件退回，直到它们全部物归原主。他没有能力再寄稿子了，因为他已经欠了一个月的打字机租用费，这笔钱他拿不出来，手头的一点钱差不多刚够支付已到期的本星期的食宿费和职业介绍所的手续费。

他坐下来，若有所思地望着写字桌。桌子墨迹斑斑，他突然感到自己很喜欢这张桌子。

“亲爱的桌子呀，”他说道，“我和你一起度过了美好的时光，总而言之，你一直是我的好朋友。你从不拒绝我的要求，从不给我不应得到的退稿单，对于加班加点的工作也从不发一句怨言。”

他把胳膊放到桌上，然后将脸埋在肘弯里。他喉头发痛，直想哭一场。他想起了六岁时第一次打架的情形，当时他脸上淌着泪水一拳拳打出去，而对方是个比他大两岁的男孩，不停地揍他，直揍得他筋疲力尽。四周围观的孩子们像野蛮人一样大喊大叫。最后，他感到头晕目眩，终于摇摇晃晃地倒了下去，鼻孔里鲜血纵流，泪水从被打伤的眼里泉涌而出。

“可怜的小伙子，”他喃喃地说，“现在你也遭到了同样的惨败，你被打得血肉模糊，倒在地上爬不起来。”

第一次打架的情景仍滞留在他的眼帘下，后来在他的注视下逐渐消失，演变成了以后所打的几场架。过了半年，干酪脸（这是那个对手的绰号）又把他揍了一顿。不过，他也打青了干酪脸的一只眼睛，所以战绩还算不错。现在回想起一次次打架的经过，他总是失败，而干酪脸总是为战胜他欣喜若狂。可是他从未临阵脱逃过，想起这些他就感到力量倍增。他每次都坚持到底，苦苦忍受。打架时的干酪脸简直是个小魔鬼，对他从来都不留情面。可是他坚持了下去！坚持了下去！

他下一幕看到的是一条窄巷子，两边是摇摇欲坠的木板房。一幢砖砌平房堵在巷尾，里面传出印刷机有节奏的隆隆声，那是在印《问讯报》的第一版。他当时十一岁，干酪脸十三岁，两人都是《问讯报》的报童，所以都在那儿等着取报。当然，干酪脸又找起了他的事，两人又打了起来。打到半截他们就停了手，因为四点差一刻印刷所的门一开，孩子们便蜂拥而入取自己的报纸。

“明天再收拾你。”干酪脸对他说，而他噙着满眼的泪水，用尖厉、颤抖的嗓音答应第二天一定到场。

次日，他一出校门便匆匆往那儿赶，为的是当第一名，结果比干酪脸早到了两分钟。孩子们夸他是好样的，接着便为他出谋划策，并指出他出手时的缺点，说如果按他们的办法打，一定能取胜。这些孩子也为干酪脸出了主意。那次打架，他们看得真是过瘾！他停止了回忆，不由羡慕起那些孩子来，因为他们目睹了他和干酪脸创造的壮观景象。那场架不分回合，一口气打了半个小时，直至印刷所开门。

他观望着自己小时候的幻象，观望着自己是怎样日复一日地从学校往《问讯报》巷子里赶。那时，他走不快，由于持续不断地打架，关节僵硬，腿一瘸一拐。他用前臂挡住了无数次拳击，所以从手腕一直到肘关节处，全都变成了青紫色，有好多溃烂处已开始化脓。他的脑袋、胳膊和肩膀在发痛，腰也在发痛——全身上下都在发痛。他大脑昏沉，两眼发花，在学校里既不玩耍也不学习。整天守在课桌旁，就是一种折磨。自从开始天天打架以来，似乎已过了几个世纪，可是，这样的打架还得像噩梦一样，无休无止地持续下去。他常想：干酪脸为什么不垮下去呢？干酪脸一垮，他马丁就可以摆脱苦难了。他从来没想到过自己停下手来，让干酪脸把他击垮。

他拖着沉重的步子向《问讯报》巷子走去，虽感心力交瘁，但培养了持久的耐力，去迎击他的死对头；干酪脸也和他一样疲惫不堪，要不是那帮报童在旁边观战，使他不得不痛苦地考虑到面子问题，他真有点想退出战场。根据规矩，不准脚踢和拳击裤带以下的部位，一方倒下后应立刻停手。一天下午，两人依照这种规矩鏖战了二十分钟，后来干酪脸气喘吁吁、东摇西晃地提出了休战的建议。马丁脸埋在胳膊上，激动地回想着那个很久以前的下午自己的情形：他也摇摇晃晃，气喘吁吁，干裂的嘴唇鲜血直流，那血淌进他的嘴里，然后滚入嗓子眼，呛得他透不过气来；他步履蹒跚地向干酪脸走去，吐出一口血才说出话来，大声嚷嚷自己决不休战，除非干酪脸低头认输。可干酪脸没有认输，于是两人又继续开战。

过了一天又一天，日子简直没个尽头，每天下午都有一场恶战。每次一举拳头，他就感到胳膊痛得要命，刚交手的头几拳，无论是打出去的还是身上挨的，都叫他一直痛到心头；之后，他就感觉麻木了，只顾胡乱厮打，像做梦一样看到干酪脸的那张大脸和那双燃烧着怒火、野兽般的眼睛晃来晃去。他把注意力都集中到了那张脸上，而周围其他的东西全变成朦胧一片。除了那张脸，世界上的所有事物都不复存在；他绝不住手，绝不，一定要用自己血淋淋的拳头把那张脸揍个稀巴烂，或者让眼前那双血拳头和那张脸的主人把自己揍得体无完肤。到了那个时候，他才会得到某种形式的安歇。但是，要让他休战，让他马丁休战，是绝对办不到的！

总算有一天，当他拖着沉重的脚步走进《问讯报》巷子时，没看到干酪脸的踪影。那天，干酪脸没来。孩子们恭贺他打败了干酪脸。但马丁并不感到兴奋，因为他没打败干酪脸，干酪脸也没打败他。问题并没有得到解决。直到后来大家才得知，干酪脸的父亲那天突然死了。

马丁的思路跨过好几个年头，跃到了在大剧院楼厅看戏的那个夜晚。那时他十七岁，刚刚出海归来，剧院里出了事，有人在欺负人。马丁挺身出来打抱不平，结果遇上了眼睛里冒火的干酪脸。

“看完戏等着我收拾你。”他的老对头恶狠狠地说。

马丁点了点头。此时，楼厅里的值班员正朝出事地点走来。

“看完最后一出戏，我到外边恭候你。”马丁低声说，而眼睛却看戏台上的木屐舞，满脸津津有味的表情。

那位值班员怒目扫了扫，便走开了。

“有帮手吗？”待木屐舞跳完时，他问干酪脸。

“当然有。”

“那我也得找几个人来。”马丁宣称。

幕间休息时，他寻来了自己的帮手——三个他在铁钉厂认识的工人、一位机车司炉工、五六个街头流氓，还有五六个十八街区和市场街黑帮里的恶棍。

散戏后，两班人马不引人注意地沿街道两侧鱼贯来到一个没人的拐角，然后聚在一起开了个作战碰头会。

“地点选在八马路桥吧，”干酪脸帮内的一个红头发小伙子说，“你们就在中间的电灯底下打，警察不管从哪边来，咱们都可以从另一边溜掉。”

“这主意挺好。”马丁和自己帮里的头儿商量后说道。

八马路桥架在圣安东尼奥河口湾的一个支流上，有城市里的三段街区那么长。桥中央以及桥的两端都安着电灯。警察从桥头的灯下一走过，就会被看到，所以在这儿打架是很安全的。马丁的眼帘下又复现出当时的情景，他看到两班人马都气势汹汹，阴沉着面孔，分成两个阵营为各自的斗士助威；他看到自己和干酪脸在脱衣服。附近的地方布置了瞭望哨，负责监视灯火通明的桥头。一个小流氓为马丁拿着外衣、衬衫和帽子，一旦警察来干涉，就带着东西往安全的地方跑。马丁看到自己走到桥中央，面对着干酪脸，警告似地举起一只手说道：“这次没有握手言和的余地，懂吗？什么都不用讲，光出手打就行了。也不能半途退，这是一场解决恩怨的战斗，必须打到底。懂吗？得有一方被打败才算数。”

干酪脸想反对——这马丁看得出来——可是当着两班人马的面，干酪脸又得顾及自己那受到威胁的面子。

“好啊，那就来吧。”他答道，“唠唠叨叨地吹牛皮顶个屁用！我一定奉陪到底。”

接着，他们打了起来，活似两头小公牛，带着全部的青春活力，挥舞着拳头，怀着仇恨，怀着伤害、残杀和毁灭对方的强烈愿望。人类在千年发展史中辛辛苦苦取得的成就便这样被葬送了。剩下的只有那盏电灯——人类伟大的冒险历程上的一块里程碑。马丁和干酪脸是两个野人，他们属于石器时代，属于洞穴和莽林。他们在泥潭里越陷越深，又回到了生命起源时愚昧的原始时期，像起了化学反应似的盲目冲击，宛如原子或太空中的星尘，相撞在一起，然后分开，再撞在一起，以至永远。

“天啊！我们简直是畜生！凶残的野兽！”马丁观看着这场恶战，不由喃喃出声。他具有超凡的想象力，所以这情景就似看电影一样清楚。他既是旁观者又是参与人，由于已经具备了数月的文化修养，他看到眼前的情景，不禁浑身打战；接着，“现在”从他的意识中消失了，“过去”的鬼魂却附在了他的体内。他又成了那个刚刚出海归来，和干酪脸大战于八马路桥的马丁·伊登。他忍受着痛苦，坚持打下去，脸上淌着血和汗，每当自己的拳头击中对方，便感到一阵欢喜。

他们是两股仇恨的旋风，凶狠地扭打在一起。过了一会儿，两班充满敌意的人马都鸦雀无声了。他们从未目睹过如此凶残暴虐的场景，敬畏之心油然而生。这两位战士比他们所有的人都野蛮，青春和身体里最初所爆发出的充溢着勃勃生气的活力已消耗殆尽，两人的搏斗趋于谨慎和小心，双方谁都没有占优势。马丁听到有人说：“鹿死谁手，还不知道呢。”随后，他使了个假动作，再左右出拳，而对方也猛烈还击，他感到腮帮子被打裂了开来，露出了骨头，光用拳头是做不到这一点的。他听到了旁观者看见这可怕的伤口时低声发出的惊叫。鲜血流了他一身，可他却丝毫不动声色。他格外警惕起来，因为他清楚自己的同类善于玩卑鄙的花招、使出见不得人的手段。他注视着，等待着，最后疯狂地扑了上去，但冲到半截却停了下来，因为他看见了金属的闪光。

“把手举起来！”他厉声喝道，“原来戴着指节铜套，用它来打我！”两边的人涌上前来，愤怒地吼叫和咆哮。眼看一场混战一触即发，那时他就没机会报仇了，他气得发了疯。

“你们都退下去！”他嘶哑着声音喊道，“明白了吗？你们听懂了吗？”大伙儿畏缩地退了回去。他们是野兽，而他是野兽之王，是一种凌驾于他们之上和支配着他们的恐怖生物。

“事情由我解决，谁都不许介入。快把铜套交出来。”

干酪脸清醒了过来，显得有些惊慌，把凶器交了出去。

“那个藏在后边的红毛鬼，是你把铜套递给了他。”马丁把铜套扔进河里说，“我看到你鬼鬼祟祟的，当时还不知道你在玩什么花样。要是再敢做这种事情，我就打死你。懂吗？”

他们继续开战，直打得筋疲力尽还不住手，后来，他们疲劳的程度简直超出了人们的估量和想象。旁观的恶棍们已满足了嗜血欲，被眼前的情景吓坏了，不偏不倚地劝他们休战。干酪脸随时都会倒下死去或站着死去，一副面孔被打得变了形，显得狰狞可怕。他摇晃着身子，犹豫着，可马丁却扑上来，一拳又一拳地向他猛击。

时间仿佛过了有一个世纪，干酪脸的攻击在迅速减弱。接着，在一阵混战当中传来了咔嚓一声响，马丁的右臂垂了下来，一根骨头折断了。所有的人都听到了，并知道是怎么回事；干酪脸也知道发生了什么事，于是便趁着对方情况危急，猛虎般扑上去，拳头似雨点一样落下。马丁的人马涌上前想干预。尽管被接二连三的猛拳打得头昏眼花，马丁还是骂着脏话，呵斥他们退下去。在这极端危急和凄惨的时刻，他一声声地呻吟着。

他仍在坚持战斗，现在仅出左拳，一边顽强而迷迷糊糊地打着，一边听到人群里传来了像是来自远方的恐慌的低语，其中有个家伙用发抖的声音这样说：“这不是打架，伙计们，简直是在杀人，应该制止住他们才对。”

然而，没人出来制止，这叫马丁感到高兴。他疲倦地挥动着一条胳膊，永无休止地击打眼前的那团血淋淋的东西——那东西不是人的面孔，而是恐怖的怪物，是一种摇摇晃晃、丑陋可怕、哼哼哧哧、难以名状的怪物，滞留在他昏花的眼前，硬是不肯走开，他一拳一拳地打着，但动作愈来愈慢，最后的一丝力气好像经历了千百年的漫长时期，从体内渗光了。最后，他朦胧地觉察到那团难以名状的东西在慢慢倒下去，倒向那粗糙木板铺就的桥面。紧接着，他居高临下地站到了那团东西前，摇摇摆摆、双腿打战，用手在空中乱抓一气想找寻支撑物，以一种自己都辨不出的声音说：

“还想打吗？说啊，还想打吗？”

他把这话说了一遍又一遍——又是询问、又是恳求、又是恫吓，想知道对方是否还想打下去。后来，他感到自己帮内的人把手放到了他身上，拍了拍他的脊背，要为他穿衣服。接着，他眼前突然一阵昏黑，失去了知觉。

桌上的白铁闹钟嘀嗒嘀嗒地响着，可马丁·伊登脸埋在臂弯里，却没有听见。他什么都听不见，也什么都不想。他真实地重新体验着当时的生活，竟然昏了过去，就像数年前在八马路桥昏倒一样。足足有一分钟的时间，他两眼昏黑，脑子一片空白。随后，仿佛死而复生一样，他一跃而起，眼睛里冒着火，脸上淌着汗，高声喊道：

“我打败了你，干酪脸！我等待了十一年，但终于还是打败了你！”他双膝颤抖，感到浑身无力，于是踉跄着步子走到床前，身子朝下一沉，坐在了床沿上。他仍然沉湎于对往事的回忆。他向屋子的四周望望，感到既困惑又慌张，不知自己身在何处，直到看见了屋角的那堆稿件，心里才明白过来。回忆的车轮向前滚动，穿越了四个年头，他才意识到了“现在”，意识到了自己翻开的书以及从书中看到的天地，意识到了自己的梦想和雄心；意识到了自己对一位精灵般白皙女子的爱——那女子生性敏感、娇生惯养、温文尔雅，只消看一眼他刚才经历过的场景，看一眼他体验过的肮脏生活，准会被活活吓死。

他立起身来，直视自己在镜中的映影。

“你从污泥里爬了起来，马丁·伊登，”他庄重地说，“你迎着灿烂的光芒擦干净眼睛，跻身于群星之间，像所有的生物一样，‘摆脱野蛮和残暴’[1]，不畏千难万险，为自己争取最好的命运。”

他更加仔细地打量着镜中的影子，哈哈笑出声来。

“有点歇斯底里，也有点戏剧味，是吧？”他问道，“哦，请别在意。你打败了干酪脸，也会打败那些编辑，哪怕花去两个十一年也在所不惜。你不能就此罢手，必须坚持下去，一战到底，这一点你可要明白。”

[1]　丁尼生的长诗《纪念》中的诗句。

第十六章

闹钟丁零零响起来，霍然把马丁从睡梦中惊醒，若是换上一个体质差些的人，肯定会闹头痛。虽然睡得很死，但他马上似猫儿一样醒了过来，而且醒得很急切，庆幸无知无觉的五个小时已经过去。他痛恨昏昏沉沉的睡眠，因为有许多事情要做，有许多生活等待他去体验。睡眠夺走的一分一秒都令他感到心疼，未等闹钟的丁零声停止，他就连头带耳浸在了脸盆里，被冷水激得直哆嗦。

可他没有依照计划按部就班地工作，手头既无未完稿的文章，也无新作需要付诸笔端。昨夜他学习一直学到很晚，现在醒来已快到吃饭时间了。他想把费斯克[1]的作品看上一个章节，但脑子里太乱，只好合上了书。今天将拉开一场新的战斗的序幕，在今后的一段时间里他将辍笔停止写作。他感到一阵凄哀，心情类似那些离家别亲的人们。他望了望屋角的稿件，原因就在那里。他就要离开它们，离开他的这些受尽欺侮、到处都不受欢迎的可怜孩子了。他走过去，动手翻阅那些稿件，拣自己喜欢的段落，这儿看一段那儿看一段。他特别欣赏《罐子》，大声朗读了一遍，而对待《冒险》也是如此。最令他垂青的是新作《欢乐》，这篇作品昨天才完稿，由于没邮票寄，便抛到了屋拐角。

“我简直不理解，”他自言自语道，“或者，也许是那些编辑无法理解。这篇东西看不出哪个地方有毛病。他们每个月都登劣质文章，篇篇——几乎是篇篇都比这差。”

用过早餐，他把打字机装进箱子，然后提着来到了奥克兰。

“我欠了一个月的租借费，”他对租赁店里的职员说，“不过你可以转告经理，我要去找活干，不出一个月我就会回来把账还清。”

他乘轮渡到了旧金山，向一家职业介绍所走去。“我什么活都愿干，就是不会手艺。”他对办事员说。这时进来一个人打断了他们的谈话，只见此人衣着花里胡哨，完全是有些爱赶时髦的工人那样的打扮。办事员沮丧地摇了摇头。

“一点办法都没有，呃？”来者说，“唉，今天我必须雇到人手。”他转过身，把眼光投向了马丁。马丁也打量起他来，看到那张浮肿和苍白的脸倒是很英俊，但却无精打采，显然是昨夜熬通宵的缘故。

“找工作吗？”对方问，“能干什么活？”

“干重活，还能当水手、打字，就是不会速记；会骑马，什么活都愿意干，也愿意尝试。”马丁说。

对方点了点头。

“听起来倒是不错。我叫道森，乔·道森，正想物色一个洗衣工。”

“这活我可干不了。”马丁说着，心里想到了自己为娘们家熨白色绒毛衣的可笑场景。可是他对那人产生了好感，于是便补充说：“光洗洗衣服我还是可以干的，那是我在航海时学会的。”

乔·道森一时没吭声，显然在考虑。

“这样吧，咱们一块合计一下，愿意听吗？”

马丁点了点头。

“那是家小洗衣店，位于内地，归属雪莱温泉旅馆，干活的只有两个人：老板和伙计。我是老板。你不是为我干活，但你得听我的指派。你考虑一下，是不是愿意去试试？”

马丁没言声，暗自考虑起来。前景是诱人的，干上几个月，他就可以腾出时间学习了。他可以边发愤工作边刻苦学习。

“伙食不赖，而且还有自己的房间。”乔说。

这一说使他打定了主意。有了自己的房间，他可以不受干扰地挑灯夜读。

“但工作却非常重。”对方追加了这么一句。

马丁意味深长地摸了摸肩膀上隆起的肌肉说：“这是干重活练出来的。”

“那咱们就谈正经事吧。”乔把手放到头上，按了一会儿，“唉，有点头晕，简直看不清东西。昨天喝了一夜酒，把钱花了个精光。情况是这样的：除了吃住，两个人的工资总共是一百块钱。平时都是我拿六十块钱，伙计拿四十块钱。可他是内行，你却是生手。要是由我来带你，开始的时候我得替你干许多活，所以你先拿三十块钱，干一阵再升至四十块。我会对你公平的。你一干完自己分内的活，就拿四十块钱。”

“一言为定。”马丁说着，伸出手和对方握了握，“能预支点钱吗？买火车票和做盘缠，行吗？”

“我把钱都花光了，”乔愁眉苦脸地回答，又用手摸了摸发痛的脑袋，“身上只剩下一张往返车票了。”

“付过食宿费，我就分文全无了。”

“那就一溜了之呗。”乔建议道。

“不行，那是欠我姐姐的钱。”

乔不解地吹了一声长长的口哨，然后挖空心思想办法，但终究无计可施。

“我还有点喝酒的钱，”他绝望地说，“咱们去喝一盅，也许能想出个办法来。”

马丁谢绝了。

“戒掉啦？”

马丁这次点了点头，而乔哀叹道：“我要是也能戒掉就好啦。”

“可不知怎么，这酒就是戒不掉，”他为自己辩解说，“辛辛苦苦干上一个星期的活，我就要喝个酩酊大醉。要是不喝酒，我会割破自己的喉管，或者放把火将房子烧掉。不过，你能戒酒，这让我感到高兴。望你坚持下去。”

马丁情知自己和这个人之间横着一条巨大的鸿沟；但他觉得，要让他回到鸿沟的对岸，也绝非难事。他过去一直都生活在劳动阶级的圈子里，劳动人民之间的友谊和忠诚是他的第二天性，至于对方那发痛的头脑解决不了的交通费用问题，他倒想出了个办法。他可以托乔乘车，把自己的箱笼捎到雪莱温泉旅馆去，他有自行车当交通工具。到那儿的路程有七十英里，他星期天动身，星期一早晨就能够开始干活了。当务之急是回家收拾行李，他不用和任何人告别，因为露丝和她全家都到内华达群山中的太滹湖畔消磨漫长的夏季了。

星期天晚上他赶到雪莱温泉旅馆时，已是筋疲力尽、风尘仆仆。乔热情地欢迎他。乔发痛的头上缠着湿毛巾，已干了整整一天活。

“上个星期我去雇你的时候，一部分活就积压了下来，”他解释道，“你的箱子已平安到达，现在你的房间里。把那称为箱子未免太沉了些。里边装的是什么？莫非是金砖不成？”

乔坐到床上，看着马丁解行李，行李箱原是装早点的货箱，希金波森先生收了马丁五角钱才把箱子给了他。马丁在上边钉了两个绳柄，巧妙地把它变成了能上行李车的衣箱。乔鼓起眼珠，看到他拿出几件衬衫和换洗的内衣后，就源源不断地朝外取书。

“底下全都是书啦？”他问。

马丁点点头，接着便开始把书排列到一张在这间房里充作脸盆架的餐桌上。

“好家伙！”乔惊叹一声，随后就哑了音，琢磨起其中的名堂来。最后他终于悟出了点道理。

“你不追女孩子——不太追女孩子吧？”他问。

“是的，”马丁回答说，“以前倒是经常追，可后来迷上了书，我就没时间了。”

“到这儿来也没时间，除了干活就是睡觉。”

马丁心想自己每天只睡五个小时，于是微微笑了笑。他的房间位于洗衣房的楼上，和那架抽水、发电以及带动洗衣机的引擎在同一幢房屋里。住在隔壁的技师来迎接新人时，帮马丁在分线上装了个灯泡，这灯泡可以顺着一条绷在桌子上方的绳子拉到床前。

次日清晨六点一刻，马丁被从床上唤了起来，因为六点四十五要吃早饭。洗衣房里有一个工作人员用的澡盆，他在里边洗了个冷水浴，这叫乔极为震惊。

“好样的，你可真是好样的！”他们在旅馆厨房里的一个角落坐下来用餐时，乔这样称赞他。

同他们一道就餐的还有那位技师、花匠、助理花匠以及两三个马房里的人。大伙儿阴沉着脸急匆匆地吃着，都不太讲话。马丁边吃边听，心中意识到自己已远远地离开了他们的阶层。那些人低下的智能叫他伤心，于是他巴不得赶快从他们身边躲开。他和他们一样，匆匆吞下这顿令人作呕的、泥浆般的早饭，待到出了厨房门，才轻松地舒了口气。

这是家设备齐全的小型蒸汽洗衣房，凡是机器能做的事情都由最新式的机器代劳。马丁得到些许指点，开始把大堆的脏衣服按种类分开，而乔开动洗衣机，又调制了一些软皂——这是一种含有腐蚀性化学物质的半液体肥皂，逼得他只好用浴巾把口鼻及眼目团团裹住，活似一个木乃伊。马丁分完类，就帮着把衣服弄干。干这种活，得把衣服扔进一个每分钟转几千圈的容器里，靠离心力把衣服里的水分甩出来。接着，马丁在烘干机和绞干机之间跑来跑去，叼空还“抖平”短袜和长袜。下午，他们边加热熨斗，边用轧液机处理短袜和长袜，一个负责往里放，另一个则把袜子拿出来摞好。随即，就用热熨斗烫内衣，一直干到六点钟，乔还是没把握地直摇头。

“干得太慢了，”他说，“吃过饭还得干。”

晚饭后，他们在雪亮的电灯光下一直干到十点钟，直至把最后一件内衣烫好和折叠好，送入分发室里。这是一个炎热的加利福尼亚之夜，窗户虽然都大敞着，但由于生着火红的熨铁炉子，屋里简直成了个大熔炉。马丁和乔只穿着件背心，光着膀子，冒着热汗，大口喘着粗气。

“这活真像是在热带装卸货物。”两人上楼的时候，马丁说。

“你能干得了，”乔回答说，“你工作起来真是好样的。照这样干下去，你这三十块钱的工钱恐怕只拿一个月，第二个月就可以拿到四十块钱。别跟我说你以前没熨过衣服，我可是明眼人。”

“不骗你，我以前从来没熨过衣服，今天这是第一次。”马丁争辩道。

回到房间里，他吃惊地发现自己已十分疲惫，全然忘了他一刻也没停地站着干了十四个小时的活。他把闹钟上到六点钟，屈指一算，减去五个钟点就是一点钟。看书可以看到那个时候。他脱掉鞋舒展发肿的脚，然后在摆满了书的桌旁坐了下来，他把费斯克的书翻到两天前合上的地方，开始阅读。可是刚看第一段就有些吃力，于是他把那段又看了一遍。他不知不觉睡着了，醒来时感到浑身酸痛、肌肉僵硬，叫窗口灌入的山风吹得发冷。他看看表，时针指着两点钟，他已经睡了四个小时。他把衣服脱掉，爬到床上，头一挨枕头就睡着了。

星期二仍是一个不停干活的日子。乔手脚麻利，干活一个人顶十二个魔鬼，深得马丁的敬佩。他工作效率极高，在漫长的一天里无时无刻不在争分夺秒。他干活精力集中，千方百计节省时间，指教马丁在哪些地方可以用三个动作干原需五个动作的活，或者用一个动作干三个动作的活。马丁边观看边效仿，称其为“取消无用动作”。他自己也是个干活能手，又快又灵巧，而且一向引以为自豪的是：不让别人替他干一点活，也不让别人超过他。所以，他工作起来也是精力集中、全神贯注，热心接受工友的提示和建议，他“擦净”领子和袖口，将两层亚麻布之间的浆水揩掉，免得熨时起泡，其工作速度赢得了乔的赞扬。

他们一刻也不闲，从未遇到无活可干的时候。乔不是等着活儿找他，也不专门料理一件事情，而是连续不断地把活干了一件又一件。他们为两百件白衬衫上浆，干的时候一把抓起一件衬衫，让袖口、领子、抵肩和前胸都突出在这只紧握着的右手之外。同时，左手托起衣身，免得沾上浆水，而右手则浸入浆水里——由于浆水烫得厉害，他们必须时不时地把手伸进冷水桶里泡泡，才能把浆好的部位弄干。这天晚上，他们一直干到十点半，给“高档服装”上浆——这些都是小姐太太们穿的那种镶着褶边、既轻薄又精致的衣服。

“我情愿上热带去，那就不用洗衣服了。”马丁笑着说。

“那我可就要失业了，”乔一本正经地答话道，“除了洗衣服，我什么都不会干。”

“洗衣这一行你十分精通。”

“这倒是真的。十一岁时，我就在奥克兰的康特拉·科斯塔开始为人家洗衣服，把衣服一件件“拉平”送入轧液机。那是十八年前的事情，至今都没干过别的工作。这活真是太吓人了，至少得两个人联手干，明天夜里还得加班，因为星期三夜间总少不了用轧液机处理领子和袖口。”

马丁拨好闹钟，来到桌前，将费斯克的书翻开，可是连一段也没看完。一行行的字模糊起来，挤到了一处，而他打起盹来。他起身来回走动，用拳头猛擂自己的脑袋，还是驱赶不走睡意。他把书竖到面前，用手指撑开眼皮，就这么睁着眼入睡了。最后，他只好作罢，几乎无知无觉地脱掉衣服，倒在了床上。他睡了七个小时，像野兽一样睡得很死，被闹钟叫醒时还觉得自己没睡够。

“书看多了吧？”乔问。

马丁摇了摇头。

“没关系，今晚是得操纵轧液机，但星期四六点钟就歇工，让你有时间看看书。”

这一天，马丁用手在一个大桶里洗毛料衣服，软皂调得浓浓的，而且借助于一个装在一根杆子上的马车轮子的车毂，那杆子连着头顶上方的一根弹簧杆。

“这是我的发明，”乔自豪地说，“比用洗衣板和指关节强，除此以外，每星期至少还能节省十五分钟的时间。十五分钟，在这种行当里，可是不能小瞧的。”

用轧液机处理领子和袖口，也是乔想出的主意。这天夜里他们在电灯下一边苦干，他一边解释着。

“除了这家洗衣店，别人没这样干过。要想在星期六下午三点钟完工，我只得这么干。我知道怎么去做，这就是诀窍。必须有适当的温度和适当的压力，而且要处理三次。你瞧！”他用手拎起一只袖口，“无论是手工还是用熨衣机，都不会有这么好的效果。”

待到星期四，乔却火冒三丈，因为有人送来一捆额外的“高档服装”让他们洗。

“我不打算干啦，”他宣称道，“简直让人无法容忍，我干脆辞职算啦。整整一个星期，我像奴隶一样只知道干活，节省一分一秒的时间，可他们却跑来把额外的衣服堆到我的头上，这算怎么回事呢？这是个自由的国家，我要去找那个肥胖的荷兰猪讲讲我对他的看法。我在他面前才不说法语呢。我觉得美国话对我挺合适。哼，他竟敢把额外的衣服推给我浆洗！”

“今晚咱们又得干活了。”他紧接着就这样说道，态度来了个一百八十度大转弯，向命运屈服了。

这天晚上，马丁没有看书。他已经整整一星期没看日报了，而且惊奇地发现自己竟然失去了阅报的欲望。他对新闻不感兴趣。由于疲倦和劳累，他对什么事情都不感兴趣。星期六下午三点如果能把活干完，他打算骑车子到奥克兰去。到那儿的路程是七十英里，星期天下午赶回来还得骑七十英里，这一来一去就会使他无法得到休息以应付下个星期的工作了。乘火车倒是挺便当，但来回得花两块半钱，而他正在一个心思攒钱呢。

[1]　19世纪美国历史学家和进化论者。

第十七章

马丁学会了干许多活。头个星期的一天下午，他和乔一起熨烫二百件白衬衫。乔操纵熨衣机，这种机器里有一只钩在一根钢丝上的热熨斗，而钢丝的作用是提供压力。用这种工具，他又是烫抵肩和袖口又是熨领子，使领子和衣身形成一定的角度，最后再把前襟熨得平平展展。一熨好，他就把衬衫扔到他和马丁之间的一个架子上，由马丁拿去“复熨”。马丁的这项工作是熨烫未上浆的所有部位。

这是件耗人体力的工作，以极高的速度一个钟点一个钟点地持续着。在外边，旅馆宽敞的阳台上，一些男女穿着凉爽的白衣服，呷着冰镇饮料，保持着正常的体温。可是在洗衣房里，空气却热得发烫。大火炉子呼呼吐出火红和白热的火焰，熨斗在湿布上移来移去，散发出如云似雾的水蒸气。这些熨斗的热度与家庭妇女所用的是不一样的。通常用湿指头测其温度的熨斗对乔和马丁来说就太凉了，所以这样的测试是无用的。他们把熨斗拿起来靠近脸颊，完全靠某种玄妙的心理活动测试温度，对此马丁很是欣赏，可就是弄不明白其中的道理。当刚热好的熨斗太烫的时候，他们就把熨斗挂到铁棒上，浸泡到冷水里去。这也需要精确而微妙的判断力。在水中哪怕多泡几分之一秒，那不太冷不太热恰到好处的温度就会消失。马丁感到惊奇的是，自己竟能达到如此高的精确度——这是一种无意识的精确度，所依据的准则似机械般万无一失。

可是，马丁没有时间去赞叹，他的全部精力都集中到了工作上。他一刻不停地干着活，头脑并用，活像一台智能机器，而提供这种智能的是他的全部身心。他的大脑里没有余地可以容纳宇宙以及宇宙间的重大问题，那儿的所有宽阔的通道都已关闭，封得严严实实。他心里的回音堂变成了斗室和控制塔，只知道操纵他的胳膊、肩上的肌肉和灵巧的十指去移动熨斗——那熨斗来去如飞、上下舞动，精确得不多不少、不远不近，身后留下团团水蒸气；他永无休止地熨着衬衫的袖子、腰身、后背和后摆，熨好一件就扔到架子上，一点皱襞也不起。他心情急切，扔着第一件的当儿，就去取第二件。这样的工作一个钟点又一个钟点地连绵不断。加利福尼亚的太阳顶头高照，外面的整个世界都昏昏欲睡，而这间闷热难熬的房子里却没有人昏睡，因为阳台上的那些乘凉的客人需要穿干净的衣服。

马丁汗如雨下。他喝了大量的水，可是由于天气太热、用力太猛，他体内的水分从每个毛孔不停地朝外泄。在海上作业的时候，少数情况除外，他总是有许多时间思考问题。船主仅仅支配马丁的时间；可是在这儿，旅馆的经理不仅支配马丁的时间，还支配他的思想。他万念俱空，除了这折磨精神，摧残肉体的苦活，什么都不想，而且也不可能去想。他忘掉了自己在爱着露丝，她甚至压根就不存在，因为他那颗受人驱使的心无暇想到她。只有夜间爬到床上，或早晨用餐的时候，他才会想到她，但这种回忆转瞬即逝。

“这儿是地狱，对吗？”有一次，乔这样说道。

马丁点了点头，可是心里却感到一阵恼怒。这句话是无可非议的，就是有点多余。他们干活时是不讲话的，因为一讲话会打乱他们的步调。譬如，这一次马丁就少熨了一下，他只好又补熨了两下才赶上了原来的步调。

星期五上午，洗衣机开动了。每星期两次，他们得洗旅馆里的亚麻织物——被单、枕套、被罩、桌布和餐巾。洗完这些，他们又接着认认真真地开始对付“高档服装”。干这活可快不成，既讲究又细致，马丁学来着实不容易。再说，他可不能鲁莽行事，一出错就会造成灾难。

“你瞧，”乔拎起一件薄如蝉翼、团在手心里就可以让人看不见的紧身胸衣，说道，“要是把这玩意儿熨糊了，就得扣你二十块钱的工钱。”

所以，马丁没有把衣服熨糊。他放松了紧绷的肌肉，可精神却空前紧张起来，艰难而痛苦地熨着那些无须自己洗衣的女人们所穿的漂亮玩意儿，一边同情地听乔在那儿骂骂咧咧。“高档服装”给马丁带来了噩梦，也给乔带来了噩梦。正是这种“高档服装”剥削走了他们辛辛苦苦节省下的时间，使他们终日劳作。傍晚七点钟，他们停下手中的活，把旅馆里的亚麻织物送入轧液机。十点钟，当旅馆客人入睡时，这两位洗衣工又继续汗流浃背地熨“高档服装”，直至午夜一点钟，两点钟。干到两点半钟，他们才歇工。

星期六上午又穷于应付“高档服装”和一些零碎的小玩意儿，下午三点钟这一星期的活才算干完。

“这么累了，你不会又要骑车赶七十英里的路跑到奥克兰去吧？”当他们坐到楼梯上，悠然自得抽烟的时候，乔问道。

“我得去。”马丁回答。

“图什么呢？——去追求姑娘？”

“不是。是为了节省两块半钱的火车票。我想到图书馆续借几本书。”

“为什么不用快件把书寄去，再求他们寄来呢？来去都只花两角五分钱。”

马丁考虑着他的建议。

“明天休息一下，”对方劝告道，“你需要休息，我知道我也需要。我简直累得要死。”

他的确是倦容满面。他一往无前，未有过片刻的休息，一星期来争分夺秒，避免了种种耽搁，摧毁了道道险障，活似不可抗拒的力量源泉和开足马力的肉体机器，工作时显示出超人的精力。现在，一星期的任务已经完成，他却处于崩溃的境地。他疲倦、憔悴，一张英俊的面孔累得颓萎不振。他无精打采地抽着烟，声音出奇地单调和死气沉沉。他体内的活力和生气消逝得无影无踪。他的胜利看来是场凄惨的胜利。

“下星期还得从头干，”他忧郁地说，“唉，累死累活有什么用呢？有时候真想当个流浪汉，因为他们不用干活，照样可以活下去。老天！多么希望能有杯啤酒喝，可就是打不起精神到村里去买。你最好留下来养精蓄锐，把书邮寄过去，不然你就太傻啦。”

“星期天在这儿待一天，能干什么呢？”马丁问。

“休息。你意识不到你有多疲倦。唉，一到星期天我就累散了架，连报纸也看不进去。有一次我染上了伤寒，在医院里躺了两个半月，一点活也不干。那滋味真是美。”

“真是美啊！”隔了一小会儿，他又做梦似的重复了一遍。

马丁洗了个澡，出来却发现洗衣工头不见了踪影，心想他八成去喝酒了，可是要到村里找他得走半英里的路，未免太远了些。他脱掉鞋躺到床上，想集中一下思想。他没有伸手取书看，累得连睡意也没有了，而只是昏昏沉沉躺在那儿，几乎什么也不想，一直到吃晚饭的时候。乔没回来吃饭，马丁听花匠说他很可能是到酒吧痛饮去了，这才明白了过来。吃完饭他就上床睡觉了，第二天早晨觉得体力已大大恢复。此时，乔仍未归来。马丁拿上一份星期日报纸，找块树荫躺了下来。于不知不觉之中，一上午的时间都过去了。他没有睡着，也无人来打扰，可他连一份报纸也没看完。吃过饭后，他下午又回到原地看报，看着看着就睡着了。

星期天就这么打发掉了。星期一早晨，他又开始苦干，忙着对衣服进行分类，而乔把一条毛巾紧缠在头上，哼哼唧唧、骂骂咧咧地又是操纵洗衣机又是调制软皂。

“我简直克制不住自己，”他解释说，“一到星期六的晚上，就得一醉方休。”

又一个星期过去了。他们天天晚上都鏖战于电灯之下，这场恶战一直持续到星期六下午三点钟才宣告结束。此时的乔仅仅短暂地品尝一下苦涩的胜利滋味，便又溜到村里借酒浇愁了。马丁的星期天过得一如以往。他躺在树荫下漫无目的地胡乱看着报，仰面朝天躺在那儿，一待就是好几个小时，什么也不干什么也不想。他头脑昏昏沉沉，思考不成问题，但心里却明白他并不喜欢自己的这个样子。他自我厌恶，仿佛他已经堕落，或者原本就是个混蛋。他心里所有的神圣观念都化为乌有，勃勃雄心变成了麻木不仁；他已经丧失了所有的活力去感受雄心的跳动。他死了。他的灵魂似乎死了。他是一头畜生，一条干活的牲口。在他的眼里，绿色的树叶间洒下的阳光失去了美感，蔚蓝色的天空不再像以前那样对他窃窃私语，向他描绘浩瀚的宇宙和急切地吐露秘密。生活枯燥乏味得令人无法忍受，含到嘴里是苦涩的味道。他心里的明镜蒙上了一层黑布，而幻想则躺在一间不透光线的昏暗病房里。他羡慕乔，因为乔可以毫无顾忌地跑到村里的酒吧间畅饮，任大脑胡思乱想，发发伤感的感慨，痛痛快快、欢欢喜喜喝个酩酊大醉，忘掉星期一，忘掉下个星期那叫人死去活来的苦活。

第三个星期过去了；马丁憎恨自己，也憎恨生活。一种失败的感觉在左右着他。那些编辑冷落他的作品，是有原因的。这些他现在看得一清二楚，于是不禁嘲笑自己，嘲笑自己曾经怀有的梦想。露丝把《海洋抒情诗》寄还给了他。他冷淡漠然地看了她的来信。她竭力声明自己是多么喜欢这些诗，说这些诗写得非常美。可是她不会撒谎，掩饰不住内心的真实看法。在她看来，这些诗是失败之作，从她的信中每一句敷衍和淡漠的话里他都可以瞧出她的不满。按说，她是没有错的。他把这些诗又重新看了一遍，对这一点深信不疑。他已经失去了美感和幻想，而今重温诗句，禁不住纳闷起来，不知自己当初创作的时候心里想的是什么。那些大胆的词语现在读起来显得荒诞不经，巧妙的措辞显得滑稽可笑，一切都是那样荒唐、不真实和无法思议。他恨不得立时就把《海洋抒情诗》付之一炬，只是他缺乏这样的强烈愿望。引擎机房就在那儿，可是要把诗稿拿去投入火炉却有些得不偿失，因为他的全部气力都用于为别人洗衣服了，已没有丝毫的精力干私事。

他决定待到星期天，自己将打起精神给露丝回封信。然而星期六下午一干完活，他洗了个澡，就涌起了忘掉一切的欲望。“我想还是去看看乔的情况吧，”他这样对自己说；话一出口，他就知道自己在扯谎。不过，他没有精力考虑这是否谎话；即便有精力，他也不愿考虑，因为他想忘掉一切。他慢吞吞信步朝村里走去，接近酒吧时，脚下不由自主加快了步伐。

“我原以为你戒酒了呢。”乔招呼他道。

马丁不屑辩白，而是要了瓶威士忌，为自己斟满一杯，然后把瓶子递给了对方。

“别净扯这些。”他粗鲁地说。

对方斟酒时慢慢悠悠，马丁等不及，便把杯里的酒一口饮干，又斟了一杯。

“这一杯可以等等你，”他冷冰冰地说，“不过，请你放快点。”

乔连忙为自己斟上酒，二人对饮起来。

“干这样的活叫你开了戒，是吗？”乔问道。

马丁不愿讨论这个问题。

“这儿是活地狱，我心里清楚，”对方继续说道，“但我不愿看到你大开酒戒，马特。算啦，让我敬你一杯！”

马丁默不作声只顾喝酒，把自己要的酒以及对方请的酒都一杯杯饮干，使那位长着一双水汪汪的蓝眼睛、梳着中分头的女里女气的乡下年轻招待肃然起敬。

“他们逼着咱们这些可怜人拼命干活，实在是可恶，”乔说道，“要是没酒做伴，我准会失去控制，把那地方放火烧掉，告诉你，多亏有了酒，才使他们幸免于难。”

马丁没搭腔，又喝了几杯，有些陶陶欲醉，觉得有些小虫在脑子里爬来爬去。啊，这才是生活！三个星期来，他第一次呼吸到了生活的气息。美梦又重新出现，而幻想步出昏暗的病房，似一团灿烂夺目的火球，诱引他前行。他心里的那面镜子洁净如洗，宛若一尊光芒四射、令人眼花缭乱的铜像。奇迹和美感与他携手并进，把力量注入他的全身。他想把这情形讲给乔听，可是乔也沉湎于幻想，勾画着自己的宏伟蓝图——摆脱奴役般的洗衣苦活，开一家大规模的蒸汽洗衣店，自己当老板。

“告诉你，马特，我的洗衣店不雇童工——绝对不雇。下午六点钟一过，所有的人都停止工作。你听我说！我的店里机器多，人手也多，正常的上班时间就能把活干完。说真的，马特，我要任命你为洗衣店的总管，所有的一切都听命于你。你听听我的计划。我要把酒戒掉，攒上两年的钱——有了钱就——”

可是马丁把身子转了过去，丢下他把心里的话向那位招待倾吐。后来，那位招待也受到马丁的支使，去为两位刚进门的庄稼汉取酒。马丁慷慨解囊，请大家一道痛饮，其中有几位庄稼汉、一个马夫、旅馆里的花匠助手、酒吧招待，还有一个似幽灵般溜进来又似幽灵般在酒吧间的一端转来转去的流浪汉。

第十八章

星期一早晨，乔哼哼唧唧地把第一车衣物推到洗衣机跟前。

“听我说。”他启口道。

“别跟我讲话！”马丁咆哮了起来。

“对不起，乔。”中午歇工吃饭的时候，他说道。

对方的眼里涌出了泪花。

“没什么，老伙计，”他说，“咱们都生活在地狱里，控制不了自己。你知道，我是非常喜欢你的，这才是让我伤心的原因。从一开始我就对你产生了好感。”

马丁握了握他的手。

“干脆不干啦，”乔建议道，“咱们丢下这份工作流浪去。我虽然没尝试过，但四处流浪一定轻松得很。什么事情都不用做。你想想吧，什么事情都不用做！有一次我患伤寒症住院，那滋味真是美。真希望再病上一场。”

这个星期，时光过得很慢。旅馆里人满为患，“高档服装”似潮水向他们涌来。他们创建了英雄的业绩。每天他们都在电灯光下奋战到深夜，吃饭时狼吞虎咽，甚至在早饭前还要赶半个小时的活。马丁不再洗冷水澡。每一分钟都是拼搏、奋战和苦干；而乔是个专横的时间牧人，细心地控制着分分秒秒，不让有丝毫闪失，像守财奴数金子一样把时间计算来计算去，干起活就发疯，恰似一台开足马力的机器。为他充当干练助手的是另一台机器，这台机器自以为曾经是个名为马丁·伊登的人。

不过，马丁很少去思考。思想的殿堂大门深锁，窗户被木板钉得严严实实，而他是这座殿堂影影绰绰的守门人。他是个幽灵。乔说得对，他们俩都是幽灵，永无休止地干着地狱里的苦役。莫非这是一场梦？有时，当他把沉重的熨斗在白色的衣服上拉来推去，周围升腾起热烫的蒸汽时，他觉得眼前的一切都是梦。只消一会儿工夫，但也许要在一千年之后，他就会从梦中醒来，回到自己的小屋里和那张沾满墨迹的桌子前重新开始撰稿，从昨天辍笔的那个地方写起。或者，这也是一场梦。他醒来时也许会赶上换夜班，那时他将在东摇西晃的水手舱里跳下床铺，登上甲板，头顶热带的繁星操掌舵轮，听凭凉爽的贸易风渗透肌肤。

星期六下午三点钟，空洞的胜利再次来到。

“我得去弄杯啤酒喝喝。”乔说道，声音古怪而单调，流露出周末的疲倦。

马丁似乎猛然从梦中惊醒。他打开工具包，给自行车上好油，往链条上涂些石墨，又调了调轴承。他超过正在朝酒吧走的乔，弯下身子，手握车把，两腿均匀用力蹬动九十六齿的齿轮，表情坚定地赶那高低不平、尘土飞扬的七十英里路程。当天夜里他宿在奥克兰，星期天又骑了七十英里朝回赶。星期一早晨，又一个星期的活儿开始了，他虽然周身疲倦，但头脑却得到了清醒。

第五个星期过去了，紧接着就是第六个星期。他生活和工作都像台机器。体内只剩下了一点点活力和一丝丝精神，就靠这些他每个周末要走一百四十英里的路程。这样的旅行根本不是什么休息，而是地地道道的机械运动，摧毁了他以前所残留下的最后一丝精神。第七个星期结束时，他抵挡不住诱惑，身不由己地跟乔一道跑到村里喝得死去活来，直至星期一早晨。

以后每逢周末，他又紧着赶那一百四十英里的路程。平时干活他耗力太多，感到头脑麻木，而骑车子旅行耗力更多，所以头脑更麻木。第三个月结尾时，他和乔第三次到村里喝酒。他喝得忘掉了一切，接着又清醒过来，就在清醒的当儿，他清楚地看到自己正在变成畜生——这并非饮酒的缘故，而是由苦活所造成。饮酒是结果，不是原因。它是苦活的必然结果，就像白天过后紧跟着就是黑夜一样。威士忌悄悄告诉他，沦为干活的牲口是无法跻身社会上层的，对此他点头称是。威士忌是明智的，它吐露了生活的秘密。

他要来纸和笔，然后为大伙儿斟酒。当人们为他的健康干杯时，他却伏在柜台上挥笔疾书。

“这是份电报，乔，”他说，“你把它看看。”

乔醉醺醺、好奇地斜眼瞧了瞧，但他所看到的电文似乎让他清醒了过来。他责怪地望着对方，泪珠打眼里滚出，顺着脸颊朝下淌。“你难道要背叛我，马特？”他绝望地问。

马丁点点头，随后把一个闲汉唤到跟前，让他把电文送到电报局去。

“请等一下，”乔口齿不清地说，“容我想想。”

他用手抓住柜台，两条腿抖如筛糠，马丁伸出条胳膊搂住他，扶着他让他思考。

“把电文改为两个洗衣工，”他霍然开口说，“拿来，让我改吧。”

“你为什么也不干了？”马丁问。

“和你的原因一样。”

“我去航海，那活你是干不了的。”

“不错，”对方说，“但我可以流浪呀，那也挺好的。”

马丁对着他仔细打量了一会儿，然后叫嚷道：

“老天，我觉得你是对的。宁肯当一个流浪汉也比做只知道干活的牲口好。啊，老兄，你会过上满意生活的，以前你可没过上一天舒心的日子。”

“我住过一次医院，”乔纠正他的话说，“那段时间过得很舒心，当时染的是伤寒症——这事我对你讲过吧？”

马丁把电文改成了“两个洗衣工”。趁他修改的工夫，乔又接着说：“我住院的时候，一点都不想喝酒。听起来有点可笑，是吧？我要是像奴隶一样干上一个星期的活，就必须痛饮一顿。你可曾留意过厨子们都是不要命地喝酒？——面包师不是也一样？那是干活导致的，是一种必然结果。来，让我付一半电报费。”

“咱们抛骰决定谁付钱吧。”马丁建议道。

“来呀，大伙儿都喝呀。”乔叫喊道。他和马丁咔啦咔啦地摇着骰子，抛到湿漉漉的柜台上。

星期一早晨，乔怀着急切的心情期待着。他不顾自己的头痛，对工作也不热心了。大量的时间悄然走失，而心不在焉的时间牧人却呆望着窗外的阳光和树木。

“瞧那儿的风光！”他叫喊道，“全是我的，一个铜板也不收！我可以躺到树下，随心所欲地睡他一千年。喂，你过来，马特，咱们现在就离开这儿吧。再多待一会儿也早晚是个走。到自由的天地去，那儿什么活都不用干。我有一张到那里去的车票——这次可不是往返车票！”

几分钟后，乔把一些脏衣服装到车上，准备送到洗衣机那儿，不料看到了旅馆经理的衬衫。他认得衬衫上的标记，心里突然产生了一种大胆的念头，于是把衬衫扔到地上，用脚乱踩一气。

“真希望你就在衣服下，猪头猪脑的荷兰佬！”他喊道，“你要是真在这儿，就让我踩着了！把这一脚送给你！还有一脚！还有一脚！去你妈的！拉住我呀，让人拉住我呀！快把我拖回去呀！”

马丁哈哈大笑，拉着他让他干活去了。星期二晚上，新雇的洗衣工来了，这星期剩下的几天就是调教他们，让他们熟悉工作。乔坐在一旁讲解他的那套方法，自己却什么也不干。

“再也不干了，”他声称，“一点都不干了。想开除就让他们开除吧。他们一解雇我，我正好离开。谢谢你们喽，我可是再也不干啦。我向往的是货车和树荫。加油干呀，你们这些奴隶！对，汗流浃背地拼命干吧！累个半死，流一身臭汗！你们死后会和我一样腐烂掉，所以你们现在过怎样的日子又有什么关系？呃？说呀——到头来有什么关系呢？”

星期六他们领到工钱，就到了各奔东西的时候。

“你愿意听我的劝告，改变主意，和我一道浪迹天涯吗？”乔绝望地问。

马丁摇了摇头。他站在自行车旁，已准备启程。他们握手时，乔把他的手拉紧说：

“在你我离开人世之前，我还会见到你的，马特。这可不是虚无缥缈的愿望，我打骨头缝里都能感觉得到再见，马特，请多保重。你知道，我是非常喜欢你的。”

他站立在路中央，一副凄惨的样子，目送着马丁拐过弯去，不见了踪影。

“那小伙子是好样的，”他自言自语地说，“他是好样的。”

随后，他拖着沉重而缓慢的步子朝水塔的方向走去，那儿有六七节空车皮停在支线上等待装货。

第十九章

露丝和家人都回到了府里。马丁返回奥克兰后，他们常见面。她拿上了学位，就不再看什么书了；而他累得心力交瘁，所以也没有写作。这样，他们便有了大量时间相处，这是前所未有过的，两人的关系一天天亲密起来。

起初，马丁无所事事，只顾一个劲地休息。他老是睡觉，除此之外就长时间地沉思默想，别的什么都不干。他像是经历了一场可怕的灾难，正在逐渐恢复。这种复苏的最初迹象表现在他对日报不再是漠不关心，而是产生了一定的兴趣。接着，他又开始看起书来——先是看轻松的小说，继而读诗歌；几天之后，他便全神贯注地阅读起搁置已久的费斯克的作品来。他那强壮和健康的身体里又涌出了新的活力，青春又重新焕发，回到了他的身上。

当他声称自己一休息好还要再次出海远航时，露丝明显地露出了失望的神情。

“为什么要出海呢？”她问。

“为了钱，”马丁答道，“我得积聚实力，再次向编辑们发动进攻。钱就是军费，而我既需要钱也需要耐心。”

“如果你想得到的仅仅是钱，那你为什么不留在洗衣店呢？”

“因为洗衣店把我变成了一头牲口。那种活干得太多，就会把人逼得酗酒。”

她向他投来惶恐的目光。

“你是说——？”她的声音都在颤抖。

按说，要想摆脱眼前的困境也不难，可他生性喜欢直来直去，此时他没忘记自己以前做出的决定：不管发生什么情况，对人都以坦诚相见。

“是的，”他答道，“是那么回事，喝过几回酒。”

她身子一哆嗦，朝后缩了缩。

“我认识的人没有一个喝酒——那是绝没有的。”

“那是因为他们没一个在雪莱温泉旅馆的洗衣店里干过活，”他苦笑一声说，“劳动是桩好事情，为保持健康所必需，所有的传教士都这么说，上天知道我从来就不害怕劳动。但有的时候，好事会过了头变成坏事，洗衣店里的工作就属于这种情况。所以，我要再次出海。我觉得这将是我的最后一次航行了，因为回来后，我就会打入杂志社。对此，我是有把握的。”

她没有作声，对他的话无动于衷。他闷闷不乐地望着她，意识到如欲让她理解他所经历过的事情，简直是不可能的。

“总有一天，我会把洗衣店里的生活详细写出——用《劳役使人堕落》或《工人阶级中的喝酒心理》这一类题目。”

自打第一次见面以来，他们似乎从未像今天这样疏远过。他的坦率直言里隐含着反抗精神，这让她感到厌恶。然而，使她最为吃惊的还不是厌恶本身，而是引起厌恶的原因。这说明她和他已过于接近，她一旦承认了这一点，他们之间的关系会更加亲密。怜悯之情在她的心里油然而生，随之而至的是改造对方的天真和充满理想主义色彩的念头。她要挽救这个尚未成熟的堕落青年，使他摆脱早期环境种下的祸根，帮助他走上正道。她以为这是一种崇高的思想境界，可她万万想不到这种念头的背后和深处暗藏着恋人的挑剔及欲望。

在秋高气爽的季节，他们常骑自行车外出兜风，到群山里轮流朗诵诗歌，朗诵那些催人向上、令人向往崇高事物的诗句。通过诗歌她所间接宣扬的是克己、牺牲、忍耐、勤勉和发愤努力这样的原则——在她的心目中，能够体现这种抽象概念的是她的父亲、勃特勒先生，以及安德鲁·卡内基——此人从一个穷苦的移民小孩奋斗成了青史留名的世界名人。

这一切都深得马丁的欣赏和喜欢。现在他比较清楚地看出了她的心理活动，而她的灵魂不再是神奇的谜。他和她在智力上是平等的。不过，他们之间观点的分歧并未影响他的爱。他爱得反而更加热烈了，因为他爱的是她本人，连她娇弱的身体在他眼里也增加了她的几分魅力。在书上他看过体弱多病的伊丽莎白·巴莱特的事迹，那女人多年来从未下过床。可是有一天却激情勃发，和勃朗宁一道私奔，挺起腰杆站立于天地之间；勃朗宁为她做的事情，马丁认为自己也能为露丝做到。不过，首先她必须爱他。剩下的事情就容易办了。他可以给她带来力量和健康。几幕未来生活的场景在他的眼前闪现，他看到自己在工作之余过着一种舒适、温馨的日子，他和露丝一起朗读、讨论诗歌，露丝朗读时坐在地板上，身子靠着一大堆靠垫。这就是他们未来生活的基本调子。他所看到的总是这样的场景。有时，由他朗读，一条胳膊搂着她，而她紧偎在他的怀里，把脑袋枕在他肩上。有时，两人则一道在美丽的诗行中遨游。另外，她也是热爱大自然的，所以他常常发挥丰富的想象力去改变读书的环境——他们有时到悬崖峭壁环绕的山谷里，有时登上高山草地，有时卧身于灰白色的沙丘旁，脚下踩一圈起伏的沙浪，有时则远道前往一座热带火山岛，那儿飞泻的瀑布化云变雾冲向海洋，似缕缕水蒸气在阵阵微风的吹拂下游荡和颤抖。但他和露丝总是处于前景，他们是美的主宰，时时都在读诗和分享幸福，而大自然的背景后边则是隐隐约约、朦朦胧胧闪现出工作、成就和挣来的金钱，这些钱可以使他们自由自在生活在这个世界上、充分享受人世间的财富。

“我可要劝劝我的小女，让她多加留意。”一天，母亲警告露丝说。

“我明白你的意思。可是，这是不可能的。他不是——”

露丝飞红了脸。一个姑娘家在母亲面前第一次论及生活中的神圣事情难免会红脸，尤其是这位母亲在她的心目中占有同样神圣的位置。

“不是和你一类的人。”做母亲的把后半句话替她说了出来。

露丝点了点头。

“我本来不愿直说，但他和我的确不是一类人。他粗鲁、野蛮、强壮——简直过于强壮。他的生活——”

她犹犹豫豫，无法再朝下说。跟母亲谈论这种事情对她而言是一种新的体验。这次，还是母亲替她说出了心里的看法。

“他的生活不洁不雅——这就是你想说的话。”

露丝又点点头，脸上又泛起了红潮。

“正是这样，”她说，“虽然并非他的过错，可他接触的尽是——”

“尽是肮脏的事情？”

“对，尽是肮脏的事情。他让我感到害怕。有时，他讲起自己的经历竟不遮不掩、轻轻松松，好像一点也不在乎，真叫人不寒而栗。他的经历是骇人的，对吧？”

她们俩坐在一起，相互用胳膊搂着对方的腰，沉默了片刻。后来，她母亲拍拍她的手，等待她继续往下说。

“不过，我对他非常感兴趣，”她朝下说道，“从某种程度而言，他是我的学生。另外，他也是我交的第一个男朋友——但确切讲又不是朋友，而是学生和朋友的综合体。他让我感到害怕的时候，我有时又觉得他像一条斗牛狗，我和一些喜欢狗的女大学生一样把他当成宠物，可他却使劲挣扎，龇出牙齿，直想摆脱我。”母亲仍未开口，等她说下去。

“依我看，他使我感兴趣，是因为他像斗牛狗。而且，他身上也有许多优良品质；然而，他身上的另外一种我不喜欢的东西也的确不少。你要知道，我一直在考虑这方面的问题。他骂人、抽烟、喝酒，还动拳头跟别人打过架（这是他亲口告诉我的，而且说他喜欢打架）。他根本不符合做人的标准，绝不是我心目中的——”她把声音压得非常低——“丈夫。他的身材太魁梧了。我的白马王子必须身材修长、皮肤黝黑、风度翩翩，叫我一见倾心。我绝对不可能爱上马丁·伊登。如果爱上他，那才是天大的不幸呢。”

“我指的不是这个，”她母亲支支吾吾地说，“你考虑过他的情况吗？他虽然各方面都没资格，但假如他爱上你怎么办呢？”

“他已经——已经爱上了我。”她高声说道。

“这是意料之中的事，”摩斯夫人柔声细语地说，“凡是认识你的人，有哪一个会不爱你呢？”

“奥尔奈就讨厌我！”她情绪激昂地嚷嚷道，“我也讨厌奥尔奈。他一在跟前，我总觉得自己像个恶女人。我觉得我必须对他恶声恶气，即便我没这种感觉，他也照样会对我尖酸刻薄。可是和马丁·伊登在一起，我却心情愉快。没有人那样爱过——我是说没有男人那样爱过我。得到那样的爱，给人以甜蜜的感觉。好妈妈，你知道我的意思。能感受到自己是个真正的女人，该有多幸福啊。”她把脸埋在母亲的膝间，抽噎着，“你一定认为我的想法太可怕，但我说的都是实话，告诉你的都是我心里的感觉。”

摩斯夫人悲喜交集。她的文学学士小女儿不见了，取而代之的是一个成熟的女儿。实验取得了成功。露丝心灵里的那片不正常的空白被填满了，不会有任何危险，也不会产生不良后果。这位粗鲁的水手在中间充当了工具。虽然露丝并不爱他，可是他却让露丝认识到了自己是个女人。

“他的手老是发抖，”露丝说，由于害羞，脸儿仍埋在母亲的膝间，“他那副样子实在滑稽可笑，不过我又为他感到难过。他的手抖得太厉害，眼光太咄咄逼人的时候，我就谈他的生活，向他指出他改变生活所采取的方式是错误的。我看得出他崇拜我，因为他的眼睛和手是瞒不过人的。一想到这一点，一想到他的崇拜，我就感到自己已经长大成人；我觉得自己获得了应该属于我的东西——这样东西使我和其他的姑娘一样，和其他的年轻女人一样。以前我也知道自己与她们不同，知道你为此忧虑万分。你以为我不了解你的心事，但其实我是了解的，而且想——如马丁·伊登所言‘干出成绩来’。”

对母女俩来说，这是个神圣的时刻。两人在暮色里促膝交谈，泪水湿润了她们的眼睛。露丝说话始终天真而坦率，充满同情心的母亲侧耳静听，还心平气和地对她解释及引导。

“他比你小四岁。”母亲说，“在社会上他未赢得一席之地，既无地位又无收入，而且非常不实际。既然爱上了你，按照常理，他就该干点事情，这样才有资格结婚，而不应瞎写什么短篇小说，沉湎于幼稚的幻想。马丁·伊登恐怕永远也长不大。他不愿负起责任来，不愿在社会上承担男子汉的工作，就像你父亲或我们所有的朋友那样——如勃特勒先生便是其中的一个。马丁·伊登恐怕永远也成不了一个挣钱养家的人。这个世界有一条规律：要想幸福，就离不开钱。当然，不一定大富大贵，只要够维持一般性的舒适和像样的生活就行了。他——他从来没放出过话吗？”

“连一个字也没吐过。他没做过这方面的尝试；不过，即便他尝试，我也不会允许，因为你知道我并不爱他。”

“这让我十分高兴。我可不愿看到自己的女儿，自己冰清玉洁的独生女儿，去爱一个他那样的人。天下多的是纯洁、真诚和富于阳刚之美的好男儿。你要耐心等待，总有一天会找到如意郎君，过上相亲相爱的生活。和他在一起，你将会得到幸福，就像我和你父亲一样美满。有一件事你必须时刻牢记心头——”

“是，妈妈。”

摩斯夫人以低沉和亲切的声音说：“那就是孩子的问题。”

“这事我也考虑过。”露丝承认说。她想起自己曾一度产生过的淫荡念头，现在又讲出这种话来，少女的害羞心理使她的脸上又泛起了红晕。

“正是考虑到孩子，才不能选择伊登先生，”摩斯夫人入木三分地说，“后代的血统不能有脏污，而他恐怕并非清白之人。你父亲给我讲过水手的生活——这你是明白的。”

露丝紧紧握了握母亲的手表示同意，觉得自己的确一清二楚，但实际上她想象不来水手的生活，对此只有一种模糊、缥缈和可怕的概念。

“你知道，我干任何事情都不会瞒着你。”她说道，“只不过有的时候你得开口问我，就像这次一样。我原来是想告诉你的，但不知怎样说才好。我知道这是虚伪的矜持，但你可以为我创造条件，让我轻轻松松说出来。有时，你得像这次一样开口问我，给我机会。”

“妈妈，你也是女人呀！”她充满喜悦地嚷嚷道。母女俩站起身来，她拉住母亲的手，挺直腰杆，在暮色中面对着她，想到她们两人都是女性，亲切之感便油然而生。“要不是咱们这样交谈，我怎么也不会把你当作女人。我是了解了自己是个女人，才意识到你也是女人。”

“咱们都是女人。”母亲把她拉到跟前，亲吻着她说，“咱们都是女人。”两人走出房间时，母亲又重复了一遍。她们用胳膊搂住对方的腰肢，心里洋溢着一种志同道合的新感觉。

“咱们的小女儿长大成人啦。”一小时之后，摩斯夫人自豪地对丈夫说。

“你的意思是，”他把妻子盯着瞧了好一会儿，才说道，“你的意思是她恋爱啦。”

“不对，是别人爱上她了，”对方笑盈盈地说，“实验取得了成功，她终于苏醒了。”

“那么，咱们得把他打发掉啦。”摩斯先生说话的口吻既轻松又实际，像做生意时一样。

然而他的妻子却摇了摇头。“没这个必要。露丝说过几天他要出海去。他回来的时候，她就不在这儿了。咱们把她送到克莱拉姑妈家去。再说，到东部住上一年，接触一下不同的气候、人物和观念，一切都换个样，正是她所需要的。”

第二十章

写作的欲望又开始在马丁的心头冲撞。他在大脑里构思出一篇篇的短篇小说和诗歌，打算将来把它们写出来。现在，他不动笔写作，因为他正在度假。他决定把时间都用到休息和爱情上，而且这两桩事情他都干得有声有色。不久，他的周身便充满了活力。每天他都去看望露丝。一见到他，露丝就和以前一样，为他的力量和强健感到震惊。

“当心点，”她母亲又一次警告她说，“恐怕你和马丁·伊登见面见得太勤了些。”

可是露丝仅仅付之一笑，认为没必要担心。她对自己是有把握的，况且再过几天他就要出海去了。待他归来，她已经登上了东行之路。然而，马丁的力量和强健对她具有一种魔力。至于她准备到东部去的事情，马丁也听说了。他觉得必须加快步伐，可是却不知怎样向露丝这样的姑娘求爱。跟那些截然不同于她的姑娘及妇女打交道，他经验丰富，连这些也成了他的不利因素。那些娘们儿懂得爱情、生活和调情，而她在这方面却一无所知。她纯洁得令他吃惊，使他把所有溜到嘴边的热情话又咽回肚中，叫他不由自主地认为自己是个下流胚。另外，他还有一个不利因素：从前他从未恋爱过。过去他生活放荡，喜欢女人，而且曾经迷恋过几个女人，可是却不知道爱情的滋味。他只消专横和漫不经心地吹声口哨，她们就会跑到他身边来。她们是娱乐、插曲，是男人游戏中的一个部分，而且是一个极小的部分。现在，他破天荒第一次成了温柔、胆怯和迟疑的追求者。他不懂恋爱的方式及恋爱的语言，同时又被心上人的天真无邪弄得手足无措。

他接触的是一个纷然杂陈的世界，周旋于千变万化之中，从而学会了一条行为的准则，其大意是：玩陌生的游戏，应该让对方先动手。这条准则给他带来过上千次好处，还把他训练成了观察家。他懂得怎样观察陌生的事物，等待它露出弱点，捕捉可乘之机。这就和打架一样，在搏斗中寻觅机会。这种机会一旦来临，他便会依照长年积累的经验进行出击，狠狠地下手。

他对露丝采取的就是等待的策略，恨不得把自己的爱一吐为快，然而却没这份胆量。他生怕吓坏了她，而且他对自己也缺乏信心。他走的是一条正确的道路，只不过他自己还不知道罢了。世界上是先有爱情，然后才出现了表达爱情的语言。爱情在萌动时期便总结出了种种方法和格式，以后再没有忘记过。而今马丁追求露丝，采用的就是这种古老、原始的方法。起初他还认识不到，后来才有所体会。他用手摸一下她的手，这其中所产生的威力胜过千言万语，他的力量给她的想象带来的影响要大于书中的诗歌以及历代恋人炽烈的情话。无论他说出什么样的话，从某种程度而言，都针对的是她的思想；然而手的抚摸，这极为短暂的接触，却直接针对的是她的本能。她的思想跟她本人一样年轻。而她的本能却似人类历史一般古老，甚至比人类历史更为古老。这种本能随着爱情一道诞生，比习俗、舆论以及所有的新生事物都明智。她的思想毫无动静，因为没有接收到外来的刺激，同时她也不知道马丁在时不时地触动她那爱的本性。从另一方面来看，他深爱着她——这是再明显不过的了；看到他的爱情表露——含情脉脉和燃烧着烈火的眼睛、颤抖的双手、太阳晒黑的脸膛上泛起的暗色红潮，她便感到心花怒放。她甚至向纵深发展，怯生生地挑逗他，然而做得十分巧妙，让他无法觉察；这种行为只是半心半意，所以她自己也几乎认识不到。他为她的魅力倾倒，这证明她是个女人，令她激动不已，而她像夏娃一样以折磨和玩弄他为乐。

马丁感情过于强烈，但经验不足，所以结结巴巴说不出话来，使他的追求显得缺乏意识和尴尬，于是他只有靠手的触摸接近她。他的触摸令她感到惬意，甚至给她带来了快感。这一点马丁并不知道，但他知道她不讨厌他的触摸。他们并非经常手拉手，而只是在见面和分别时握握手。不过，在搬动自行车的时候，把诗集捆在一起带往山里去的时候，以及肩并肩一道看书的时候，他们的手倒是偶然会触触碰碰。他们凑在一起欣赏书中的美丽诗句时，她的秀发常常轻拂他的面颊，他们的肩膀紧挨在一起。她笑自己无端端会生出几丝冲动，想去揉乱他的头发；而他看书看累的时候，渴望把头枕在她的膝上，闭眼幻想他们的未来。过去的星期日，无论是到贝冢公园还是到许采恩公园野餐，他都枕过不少女人的膝盖，通常自顾自地酣睡不醒，而那些姑娘则为他遮挡阳光，低头用疼爱的目光打量着他，弄不懂他为什么那么高傲，对她们的爱为什么那么漫不经心。把头枕在姑娘的膝盖上，对他来说一直是天底下最容易的事情，可现在他却觉得没有办法，也不可能接近露丝的膝盖。不过，他默默地想到，正是这一点给了他追求的力量。由于他秘而不宣，才没有使她感到恐惧。她虽然难以取悦和谨小慎微，然而觉察不到他们的交往在向危险的方向发展。她不知不觉、一点一点向他靠拢，和他越来越近乎，他感觉到了这种亲密性。真想放大胆试一次，可就是心存戒虑。

一天下午，他看到她头痛欲裂地坐在昏暗的起居室里，终于做出了大胆的举动。

“简直一点办法都没有，”她在回答他的询问时说，“再说，我不能服头痛粉，这是霍尔医生所不允许的。”

“我想我可以治好你的病，而且不用药物。”马丁说，“当然，我不敢保险，只是想试试。我用的是按摩法。这种窍道最初是跟日本人学的。你知道，他们都是些按摩专家。后来，我又跟夏威夷人学，又学到一些新方法。夏威夷人管按摩叫‘洛米—洛米’药物起的效用，按摩一般都能办到，有些药物起不到的效用，它也能办到。”

他的手刚一触摸到她的头，她便深深舒了口气。

“真舒服啊。”她说。

半个小时之后，她才再次开口，问道：“你累吗？”

这句话问得实在没必要，因为她明知他会怎样回答。随后，她迷迷糊糊地遐想起来，一味想着他的力量所具有的止痛功效。他的指尖散发出生命力，将疼痛赶散驱尽，或者，在她看来是这样的。疼痛消除之后，她熟睡了起来，而他悄然无息地溜走了。

傍晚，她给他打了个电话向他致谢。

“我一直睡到吃晚饭的时候，”她说，“你彻底医好了我的病；伊登先生，真不知怎样感谢你。”

他欣喜若狂，心里暖洋洋的，拙嘴笨舌地回着她的话。他们一边在电话上交谈，他在脑海中一边思想着勃朗宁和多病的伊丽莎白·巴莱特的爱情。他马丁·伊登可以让过去的事情重新发生，可以为露丝·摩斯做同样的事情。他回到自己的房间，又拿起了摊开放在床头的斯宾塞的那本《社会学原理》。然而，他却看不下去。爱情折磨着他，战胜了他的意志。所以，他尽管打定主意不写作，还是身不由己地坐到了墨迹斑斑的小桌旁。这天夜里他创作的一首十四行诗，为他的爱情组诗开了个头，后边的四十九首于两个月内完稿。他写作时，脑子里想的是《葡萄牙人的爱情诗》，处于创作伟大作品的最佳状况，因为他本人置身于生活的转折点，被疯狂和甜美的爱情所折磨。

离开露丝的身旁，他就用大量的时间创作《爱情组诗》、在家看书，或者到公共阅览室细致地阅读当天的杂志，了解杂志的方针政策及思想内容。他和露丝在一起度过的时光虽充满希望，但毫无结果，这两点同样都叫他乐得发疯。他为她医好头痛症一个星期后的一天，诺曼提议到梅里特湖在月下泛舟，阿瑟和奥尔奈一致赞同。只有马丁一人会驾船，所以大伙儿硬是强迫他跟着去。他和露丝坐在船尾，两人之间隔着很近的距离，而那三个小伙子斜躺在船中央，在激烈地争论“大学联谊会”的事务。

月亮还没有升起来。露丝望着星光灿烂的苍穹，跟马丁一句话也不说，心里突然产生了一股寂寞感。她用目光扫了他一眼。一阵风吹斜了船身，甲板都给水打湿了，但见他一手掌舵，一手抓住主帆索，轻轻拨动船头使其朝着风向，同时目视前方，想辨清不远处的北岸。他没有留意到她投来的目光。她出神地望着他，脑子里胡思乱想起来；想到像他这样一个才华出众的青年竟然鬼迷心窍浪费时间去写一些注定要失败的平庸小说和诗篇。

她的目光溜到他那在星光下朦胧可见的粗壮脖颈上，溜到他纹丝不动的脑袋上，昔日的欲望又重新燃烧，她真想把手放到他的脖子上。那股她所厌恶的力量此时在吸引着她。她的寂寞愈加强烈，同时她觉得浑身疲倦。小船倾斜着，使她坐得很不舒服。她回想起他曾经为她治过头痛症，他身上具有消除疼痛的功力。他现在就坐在她旁边，离她非常近，而小船微微倾斜，似乎在把她朝他的怀里送。她心里一阵冲动，想靠到他身上去，依偎那强壮的躯体——这种冲动朦胧不清，然而正当她考虑之际，她已被冲动左右，偎到了他身上。或者，这是由于船体倾斜的缘故？她不清楚，也始终没弄清楚。她只知道自己靠在他身上，那种舒适和安逸的感觉叫她心旷神怡。也许，这都是小船闹出的乱子，可她一点都不想恢复原来的姿态。她斜倚在他的肩头上，虽然靠得很轻，但毕竟还是靠了，而且当他挪挪位置让她更舒服些时，她仍靠着不动。

这真是疯狂的举动，然而她却不愿多想。她不再是从前的她了，而变成了一个妇人，一个怀着热烈欲望的妇人。她虽然靠得很轻，但她的欲望似乎得到了满足。她不再感到疲倦了。马丁没有言语，因为他一开口说话，这令人陶醉的场景便会烟消云散。而他那闷在肚子里的爱情怂恿他维持住这幕场景。他眼花缭乱、头晕目眩，弄不清这是怎么回事。这件事太美妙了，绝不是真的，只会是梦幻。他克制住了内心涌起的疯狂欲望，才没有丢开帆索和舵柄，将她拥抱在怀里。他的直觉告诉他，那样做是不对的。他暗自庆幸自己的双手忙于拉帆索和掌舵，才算抵制住了诱惑。但他肆无忌惮地让船儿贴风行驶，恬不知耻地叫风儿从船帆上漏掉，以拖延时间，慢一些抵达北岸。因为一到岸上，他就得离开，他们就不能依偎在一起了。他熟练地驾着船，慢慢使船儿减速，而又不让那几个争论的人觉察。他心想自己正是因为经历过极为艰险的航行，才掌握了驾驭大海、船只和风儿的本领，才可以带着她一起泛舟，让她那可爱的身子靠在他的肩头，度过一个奇妙的夜晚。

月亮升起来，第一缕月光照到船帆上，给船体洒上一层珍珠般的银白色。露丝急忙把身子从他跟前挪开。就在她移动时，她感到他也在挪开。原来他们俩都害怕被人瞧见。刚才的那段亲密的小插曲是心照不宣和偷偷摸摸的。她远离开他，两片脸蛋发烧，直到此刻才完全明白过来。刚才干的亏心事，她不愿让两个弟弟看到，也不愿让奥尔奈看到。她为什么要那样做呢？以前虽然也跟年轻男子在月下泛过舟，但她从未做过这种事，而且也从未有过这方面的欲望。她羞得无地自容，但同时也对自己初开的情窦产生了神秘感。她偷偷扫了马丁一眼，见他正忙于调整航向。她完全可以迁怒于他，因为正是他诱惑她干下了荒唐、可耻的事情。是他，而不是别人！也许母亲说得对，她见他见得太勤了些。她决不会再让这种事重新发生；以后少跟他会面。她突发异想，打算他们单独在一起时向他做做解释，跟他撒谎，假装漫不经心地说就在月亮升起前的那一刻工夫，她感到一阵眩晕。这时，她记起他们两人在月亮升起时怎样不约而同地移开了各自的身子，于是便知道他定会识破她的谎言。

后边的一些日子飞快流逝，她与以前判若两人，变得古里古怪，叫人困惑不解。她看待问题任性固执，不屑自我分析，不愿展望未来，不愿考虑自己的何去何从。她激动得发狂，令人捉摸不透，有时惊慌失措，有时陶然若醉，始终在迷惘中挣扎。不过，她坚定不移地抱着一种想法，不让马丁表露心中的爱，这样可以保障她的安全。她只要能做到这一点，便可以高枕无忧。过不了几天，他就要出海去了。即便他吐露了爱情，也无妨大局。情况不会发生变化，因为她不爱他。当然，那种时刻他会感到十分艰难，而她则困窘不堪，因为她第一次遇到男人向她求婚。想到这里，她乐得心花怒放。她是一个真正的女人，一位男子正准备向她求婚哩。这对她那颗女性的心是一种诱惑。她的整个生命和整个身心都为之震颤和发抖。这想法在她的大脑里飞上舞下，宛若一只扑火的灯蛾。她甚至幻想起马丁向她求婚的情景，自己代他说起话来；她练习说拒绝的话，好言好语规劝他做一名真正的、高尚的男子汉。尤其是，他必须把烟戒掉，这一点她一定要讲明。噢，不行，她不能允许他求婚。她可以阻止他把话讲出来，她向母亲下过保证。她满脸飞红，火辣辣地发烧，恋恋不舍地打消了自己幻想出的情景。她第一次接受求婚，得有一个比较吉利的日子和一个比较有资格的求婚者。

第二十一章

这是加利福尼亚的一个美丽的秋日，一个晴朗宜人的日子，暖意浓浓，使人昏昏欲睡，空气随着季节的悄悄变换而悸动，太阳朦胧模糊，天空中飘着几丝微风，却并不惊动这沉睡的气氛。迷蒙的紫色雾霭不像是水汽，而像由色彩织成的帷幕，躲藏在山坳里。旧金山似轻烟般影影绰绰，耸立在高地上。横在中间的海湾就好像一汪熔化了的金属闪着暗淡的光泽，水面上的帆船有的纹丝不动，有的则随着缓缓的潮汐漂荡。远处的塔马尔派斯山银雾缭绕，隐约可见，巍然高耸在金门海峡旁，而海峡在西斜的阳光下宛如一条淡金色的小道。再往远处，便是苍茫、浩渺的太平洋；地平线上涌起滚滚的云团，朝着陆地奔腾而来，预示着第一场冬季风暴即将来临。

夏季已成强弩之末，然而却久久不肯离去，奄奄一息地徘徊于群山之间，给沟沟壑壑蒙上暗紫色，以衰竭的力量和心满意足的喜悦编织出雾霭寿衣，安详和满意地等待死神的降临，因为它来到过这个世界，而且有过风光的时候，在群山之间，马丁和露丝并排坐在他们心爱的小丘上，一道欣赏同一本书。他高声朗读那个钟情于勃朗宁的女人所写的爱情诗，诗中抒发的那份爱真是世间少有。

然而，读诗的兴头渐渐淡漠下来。周围的美景千变万化，散发出不可抵御的魔力。金色的年头已耗尽精华，正在走向死亡，但仍然像风韵犹存、执迷不悟的轻浮女子，空中荡漾着浓郁的怀旧的喜悦和满足。这景色似梦一般叫人感到迷迷糊糊，一直钻入他们的心里，动摇了他们的意志，给他们的道德和理智罩上一屋雾霭和紫色的烟云。马丁心里充满了柔情蜜意，身上不时涌起热的浪潮。他们俩的脑袋挨得很近；当她的秀发在若有若无、游移不定的微风中飘起，拂在他的脸上时，他就觉得书中的诗句也在游荡。

“看来连你自己都不知道你在念什么。”一次，当他找不到地方的时候，她这样说道。

他用火辣辣的目光望着她，正感到十分困窘，却想起了一句反驳的话。

“我觉得你也没听懂，刚才的那首诗讲的是什么？”

“不知道，”她笑着坦率地说，“都让我给忘了，别再读诗了，瞧这天气有多美。”

“这是最后一次了，很长时间都不能再到这山里来了，”他语调沉重地说，“那边海洋上正在酝酿着一场风暴。”

书从他的手中滑落到了地上。他们懒散地坐着，默默无语地望着那梦一般的海湾，眼睛似乎也进入了梦境，对跟前的一切视而不见。露丝斜眼瞧了瞧他的脖颈。她没有朝他身上靠，而是被一种来自体外力量，一种比地心引力大、同命运一样强烈的力量吸引了过去。他们之间仅隔着一英寸，她不由自主地越过了这段距离。她的肩膀轻轻碰了碰他的膀子，就像蝴蝶触及花朵一样，而对方的碰触也是同样轻盈。她感到他把肩膀靠了过来，感到他的全身在颤抖。这时她该缩回身去，然而她却变成了一个机械人。她的举动超出了意志的控制范围——她根本就没想到控制自己或运用意志的力量，因为她被一种甜蜜的疯狂感所左右。他的一条胳膊偷偷从后边伸过来，企图搂住她。她高兴得心痒难熬，期待着那条慢吞吞的胳膊。她等待着，也不知道自己在等待着什么结果，嘴里喘着粗气，双唇发干、发烫，脉搏加速跳动，热烈的欲望在血液中沸腾。那条搂着她的胳膊朝上移动，把她朝他怀里拉，那动作慢条斯理但充满了柔情。她再也忍耐不住了，于是在一阵冲动之下，连想也不想，疲倦地叹了口气，便一头倒在他的胸膛上。他立刻便低下头，把嘴唇印上去，而她也用芳唇去迎接。

在头脑清醒的一刹那间，她心想这大概就是爱情了。这要不是爱情，那才羞煞人呢。这不可能是别的，只能是爱情。她爱这个伸开双臂拥抱她、热烈吻她的男子。她蠕动了一下身子，牢牢贴紧他。过了一会儿，她挣出他的怀抱，突然兴奋地伸出手来，放在马丁·伊登那太阳晒黑的脖子上。强烈的爱和欲望得到了满足，她低低呻吟一声，松开双手，半昏半迷地倒在他的怀里。

两人刚才都没说话，此刻也长久地一言不语。他两次低下头去吻她，每次她都启开双唇害羞地迎接他，同时快乐地蠕动着身子。她贴紧他，一刻也不离开，而他将她半抱半拥在怀里，坐在那里视而不见地望着海湾彼岸朦胧一片的城市。在这一时刻，他的大脑里没有出现幻景，只有跳动的色彩、光线和火焰，似天气一般暖意袭人，如爱情一样温馨。他俯下身子，而她却启口说了话。

“你是什么时候爱上我的？”她悄悄声儿地问。

“从一开始，我第一次见到你就疯狂地迷恋上了你，以后随着时间的推移我的爱情愈来愈炽烈。而现在，亲爱的，我爱你都爱得快要发疯了，喜悦使我神魂颠倒。”

“我庆幸自己是个女人，马丁——亲爱的。”她深深喘了口气说。他紧紧拥抱她，拥抱了一次又一次，最后问道：

“你呢？你是什么时候知道的？”

“哦，我早就知道了，几乎从一开始就知道了。”

“我真是瞎了眼，像蝙蝠一样！”他叫喊起来，声音里含着懊悔，“我实在没想到，直至刚才——刚才我吻你的时候，才明白过来。”

“我不是那意思。”她朝后缩了缩身子，用眼睛望着他，“我是说我几乎一开始就知道你爱上了我。”

“那你呢？”他问道。

“我是猛然之间才意识到的。”她说话的语调非常慢，忽闪着温柔多情的眼睛，脸上挂着持久不退的微微红晕，“从前我一直都没觉察，直到刚才你搂住我，我才恍然大悟。我从来就没想过嫁给你，可刚才我改变了主意。你是怎么使我爱上你的？”

“不知道，”他笑着说，“我只知道我爱你，爱得那么执着，足可以感动铁石心肠，就更别提你这样的有血有肉的女人了。”

“这样的爱情与我想象的爱真是天差地别。”她前言不对后语地说。

“你想象的是什么样的爱呢？”

“反正和这种不一样。”她盯着他的眼睛，可是再朝下说时，却垂下了眼睑，“告诉你，我真不知道爱情是这种样子。”

他想把她再次拉进怀里，然而却仅仅试探性地动了动那条搂着她的胳膊，因为他生怕自己显得太贪得无厌。这时，他觉得她的身子顺从地贴了过来，再次投入他的怀抱，两人的嘴唇牢牢锁在一起。

“我家里人会说些什么呢？”她在一次间歇时突然担忧地问。

“不知道，但只要想知道，随时都可以轻而易举地找出答案。”

“妈妈要是反对呢？我真怕告诉她。”

“让我对她讲吧。”他自告奋勇地说，“我觉得你母亲不喜欢我，但我可以让她回心转意。一个人只要能赢得你，就能赢得一切。假如咱们不能——”

“什么？”

“噢，咱们会在一起的。不必担心你的母亲，她会同意咱们的婚事的，因为她太爱你了。”

“我可不愿伤她的心。”露丝忧郁地说。

他想安慰她，告诉她说母亲是不会这么轻易伤心的，然而说出的话却是：“爱情是世界上最伟大的东西。”

“你要知道，马丁，你有时候让我害怕。一想到你，想到过去的你，我现在就感到害怕。你必须对我十分十分好。别忘了，我毕竟还只是个孩子，以前从未恋爱过。”

“我也没恋爱过，咱们都是小孩子。但咱们是最幸运的人，都在对方的身上寻觅到了自己的初恋。”

“这不可能！”她嚷嚷道，同时情绪激昂地猛然缩身挣出他的怀抱，“对你来说这不可能。你当过水手，而我听说水手都——”

她支吾着，再也说不下去了。

“都是每到一个港口就找一个妻子？”他提醒道，“你是这个意思吧？”

“是的。”她低声回答。

“那可不是爱情。”他以权威性的口气说，“我去过不少港口，但在那天晚上见到你之前，我从未品尝过一星一点爱的滋味。你要知道，那天晚上我离开你家，差点给抓起来。”

“给抓起来？”

“是的。警察以为我喝醉了；其实当时我真醉了——是陶醉于对你的爱之中。”

“你刚才说咱们都是小孩，我说你不可能是初恋，而现在却扯到一边去了。”

“我刚才说，除了你，我没爱过任何人。”他回答，“你是我的第一个心上人，是我的初恋。”

“可你当过水手呀。”她反问。

“这也不能妨碍我把初恋给予你。”

“你有过女人——有过其他的女人——天哪！”

马丁·伊登感到十分意外，万万想不到她竟会潸然落下泪来，于是又是亲吻又是哄劝才使她安静下来。在这段时间里，他心中始终在想着吉卜林的那句话：“上校夫人和裘蒂·奥格莱迪，骨子里原是亲姐妹。”他所看过的小说讲的不是这么回事，但现在他却认为这是真理。在小说的影响下，他一直认为只有上流阶层的男女才正式求婚。而他的那个下层社会里，小伙子和姑娘们则通过躯体的接触赢得对方的爱；上层社会的高贵人物们要是以同样的方式求爱，就显得不可思议了。然而，小说里的观点是错误的。这一点，是有证据的。无须语言，拥抱和抚摸对工人阶级里的姑娘可以产生效用，而这一套对上流社会的女子也同样有效。她们都是凡身俗体，骨子里都是姐妹。如果没忘记斯宾塞书中的话，这种事他原来应该是清楚的。他把露丝抱在怀里，安慰着她，心里想着上校夫人和裘蒂·奥格莱迪骨子里原本不差上下，从中获取莫大的慰藉。这一来，露丝和他的差距就缩短了，是可以弄到手的。她和他一样，和所有的人一样，都是血肉之躯。没有什么能够阻止他们结合。阶级差别是唯一的差别，但阶级并非本质性的东西，是可以克服的。他在书中曾看到过，一位奴隶当上了罗马红衣主教。所以，他也可以步步高升，与露丝相匹配。她虽然冰清玉洁，具有良好的教养，心灵纯洁美好，但从人的本性上来说，却和丽茜·康诺莱及所有丽茜·康诺莱之类的姑娘是一模一样的。她们能干的事情，她也能干。她能爱会恨，也许还有点歇斯底里；当然，她还会醋意大发，就像现在一样，倒在他怀里忌妒地抽泣了一阵。

“另外，我比你年龄大，”她睁开眼皮，抬头望着他，突然说道，“比你大三岁。”

“算了吧，你还是个孩子呢。要论经历，我比你大四十岁。”他回答说。

尽管她受过高等教育，尽管他的脑子里装满了严谨的哲学理论以及生活中积累的铁的事实，但他们俩在爱情方面还都是孩子，吐露爱情时像孩子样天真和幼稚。

他们坐在逐渐暗淡的日光中，说着恋人们挂在口头的那套情话，赞叹着美妙的爱情以及把他们联系在一起的奇特命运，武断地认为他们炽烈的爱是前人所无法企及的。他们总爱回过头来，一遍遍地回忆见第一面时各自的印象，并徒劳无益地试图精确地分析彼此的感情，分析他们的感情到底有多深。

西边地平线上的云堆吞没了落日，天边变成一片玫瑰色，而天顶也染上了这种温暖的色彩。玫瑰色的光线到处闪耀，将他们沐浴在其中。她唱起歌来：“再见，甜蜜的日子。”她依在他的胳膊弯里，让他握住自己的手，用柔和的声音唱着，使两人的心交融在一起。

第二十二章

露丝回到家中，摩斯夫人无须母亲的直觉便能从她的脸上看出发生了什么事情。她脸上那不消退的红晕叫人一瞧就一目了然，尤其是那双又大又亮的眼睛更能说明问题，准确无误地反映出她内心的喜悦。

“出什么事啦？”摩斯夫人瞅准时机，待露丝上床睡觉时，这样问道。

“你知道啦？”露丝哆嗦着嘴唇，反问道。

母亲没有回答，而是伸出胳膊搂住她，用手轻轻抚摸她的头发。“他没把话说出来。”她脱口而出，“我原本不想让这种事发生，也绝不让他把话挑明——所以，他没有开口。”

“既然他没开口，那么什么事情也不会发生，对吧？”

“但事情终究还是发生了。”

“看在上帝的分上，我的孩子，你到底在胡说些什么呀？”摩斯夫人给弄糊涂了，“真不知出了什么事。究竟是怎么一回事？”

露丝惊讶地望着母亲。

“我还以为你知道了呢。是这么回事，我和马丁订婚了。”

摩斯夫人既怀疑又恼火，不由笑了起来。

“他没有把话挑明，”露丝解释道，“但他爱我，就这么回事。我当时和你现在一样感到意外。他只字未吐，只是用胳膊搂住了我。我——我一下子失去了控制。他吻我，我也吻了他。我实在是身不由己，只有那样做了。直到那时，我才知道自己是爱他的。”

她打住话头，期待母亲以热吻为她祝福，然而摩斯夫人却冰冷冷地一言不发。

“我知道这是件可怕的事情。”露丝以消沉的声音继续说道，“我也知道你是绝对不会原谅我的，但我当时的确一筹莫展啊。直到那一时刻，我才意识到自己在爱着他，请你务必替我告诉父亲一声。”

“不告诉你父亲，岂不是更好些吗？让我先见见马丁·伊登，和他谈谈，把情况解释一下。他会理解的，会离开你的。”

“不！不！”露丝跳起身，嚷嚷开来，“我可不想让他离开我。我爱他，而爱情是非常甜美的。我要嫁给他——当然，这得先征求你的同意。”

“亲爱的露丝，我和你父亲对你另有打算——噢，不，不，不是为你挑好了丈夫，绝不是这种情况。我们只不过想让你自己物色一个门当户对、规矩体面的上等人，待你爱上他，就嫁给他。”

“可我已经爱上了马丁。”露丝哀怨地辩驳道。

“我们无论怎样也不会对你的选择进行干涉；但你是我们的女儿，我们不忍心看着你嫁给这样的男人。他粗鲁、庸俗，没有一样能配得上你的高贵和典雅。不管从哪种角度讲，他都配不上你。他没有能力养活你。我们对荣华富贵并无奢望，但舒适的生活却是另外一码子事，我们的女儿至少得嫁一个能让她过好日子的丈夫——而不是一个身无分文的冒险家、水手、牛仔、走私者。鬼知道他还干过什么，反正他是个轻率浮躁、缺乏责任心的家伙。”

露丝没有言声，觉得母亲的话句句属实。

“他把时间都耗费在写作上，妄图取得只有天才以及极少数受过高等教育的人有时才能够获得的成就。一个人考虑到结婚就应该为结婚做准备，而他却不然。正如我刚才所言，我相信你也同意我的话，他缺乏责任心。他还会怎样呢？水手就是这个样子，从不知节俭和收敛自己。多年来的挥霍浪费已在他身上打下了烙印。当然错不在他，但这并不能改变他的天性。这些年间，他注定要过放荡的生活，你想到过吗？你想过这些吗，孩子？你该懂得结婚意味着什么。”

露丝浑身一哆嗦，紧偎在母亲的怀里。

“我想过。”露丝待了老半晌，等考虑成熟后，才说道，“真叫人毛骨悚然，想到这些我身上就起鸡皮疙瘩。我告诉过你，我爱上他，完全是个可怕的意外，我也是身不由己啊。难道你有办法不爱父亲吗？我的情况也是这样。他心里有我，我心里也有他——直到今天我才知道——但事实早就存在，正因为如此我才爱上了他。我从没想过会爱上他，可你瞧，我真的爱上了他。”说到最后，她的声音里微微掺杂着几分喜悦。

母女俩谈了许久，没谈出个名堂来，最后双方都同意先等上一段时间，暂不采取行动。

过了一会儿，摩斯夫人当夜就向丈夫承认自己的计划已经流产，他们之间也做出了相同的决定。

“看来，情况只能是这样，”摩斯先生发表看法说，“这个水手是唯一她经常接触的男子。她的情窦早晚都会开的；瞧，她现在动情了吧！眼下只能与这个水手交往，所以她便草率地爱上了他，或自以为爱上了他，这反正都一样。”

摩斯夫人提议不要和她争执，由自己慢慢从侧面开导她。时间很充裕，因为马丁目前的情况还不适合于结婚。

“让她尽量去了解他吧，”摩斯先生出主意说，“我保证，她愈了解他，对他的爱就愈淡漠。让她多做些比较，一定要请些青年男女到家里来，要请各种各样的年轻小伙子——头脑聪明的、有成就的、正在开拓事业的、和她同阶层的以及有身份的。她会以他们作标准衡量他，这一比就会叫他原形毕露。不管怎样，他毕竟才二十一岁，露丝也还是个孩子，他们之间的感情是幼犊般的爱，长大了便会忘得一干二净。”

这件事就这样搁置了起来，露丝和马丁的订婚只是在家里得到了承认，对外却不公布，因为露丝的父母认为没这个必要。而且，他们心照不宣地要把婚期拖延下去。他们没要求马丁去工作，也没要求他停止写作，因为他们根本无意鼓励他改变自己的条件。而他丝毫不想找工作干，这无形中对他们执行那不友好的计划起到了帮助作用。

“真不知你同不同意我的做法！”几天后，马丁对露丝说，“我觉得在姐姐家食宿太费钱了，所以我要自立门户。我在奥克兰北区租了间小屋，那儿环境幽静，好处很多，这你知道。另外，我还买了只油炉，用它做饭吃。”

露丝大喜过望。尤其让她高兴的是那只油炉。

“勃特勒先生刚开始起步时就是这样。”她说。

马丁听她提起那位可敬可爱的大人物，心里觉得不舒服，但还是说了下去：“我给所有的手稿都贴上邮票，又给编辑们寄去了。今天我搬了家，明天就开始工作。”

“有职业啦！”她喊出了声，全身上下都显露出她的惊喜心情，更紧地依偎在他身上，握紧他的手，满脸含笑，“你从没告诉过我！是什么职业呀？”

他摇了摇头。

“我的意思是我要开始写作了。”她的脸色沉了下来，他连忙继续说道，“请别误解。这次我可不是招摇过市、想入非非，而要埋头苦干，脚踏实地地干出点事情来。这比再次航海强，挣的钱要多于奥克兰任何一个行业的没有技能的人。

“要知道，这段假期使我能够正确地看待问题了。我既没有拼死拼活地劳动，也没有写作，至少没有为了出版而写作。我所干的只是爱你，以及思考问题。我看了些书，主要是杂志，这也属于思考问题的范畴。对于我自己，对于这个世界以及我在世界上的位置，对于是否能争取到一个与你相配的地位，我都总结出了一些道理。我还看了斯宾塞的《文体论》，发现了我的许多毛病——或不如说是写作中的问题；每个月的杂志上刊登的文章，大多数都存在着缺点。

“通过思考、阅读和爱情，我所得出的结论是我要鬻文为生。对于大作我暂不涉笔，而仅仅写能卖得出的文章——笑话、短评、特辑、幽默诗以及社交诗——这类东西似乎很受欢迎。另外，还有报业辛迪加、报纸短篇小说辛迪加和星期日副刊辛迪加呢。我可以为他们撰稿挣钱，这跟拿高薪水差不多。要知道，有些自由撰稿人每月能挣四五百块钱呢。我并不期望同他们一样；但我要挣钱过好日子，而且有充足的闲暇，从事任何其他的职业都不会有这等好事。

“有了空闲时间，就可以用来学习和干正经事。除了写小块文章，我还要在大部头作品上试试身手。我要发愤学习，为写出大作品打基础。令我不胜惊讶的是，我已经走了很远的路。刚开始写作的时候，我简直没有东西可写，只有一些连自己也理解不透、欣赏不了的经历。老实讲，我当时缺乏的是思想，甚至还缺乏用于思考的语言。我的经历是一大堆毫无意义的图像。但随着知识的增长和词汇的丰富，我看到自己的经历不仅仅是图像，里边还有别的东西。我牢记住那些图像，并寻觅到了表现它们的方式。从那时起，我开始写优秀的作品，于是，《冒险》、《欢乐》、《罐子》、《生活的美酒》、《拥挤的街道》、《爱情组诗》和《海洋抒情诗》便相继诞生了。我要写更多的这类作品，而且还要写得更好，但这些得在空闲时间完成。我现在已脚踩坚实的大地。先鬻文挣钱，然后再写大作品。为了让你瞧瞧，昨晚我给喜剧周刊撰写了六七则笑话。另外，刚要上床睡觉的时候，我突然想在八行两韵诗上试试笔——写首幽默的，谁知在一个小时内竟写成了四首。每首诗按一块钱计算，那么，上床时只消动动脑筋，就可以挣四块钱。

“当然，这些都毫无价值，全是枯燥乏味、庸俗下流的东西；但是和记账相比就不怎么乏味庸俗了，因为为人记账每月拿六十块钱的工资，整天把一行行毫无意思的数字加来加去，一直到老死方休。再说，鬻文为生可以使我经常接触文学，给我提供时间写大作品。”

“可是写大作品，写优秀的作品又有什么用呢？”露丝责问道，“反正是卖不出去。”

“不对，是可以卖出去的。”他刚开口说话，却被她半截子打断了。

“你刚才提到的那些作品，你自诩为优秀作品，还不是一篇都没卖出去。咱们总不能拿卖不出去的优秀作品来结婚吧。”

“那咱们就靠能卖出去的八行两韵诗结婚。”他语气坚定地说，同时用胳膊搂住她，把这位态度冷漠的心上人拉到身边。

“你听听这首诗，”他强作笑脸地继续说道，“这不是艺术作品，却是一块钱的现金。

我出门时

他进门；

他登门，

目的是借几文，

没借上，

又空手出了门；

他走后，

我才进了门。”

他写的这首小诗韵律轻快，与他念完诗后脸上流露出的沮丧表情格格不入，未博得露丝的丝毫笑意。她向他投来的是严肃和不安的目光。

“这也许能换来一块钱，”她说，“可这是一块丑角的钱，是小丑求来的赏钱。你应该明白，马丁，这样做是多么下贱。我希望自己所爱慕和尊崇的是个杰出、高雅的人，而非撰写笑话及打油诗的庸俗文人。”

“你希望他像——像勃特勒先生一样吗？”他提醒道。

“我知道你不喜欢勃特勒先生。”她说。

“勃特勒先生没什么不好，”他打断她的话说，“我不喜欢的只是他的消化不良症。请原谅，我实在看不出撰写笑话或喜剧诗与打字、速记及为人管账有什么差别。你的意见是让我从记账入手，最终当一名成功的律师或实业家。而我的意思是先靠鬻文为生，逐渐锻炼成一个有才干的作家。”

“这里边是有差别的。”她执拗地说。

“什么差别？”

“你的那些优秀作品，那些自以为得意的作品，是卖不出去的。你尝试过——这你要知道——可编辑们硬是不肯收购。”

“你得给我时间，”他央求道，“鬻文只是权宜之计，我并不把它看得太认真。给我两年的时间，我就可以大功告成，那时编辑们会很乐意收购我的作品。我知道自己在说什么，我对自己有信心。我了解自己的能力，了解文学是怎么回事；我知道那些小人物源源不断推出的都是平庸之作，知道两年之后我将走上成功的康庄大道。要说做生意，我是绝对不会成功的，因为我不喜欢这个行当。我觉得那是乏味、愚蠢而又棘手的职业。总之，我不是做生意的料，顶多只能当个小职员。靠一个职员的微薄收入，你我怎能过上幸福生活呢？我希望能把世界上最好的东西奉献给你，除非还会出现更好的，否则我绝不甘心。我会得到的，所有的一切我都会得到的。一位成功作家所挣的钱会让勃特勒先生相形见绌。一部畅销书可以挣五万至十万块钱——有时多些，有时少些；但一般来说，差不多就是这么个数目。”

她依然默不作声，显然有些大失所望。

“你说呢？”他问道。

“这和我所希望及计划的迥然两样。我曾经认为，现在仍旧认为，你最好学学速记——打字的技巧你已经掌握了——争取进家父的事务所工作。你有一副好头脑，我坚信你一定能成为出类拔萃的律师。”

第二十三章

露丝不相信马丁能成为作家，而马丁却并没因此改变对她的看法，也丝毫不减对她的感情。在那段休心养性的假期里，他用去大量时间分析自己，对自己有了深入的了解。他发现自己爱美胜过爱名，而他追逐名利的欲望主要是为了露丝。正是出于这个原因，他的成名欲才特别强烈。他要当世人眼里的伟人，按他自己的说法是“干出点名堂”，让他钟爱的女人为他感到自豪，把他视为可敬慕的人。

至于他本人，他的爱美之心非常强烈，同时，他从为露丝服务中获取欢乐，并把这看作丰厚的报酬。他爱露丝又胜过爱美。他觉得爱情是世界上最美好的东西。正是爱情在他心里引发了一场革命，把他从一个粗鲁的水手变成了一位学者和艺术家，所以在他的眼里，爱情比学问和艺术都伟大，是这三者当中最美好、最重要的一个。他早就发现自己在智能上胜露丝一筹，也为她的父兄所不及。尽管她条件优越，受过高等教育，又获得了文学学士学位，但他的智力却是她望尘莫及的。经过一年来的自学和提高，他对世界大事、艺术和生活都有了深刻的了解，这是她无法比拟的。

这些他全都意识到了，但这并未影响他对她的爱，也没影响她爱他。爱情是极其美好、极其崇高的，而他又是个极其忠诚的恋人，所以他绝不会以指责挑剔玷污爱情。对于艺术、道德品行、法国革命以及平等选举权，露丝固然持不同见解，但这和爱情有什么关系呢？这些都属于思维活动，而爱情却凌驾于理智之上，是超理性的。他不能贬低爱情的价值，因为他对爱情顶礼膜拜。爱情耸立在理智峡谷旁的山巅之上，它是人生的升华，生命的辉煌顶点，是非常珍贵的。由于喜欢看哲学家的科学论著，他了解爱情在生物学上的重大意义；但是用同样的科学理论进行进一步的分析，他得出了这样的结论：爱情是人类的最高目标，容不得有半点怀疑，应该被视为生活的最丰厚报酬。所以，他认为在所有的生物中恋人是最幸运的。一想到“疯狂的恋人”超越于世间万物，超越于财富、理智、舆论和赞誉，超越于生活本身，想到“愿为一吻而死”，他便感到欣喜。

这些道理，有许多马丁早就琢磨出来了，而有些则是他以后悟出的。同时，他发奋工作，除了去看望露丝以外，再没有别的消遣，过着斯巴达式的艰苦生活。他租葡萄牙女房东玛丽亚·西尔瓦的那间小屋，每月要交两块半钱的房租。女房东是个泼辣的寡妇，手脚勤快，脾气却很暴躁，辛辛苦苦拉扯着一大群孩子，隔三岔五就到街拐角的杂货铺或酒馆里花上一角五分钱打一加仑发酸的淡酒，借酒浇愁解乏。起初，马丁讨厌她，讨厌她那张爱说脏话的臭嘴，可后来看到她在生活中不屈不挠的精神，便渐渐产生了敬意。这个小户人家只有四个房间，被马丁租去一间，就只剩下三间了。其中的一间是客厅，里面铺着一块色彩鲜艳的地毯，散发出轻松的情调，但厅里还挂着她的一个亡婴（她有许多孩子都早年夭折）的丧葬卡片和遗像，未免有几分悲凉。这间房子按严格规定只用作接待客人。这座圣堂里的百叶窗帘常年低垂，除非发生重大事情，否则绝不允许那些赤着脚的孩子们涉足此地。无论是她煮饭还是全家吃饭，都在厨房里。而且，除星期天以外，她每天都在厨房里浆洗衣服和熨烫衣服，因为她的收入主要是靠为境遇较好的邻居们洗衣服挣来的。最后还剩下一间卧室，同马丁的那间一般狭小，她和她的七个孩子都挤在里边睡觉。马丁一直都想不透他们怎么能挤得下，他每天晚上隔着薄薄的板壁，都能听得见那边上床睡觉时发出的声响，听得见孩子的啼哭、争吵以及似鸟叫一样的喋喋不休的低语。玛丽亚的另一收入来源是两头奶牛，她每天一早一晚挤两次奶。这两头奶牛偷偷摸摸地吃长在空地上和人行道两旁的草赖以活命，老是由她的一两个衣衫褴褛的孩子看守着。孩子的任务主要是担任警戒，严防牲畜管理员不期而至。

马丁在自己的小房间里生活、睡觉、学习、写作和料理家务。屋里唯一的窗户面朝狭小的前廊，窗前摆着一张桌子，既当写字台，又当书架和打字机台。床铺靠后墙放着，把整个房间三分之二的地方都占了去。桌子的一边摆着一个俗丽的衣柜，造衣柜的人光顾赚钱，不管能不能用，上面的装饰板每天都要裂开一点。这个柜子放在屋角，

而对面的那个角落，也就是桌子的另一侧，是他的“厨房”——一只油炉放在棉布箱上，箱里有碗碟及炊事用具；墙上装着搁板架，供放食品用；地板上放着一桶水。马丁的房间里没安水龙头，所以他得到厨房去打水。有时，他煮饭产生大量水蒸气，致使柜上的装饰板一块块往下掉。他的自行车用滑车吊起，挂在床头上方的天花板上。起初，他把车子放在地下室里，但西尔瓦家的那帮孩子拧松了轴承，扎破了车胎，吓得他把车子又搬了出来。随后，他把车子存放在狭小的前廊里。有一天，呼啸的东南风把雨吹进来，将车子淋了一整夜，他只好把它弄回自己的房间，高高挂起来。

一个小橱里盛着他的衣物及藏书，因为无论是桌上还是桌下都没有放书的地方。在看书的过程中，他养成了做笔记的习惯。他写出的笔记铺天盖地，要不是在屋里拉了几根晾衣服的绳子把笔记挂上去，恐怕连他的生存之地都不会有了。即便如此，屋里还是拥挤得使走路都成了困难。必须先关上橱门才能打开房门，而开橱门时，得先关房门。在屋里直来直去地移动是不可能的。从房门口到床头，必须走一条弯曲的路线，黑暗中免不了会磕磕碰碰。刚刚历尽艰难绕过水火不相容的房门和橱门，又得向右急转弯，以免碰上油炉。然后，必须朝左拐，绕开床腿；但这个弯不能拐得太大，不然会撞到桌角上。他拐弯时把身子猛然扭动和歪斜，接着又沿着一条“运河”向右走，“运河”的两岸一边是床，另一边是桌子。如果屋里仅有的那把椅子放在桌前的老地方，“运河”便阻塞不通了。那椅子不用的时候，便放到床上去，但有时他坐在椅子上煮饭，边看书边等水开，甚至熟练得在炸牛排时也能看上一两段。存放炊具的那个角落也小得可怜，他坐在那儿便能够得着自己所需的一切东西。说实在的，还是坐着煮饭便利；如果站着，太容易自我妨碍。

他的肠胃无可挑剔，不管吃什么都能消化。而且，他在食品方面知识渊博，知道哪些食物既富于营养又价格便宜。他的食谱里常有豌豆汤、土豆和扁豆，这种扁豆是大颗粒、棕褐色，烹饪时依照墨西哥人的方法。米饭每天至少在马丁的饭桌上出现一次，其做法是美国家庭主妇从未采用过，也永远学不会的。干果比新鲜水果便宜，他常常煮一锅干果备在手头，代替黄油抹在面包上吃。有时，他会煮一大块牛肉或一道骨头汤，丰富一下饭桌。他的咖啡不掺乳脂或牛奶，每天喝两次，晚上的一次代替喝茶；但无论是咖啡还是茶，都煮得恰到好处。

勤俭节约对他来说是很有必要的。休假时，他几乎花光了从洗衣店挣到的钱，但离市场还有相当长一段路，必须等待很久才能指望拿到第一笔卖手稿的钱。除了去看望露丝，或者到姐姐葛特露那儿坐坐以外，他过的是隐士生活，每天至少完成普通人三天的工作量。他每天的睡眠时间几乎不足五个小时，剩下的十九个小时埋头苦干，天天如此，只有钢筋铁骨的人才能与他抗衡。一分一秒他都不浪费。镜子上贴着单词的注解和发音，以便在刮脸、穿衣或梳头时默记。油炉旁的墙上也贴着这类表格，供他在煮饭时或洗盘子时记忆。他时不时地用新表格换下旧表格。看书中遇到生词或半生半熟的词，他便立刻抄下来。积到相当的数量，便用打字机打好，贴到墙上或镜子上。他甚至把表格装在衣袋里随身携带，上街时或者到肉店及杂货铺等着买东西时，便抽空复习。

这还不算，在阅读成名作家的作品时，他对他们的每项成果都十分关切，并寻找出他们成功的诀窍，有铺笔上的诀窍，有叙述和风格上的诀窍，也有表现观点、运用对比和警句的诀窍。所有的这一切他都制成表格加以研究。他并不着意模仿，而是从中吸取精华。他在表格中记载的是卓有成效、生动感人的表现手法。待研究了许多作家和记录下许多表现手法后，他才总结出了表现手法的一般性原则，从而为创造自己崭新、独特的风格，以及正确地权衡、估量和评价自己的风格，铺平了道路。以同样的方法，他还把感染力强的词句制成表格，这类词句是生龙活虎的语言，像硫酸一样具有腐蚀性，似火焰一般灼人，在平庸语言的荒漠中闪闪发光，带来醇香、甘美的气息。他始终探索的是深藏在内的原则，因为只有了解了事物的根由，他自己才能行动。他并不满足于美的表面光华。于是，他在自己拥挤不堪、既当卧室又为实验室的小屋里把美加以解剖——在这儿，有时可闻到煮饭的气味，有时则能听到外边西尔瓦家那帮孩子的喧闹声；在解剖了美，了解了美的五脏六腑之后，他就向自己创造美的目标接近了一步。

根据天性，只有在理解之后，他才能开展工作。他无法在黑暗中盲目地工作，对自己创造的东西缺乏了解，只一味依靠运气和天赋去寻求完美的效果。他对偶然性的效果嗤之以鼻，只想弄清事情的原委和经过。他的天赋是有意识的创造性的天赋。在动笔写故事或诗之前，作品的内容已在他的脑海里翻腾，无论是写作的目的还是实现这一目的的方法，他都一清二楚、胸有成竹。如若不然，他的创作就注定会失败。可话又说回来，对于那些轻松自然出现在他脑海中的词语，他又相信偶然性效果了，因为这些词语能经得住美和力量的一切考验，能产生种种惊人的无法言喻的含义。他对它们顶礼膜拜，认为它们并非任何人着意编造出来的。不管他怎样解剖美，怎样寻觅深藏在它之中使之成其为美的原则，他都始终感觉得到自己并未理解美的深层秘密，而且从来没有人深入那个领域。他从斯宾塞的作品中清楚地看到，人类对任何事物都不可能彻底了解，美的秘密不亚于生活之谜——啧，美比生活更为玄妙；他还看到美和生活紧密交织在一起，而他本人只是这种由阳光、星尘及奇迹组成的不可思议编织物当中的一根棉线。

说实话，此时他正抱着这样的观念撰写名为《星尘》的论文，文中攻击的对象不是评论的原则，而是那些著名的评论家。文章写得精彩、深刻、富于哲理性，同时又耐人寻味地带有几丝诙谐。他屡次投稿，屡次被杂志社即刻退回。然而，他的大脑并不纠缠于此，而是安安稳稳地继续耕耘。他养成了一种习惯：先对一个问题深思熟虑，然后一口气用打字机打出。至于文章是否能刊出，他倒觉得无所谓。写作是长期思维的顶点，是对千丝万缕思绪的集中，是对大脑中所有材料的最后总结。写这样的文章是一种有意识的活动，他可以借此解放大脑，使其准备接受新的材料、思考新的问题。这种情况有点类似受了委屈或自以为受了委屈的男男女女所普遍养成的习惯：隔一段时间就要打破忍耐已久的沉默，滔滔不绝地“倾吐衷肠”，吐尽方休。

第二十四章

几个星期的时间一闪而过。马丁的钱囊告罄，而出版商的支票仍遥遥无期。那些重要稿件全如数退回，又被他寄了出去，卖钱作品的下场也同样糟糕。小“厨房”里不再有形形色色的食物。他处境艰难，只剩下了半袋米和几磅干杏，于是他一日三餐都吃米饭和干杏，一连凑合了五天。接着，他便开始赊账了。那位葡萄牙食品商一贯收马丁的现金，这时见他欠的钱已多达三元八角五分，便要停止供货。

“你该放明白些，”食品商说，“你不去找工作干，我就得赔钱。”马丁无法解释，一时答不上话来。赊账给一个懒得不肯干活、身强力壮的工人阶级的小伙子，是不符合生意准则的。

“你一找到工作，我就供给你食品。”食品商向马丁保证说，“没有工作，就没有食品，这就是生意。”随后，为了表明这纯粹是生意上的远见，而非偏见，他又说，“来，请你喝杯酒——咱们还是好朋友嘛。”

马丁洒脱地喝了酒，以示他对食品店的友好之情，当天晚上没吃饭就上了床。

马丁买蔬菜的那家果品店是由一位美国人经营，此人做生意的原则性非常差，竟让马丁赊了五块钱的账才宣告停止。另外，还欠面包坊两块钱，欠肉铺四块钱。马丁把所有的债加在一起，发现自己总共欠下十四元八角五分。打字机的租赁费也该交了，但他估计还能赊两个月的账——共八块钱。待到那时，他便到了穷途末路，再也赊不来账了。

从果品店最后一次赊来的是一袋土豆，于是他在一个星期里一天吃三顿土豆，别的什么也不吃。偶尔在露丝家吃顿可以帮助他恢复体力，可是看到那么多的食物摆在面前，自己又不好多要，他觉得实在馋得难熬。隔上一些时候，他就会怀着惭愧的心理在吃饭时间跑到姐姐家，放开胆子吃一顿——在摩斯家的饭桌旁他可不敢大吃特吃。

他天天写作，日日接到邮递员送来的退稿。由于没钱买邮票，稿件在桌下堆成了小山。一次，他连着四十个小时粒米未进，又不能指望到露丝家混饭，因为露丝到圣拉斐尔去了，两个星期后才回来。出于羞愧的心情，他不愿到姐姐家去。雪上加霜的是，邮递员在当天下午送来了五份退稿。于是，马丁披上外套去了奥克兰。回来时外套不见了，口袋里却有五块洋钱在叮当作响。他向那四个生意人每人还了一块钱的欠款，随后就在“厨房”里炸牛排、炒洋葱、烹咖啡，还炖了一大锅梅干。饱餐一顿之后，他伏于案头，赶午夜之前写完了一篇名为《高利贷的尊严》的论文。他把论文用打字机打出，然后扔到了桌子底下，因为那五块钱已花光用尽，再没有钱买邮票了。

后来，他先后当掉了手表和自行车，给所有的稿件都贴上邮票，邮寄出去，所剩下的买食品的钱就不多了。对于自己写的卖钱的作品，他大失所望，因为无人愿意购买。与报纸上、周刊上以及廉价杂志上的文章相比较，他认为自己的作品比一般水平要强，而且要强得多，但就是兜售不出去。这时，他发现多数报纸都大量刊载所谓的“铅版文章”，于是便找来了提供这类文章的那家社团的地址。可是他寄去的作品却给退了回来，并附着一张铅印的条子，说明所需稿件全由社团成员撰写。

在一份大型少年期刊上，他发现整栏整栏都登载的是奇闻逸事，心想这下机会来了。但他寄去的文章却吃了闭门羹，虽几经尝试，也一篇打不进去，后来，当他已经无所谓了的时候，方才得知那些副编辑以及助理编辑都是亲自撰文捞取外快。喜剧周刊退回了他的笑话和幽默诗，而他为大杂志撰写的笔调轻松的社交诗也未寻到立足之地。他心里清楚，自己的文章比那些登出的作品写得好。他设法搞到两家报业辛迪加的地址，源源不断地把短篇小说投给它们。写完二十篇，却一篇也没投中，他这才罢了休。天天都能在日报和周刊上看到短篇小说，看到的岂止几十篇，但没有一篇可与他的作品相媲美。于绝望之中，他断定自己失去了判断力，无端陶醉于自己的文章，是个自欺欺人的冒牌作家。

缺乏人性的编辑机器依然在有条不紊地运转。他把邮票夹入稿件，投进邮筒，待三个星期乃至一个月后，邮递员便会走上台阶把稿件递还给他。那一端肯定不存在有血有肉有感情的编辑，而只存在着轮盘、齿轮和注油器——一台自动控制的灵巧机器。他失望到了极点，甚至怀疑根本就没有什么编辑，因为在他的退稿单上没有一丝一毫的痕迹可以证明编辑的存在。他的作品不分青红皂白就被全部退回，由此可见，所谓的编辑很可能是办公室差役、排字工人及印刷工人杜撰和宣扬的虚构人物。

只有和露丝在一起时，他才感到幸福，但也并非每时每刻都感到幸福。他始终都受到痛苦和不安情绪的折磨，比过去得到她的爱之前的那些日子更为焦虑担忧；因为他现在虽然获得了她的爱，但离得到她还相距甚远。他曾经请求给他两年的时间；时光如白驹过隙，而他却一事无成。而且，他老是念念不忘一个事实：她不赞成他所干的事情。她虽然没有直接说明，但却拐弯抹角让他明白这一点，效果与把话挑明一样清楚和确切。她没有勃然大怒，而只是不赞成。换上天性缺乏善良的女人，很可能会雷霆大怒，可是她仅仅流露出一些失望的情绪。她失望的原因在于，她立志要重新塑造的这位男子，不该拒绝接受塑造。从某种程度而言，她一度认为他是块可塑的材料，但这块材料越来越倔强，不愿被塑造成她父亲或勃特勒先生的那种模样。

他身上伟大和坚强的品质，她全视而不见，或者更为糟糕，全遭到了她的误解。这位男子的确可塑性很强，可以在人类社会任何一个狭小的角落生存，而她却觉得他任性和泥古不化，因为她无法把他塑造成一个适于生活在那个她唯一所熟悉的小天地里的人。她理解不透他那奔放的思想，一旦跟不上他的大脑运转时，就说他古怪乖僻。除了他，还没有谁的思想使她感到困惑。对于她的父母、弟弟以及奥尔奈，她素来都了如指掌；因而，她理解不透马丁时，就坚信毛病出在他身上。思想褊狭的人妄图给思路开阔的人当导师，总会演出这样的悲剧。

“你所膜拜的是正统思想的神殿，”一次在谈论普莱普斯和范德尔瓦特时，他对她说道，“我承认，拿他们当权威来引用，是再好不过了——因为他们俩毕竟是美国一流的文艺评论家嘛。国内的每一位教师都把范德尔瓦特尊为美国评论界的老前辈。我看过他的文章，觉得那是一个措辞巧妙但头脑空洞的人写的杰作。说穿了，正如葛莱特·伯吉斯所言，他只不过是个平庸之辈。普莱普斯也并不比他强。就拿他的《毒苔藓》来说吧，写得倒是很漂亮，没有用错一个标点，格调也定得很高——嗬，高得惊人哩！他成了美国稿酬最高的评论家。但是，苍天在上，他算什么评论家呀！英国人的评论文章写得比他强。

“可问题在于，他们唱的是迎合大众的调子，而且唱得是那么堂皇、崇高和自得。他们的评论文章会让我想起英国的礼拜日布教，不愧是颇得民意的传话筒。他们和你的那些国语教授一唱一和，相互吹捧，他们脑袋瓜里没有一丁点自己的独到见解，只懂得正统思想——其实，他们自己的思想也是正统的。他们观念淡薄，极易受到正统思想的影响，这就和把酿酒厂的标签贴在啤酒瓶子上一样简单。他们的任务是把所有上大学的年轻人都控制在手中，清洗净他们头脑里可能有的独特见解，然后打上正统思想的烙印。”

“我拥护正统思想，而你狂怒暴烈得像一个反对崇拜偶像的南洋岛国居民，相比较而言，我觉得我更接近真理。”她回答道。

“反对偶像崇拜是传教士的作为，”他笑着说，“可惜传教士全跑到国外向异教徒传教去了，要是国内留下一个，也可以向范德尔瓦特先生及普莱普斯先生这两个古老的偶像开刀。”

“还有大学里的教授呢。”她补充说。

他断然地摇了摇了头。“不，应该让理学教授活下来。他们是真正伟大的人。但如果能敲碎国语教授的脑壳，那才是好事呢，因为这些人十之八九都是思想狭隘、人云亦云的应声虫！”

针对教授所发的这通言论未免有些尖刻，在露丝听来简直是亵渎。她情不自禁地把那些干净整洁、知识渊博、衣着称体、说话的声调抑扬有致、谈吐文雅和富于教养的教授跟这个她鬼使神差般爱上的几乎无法形容的年轻人放在一起比较了一番——这位年轻人穿着总不合体，发达的肌肉标示出艰辛的劳作，一说话就激动，不是心平气和、态度冷静，而是满口脏话、语言刻薄。教授们至少挣着高工资——是啊，她强迫自己面对现实——属于上等人，而他一个子儿也挣不来，和他们是两个等级的人。

她没有掂量马丁的话，也没有根据他的话判断他的观点是否正确，而是拿表面现象做比较，认定他的看法是错误的——说实话，这是一种缺乏意识的结论。那些教授在文学上的见解之所以正确，是因为他们是成功者，马丁的文学论点之所以错误，是因为他兜售不出自己的作品，用他自己的话形容，他们“干出了名堂”，而他一事无成。再说，不久之前他站在这间客厅里被别人介绍时还面红耳赤、一脸窘相，惊恐地望着周围的古玩，生怕自己一摇一晃的肩膀会把它们撞碎，而且还问起斯温伯恩死了多久，大言不惭地宣称自己读过《精益求精》和《赞美生活》——这样一个人的观点要是正确，那才荒唐哩。

露丝无意中证实了他的看法：她崇拜正统思想。马丁理解她的思维方式，却不愿追根问底。她怎样尊崇普莱普斯、范德尔瓦特以及那些国语教授影响不到他对她的爱，但他愈来愈肯定地认识到她永远也不会理解或知晓他的思想深度和知识范围。

谈到音乐时，她觉得他不可理喻；论及歌剧，认为他不仅无法理喻，还刚愎自用，抱着错误的观点不放。

“你觉得怎么样？”一天夜里，在看完歌剧回家的路上，她这样问他。

这天晚上的歌剧票是他用一个月来一口一口从嘴里省出的钱买下的。她原想等他发表看法，但不见动静，而她自己被刚才看到和听到的感动得浑身颤抖、情绪激昂，于是便问了以上的那句话。

“我喜欢那支序曲，”对方答道，“真是好听得很。”

“是好听，可歌剧本身怎么样呢？”

“也很好听；我是说乐队演奏得很好。要是那些蹦蹦跳跳的人不咋咋呼呼的，或者干脆走下台，我听歌剧的劲头会更大些。”

露丝一下子惊呆了。

“你指的不是台特拉兰尼或巴利洛吧？”她问道。

“指的是他们全体——全体演出人员。”

“他们可是杰出的艺术家呀。”她抗议道。

“他们古里古怪，显得很不真实，即便杰出的艺术家，也是在糟蹋音乐。”

“难道你不喜欢巴利洛的歌喉？”露丝问，“据说，他仅次于卡鲁索呀。”

“我当然喜欢他，我还更喜欢台特拉兰尼哩。她的歌喉珠圆玉润——起码我是这样想的。”

“可是，可是——”露丝说话结巴起来，“我不明白你的意思。你欣赏他们的歌喉，却又说他们糟蹋了音乐。”

“正是这么回事。我希望能听上他们的音乐会，然而却一百个不愿意听他们在乐队演奏时歌唱。恐怕我是一个无可救药的现实主义者。杰出的歌唱家不一定就是杰出的演员。在五光十色、余音绕梁的音乐伴奏下，听巴利洛亮起天使般的歌喉唱段情歌，听台特拉兰尼也像天使一样同他对唱，那才叫人心醉神迷哩，简直会飘飘欲仙。这可不是我的承认，而是我的强调。不过，要是看到其人，整个效果就破坏掉了——台特拉兰尼不穿鞋身高也有五英尺十英寸，体重高达一百九十磅；而巴利洛则高不足五英尺四英寸，脸上油光闪闪，胸脯厚实得像个五短身材的铁匠；他们俩装腔作势，不是紧紧抱住自己的胸膛，就是像疯人院里的疯子把胳膊在空中胡挥乱舞。让我把这一切幻想成苗条、美丽的公主和英俊、浪漫的年轻王子之间的爱情场景，我可是万万做不到。总之，这太荒唐、太可笑、太不真实，问题就在于此。在这个世界上，绝没有人那样谈情说爱。倘若我用这样的方式和你谈恋爱，你一定会掴我一耳光。”

“你理解错了，”露丝反驳道，“每一种艺术都有其局限性。”（她搜索枯肠地回忆着自己在上大学时所听的关于艺术常规的讲座。）“拿绘画来说吧，画面上只展现物体的二维性，但画家却运用艺术让你产生错觉，认为他画中表现的是三维物体。再以写作为例，作家必须无所不能，让你觉得他对主人公心理的描绘是合情合理的，但实际上你也知道主人公心里考虑问题时并无他人在场，无论是作家还是别的任何人都听不到主人公的声音。戏剧、雕塑、歌剧——各种类型的艺术全都是这样。有些不可调和的事物应该得到人们的接受。”

“是的，这我明白，”马丁说，“所有的艺术都有其常规。”（露丝听他使用这个字眼，不禁感到意外。仿佛他自己也上过大学，而非缺乏真才实学，只知道在图书馆里胡乱翻阅书刊。）“但就连常规也必须是真实的。把一棵棵树画在平面硬纸板上，竖在戏台的两侧，我们可以把它们看作森林。这种常规是够逼真的了。但话又说回来，我们不会把海洋景色视为森林。这是绝对不可能的，因为我们的感官不允许我们这样做。你绝不会，或更确切地说，你不应该把今晚那两个疯子的狂呼乱吼、扭捏作态和痛苦的痉挛看作对爱情的真实刻画。”

“你难道自以为比所有的音乐鉴赏家都高明不成？”她不屑地问。

“不，不，压根就不是这么回事。我只是想保留我个人的看法罢了，我刚才讲出自己的观点，是想向你解释台特拉兰尼夫人笨拙的表演是怎样破坏了我对音乐的雅兴，全世界的音乐鉴赏家也许都是对的，但我是我，我可不愿委曲求全去迎合整个人类一致的看法。如果我不喜欢一样东西，那就是不喜欢；我无论如何也不会因为自己的大多数同胞喜欢或假装喜欢，就做出一副喜欢的样子。在这种事情上，我可不会赶时髦。”

“可你知道，音乐涉及修养问题，”露丝不服气地说，“歌剧更是如此。也许——”

“也许我对歌剧缺乏修养吧？”他快言快语地打断她的话说。她点了点头。

“正是这样。”他赞同地说，“我可自以为是幸运儿呢，因为我小时候没有对歌剧入迷。要是真入迷，今天晚上闹不定会洒下多愁善感的眼泪呢；看过那对宝贝的丑角戏，还会觉得他们的歌喉更优美、伴奏的音乐更动听哩。你说得对，这多半涉及的是修养问题。我现在年龄太大了，必须看真实的东西，要不什么都不看。令人难以信服的假象显然是骗人的把戏。当矮小的巴利洛发起神经来，把人高马大的台特拉兰尼搂在怀里（她也在发神经），向她表白自己在爱着她时，我觉得大歌剧就是这种骗人的把戏。”

露丝又在用表面现象做比较，并根据自己对正统思想的信仰衡量他的思想。他算老几，难道就他一个是对的，而所有有教养的人都是错的？他的话以及他的观点对她丝毫不起作用。正统思想在她的脑海中已过于根深蒂固，所以她不会对创新的思想产生共鸣。她一直都在受着音乐的熏陶，打孩提时代就喜欢听歌剧，她那个阶层的人也都喜欢歌剧。马丁·伊登刚刚从低劣的工人阶级歌曲堆里走出来，有什么权利对世界一流的音乐说东说西呢？她对他感到恼火，走在他旁边隐隐约约地滋生出些许愤恨的情绪。就算她怀有最宽大的胸怀，也顶多认为他的言论是任性的怪话及不合情理的玩笑。然而，当他在大门口把她拥入怀中，以温柔的恋人方式对她吻别时，她心头涌起一股对他的爱，忘掉了所有的龃龉。这天夜里，她躺在枕上难以成寐，脑子里想个不停（她近来常这样），猜不透自己怎么会不顾家里人的反对爱上这样一个怪人。

次日，马丁·伊登把手头的文章搁置一旁，鼓足劲挥笔疾书，写出了一篇名为《论假象》的论文。贴上邮票，这篇文章便上了路，而在以后的日月里，它注定还要贴许多邮票，还要进行许多趟这样的旅行。

第二十五章

玛丽亚·西尔瓦家境贫寒，了解穷困给人带来的种种不幸。穷困这个词，在露丝看来，指的只是一种不美好的生活环境。她对这个问题的了解仅限于此。她知道马丁一贫如洗，心里却把他的境遇跟亚伯拉罕·林肯、勃特勒先生及其他功成名就者的童年时代联系在一起。她虽然也知道穷困不是件叫人高兴的事，但是却以中产阶级的心理自我安慰地想道，穷困是有益处的，它是一种有力的鞭策，可以激励所有不甘堕落、不甘沉沦的苦人儿走上发迹的道路。所以，当她知道马丁穷得把手表和外套都送到了当铺时，并没有为之担心。她甚至认为这是充满了希望的一个方面，坚信这种情况早晚都会让他清醒过来，迫使他放弃写作。

露丝从未看到过马丁的饿相，但他的脸却消瘦了下去，双颊的微微凹陷变得愈来愈明显。实际上，她注意到了他脸上的变化，而且感到很满意。他似乎变得雅气了一些，身上的糟肉以及那种既叫她厌恶又引诱着她的野兽般的活力都减去了许多。有时两人在一起，她发现他的眼睛里闪射出一道令她倾心的异彩，那非凡的闪光给他增加了诗人和学者的风度——他希望自己能成为这两种人，同时这也是她的愿望。但在玛丽亚·西尔瓦的眼里，他那凹陷的双颊和燃烧的目光显示的却是另外一种情况，她天天观察这种变化，并以此判断他命运的起伏。她看到他披着外套走出家门，虽天气阴冷，但回来时却不见了外套；紧接着，她发现他的双颊略微丰润了些，眼里饥饿的火焰也熄灭了。她还看到他的自行车和手表也是这样不见了踪影；每一次过后，她都会看到他重新涌发出勃勃生气。

而且，她还注意到他在勤奋工作，知道他是怎样挑灯夜战。多么艰苦的工作啊！他们俩干的活儿虽然性质不同，但她知道他胜过自己一筹。她诧异地发现，他吃的东西愈少，工作的劲头反而愈大。有几次，她觉得他饥饿难熬时，就若无其事地送一块刚出炉的面包给他，并以开玩笑的口吻声称这面包要比他烘得好，尴尬地说些掩饰的话。她还会指派自己的一个刚学步的孩子送去一大罐热汤，但她心里却很矛盾，不知这样从自己的亲骨肉嘴里夺食应该不应该。马丁对此十分感激，因为他了解穷人家的生活，知道这是一种慈善行为——如果这个世界上还有慈善的话。

一天，玛丽亚把家里剩下的一些东西让孩子们吃了，用口袋中最后的一角五分钱打来一加仑的劣质酒。马丁走进厨房打水，被邀请坐下来同她一道喝酒。他为她的健康干杯，而她也为他祝酒。接下来，她祝他事业发达，马丁的祝酒词是希望詹姆士·格兰特能走上门来，把洗衣服的钱付给她。詹姆士·格兰特是个打短工的木匠，有时也拖拖账，这次欠了玛丽亚三块钱。

玛丽亚和马丁都空着肚子喝这刚酿出的酸酒，很快便上了头。他们是截然不同的两类人，在苦难之中却是一样悲惨凄凉，不过，他们在心里谁都没把这苦难当回事。玛丽亚听说他去过亚速尔群岛[1]，感到十分惊异，因为她是十一岁才离开那儿的。当得知他还到过夏威夷群岛时，她就更惊异了，她们全家离开亚速尔群岛后便是移居到了那里。然而，当他说自己去过毛伊岛[2]时，她便惊奇得无法形容了——正是在这座岛上，她步入青春期并嫁了人。而且，马丁竟两次光顾卡胡鲁伊港——她和丈夫初次相遇的地方！他搭乘过那些仍然存留在她记忆中的运糖船——啧，啧，这个世界可真小啊。还有瓦伊鲁哥村，那地方也留下了他的足迹！他认识种植园的总管吗？哈，他认识，还跟总管干过两杯酒呢。

他们一边缅怀往事，一边喝着未兑水的酸酒压饥。对马丁来说，前途并不十分暗淡。成功在他的面前扑闪着，眼看就要成为他的囊中之物。此刻，他端详着跟前这位劳累不堪的妇女那深刻着皱纹的面孔，回想起她的菜汤和刚出炉的面包，心中不由涌起极其强烈的感激和报恩之情。

“玛丽亚，”他突然喊叫起来，“你想要什么东西？”

她望望他，给弄得莫名其妙。

“如果你能如愿以偿，那么现在，就在这一刻工夫，你想要什么呢？”

“想要七双鞋，给孩子们每人一双。”

“你会得到的，”他宣布道，而她则庄重地点了点头，“但我指的是大愿望，不知你想得到什么大的东西。”

她眼睛里闪射出温厚的光芒，以为他在跟她玛丽亚开玩笑，而这种年头难得有人和她逗个乐子。

“好好想想。”她正要启口说话，他却劝告她道。

“好吧，”她说，“我仔细想过啦。我想要这幢房子，让它完全属于我，再不用交每月七块钱的房租。”

“你会得到的，”他向她保证说，“而且要不了多少时间。现在讲讲你的最大愿望吧。全当我是上帝，我告诉你，你想要什么就可以得到什么。说出你的愿望吧，我在听着呢。”

玛丽亚一本正经地思考了一会儿。

“你不怕我太贪心吗？”她警告地问。

“不，不，”他笑着说，“我不怕。请说吧。”

“这可是非常大的愿望啊。”她再次警告道。

“没关系，请你说吧。”

“那好——”她像小孩子样深深吸了口气，说出了她对生活最大的要求，“我希望能有一个奶牛场——一个地地道道的奶牛场。有成群的奶牛、大片的土地和丰盛的草场。我希望奶牛场设在圣莱安附近，因为我的姐姐住在那儿。我把牛奶卖到奥克兰去，赚取很多很多的钱。乔和尼克不用再牧牛，他们可以到学校上课，将来当工程师，到铁路上工作。是的，我想要一个奶牛场。”

她停下来望着他，眼睛里闪闪发光。

“你会得到的。”他即刻便做出了答复。

她点了点头，把嘴唇有礼貌地凑向酒杯，为赐给她礼物的人干杯，虽然她知道这样的礼物永远也拿不到手。他的心地是好的，她衷心感激他善良的意图，就仿佛对方把好意和礼物一道送给了她。

“对，玛丽亚，”他继续说道，“尼克和乔不用去卖牛奶，所有的孩子都上学去，而且一年四季都有鞋穿。那将是一流的奶牛场，所有的东西一应俱全。有住房、马厩，当然还有牛棚；要养鸡和猪，种蔬菜瓜果，凡此种种。奶牛数量多，赚的钱也多，可以雇一两个帮手。你什么都不用干，只招呼招呼孩子就行了。如果碰上好男人，你可以嫁给他，把奶牛场交他管理，而你舒舒服服地过日子。”

马丁对于未来许下了漫天大诺，但一转身却把自己仅有的一套像样的衣服送进了当铺。这一来，他简直陷入了绝境，因为他会因此和露丝断掉联系。他连件较差的能穿得出去的衣服都没有了；他虽然还能到肉铺和面包店去，甚至还可以偶尔去去姐姐家，但他绝不敢衣着寒碜地登摩斯府邸的门槛。

他继续写作，但心里却非常痛苦，几乎万念俱灰。他开始意识到第二场战斗已经失败，自己迫不得已还要出去找工作。找到工作，便会皆大欢喜——食品商、他姐姐、露丝，甚至连玛丽亚包括在内，都会心满意足，因为他欠玛丽亚一个月的房钱呢。他已经两个月没交打字机租赁费了，店方催他付钱，否则他就得把机子还回去。绝望的他准备低头认输，和命运暂时休战，以待将来东山再起，于是，他投考了铁路邮政处的公务员。他没想到，自己竟然考中了。工作算有了着落，但不知何时才会通知他上班去。

正当命运处于最低潮的节骨眼上，那台平稳运转的编辑机器出了毛病。一定是齿轮脱落了一个轮牙或者注油器里润滑油用干了，因为邮递员在一天早晨送来了一个又薄又小的信封。马丁扫了一眼信封的左上角，看到了《横贯大陆月刊》的刊名和地址。他怦然心跳，顿时感到头晕目眩，直想栽倒，双膝奇怪地抖动起来。他跌跌绊绊回到自己的房间，拿着仍未拆开的信封一屁股坐到了床上。直到这时他才明白，为什么有些人在接到惊人的好消息时会当场丧命。

毫无疑问，这次有好消息。那个薄信封里没装稿件，所以他的稿子被采用啦。他记得送往《横贯大陆月刊》的是一篇名为《嘹亮的钟声》的恐怖故事，足有五千字。由于一流杂志一贯是在采用稿件时立即付稿酬，信封里该附有支票。每个字两分钱，一千字就是二十块；那么支票的钱数肯定是一百块钱。天啊，一百块钱呀！拆信封的时候，他的脑海里浮现出他的每一笔欠款——欠食品商$3.85，肉铺$4.00，面包店$2.00，水果店$5.00，总共$14.85。另外，欠房租$2.50，预交一个月的房费$2.50，欠两个月的打字机租赁费$8.00，再预交一个月的租赁费$4.00，总共$31.85。最后还得加上向当铺赎东西的钱，外带利息——手表为$5.50，外套$5.50，自行车$7.75，一套衣服$5.50（利息是60%，可这又有什么关系呢？）——这几笔钱的总数是$56.10。一笔笔欠款变成闪光数字，历历如在眼前，经过一番加减，稿酬还剩下$43.90。还清每一笔债务、赎回每一件东西之后，他的口袋里还会有$43.90。这样一大笔叮当作响的钱哩。更令人欣慰的是，他还预交了一个月的打字机租赁费和房租呢。

想到这里，他抽出了那页用打字机打出的信函，把它铺展开。里面没有夹支票。他朝信封里瞧了瞧，又把信封放到亮光里照照，还是不相信自己的眼睛，于是用哆嗦的手急忙将信封一撕两半。仍然不见支票的踪影。读信的时候，他一目数行，匆匆掠过编辑对故事的赞誉之辞，想看看这封信的实质内容——为何没有附上支票？这方面的内容他未看到片言只语，看到的只是让他突然如坠冰窖的话。那封信从他的手里掉落下来。他眼中失去了光彩，躺倒在枕头上，拉过毛毯盖在身上，一直盖到下巴处。

《嘹亮的钟声》的稿酬是五块钱——五千字才卖五块钱啊！不是每字二分，而是每分十字呀！哼，编辑还把文章夸奖了一通呢。要等到故事刊载出来，他才能拿到支票。什么每个字的最低稿酬是两分钱，什么稿子一经采用便付钱，全是胡扯八道。这套骗人的鬼话使他误入歧途。当初要是知道这么回事，他绝不会投身写作。他会出外找工作——为露丝而苦干。他回想起最初试笔的那一天，一想到自己浪费了这么多的时间，全为了十个字一分钱的稿酬，他便感到心寒。报上宣扬的那些关于作家领取高稿酬的言论肯定也是弥天大谎。看来，他间接得知的那些情况都是无稽之谈，因为铁证就在眼前。

《横贯大陆月刊》的单本定价是两角五分钱，它那气势恢宏、富于艺术性的封面充分说明它是第一流的杂志。它既庄重又高雅，早在他出生之前便已发行，延续至今。杂志的封面上月月都印着一位世界著名作家的话，申明《横贯大陆月刊》的使命，而那位文学巨匠曾经就是在这本杂志上初露锋芒的。这样一本庄严、高尚、从上天获取灵感的杂志，竟然五千字只付五块钱的稿酬！那位伟大作家最近死于异国他乡——马丁记得他是穷困潦倒中殒命的——既然作家的稿酬如此“丰厚”，这也就不足为奇了。

唉，他看过报上的那套关于作家及稿酬的谎言，竟然上了钩，白白浪费了两年的时间。现在，他要吐出饵钩，从今往后再也不写一个字。他要满足露丝的愿望，满足大家的愿望，去找个工作干。此念一生，他想起了乔，想起了乔已前往无事可干的地方流浪，马丁羡慕得深深叹了口气。长期以来，每天写作十九个小时，这样的生命真够他呛。可是，乔并没有坠入爱河，并不肩负爱情的义务，故此可以无所事事、四方流浪。他马丁则必须去奋争，去工作。他打算第二天一大早就出外寻工作。他还要让露丝知道他已改弦易辙，愿意进她父亲的事务所工作。

五千字五块钱，十个字一分钱，这就是艺术的市场价格。他心里产生出深深的失望、上当和耻辱的感觉；合上眼皮，就可以看到自己欠食品商的那$3.85似火焰般熊熊燃烧。他不寒而栗，觉得骨头里发痛。他的腰和背钻心地痛，头也痛得难忍——天灵盖痛、后脑勺痛、脑仁痛，整个头都似乎要炸开；眉毛上方的部位更是痛得叫他受不了。眉毛下首的眼皮底下则残酷无情地燃烧着那个数字——$3.85。他睁开眼以求解脱，但屋里白亮的光线似乎要烧焦他的眼球，迫使他又闭上眼，再次面对那$3.85。

五千字五块钱，十个字一分钱——这一思想在他的大脑里扎了根，令他无法摆脱，就像他摆脱不了眼皮底下的$3.85一样。随即，后边的那个数字似乎发生了变化，他惊奇地看着它变成了另一个燃烧的数字——$2.00。啊，他知道那是欠面包店的钱，接着出现的是$2.50。

这下他可犯了难，用力地思考起来，仿佛在决断一个生死攸关的问题。他的确欠别人两块五，但债主是谁呢？这个专横和恶毒的世界命令他找出答案，于是他沿着大脑中无端无尽的长廊搜索，打开各种各样房间的门户，把自己所能记得和了解的零碎东西都抖搂了一遍，但终无结果。仿佛过了几个世纪之后，他才恍然大悟，不费吹灰之力得到了答案——这笔钱是欠玛丽亚的。他松了口大气，然后又把注意力转向眼皮底下那折磨人的银幕。他以为既然已找出了答案，自己总算可以获得安宁了。可是，在$2.50消失的地方，又出现了一个燃烧的数字——$8.00。债主是谁呢？他又得在消沉的大脑中搜索，寻找答案了。

这次寻找不知花费了多少时间。似乎过了很长很长时间，他被敲门声惊醒过来——玛丽亚跑来询问他是不是病了。他用一种连他自己都无法辨认的沉闷的声音说他没有病，只是在睡午觉。可他吃惊地发现夜幕已悄然潜入房间。信是在下午两点钟收到的，他这才意识到自己的确病了。

此刻，$8.00又开始在他的眼皮底下冒火焰，而他又得苦苦思索了。不过，这次他变聪明了，觉得没必要搜索枯肠地傻想，觉得自己刚才真是太愚蠢。他用杠杆拨动思想，让思想围着他旋转，像命运的巨大车轮、记忆的旋转木马以及智慧的滚动圆球。思想愈转愈快，最后把他卷入旋涡之中，使他在漆黑的混沌里飞转。

就这样，他非常自然地置身于一台轧液机旁，把上过浆的衣袖朝里填。正在朝里填的当儿，他留意到袖口上印着数字。他原以为这是做标记的新方法，但凑近一瞧，却看到一个袖口上有$3.85字样。他意识到这是食品商的账单，而轧液机的滚筒里上下翻腾的全是他欠的账单。他心生一诡计，觉得把那些账单都扔到地上，就不用再付账了。他想到做到，即刻把那些衣袖仇恨地揉作一团，抛到脏得出奇的地板上。衣袖聚成一堆，而每份账单都有一千个副本，可他偏偏只去寻找一个两块五的账单——那是他欠玛丽亚的。玛丽亚不会催他付钱，而他慷慨激昂地决定只还这一笔账；于是他开始在衣袖堆里寻找她的账单。他不顾一切地寻找，找了很长时间，直至旅馆里的那个肥胖的荷兰经理进来时，他还在寻找。荷兰佬满脸怒容，以响彻寰宇的洪亮嗓门叫嚷道：“我要从你的工资里扣除这些衣袖的钱！”望着那堆积成小山的衣袖，马丁知道自己必须干一千年的牛马活才能还清这笔债。唉，别无良策，只有杀死经理，放把火烧掉洗衣店。可是大块头的荷兰佬一把揪住他的后颈，将他凌空拎起，打破了他的如意算盘。荷兰佬拎着他在熨衣台、炉子和轧液机的上方摇来晃去，又把他拎到洗衣间，放在绞衣机和洗衣机的上空摇晃。马丁被摇得上下牙齿打架、头痛欲裂，他真不知荷兰佬哪儿来这么大的力量。

后来，他又回到了轧液机跟前，这次是一家杂志社的编辑从一边往机器里填袖口，而他在另一边接。每一个袖口都是一张支票，马丁怀着满脸的希望急不可耐地一张张检查，可看到的全是空白支票。他站在那儿接支票，足足接了有一百万年的光景，每一张都不轻易放过，生怕上面填有数字。最后，他终于找到了，用颤抖的手指拿到亮光处查看。原来是张五块钱的支票。轧液机另一端的编辑哈哈大笑。“你等着瞧，我要杀了你。”马丁说完，跑到洗衣间去寻斧子，结果发现乔在那儿给手稿上浆。他想让乔停下来，抢起斧子就劈。可那武器举到空中就不动了，原来马丁发现自己又回到了熨衣机旁，那儿飘着鹅毛大雪。不，那飘然落下的不是雪花，而是大面额的支票，最小的面额也不少于一千块。他把支票收集到一起，进行分门别类，一百张一叠，用细绳扎捆牢。

他边干边抬头望去，瞧见乔站在他面前，把熨斗、上过浆的衬衫以及手稿舞来弄去。乔还时不时伸手取过一叠支票，混进那些东西里一起舞弄。那些乱七八糟的东西转着大圈，穿过屋顶，消失在了空中。马丁抡斧向他劈去，可他抢过斧子，把它也抛进了那旋转的圈子里。后来，他索性拎起马丁，把他也抛了起来。马丁穿过屋顶，见到手稿就抓，所以待到落下来时，怀里已抱了一大堆手稿。但他脚刚一着地，便又升腾而起，就这样一圈、两圈地转个不停，数不清究竟转了多少圈。他听到远处有人在用孩子般的尖嗓门歌唱：“跟我一起跳华尔兹舞吧，威利，跳呀跳呀跳。”

他在由支票、上过浆的衬衫以及手稿组成的“银河系”中找回了那把斧子，准备一回到地面就杀死乔。可他悬在空中没能下来。夜间两点钟，玛丽亚透过薄壁听到他的呻吟声，来到他的房间，把热熨斗放在他身上，又取来湿布蒙住他发痛的眼睛。

[1]　位于葡萄牙以西，隶属葡萄牙。

[2]　夏威夷群岛中的第二大岛。

第二十六章

这天早晨，马丁没有出去找工作。直至傍晚时分，他才从昏迷中苏醒，用发痛的眼睛望了望四周。西尔瓦家一个叫玛丽的八岁孩子一直守候在旁边，这时见他恢复了知觉，便尖声叫喊起来。玛丽亚闻声从厨房赶来，用干活干得满是老茧的手摸摸他滚烫的额头，又替他量了量脉搏。

“想吃点东西吗？”她问。

他摇了摇头。他没有一点想进食的欲望，不知自己这辈子是不是还会有饥饿感。

“我病了，玛丽亚，”他有气无力地说，“你知道是什么病吗？”

“是流行性感冒，”她答道，“过两三天就会好的。现在最好吃点东西。多吃点，也许明天胃口就开了。”

马丁对生病是不习惯的，待玛丽亚带着小女儿离开后，就想起床穿衣服。他头脑发晕，眼睛痛得睁都睁不开，靠着意志的力量，才挣扎着起了床，但伏到案头便又昏迷了过去。半个小时后，他回到床上，只好闭起眼睛躺在那儿，把自己的种种疼痛和虚弱思来想去。玛丽亚来过几次，为他更换敷在额头上的湿布，除此之外不来打搅他，因为她是个明白人，不愿唠唠叨叨地惹他心烦。他对此感激不尽，喃喃自语地说：“玛丽亚，你会得到奶牛场的，会的，一定会的。”

后来，他记起了已遗忘许久的昨日的往事。自从收到《横贯大陆月刊》的那封信，好像已经过了一辈子，因为他觉得过去的历史已经完结，打算重新开始生活。他尽了自己的努力，而且是拼命的努力，现在只落得仰面朝天卧倒病榻。如果不是把自己饿得死去活来，他就不会患流感。他垮了下来，无力击退侵入肌体的病菌。这就是他的下场。

“一个人即便著作满天飞，却命丧黄泉，又有什么用呢？”他出声地问，“这不是我的事业，再也不能从事文学写作了。我只配进会计室管管账目，按月领薪水，跟露丝过小日子。”

两天过后，他吃了个鸡蛋和两片烤面包，又喝了杯茶，然后让把他的邮件拿来，可眼睛还是痛得厉害，无法看信。

“你给我读读，玛丽亚，”他说，“别去管那些又大又长的信件，把它们全扔到桌子底下。拣小的信件念给我听。”

“我不会读信，”对方答道，“特丽莎会读，她已经上学了。”

于是，九岁的特丽莎·西尔瓦拆开信，读了起来。他心不在焉地听着打字机租赁店寄来的冗长的催债信，脑子里却在思索着如何去找工作。猛然之间，他惊得醒过了神。

“如果同意做适当修改，”特丽莎慢吞吞地读道，“我们愿出四十块钱买下你的小说连载权。”

“这是哪家杂志社？”马丁喊叫了起来，“来，把信递给我！”

他一下子可以看信了，连疼痛也不觉得了。愿出四十块钱给他的是《白鼠》杂志社，他们想买下《漩涡》——也是他早期写的恐怖小说。他把信看了一遍又一遍。编辑坦率地指出，他对素材的处理并不完美，他们之所以要买这篇小说，是因为里面不乏独特的观点。如果同意他们删掉三分之一的内容，他们就定稿，而且一接到回音就给他寄来四十块钱。

他要来笔墨，写信告诉那位编辑，说他如果高兴，可以删掉三分之三的内容，只要把四十块钱马上寄来就行了。

信由特丽莎拿去投进邮箱，而马丁又躺回床上，陷入了沉思。看来，事情并非骗局。《白鼠》一采用稿件就付钱。《漩涡》共三千字，删掉三分之一，还剩下两千字，稿酬每字按两分钱计算，刚好是四十块钱。一用稿件就付钱，每字两分钱——报上讲的全是实话。他原来还以为《白鼠》是三流杂志呢！显然他并不了解杂志界的情况。他以前把《横贯大陆月刊》视为一流杂志，可是它每十个字才付一分钱的稿酬。他总把《白鼠》看得一钱不值，然而它付的稿酬却高出《横贯大陆月刊》二十倍，而且一用稿就付钱。

现在，有一点可以肯定：病好后，他不打算出外找工作了。他的头脑中可以发掘出更多和《漩涡》同样好的文章，每篇按四十块钱取酬，他的收入会比干任何工作、从事任何职业都高。正当他以为战败的时候，却获得了胜利。经证明，他是干事业的料。道路已经畅通。从《白鼠》起始，他要把各家杂志社列成一份长长的主顾名单。卖钱的文章可以暂且搁置一旁。说实在的，那纯粹是浪费时间，未给他带来一块钱的收入。他要献身于事业，写出好文章来，把内心最出色的构思展现于纸面。他希望露丝能在跟前和他分享喜悦；他翻阅放在床头的信件时，发现了一封露丝的来信。她在信中娇嗔地责备他，问他到底出了什么事，这么长时间不去看她。他把信爱不释手地又读了一遍，仔细欣赏她的笔迹，对她的每一道笔画都充满了爱心，最后还吻了吻她的签名。

他回信时不顾后果地告诉她，他把最好的衣服送进了当铺，所以才没有去看她。他还说自己染上了病，不过现在已快康复，用不了十天或两个星期（这是一封信到纽约市去打个来回的时间），待把衣服赎回来，他就回到她身旁。

然而，露丝可不愿等十天或两个星期。再说，她的恋人在生病呢。第二天下午，在阿瑟的陪同下，她乘着摩斯府内的马车不期而至，这让西尔瓦家的孩子以及街上的那帮顽童喜不自胜，但是却叫玛丽亚慌了手脚。她扇了自家孩子几记耳光，因为他们挤在小前廊里围观客人。随后，她用比平时更糟糕的英语充满歉意地说自己的衣着不成体统。从她那高高挽起的袖子、沾着肥皂沫的胳膊以及系在腰间的湿麻袋片便可以看得出，她刚才在干什么活。这两位高贵的年轻人向她问起她的房客时，慌得她六神无主，竟忘了请他们到小客厅坐坐。要到马丁的房间去，得穿过厨房，此刻那儿由于正在大规模洗衣服，被弄得温暖潮湿、雾气腾腾。玛丽亚激动之中猛一推卧室的门，使房门和室内小橱的门卡在了一起，结果一团团带有肥皂水和尘土气息的水蒸气透过半开的门直往病人的房间灌，足足灌了有五分钟。

露丝右拐左转，然后再向右调头，沿着桌与床之间的狭窄通道顺利地来到了马丁身旁；可是阿瑟转的弯太大，把放在马丁做饭的那个墙角的盆盆罐罐碰得叮当响。阿瑟没在屋里多待。仅有的一把椅子给露丝坐了，他见自己的任务已经完成，便走出去守立在大门口。西尔瓦家的七个孩子好奇地将他围在中间，不住眼地打量着他，就像观看杂技团的一个奇特节目。十几个街区的孩子都跑了来，把马车围了个水泄不通，急切地等待着什么悲惨吓人的事情发生。在他们这条街上，只有遇到婚丧大事才可以看得到马车。这次既没人结婚又无人死亡，所以肯定出了什么他们没经历过的事，值得一等。

马丁早就盼望着能见到露丝。从根本上来说，他天性多情，比普通人更需要同情。他朝思暮想的同情对他意味着明智的理解；但他全然不知，露丝所怀有的大半是多愁善感和礼节性的同情，与其说是出于对同情对象的理解，倒不如说是出自于她那善良的天性。所以，当马丁拉着她的手高兴地说话时，她在爱情的驱使下也握紧了他的手，而且一看到孤苦、艰难的生活在他脸上烙下的痕迹，眼睛里便发湿，闪动着泪花。

他告诉她，他的两篇文章已被采用，说他在接到《横贯大陆月刊》的来信时是怎样陷入了绝望，而收到《白鼠》的来信又是多么高兴，然而她却没有仔细倾听。她听到了他说的话，也理解这些话的字面含义，可是对他的绝望和高兴却缺乏共鸣。她无法摆脱自己的看法，对卖文章给杂志社这种事不感兴趣。对她来说，成家立业才是重要的。不过，她当时并未意识到这一点，也未意识到自己希望马丁谋个职业是出自一个向往做母亲的女人本能的冲动。要是有人用清楚、肯定的语言把这话向他讲明，她会脸发烧，闹不定还会恼羞成怒，一口咬定她只对自己爱恋的人感兴趣，只希望他有一个锦绣前程。所以，当马丁向她倾吐衷曲，为自己选中的事业在这个世界上崭露头角而扬扬得意时，她只是听听表面的意思，还时不时四处张望，为自己看到的景象吃惊不已。

露丝平生第一次看到了贫困生活的凄惨面目。以前，她总以为饿肚子的恋人富有浪漫色彩，却不知饿肚子的恋人是怎样生活。万万想不到会是这样一种情形。她的目光游移不定，一会儿扫视房间，一会儿打量马丁。随着她一道从厨房进来的带有水蒸气的脏衣服味令人作呕。露丝心想，如果那个可怕的女人经常洗衣服，马丁身上一定浸透了这种气味。堕落的生活就是这样侵蚀人的。她望望马丁，似乎看到了周围环境在他身上留下的污痕。以前她所见到的他总是把脸修得干干净净，而今他脸上那三天未刮的胡须叫她觉得反感。那胡须不仅使他显得又黑又脏，和西尔瓦家的屋里屋外一样，还突出了他身上那种令她厌恶的兽性。可是他却扬扬得意地炫耀自己的两篇文章已被采用，对自己疯狂的追求更加坚定了信念。这转机要是晚来一些，他肯定会认输，老老实实去找职业。现在，他却要继续留在这幢可怕的房子里，再过上几个月忍饥挨饿的写作生活。

“这是什么味儿？”她突然问。

“我想是玛丽亚洗衣服散发出的味，”对方答道，“我已经闻惯了。”

“不，不，不是那种味，而是别的什么气味，是一种发腐的难闻气味。”

马丁先用鼻子嗅了嗅，才做出了回答。

“除了发腐的烟草味，别的闻不出什么来。”他说。

“正是烟草味，真是难闻死啦。你为什么要抽这么多烟呢，马丁？”“不知道。我只知道感到寂寞时，就比平时抽得多。再说，这是多年养成的老习惯了。小的时候我就会抽烟。”

“这习惯不好，你要知道，”她责备道，“烟味要多难闻有多难闻。”“这得怪烟不好，因为我只能买得起最低廉的烟。等我拿到那四十块钱的支票，就买好牌子的烟抽，那时连天使闻到也不会讨厌。要说三天之内就有两篇稿子被采用，成绩不算坏吧？四十五块钱的稿酬差不多可以还清我所有的债务。”

“两年的心血就为的是这个？”她问。

“不对，应该是不足一个星期的心血。请把桌子角的那本书递给我，就是那个灰色封面的账簿。”他打开账簿，一页页飞快翻动着。“哈，我说的一点不错。写《嘹亮的钟声》用了四天，《漩涡》用了两天。一星期挣四十五块钱，一个月就是一百八十块钱，比我干任何工作都强。再说，我这是刚刚起步。我要给你买许多东西，所以每月就是挣一千块钱也不嫌多。每月五百块钱的薪水就太低了。这四十五块钱仅仅是个开始。等走上正轨，那时再瞧我的本事吧。[1]”

露丝误解了他最后的这句俚语，便把话题又扯到了抽烟上。

“你抽烟抽得太厉害啦，问题并不在于更换烟的牌子。抽烟本身是有害的，不管什么牌子的烟都是如此。你真是个大烟囱、活火山和会走路的排烟筒，实在不成体统，亲爱的马丁，你要明白这一点。”

她把身子朝着他靠过去，眼睛里闪出祈求的神情；他望着她娇嫩的脸蛋，望着她纯洁、清澈的眼睛，又像过去一样，觉得自己是那样卑微。

“希望你以后不要再抽烟了，”她悄语道，“求求你，看在我的分上。”“好吧，我不抽了。”他高声说，“你让我干什么我就干什么，无论是任何事情，亲爱的，这你应该知道。”

她听后芳心大动。她清清楚楚看到了他天性中宽厚及随和的一面，坚信只要她要求他放弃写作，他一定会满足她愿望。在短暂的一瞬间，这种话在她的唇边颤抖。但她没把话说出来，因为她还不够大胆，仍然缺乏这份勇气。她迎着他凑过身去，偎在他怀里喃喃低语：“你知道，实际上这并不是为了我，马丁，而是为了你自己。我觉得抽烟对你是有害的；最好不要当任何东西的奴隶，尤其不要当麻醉品的奴隶。”“我要永远当你的奴隶。”他微笑着说。

“那我可就要发号施令喽。”

她以顽皮的目光望着他，但内心深处已经在后悔没提出自己最大的要求。

“愿听候吩咐，王后陛下。”

“我的第一道旨令是要你别忘了天天刮脸。你的胡子把我的脸扎得生疼。”

接着，两人相互抚摸，发出爱的欢笑。她已经达到了一个目的，一次一个，不能贪多。她涌起一股女性的自豪感，因为她使他戒了烟。下一次，她要劝他去谋个职业。他不是说过，她让他干什么他就干什么吗？

她从他身旁走开，去巡视整个房间。她仔细查看头顶晾绳上挂的笔记，还琢磨那架用来把自行车往天花板上吊的神秘滑车。看到桌下堆积如山的手稿，她黯然神伤，觉得那里面耗费了太多的时间。那只油炉赢得了她的敬慕，但在检查食品架时，却发现那儿空无一物。

“天哪，一点吃的东西都没有，可怜的亲人儿，”她又体贴又同情地说，“你一定饿坏了。”

“我的食物都存在玛丽亚的柜子里和厨房里，”他扯了个谎说，“存在那种地方比较好。不要担心我会饿肚子，你瞧瞧这个就知道了。”

她回到他身边，看他弯起胳膊肘，衣袖下的二头肌隆起和膨胀，变成了一大团坚硬的肌肉。那情形令她厌恶。从感情上讲，她不喜欢那肌肉。可是，她身上的脉搏、血液和每一根神经却喜欢它，向往它。于是，她又如昔日一般，产生了一种说不清道不明的感觉，非但没有躲开，而是把身体贴了过去。紧接着，他将她紧紧搂在怀里。此刻，她那只考虑生活表面现象的大脑感到的是嫌恶，而她那颗对生活本身感兴趣的心以及她的女性本能却喜不自禁。在这种时刻，她才强烈地感受到自己对马丁的爱是多么深沉，因为当马丁用有力的胳膊紧紧地拥抱她、狂热地拥抱她，把她搂得身上发疼时，她高兴得几乎要晕过去。在这种时刻，她觉得背叛自己的原则、违背自己的崇高理想，尤其是暗地违抗父母，完全是正确行动。父母不愿让她嫁给这个男人，为她爱上他而感到震惊。有时她一离开他，就会变得冷静和理智，这一点也让她震惊。和他在一起时，她爱他——老实讲，她的爱里时时掺杂着烦恼和忧虑；但这毕竟是爱情，是一种比她本人坚强的爱情。

“这种流感算不了什么，”他说，“它只是让人感到有点疼痛，让人脑袋痛得难受，但和登革热相比便是小巫见大巫了。”

“怎么，你还患过登革热？”她一边在他的怀里寻觅天赐的超脱感，一边心不在焉地问。

就这样，她以心不在焉的提问引着他朝下说。直到最后，他的一席话令她猛然吃了一惊。

原来，他是在夏威夷的一个岛屿上，三十个麻风病人秘密居住的地方染上这种热病的。

“你为什么到那儿去？”她问。

这样拿自己的身体不当一回事，简直就是犯罪。

“我当时并不知道会是那样的情形，”他答道，“我怎么也想不到会有麻风病人。我逃离帆船后，登上沙滩，往岛屿的腹地走，想找个藏身的地方。我游荡了三天，靠丛林中野生的番石榴、马来苹果以及香蕉活命。第四天，我发现了一条小路——那只不过是条羊肠小径。它深入腹地，沿山而上。我正要到那个方向去，而且看出不久前有人在小径上走过。走到一处地方，小径爬上了一道山脊，那儿窄得犹如刀口剑锋。山脊上的小径宽不足三英尺，两旁是万丈深渊。只要弹药充足，一人把关，十万人也攻不过去。

“那可是通向藏身之地的唯一道路。沿着小径走了三个小时，我总算走到了一个小山谷里，那儿四周都围着熔岩山峰。整个谷地都筑成了梯田种植芋头，那儿还栽有果树，坐落着八九间乃至十间茅草屋。但是一看到当地的居民，我就知道自己遇到了什么命运，只要瞧一眼就全明白了。”

“后来怎么样呢？”露丝问道。她听得气也透不出来了，就像苔丝德梦娜[2]那样，既吃惊又入迷。

“我无计可施。他们的头儿是个善良的老叟，虽已病入膏肓，但还像君王一样统治着他们。小山谷是他发现的，居民点也是他创建的。这样做是违法的，但他有枪支和大量的弹药，而且那些卡拿加人打惯了野牛和野猪，个个都是神枪手。在那种情况下，马丁·伊登是绝对逃不出去的。于是，他在那儿待了三个月。”

“后来你是怎么逃走的呢？”

“多亏了当地的一个一半中国血统、四分之一白人血统和四分之一夏威夷血统的姑娘鼎力相助，不然现在我还被扣在那儿呢。她是个可怜的美人儿，受过良好的教育。她母亲住在檀香山，拥有百万家产。就是这样一位姑娘最后解救了我。你要知道，居民点是她母亲资助兴办的，所以她不害怕因放我走而遭惩罚。不过，她让我发誓永不泄露那个秘密的地方；我一直信守着诺言。这是我第一次吐露，以前可提也没向人提过。那姑娘刚露出麻风病的初期症状，右手指微微弯曲，胳膊上有个小斑点，就是这些，想来她现在已经死了。”

“你当时就不害怕吗？你侥幸脱逃，没染上那种可怕的病，你就不感到高兴吗？”

“嗯，”他承认道，“起初我有点心惊肉跳，后来就习惯了。不过，我倒常常为那位姑娘感到惋惜；这使我忘记了害怕。她的心灵和外表都是那样美，而且只是稍微受了点感染；可是她注定要留在那儿，过一种原始野人的生活，慢慢地死去。麻风病真是太可怕了，可怕得令你无法想象。”

“可怜的姑娘。”露丝用一种温柔的声音说道，“奇怪的是，她竟然放走了你。”

“这话是什么意思？”马丁漫不经心地问。

“她一定爱上了你，”露丝说道，声音仍很温柔，“老实说，难道她不爱你吗？”

马丁的那张脸在洗衣店干活时脱去了太阳晒出的黑色，后来足不出户，且受到饥饿和疾病的折磨，甚至蒙上了一层苍白；这当儿，他苍白的脸上慢慢涌起了红潮。他张口欲言，却被露丝挡了回去。

“没关系，别回答了；没有这个必要。”她笑着说。

他觉得她的笑声有些生硬，眼睛里的闪光也冰冷冷的。刹那间，这让他想起了他在北太平洋经历过的一场大风。立时，大风的魔影浮现在他眼前——那场大风起于夜间，当时万里无云、满月当空，浩瀚的大海在月光下闪耀着冰冷冷的光。紧接着，他仿佛看到了麻风病人隐居地的那位姑娘，想起她正是由于爱他，才放了他一条生路。

“她是个崇高的女子，”他直率地说，“是她救了我的命。”

事情的全部经过就是这样。他听见露丝咽下了喉管里的一声啜泣，发现她转过脸去朝窗外眺望。待她把脸扭回来时，表情已恢复了平静，从她的眼睛里再也看不到大风的踪影。

“我这是在冒傻气，”她凄哀地说，“但我欲禁不能，因为我太爱你了。是的，我爱你，马丁。我早晚会变得宽宏大量的，可现在我还是不能不忌妒过去的那些鬼魂。你知道，你的过去被鬼魂所充斥。”

“情况肯定是这样，”她未容他反驳，继续说道，“不可能会是别的一种样子。唉，可怜的阿瑟在打手势唤我走呢，他等得不耐烦了。再见吧，亲爱的。”

“药剂师配制出一种药，有助于戒烟，”她走到门口回过身来说，“到时候我给你送一些来。”

房门合上了，但又被打开了。

“我爱你，我爱你。”她悄声冲着他低语；话一说完，她真的走了。

玛丽亚送她上马车，目光中充满了崇拜但也不失敏锐，注意到了她衣服的质地和款式（这种款式从未见过，所产生的效果具有神奇的美）。那群顽童失望地目送着马车从视野中消失，然后把目光转移到玛丽亚身上，她一下子变成了街上最了不起的人物。可是，她自己的一个孩子却对大伙儿说那两位高贵的客人是来找他们家房客的，这一下算毁掉了她的声望。玛丽亚又成了原先的那个默默无闻的人，而马丁却发现邻里的小孩子们开始以毕恭毕敬的态度对待他。至于玛丽亚，马丁在她眼里的身价足足提高了一倍。那个葡萄牙食品商要是目睹了这天下午客人乘马车来访的场景，准会允许马丁再赊三元八角五分钱的账。

[1]　Watch my smoke（瞧我的本事），按字面可被误解为“瞧我抽烟”。

[2]　莎剧《奥赛罗》中的女主人公，被奥赛罗讲述的英勇经历迷住，终于不顾种族的不同嫁给了他。

第二十七章

马丁幸运的太阳冉冉升起。露丝来访的第二天，他就收到了纽约一家杂谈周刊寄来的一张三块钱的支票，那是三首八行两韵诗的稿酬。两天之后，芝加哥发行的一家报纸采用了他的《宝藏探寻者》，答应刊载后付给他十块钱。稿酬是低了些，但那是他写的第一篇文章，是他打算在报刊上表述思想的第一次尝试。更令人高兴的是，这个星期还没过完，那篇写给孩子们的系列冒险故事——他的第二次尝试，便被一家自称为《青春与时代》的少年月刊所采用。不错，这篇系列故事共两万一千字，他们愿刊出后付给他十六块钱，一千字约合七角五分钱；但同样真实的是，那是他试笔时写出的第二篇作品，他自己也十分清楚，文章的笔法生硬、缺乏价值。

不过，就连他早期的作品，也没有留下平庸之作的那种粗制滥造的痕迹。他的笔调之所以生硬，完全是出于用力过猛的缘故——这是初学者的通病，就好像用攻城槌拍蝴蝶或者用大头棒绘制图案一样。所以，马丁低价卖出早期作品，心里却也高兴。他知道它们是怎样的文章，这是他完稿后不久便明白了的事情。他把希望都寄托在了以后的作品上。他力争当一名真正的作家，而不仅仅局限于为杂志撰写故事。写作时，他努力使用艺术性的表现手法。另一方面，他并未置力量于不顾，心中树立的目标是在不滥于力量的情况下增强作品的力度。同时，他也没有放弃对现实生活的热爱。虽然他竭力在作品中融入幻想出的奇观美景，但他写出的文章仍属于现实主义的范畴。他追求的是热情奔放的现实主义，贯穿着人类的愿望和信念。他想反映的是生活的本来面貌，同时又不乏精神的探索及心灵的刻画。

在看书的过程中，他发现小说作家中有两个流派。一派把人看作神，无视其凡俗的根源；另一派则把人看作一具血肉之躯，无视其天赋的梦想和神圣的愿望。在马丁看来，天神派和血肉之躯派都是错误的，错就错在他们的观点和目的都过于单调。折中的观点更接近于事实，但这会刺痛天神派，而且对血肉之躯派粗暴野蛮的理论也是一种挑战。马丁认为他的那篇叫露丝感到腻烦的短篇小说《冒险》，采用的就是既理想化又现实的写作手法；他把自己对整个问题的看法都写在了论文《天神与血肉之躯》里。

可是，《冒险》以及所有他自以为最优秀的作品仍在编辑之间转圈子，无人予以理睬。在他的眼里，他的早期作品除了能挣点稿酬，一无价值可言。他觉得，那些恐怖故事（其中的两篇已卖掉）既不是高尚的作品也不是最优秀的作品。坦白地说，它们是凭空想象出的荒诞曲，但里面也带有逼真描写的魅力，而这正是其力量所在。把真实性赋予离奇古怪、绝不可能发生的事情，他觉得是一种技巧——但充其量只是一种娴熟的技巧。这样的土壤当中是生长不出伟大文学的。它们的艺术性固然不低，可他觉得，脱离了人性的艺术性是没有价值的。所谓技巧就是在艺术性的脸上套一个人性的面具，而他在未攀上《冒险》、《欢乐》、《罐子》和《生活的美酒》创作高峰之前，就是用这种方法写了六七篇恐怖故事。

他用八行两韵诗挣来的三块钱稿酬维持朝不保夕的日子，等着《白鼠》寄支票来。他把第一张支票跟狐疑满腹的葡萄牙食品商兑换成现金，一块钱给了他还账，余下的两块钱分别给了面包铺和水果店。马丁钱囊羞涩，吃不起肉食，待《白鼠》把支票寄来时，他的日子已非常拮据。他首鼠两端，不知该怎样兑换支票。他这一辈子都没进过银行，更别说到那儿办事了。他产生了一种天真幼稚的欲望，直想走入奥克兰的一家大银行，把签过字的四十块钱支票甩给银行职员。可是，一种比较实际的思想占了上风，催促他去跟食品商兑钱，以此给对方留下深刻印象，将来好继续赊账。马丁不情愿地满足了食品商的要求，把他的账一次还清，然后接过余下的钱，装了一口袋叮当响的硬币。另外，他还清还了别的店铺的欠款，赎回衣服及自行车，付了一个月的打字机租赁费，给了玛丽亚一个月的房钱，又预交了一个月。口袋里仍剩下约三块钱，以备不时之需。

这一点钱像是一笔大款。赎回衣服后，他立刻就去看望露丝，一路上忍不住把口袋里的这一小把银币弄得叮当作响。长期以来，他一直与金钱无缘。而今，就像受到周济的饿鬼非得把吃不了的东西放在眼皮底下一样，他的手怎么也离不开那些银币。他既不吝啬也不贪婪，但这笔钱并不仅仅意味着几枚大洋和几个硬币。它们代表着成功，而币面上印的雄鹰在他看来则是一尊尊胜利女神塑像。

他下意识地觉得周围的世界真美好，而他所看到的世界似乎更美丽非凡。在长达数星期的时间里，这个世界密布愁云惨雾，一切都是那般乏味无聊；可现在，所有的债务几乎全部还清，三块钱的银币在口袋里叮当作响，心里怀着成功的感觉，于是他觉得阳光灿烂、暖意洋洋；就是天降大雨，把毫无准备的路人浇成落汤鸡，他也会觉得好玩。饿肚子的时候，他常常想到天下成千上万的饥民；现在吃饱了肚子，他就再也不去想仍有千万人在挨饿。他忘掉了饥民，但由于自己在恋爱，他却想起了天下数也数不清的情侣。未经着意思考，情诗的主题便在他心里翻江倒海。他被创作的冲动弄得出了神，电车开过了他要去的那个路口两个街区才发觉，但下车时心里一点也不窝火。

他发现摩斯家高朋满座。露丝的两个表姐妹从圣拉斐尔赶来看望她，而摩斯夫人以招待她们作幌子，却在实施自己的计划要在露丝周围聚集起一些年轻人。马丁因病不能前来时，这场战役便打响了，现在已空前激烈。她有意识请一些富于进取心的男子来家里。这样，除了多罗茜和弗洛伦丝表姐妹以外，马丁还遇到了两位大学教授（一位教拉丁语，另一位教国语）、一位刚从菲律宾归国的青年军官（此人曾是露丝的同窗）和一个名叫麦尔维尔的小伙子（此人是旧金山信托公司负责人约瑟夫·珀金斯的私人秘书）；男客中还有一个精力充沛的银行高级职员，他叫查尔斯·哈普哥德，三十五岁，看上去很年轻，毕业于斯坦福大学，是尼罗俱乐部和统一俱乐部的成员，还是共和党保守派参加竞选时的发言人——总之，他是个在各方面都有发展前途的年轻人。女客中有一位肖像画家、一位职业音乐家，还有一个得过社会学博士学位，因在旧金山贫民窟干社会救济工作成了当地的名人。女客在摩斯夫人的计划中无足轻重，顶多是些不可缺少的陪衬，因为总得想办法把有作为的男子吸引到家里来呀。

“讲话时不要激动。”在令人担心的介绍开始之前，露丝告诫马丁说。

起初，他举止有些呆板，总觉得自己笨手笨脚，尤其是那副肩膀老毛病又犯，随时都可能碰坏人家的家具和摆设。和周围的人相比，他自惭形秽。他从未接触过如此高贵的客人，更不用说这么多啦。他被那位叫哈普哥德的银行高级职员所深深地吸引，决心一有机会就把他研究研究。马丁的敬畏心理之下潜藏着强烈的自我意识，他急切地想把自己跟这群男女比个山高水低，看看他们到底从书本和生活中学到了哪些自己尚未掌握的知识。

露丝的目光时不时溜过来，看他的言谈举止是否得体。她见他和她的表姐妹交谈时显得洒脱自如，不由觉得意外，也感到高兴。他的确没有露出激动的神色，因为他坐下身子，不必再为自己的肩膀担惊受怕。露丝知道自己的表姐妹是聪明的姑娘，外表看起来才华横溢，但夜里睡觉时她们夸奖马丁的一番话却叫她简直听不明白。从另一方面来说，马丁是个独具一格的才子，在舞会上和星期日野餐时妙语连珠、诙谐幽默，所以觉得在这种场合开开玩笑以及跟别人善意地争执几句，是再简单不过的事情了。何况成功之神今晚就站在他身后，拍着他的肩膀夸他成绩斐然，于是他尽可以捧腹大笑，也逗得别人发笑，一副潇洒坦然的样子。

后来经证明，露丝的担忧是有道理的。但见马丁和考德威尔教授聚在一个惹人注目的角落，马丁虽然不再指手画脚，可在挑剔的露丝看来，他眼中频频射出逼人的光芒，说话太急促、太热烈，表情太急切，热血冲上来把他的脸弄得似鸡冠子样红。他不懂礼节、缺乏自制，与那位跟他在一起谈话的年轻国语教授形成极大反差。

可是，马丁对表面的东西一点也不关心！他立刻注意到对方的大脑训练有素，而且非常欣赏对方渊博的知识。考德威尔教授却全然不知，马丁对一般的国语教授是有看法的。马丁想让他谈谈自己的行当，他起初有些不愿意，但最后还是顺从了马丁的意愿。

“要是不愿谈自己的事业，那才既荒唐又不合理呢。”几星期前他曾对露丝这样说，“男男女女聚到一起，如果不是为了交流各人心中最美好的东西，那又是为了什么呢？人们心中最美好的东西就是他们的兴趣所在、谋生之道和专业特长，他们为之日夜奋斗，甚至魂牵梦绕。试想一下，倘若勃特勒先生为了社交礼节，针对保罗·魏尔伦[1]、德国戏剧或者邓南遮[2]的小说发表一通议论，那还不让人腻味死。拿我来说，如果非得听勃特勒先生讲话，我倒情愿听他谈法律，因为那是他最得意的事业。人生如此短暂，我所遇到的人，不论男女，我都想了解他们的长处。”

“但有些话题是所有的人都感兴趣的。”露丝不同意地说。

“这话就错了。”他忙抢着说，“社会上所有的人、社会上所有的集团——或更确切地说，几乎所有的人和集团——都模仿比自己高明的人。那么，谁是最佳的模仿对象呢？是那班闲人，那班有钱的闲人。一般来说，这个世界上脚踏实地干事的人所掌握的知识，他们是不具备的。听别人谈论这类知识，那班闲人会觉得厌烦，所以他们宣布这类知识是行话，不能当众议论。他们提倡谈非专业的话题，那就是新近上演的歌剧、新近出版的小说、牌局、弹子游戏、鸡尾酒、汽车、赛马会、钓鳟鱼、钓金枪鱼、猎兽和驾游艇等——注意，这些全是那班闲人熟悉的事情。其实，这些构成了闲人们的行话。滑稽透顶的是，许多聪明人以及所有自以为聪明的人，竟听凭闲人这样哄骗自己。而我想了解的是一个人内心最出色的东西，随你称其为庸俗的行话也罢或冠以别的名称也罢。”

露丝听不懂他的话，觉得他对正统思想的攻击只不过是些偏执的看法。

此时的马丁以自己的热情感化了考德威尔教授，鼓励他说出了心中的思想。露丝在他们身旁停住脚步时，听马丁说道：

“你肯定不会在加利福尼亚大学发表这种异端邪说吧？”

考德威尔教授耸了耸肩膀。“你知道，这是老实的纳税人与政治家之间的问题。萨克拉门托[3]给我们拨款，我们就得对萨克拉门托奴颜婢膝，对大学评议委员会奴颜婢膝，对执政党的党报或两党的党报奴颜婢膝。”

“是的，这很清楚；但你自己呢？”马丁紧追不舍地问，“你一定觉得不适应吧？”

“我觉得自己和大学里别的人不一样。有时我深切地感到自己不适应，认为我应该属于巴黎、雇佣文人街、隐士的山洞，或者混迹于狂放的艺人中，饱饮红葡萄酒——旧金山人称其为‘劣等红酒’——，就餐于拉丁区[4]的廉价饭馆，大嚷大叫地对所有的问题发表一通偏激的言论。真的，我常常怀着八九分的把握肯定自己生就是个激进分子。可是，有许多问题我都吃不准。一旦直接涉及自己脆弱的人性，我就变成了胆小鬼，这就使我无法了解人类重大问题的全部要素。”

在他侃侃而谈时，马丁觉得自己直想唱《贸易风之歌》：

中午我的势头最猛，

而明月升空时，

我把船帆紧绷。

他差点没把这几句词哼出口。他醒悟到，正是对方让他想起了贸易风，想起了从容、凉爽和强劲的东北贸易风。考德威尔教授矜持稳重，可以信赖，但他身上却有种让人猜不透的东西。马丁觉得他始终未尽抒胸臆，就像他觉得贸易风从不尽全力去吹，总是保留一些力量不加使用一样。他的幻觉又开始活跃起来。他的大脑犹如极易进去的库房，贮藏着记忆中的事实和幻景，这些货物排列得井然有序等待他查阅。不管当前的这一刻发生什么样的事情，他的大脑会立即推出与之相对照或类似的史料，而这些史料通常以幻景的形式出现。这完全是无意识的行为，他的幻想和活生生的现实默契配合。他看到露丝的那副一时充满了醋意的面孔，眼前便闪现出已经淡忘的月下大风，而考德威尔教授却使他想起了在紫色的海面上激起了千层白浪的东北贸易风。记忆中的幻景一幕幕不时浮现在眼前、铺展在眼皮底下或投射在意识的屏幕上，这非但不会给他带来困惑，还会对事物起到鉴别和分类的作用。这些幻象产生于过去的活动和感觉，产生于昨天及上个星期干过的事情、经历的事件和看过的书刊——它们犹若数不清的幽灵，不管他醒着还是在睡梦中，总是萦纡他的脑际。

所以，马丁一边倾听考德威尔教授那从容不迫的谈吐——一个聪明文化人的谈吐，一边回顾自己的往事。他看到了自己当恶棍时的情景：头戴“硬边”斯坦逊[5]帽，身穿裁剪得有棱有角、双排扣的外套，晃动着肩膀，胸怀远大抱负，决心要在警察容忍的范围内为非作歹。他内心并不想掩饰这一事实，也不想加以辩解。曾经一度，他仅仅是个粗俗的恶棍，率领着一班打手，令警方大伤脑筋，叫老实巴交的工人阶级家庭谈虎色变。可后来他的抱负发生了变化。他望望四周，看到的是一群教养良好、衣着得体的男女，吸入肺里的是高雅的文化气息，同时，他还看到了自己青少年时期的幻影，头戴硬边帽、身穿有棱角的衣服，粗暴野蛮、神气活现，大摇大摆地在屋里走动。接着，他看到这个街头恶棍的幻影与现实的自己合为一体，跟一位真实贴切的大学教授坐在一起交谈。

以前，他一直未找到永久的安身之地。不管到哪里他都如鱼得水，无论是干活还是娱乐都毫不含糊，而且愿意并有能力为自己的权益和尊严奋争，颇受大伙儿的拥戴，但他毕竟是无根的浮萍。他的随遇而安叫伙伴们称心如意，而他自己却并不满意。他心里总是感到不安宁，总是听到远方传来召唤声，于是他在生活中游历和寻求，直至找到书籍、艺术和爱情。如今，他来到了这样的一个氛围之中。他和同伙共同历险，但唯他一个有资格踏入摩斯家的大门。

这种种念头、幕幕幻景并未使他分心，妨碍他聆听考德威尔教授的话语。他以挑剔的眼光分析理解，但却发现对方的知识园地完整无缺。在谈话中，他不时发现自己漏洞百出，有些话题他一点都不熟悉。不过，幸亏看过斯宾塞的著作，他知道自己已掌握了知识园地的轮廓。只要给他时间，他定能把内容填进这些轮廓。他心想：等着瞧吧，你们这些人，看我一鸣惊人！他真想拜倒在这位教授的脚下，充满敬仰之情地聆听他的教诲；可是，他听着听着，发现对方的观点中出现了薄弱环节——那薄弱环节若隐若现、难以捕捉，若非它始终存在，恐怕他还发现不了呢。一旦有了这个发现，他立刻觉得自己能和对方平起平坐。

露丝第一次踱步到他们跟前时，正赶上马丁开始发表言论。

“让我来指出你错在哪里吧，或者，让我来指出你的观点有哪些薄弱环节吧，”他说，“你缺少的是生物学知识。在你对事物的分析中，没有一处用到这种知识。——噢，我指的是能解释一切的实实在在的生物学。这种知识起自实验室、试管以及获得生命的无机物，可以推广到美学和社会学最广泛的概念。”

露丝闻罢大惊失色。她修过考德威尔教授的两门讲座课，一直视他为一切知识的活宝库。

“你的话真让我有点听不懂。”教授迟疑地说。

马丁却十分肯定对方听懂了他的意思。

“那我就解释解释。”他说，“记得在读埃及史书时，我看到这样一句话：不先研究土地问题，就理解不了埃及的艺术。”

“一点不错。”教授点头说。

“我觉得，”马丁继续说道，“如果不先了解生命的元素和构造，就无从研究土地问题及其他任何问题。倘若既不了解人的本性，又不懂构成人体的元素本质，我们怎么能理解人所创造的法律、制度、宗教和风俗呢？难道文学的人性比埃及建筑和雕塑的人性还弱吗？在已知的宇宙中，难道有哪样事物不遵守进化法则吗？——啊，我知道你对诸多艺术的阐述详尽明了，可我觉得太呆板了些。人本身被忽略掉了。工具、竖琴、音乐、歌曲以及舞蹈的演变史全被解释得头头是道；然而，人类本身的进化是怎么一回事呢？在制造出第一件工具或含糊不清地唱出第一首歌之前，人体内部的基本因素是怎样进化的呢？这种你没有考虑到的东西，就是我所说的生物学——一种极为广义的生物学。”

“我知道自己的话缺乏连贯性，但我已经尽到了努力。你刚才说话时我才考虑到这一点，所以想法不成熟，难免欠周到。你说脆弱的人性有碍于一个人面面俱到地考虑问题。此处你忽略了生物学的因素——或者在我看来如此，而正是这种因素构成了一切艺术的基础以及人类一切活动、成就的经纬。”

露丝感到惊讶的是，马丁没有即刻被驳倒，她觉得教授说话的口气有些像容忍马丁的年少无知。考德威尔教授一言不语地足足坐了有一分钟，手里摆弄着表链。

“你可知道，”他最后终于说道，“以前有个非常伟大的人也这样批评过我——他叫约瑟夫·勒·康特，是位科学家和进化论者。可他去世了，我以为再没有人会发现我的弱点了，谁知今天又被你戳穿。说实话，我承认你的论点是有道理的——其实是大有道理。我太古板，在解释性学科跟不上时代，我只能把这归咎于自己所受教育的欠缺以及懒动脑筋的性格。我从没进过物理实验室或化学实验室，不知你信不信？但这都是事实。勒·康特的批评是对的，你也是对的，至少在一定程度上——具体对到何种程度我就说不上来了。”

露丝寻了个借口将马丁拉到一旁，低声对他说：

“你不该这样缠着考德威尔教授，谈不定别人也想和他谈谈呢。”“这是我的错，”马丁悔悟地承认说，“不过，我激起了他的兴致，他谈的问题那样有趣，使我都忘乎所以了。知道吗，和我交谈过的人，数他最聪明、最有才华。另外还有一点我要告诉你：以前我总觉得凡是上过大学的人，或者社会地位高的人，个个都似他一般才华横溢、聪颖明智呢。”

“他是个与众不同的人物。”她说。

“我也这样认为。现在想让我跟谁交谈？——啊，这样吧，带我去见见那位银行高级职员。”

马丁跟那位职员谈了十五分钟的话，言谈举止无可挑剔，令露丝对自己的恋人十分满意。他的眼睛一次也没闪射逼人的光，脸颊一次也没涨红过，那坦然的话语和平稳的语调使她颇感意外。然而在马丁的眼里，银行职员阶层的身价却一落千丈，在这天晚上后来的时间里，他不断在思索一个问题：银行职员只会讲味如嚼蜡的陈词滥调。他发现那位军官既和气又单纯，是个身强力壮、精神饱满的小伙子，满足于出身和运气给自己带来的社会地位。一听说他上过两年大学，马丁觉得惊奇，不知他把学来的知识藏到了哪里。可是与那个满口陈腐话的银行高级职员相比，马丁还是更喜欢他。

“其实我对说陈腐话并没有恶感。”他后来跟露丝说，“不过，他讲话时那种夸夸其谈、扬扬得意、盛气凌人和自以为是的样子让我感到气恼，更何况他把时间拖得那么长。用他跟我讲劳工党与民主党合并之事的那些时间，我可以把‘宗教改革’[6]史从头至尾叙述一遍。要知道，他玩的是字眼游戏，就像职业牌手在发给他的牌上做文章一样。等哪天有时间我再解释给你听。”

“很遗憾，你不喜欢他，”她答道，“他可是勃特勒先生得意的人。勃特勒先生说他诚实可靠，称他为‘磐石彼得’[7]，还说他无论到哪家银行机构都是栋梁之材。”

“我见到他的时间不长，听他谈话的时间更短，可我不怀疑你的话；不过，我不似以前那样关心银行的事啦。我这样直抒己见，你不会见怪吧，亲爱的？”

“不，我不见怪；你的话很有意思。”

“那好，”马丁激动地朝下说道，“我不过是个野蛮人，刚刚对文明产生一些印象。文明人一定会觉得这种印象既新奇又有趣。”

“你觉得我的表姐和表妹怎么样？”露丝问。

“跟别的女客相比，我还是喜欢她们，因为她们都很风趣，一点也不做作。”

“那你是怎么看待别的女客呢？”

他摇了摇头。

“那个从事社会救济工作的女人只不过是只精通社会学的学舌鹦鹉。我敢说，如果把她像汤姆林逊[8]一样放到星空里让风吹吹，她的脑子里找不到一丁点独特的见解。那位肖像女画家则让人觉得乏味透顶，给那个高级银行职员当夫人倒是挺合适。啧，还有那位女音乐家哩！我可不管她手指有多么灵巧，技巧有多么娴熟，表情有多么动人——事实在于，她对音乐一无所知。”

“她的钢琴弹得很好听。”露丝反驳说。

“不错，从表面上看，她确实是位音乐家，然而，对于音乐的内在精神她却理解不透。我曾问起音乐对她意味着什么——你知道我总是爱提这类问题；她竟然不清楚音乐对她意味着什么，只知道自己崇拜音乐，说音乐是一门最伟大的艺术，比生命还重要。”

“你这是逼她们谈自己的本行。”露丝谴责道。

“这我承认。如果她们连自己的本行都谈不好，再让她们对别的问题发表看法，可想而知那会多么大煞风景。过去我以为这里是社会的上层，具有得天独厚的文化氛围——”他停顿了一会儿，仿佛看到自己青少年时期的身影，头戴硬边帽，身穿有棱有角的衣服，大摇大摆在屋里走动。“我是说，我原以为这儿的男女人人聪明、个个博学。可现在根据我所了解到的一点情况，我觉得他们多半是笨蛋，剩下的也十之有九叫人感到乏味。不过，考德威尔教授是个例外。他不愧为一个男子汉，身上的每一根神经以及大脑里的每个元素都与众不同。”露丝不由喜形于色。

“跟我讲讲他的情况，”她催促道，“不要讲他伟大和杰出的一面，因为那些品质我都了解；只讲你认为不好的一面，这是我极想知道的。”“我要讲了，也许会遭到非议，”马丁幽默地说了一句，“还是你先说吧。不过，也许你认为他是个完美无瑕的人呢。”

“我修过他的两门讲座课，认识他有两年之久了，所以我很想听听你对他的第一印象。”

“你指的是坏印象？那么，我就讲给你听听。我想，你所说的那些优良品质他全具有。最起码，他是我认识的知识分子中的杰出榜样，但他的内心也隐藏着愧疚。”

“啊，不，不！”他急忙解释道，“那种愧疚可不是什么低级庸俗的事。我是说，我觉得他看透了事物的真相，而且为自己的所见所闻感到害怕，于是便假装什么也没看到。这样解释也许不够清楚，还是再换种说法吧。他寻找到了通达神秘殿堂的道路，可是却没有顺着那条道路朝前走；他也许已经看到了那座殿堂，却一个劲欺瞒自己，把那当作树叶构织的幻景。还有一种说法：他完全能够干出一番事业，却不加以重视，但内心深处又无时无刻不在为自己的消极惋惜；他暗暗嘲笑摆在面前的酬劳，但内心却对这份酬劳垂涎三尺，渴望享受成功的喜悦。”

“我看不出他有这种迹象。”她说，“其实，我不明白你的意思。”

“这只是我的一种朦胧的感觉，”马丁妥协地说，“我拿不出根据来，只是有这么一种感觉，很可能是错的。当然，你比我更了解他。”

这天晚上离开露丝家时，马丁莫名其妙地产生了一种迷惘和矛盾的心理。他对自己的目标感到失望，对自己孜孜以求想成为其中一员的人们感到失望。但另一方面，他又为自己的成就深受鼓舞。这场奋斗比他想象的容易，对他算不了什么（他不想以虚假的谦虚向自己隐瞒这个点），他比自己所跻身的那个圈子里的人都强——此处当然不包括考德威尔教授。无论是生活还是书本知识，他都比他们了解得多，真不知那些人把自己学的东西扔到了哪些旮旯犄角。他不知道自己具有非同寻常的智力，也不知道那种致力于探索深奥的秘密、寻求崇高理想的人，在摩斯之流的客厅里是根本找不到的；他意识不到，这种人像孤独的雄鹰一样，远离大地和大地上的芸芸众生，高高地独自展翅于蓝色天空。

[1]　19世纪法国象征派诗人。

[2]　19世纪末20世纪初的意大利小说家兼诗人。

[3]　加利福尼亚州府所在地，此处指州当局。

[4]　巴黎文人聚集地。

[5]　美国帽业大公司。

[6]　16世纪初，由马丁·路德发起，公开反对罗马天主教，并产生了新教。

[7]　圣经中的人物，十二使徒之一。耶稣称他为“磐石”，意思是可信赖的人。

[8]　吉卜林诗作《汤姆林逊》的主人公，死后魔鬼把他放到星空让风吹，看他有没有自己的灵魂。

第二十八章

然而，成功女神忘掉了马丁的存在，她的使者不再光顾他的住所。整整二十五天来，他不分节假日辛勤耕耘，撰写了一篇约三万字的论文《太阳的耻辱》。这篇文章意在抨击梅特林克[1]派的神秘主义，以科学为明确的依据对奇迹梦想家进行发难，不过，文章中仍保留了许多与确定的事实相符的美和奇迹。继这次攻击后不久，他又写了《奇迹梦想家》和《自我衡量的尺度》两篇短文。他花钱买来邮票，让这一长两短的论文开始在杂志社之间游历。

在撰写《太阳的耻辱》那二十五天里，他卖掉了一些廉价文章，计得六块半钱。一则笑话卖了五角钱，另一则卖给一家高层次的喜剧周刊，获得一块钱的稿酬。还有两首幽默诗分别卖得两块钱和三块钱。由于买东西不能再赊账（他欠食品商的钱已多达五块钱），他把自行车和那套衣服又送进了当铺。打字机租赁店也在催款，口气坚定地指出：根据协议必须提前交租赁费。

几篇小文章卖出去后，给马丁鼓了劲，于是他回过头来写廉价文章。也许，他得靠这类文章维持生活呢。他的桌下堆着二十篇短篇故事的手稿，那是被报业短篇故事辛迪加退回来的。他把稿子又看了一遍，想找出撰写报载短篇故事应该避免的问题，最后琢磨出了一条万全之策。他发现报载短篇故事绝不能是悲剧性的，不能带凄惨的结局，不能有美丽的文字、微妙的构思和真实而细腻的感情。感情是必须有的，而且愈丰富愈好，但那是纯洁和崇高的感情，是那种他青少年时期在剧院后楼厅为之喝彩的感情，是“为了上帝、祖国、皇帝”和“我人穷志不短”之类的感情。

掌握了这些注意事项后，马丁参照《公爵夫人》[2]寻找格调，并根据自己琢磨出的公式如法炮制。这套公式包括三个部分，（一）一对情侣被迫分离；（二）经过努力，或发生了意外事件，他们重新团圆；（三）两人结百年之好。第三个部分一成不变，而第一和第二部分则可以千变万化。由此说来，这对情侣的分离可能出自相互误解、命运的突然变化、吃醋的情敌插足、家长的愤怒干涉、保护人玩弄诡计、亲戚阴谋破坏，凡此种种；两人的团圆则可能是由于男方或女方做出了勇敢的举动，由于两个情侣当中的一人回心转意，由于狡猾的保护人、阴险的亲戚和忌妒的情敌被迫或主动说出了事情的真相，由于发现了什么意想不到的秘密，由于男方征服了姑娘的芳心，由于一位情侣长期做崇高的自我牺牲，或其他数也数不清的原因。在大团圆的过程当中，如让姑娘开口求婚，会增加故事的趣味性；除此之外，马丁点点滴滴地还想出了另外一些生动有趣的表现手法。但大结局时的婚礼钟声却是无论如何也不能更动的；即便天幕似轴画般卷起，即便群星陨落，婚礼的钟声照样得敲响。至于字数，这种公式规定每篇最少不能少于一千二百字，最多不能超过一千五百字。

短篇故事的写作技巧尚未达到炉火纯青的地步之前，马丁拟就了六七种固定的格式，构思情节的过程中时时参考。这种格式就好像数学家用的那种玄妙的表格，不管是从上下还是左右都可以填入内容，入口处有几十条横线和竖栏，不用推理和思考便能得出数千种形形色色、合情合理、无懈可击的结论。用这种格式，马丁半个小时就可以构思出十几篇故事的轮廓，然后放到一旁，待有空时填充内容。他发现，在奋笔写作了一天之后，临睡觉前还可以照着轮廓拟出一篇故事来。后来他向露丝透露说，他几乎在睡梦中都能够撰写故事。真正费事的是制定轮廓，但那也只不过是一种机械性的活儿。

对于这种格式将会带来的效益，他深信不疑。他总算了解了编辑们的心理，认为自己寄出去的头两篇文章一定能挣回支票来。

就在这段时期，他对杂志界又有了新的惊人发现。《横贯大陆月刊》虽然登载了他的《嘹亮的钟声》，但迟迟不见寄支票来。马丁需要钱花，于是便写信催稿酬，但收到的回信闪烁其词，只说还想请他再寄一些作品去。等这封回信，他饿了两天的肚子，最后只好又把自行车推进了当铺。他每星期两次，定期写信给《横贯大陆月刊》催要他的五块钱稿费，而对方却磨磨蹭蹭地隔一段时间才回一封信。他全然不知《横贯大陆月刊》早已步履维艰，多年来摇摇欲坠地支撑着，不知这是一家四流杂志或者十流杂志，连一点地位都没有，其经营方法十分古怪，一半靠卑鄙的坑骗，一半靠激发别人的爱国之心，上面登的广告纯粹是索取慈善捐款。他也不知道，《横贯大陆月刊》是编辑及营业经理唯一的生计，那些人全靠它维持生活，所以常常迁移赖掉房租，对欠款能不付就不付。他万万想不到本来属于他的那五块钱，已被营业经理盗用，油漆他在阿拉米达的住房。那位经理每个周日下午亲自动手油漆房间，因为他付不起工会规定的工钱，也因为他最初雇的那个拒不加入工会的匠人，被人抽走脚下的梯子，摔断了锁骨，被送进了医院。

马丁把《宝藏探寻者》卖给了芝加哥的一家报社，但十块钱的稿酬尚未拿到手。他在中央阅览室的报刊合订本里查到，那篇文章已经登出，但编辑那儿不见一点动静。他写信去，也无人理会。为了确保对方能收到，好几封信都是挂号寄去的。他觉得这简直是掠夺，是可耻的强盗行径。正当他忍饥挨饿的时候，那些人却盗去了他的商品、他的货物。要知道，他可是靠卖这些货物糊口的呀！

《青春与时代》是份周刊，把他那两万一千字的系列故事刚登出三分之二，便停刊了。这样一来，他就再也没指望拿到那十六块钱的稿酬了。

雪上加霜的是，被他视为最佳作品之一的《罐子》，也没有给他带来收益。当时他极其绝望，发了狂似的挑拣杂志社，最后把文章寄给了《浪涛》——旧金山的一份社交周刊。他把稿子送到那家杂志社，主要是因为从奥克兰到那儿只需跨越一道海峡，刊用与否很快便能见分晓。两星期之后，他欣喜万分地在书报摊上看到他的文章一字不漏地登在了最新一期《浪涛》上，位置显要，而且还附着插图。他回家时，心里嗵嗵乱跳，不知这样一篇最佳的作品会付给他多少稿酬。再说，文章这么快就被采用和刊出，想起来便让他高兴。可编辑没有通知他稿件已被采用，这倒是完全出乎他的意料。等了一个星期、两个星期，随后又等了半个星期，绝望的情绪战胜了踌躇的心理，于是他给《浪涛》的编辑写了封信，说很可能营业经理一时疏忽，忘了他的那一小笔稿酬。

马丁心想，那笔稿酬即便顶多只有五块钱，但用来买蚕豆和豌豆煮汤倒绰绰有余，肚中有了食，便可以再写出六七篇类似的文章或同样优秀的文章。

编辑回了封信，内容虽冷冰冰的，但起码赢得了马丁的敬佩。

信中写道：“足下惠赐大作，我们深为感激。我们编辑部全体同仁都欣赏备至，谅足下已看到，该稿已立刻登出，并居显要位置。衷心希望足下能喜欢该稿的插图。

“来信拜读再三，我们觉得你似有误会，以为我们对非特约稿件也付酬。按惯例并非如此，而足下来稿不是特约，实为遗憾。采用足下大作时，敝社以为足下已熟谙此情。对此不幸误解，我们深表遗憾，并顺致衷心的问候。再次感谢足下的赐稿，希望不久的将来还能得到惠赐，企候，云云——”

信的末尾有一段附言，大意是说《浪涛》虽无赠书先例，但他们很乐意明年向他提供赠书。

经过这次教训之后，马丁在所有稿件的头一页上端都打上这样的字样：“用稿请按常规付酬。”

他自我安慰地暗忖，总有一天，它们会按照我的常规付酬的。

在这段时间里，他发现自己的内心蕴藏着追求完美的热望，于是便在这种心情的驱动下对《拥挤的街道》、《生活的美酒》、《欢乐》、《海洋抒情诗》，及其他早期作品，进行了改写和润色；像过去一样，每天耕耘十九个小时他还嫌不够。他拼命地写作，大量地读书。忙忙碌碌地竟然忘掉了戒烟所带来的痛苦。露丝遵守自己的诺言，给他送来了贴着华丽标签的戒烟药，而他却把戒烟药藏到了橱柜最隐秘的角落里。尤其在饿肚子的时候，他不抽烟感到十分难受。他虽然屡屡战胜抽烟的欲望，但那种欲望始终存留在他心头，一直都是那么强烈。他把戒烟视为自己前所未有的伟大成就。露丝却把这看作应该做的事情。她用自己的零花钱给他买来了戒烟药，没过几天就把这事忘到了九霄云外。

对于那些以机械的笔调撰写的短篇故事，他既厌恶又瞧不起，可正是那些作品一炮打响。他用稿费把当掉的东西全赎了回来，清付了大部分欠款，还买了一副自行车新轮胎。起码来说，那些短篇故事使他吃上了饭，为他提供时间去实现自己的抱负。只有一件事在激励着他，那就是他曾经收到过《白鼠》寄来的四十块钱稿费。他对此抱有信念，认为真正的第一流杂志对一位不知名的作家即便不付丰厚的稿酬，也会付普通稿酬。问题在于，如何打进一流杂志？他的那些最优秀的故事、论文和诗歌一直受到一流杂志的冷遇，可每个月他一翻开那些杂志的封面，看到的尽是单调乏味、缺乏艺术性的文章。他有时心想，哪怕只有一位编辑放下高傲的架子给我写封信来，也会使我受到鼓舞！即便我的作品与众不同，出于谨慎的原因不适于登在他们的刊物上，但里面或多或少肯定有真知灼见，难道就得不到他们的赏识，激不起他们的热情吗！在这种念头的驱使下，马丁常常拿出一两部稿件来，如《冒险》等，一遍遍地阅读，徒劳无益地想找出编辑们保持沉默的缘由。

随着加利福尼亚明媚春日的到来，他的富足日子过到了头。报业短篇故事辛迪加方面已有几个星期不见音讯了，这种奇怪的现象叫他不胜担忧。但有一天，邮递员却把他的十篇无懈可击以机械的笔调撰写的短篇故事退了回来。退稿里附着一封短信，说辛迪加积压的稿件太多，要过几个月后才公开征稿。马丁把希望寄托在这十篇短篇故事上，甚至过的是无节制的生活。前不久，报业辛迪加对他的稿子投一篇登一篇，每篇付五块钱的稿费。所以，他全当这十篇稿件已被采用，全当银行里存着五十块钱，以相应的标准安排生活。而现在却猝然进入了一个拮据的时期，他只好源源不断地把早期的作品投给那些不肯付酬的刊物，把后期的文章寄给不愿采用的杂志。同时，他又和奥克兰的当铺打上了交道。纽约的几家周刊买下了他的几则笑话和几首幽默诗，这才使他得以勉强维持生计。这时，他给一些大型月刊和评论季刊写了询问信，从回信中得知他们很少采用非特约的稿件，他们的大部分文章都是向在各个领域享有权威的著名专家约稿。

[1]　19世纪末、20世纪初的比利时诗人兼作家，象征主义者，代表作是童话剧《青鸟》。

[2]　19世纪爱尔兰女作家亨格福德的著名爱情小说。

第二十九章

对马丁来说，这是一个艰难的夏季。审稿人和编辑们纷纷出外度假，所以平时不出三个星期便可见回音的刊物，现在把他的稿子一压就是三个月，或更长时间。唯一能使他聊以自慰的是，遇到这种局面倒省了他的邮票钱。只有强盗式的刊物似乎依然十分活跃。马丁把自己早期的作品，如《潜水采珠记》、《水手生涯》、《捉海龟记》以及《东北贸易风》，全都寄给了它们。这些稿件送出去，他没得到一分钱的稿酬。实际情况是这样：经过六个月的通信联络，他和对方找出了个折中的办法，用《捉海龟记》换了把安全性剃刀；《卫城》杂志采用了《东北贸易风》，答应给他五块钱的现金和为期五年的赠书，结果只履行了协议的第二部分。

用一首史蒂文森[1]风格的十四行诗，他总算从波士顿的一位编辑的手中争取到了两块钱，那人以马修·阿诺德[2]的观点经营着一家杂志，平时爱钱如命。《仙女与珍珠》是一首两百行的绝妙讽刺诗，刚从他的大脑中移上纸页，赢得了为一家铁路大公司刊行的旧金山杂志编辑的青睐。那位编辑写信提出想以免费车票充为稿酬，马丁回信问车票是否可以转让。结果，车票是不能够转卖他人的，于是，马丁要求对方退还诗稿。退稿中附着那位编辑表示遗憾的一封信，马丁把稿子拿到手，又寄到了旧金山去，这次寄给了《大黄蜂》——一家自命不凡的月刊杂志，创办人是位杰出的报界人士，曾把它捧上了第一流的高度，但早在马丁出生之前，《大黄蜂》的光辉就开始趋于黯淡了。编辑答应付给马丁十五块钱的稿费，但待到诗稿一登出来，他似乎把自己的许诺给忘了。马丁去了几封信都不予理睬，最后写了一封怒气冲冲的信，才算有了回音。回信是一个新来的编辑写的，他冷冰冰地向马丁宣称他对前任编辑的错误概不负责，还说《仙女与珍珠》在他看来没有多大价值。

按说，对马丁最为残酷的要算芝加哥的《环球》杂志。原先，他并不想公开自己的《海洋抒情诗》，后来为饥饿所迫才拿出来发表。诗稿遭到了十几家杂志社的退稿，最终在《环球》编辑部找到了归宿。这组诗共有三十首小诗，每首将付给他一块钱的稿酬。头一个月共刊登了四首，他收到了四块钱面额的支票。但当他欣赏杂志时，一幅“大屠杀”的场面使他感到触目惊心。有几首诗的题目被改头换面，如：《终》被改成了《结束》，而《外礁之歌》则改成了《珊瑚礁之歌》。一首诗的题目做了彻底更改，换成了一个不恰当的题目。他原来的《美杜莎的眼睛[3]》，被编辑印成了《倒退的道路》。但诗稿内容的“屠杀”，更叫人毛骨悚然。马丁唉声叹气，冷汗直冒，拿手用力搔着头皮。一个个短语和整行、整段的诗句被删掉、调换或窜改，不知搞的是什么名堂。有些诗行和诗段被偷梁换柱，代以他人之笔。马丁不相信一个心智健全的编辑会行此暴虐之事，于是便推测一定是编辑部的勤杂工或速记员对他的诗稿做了手术。他立即写信要求编辑停止发表他的抒情诗，把诗稿退还给他。他的信写了一封又一封，又是央求又是威胁，但对方理也不理。“大屠杀”一月月地持续着，直至三十首诗全部载完；而每当他的诗出现在杂志上，他就可以收到支票，月月如此。

尽管发生了种种不幸，他对《白鼠》的那张四十块钱的支票仍记忆犹新，于是继续耕耘，不过由于生活所迫，只好把愈来愈多的精力投放到撰写卖钱的文章上。他发现为农业周刊及行业杂志撰稿可以维持生计，但与宗教周刊打交道则只有饿肚子的份儿。他处境极为悲惨，把黑色西装又送进了当铺，可就在这时，他在共和党县委会举办的一次有奖竞赛中大获全胜——或者在他看来是这样的。竞赛共分三个项目，他全都参加了，同时心里却在苦涩地嘲笑自己为生活所迫竟沦落到了这步田地。他的诗赢得了一等奖十块钱，竞选歌赢得了二等奖五块钱，而关于共和党党纲的论文赢得了一等奖二十五块钱。他对此感到非常高兴，这种心情一直持续到该领奖金的时候。虽然县委委员里有一位腰缠万贯的银行家和一位州议员，但那里却出了问题，迟迟不见把奖金寄来。正当这件事悬而未决的时候，马丁又参加了民主党举办的一次类似的竞赛，他的论文获得了一等奖，这证明他对民主党的党纲也了如指掌。这次的二十五块钱奖金他拿到了手，可上次的四十块钱奖金却始终没有着落。

他绞尽脑汁地想见到露丝，可又觉得从北奥克兰到她家路程太远，走路太费时间，于是便把一套黑西装送入当铺，换回了自行车。有了自行车，既可以锻炼身体，又可以省下时间写作，同时还不误去看望露丝。一条齐膝盖的粗布短裤和一件旧运动衫，骑自行车穿满像样，有了这身打扮他就可以和露丝一道在下午出外兜风了。再说，他不能再频频到她家跟她见面了，因为摩斯夫人正在全力推行自己的计划，招待四方来客。他在那儿遇到的高贵人物，不久前还为他所敬仰，而今却使他厌恶。在他眼里，他们不再高贵了。一听到这些人的谈话，他就恼火和生气，这全是因为他生活艰难、情绪低落和工作紧张所导致的。他的这种自以为是并不是没有理由的。他曾拿书中看到的思想深邃的人跟这些心胸狭窄的人做过比较。在露丝家，除了考德威尔教授以外，他从未遇到过一个思想博大精深的人，只可惜他仅和考德威尔见过一面。至于其余的那些人，全是些肤浅、顽固、无知的笨蛋和愚材。他们的无知使他感到震惊。他们到底出了什么事？学的东西丢到哪里去了呢？他们和他读的是相同的书，可他们怎么会一无所获呢？他知道，胸怀坦荡、明智达观的伟大思想家确有其人。从书本中便可以得到证实，因为正是靠着那些书的启迪，他才超越了摩斯之流。他还知道，比摩斯家圈子里的那些人高雅的人士天下有的是。在描写英国上流社会的小说中，他读到过男男女女在一起谈论政治和哲学的片段。他在书中还读到了有关大城市沙龙的情况，这种沙龙甚至在美国也有，是艺术和知识交汇的地方。过去他真蠢，竟然以为凡是高居工人阶级之上的那些衣冠楚楚的人全都聪明过人，全都懂得美。他把文化与社会地位混为一谈，幼稚地认为只要受过高等教育就等于掌握了知识。

他要继续奋斗，一步一步朝高处攀登。他要带着露丝一道前进。他深深地爱着她，坚信她不管到哪里都会发出夺目的光彩。他清楚，早年的生活环境羁绊了他的手脚，而现在他观察到她也遇到了类似的障碍。她一直都没有发展的机会。她父亲书架上的书、墙上的油画，以及钢琴上的乐谱，只不过都是些虚华的摆设。对于真正的文学、真正的绘画和真正的音乐，摩斯一家以及他们的同类简直一窍不通。而对于比这些东西更为伟大的生活，他们无知到了不可救药的地步。他们虽然赞成唯一神教，戴着沉稳和思想开明的假面具，但实际上已落后于解释万物的科学有两个时代。他们的思维是中世纪式的，他觉得他们看待生活的基本事实以及整个宇宙，用的是形而上学的观点。这种观点形成的历史，近可以追溯到最年轻一个种族的诞生，远可以追溯到洞穴人时代。它使更新世的第一个猿人害怕黑暗，使希伯来的第一个野人迫不及待地用亚当的肋骨塑造了夏娃，使笛卡儿[4]从渺小的自我出发，设想出唯心论的宇宙体系，使那位著名的教士[5]用讽刺的言论攻击进化论，虽一时赢得了喝彩，但在历史上却留下了万古骂名。

马丁思来想去，最后终于如醍醐灌顶，明白了过来。他认识到，他见到的这些律师、军官、商人以及银行高级职员，跟他所熟知的工人阶级成员之间的差别在于，他们吃的食物、穿的衣服和生活的环境是不同的。当然，除此之外，这些人还缺乏一种东西，一种在他身上以及书本中可以找得到的东西。摩斯之流已经充分地向他显示了自己的社会地位，但他并没有为之倾倒。他是个穷光蛋，是受债主驱使的奴隶，可他自认为比摩斯家里碰到的那些人强；等到把那套唯一仅有的像样的西装用钱赎回来，他在那些人中间就成了生活的主宰，到时候他会产生一股无名之火，气得浑身发抖，那感觉就好像一名王子被迫与牧羊人同居一处一样。

“你痛恨和害怕社会主义者，”一天傍晚吃饭时，他对摩斯先生说，“可这是为什么呢？你可是既不熟悉他们又不了解他们的信条呀。”

谈话是摩斯夫人转过来的，她一个劲地夸赞哈普哥德先生，让人听了心烦。那位满口陈词滥调的银行高级职员被马丁视为眼中钉肉中刺，一提到他马丁就有点生气。

“是啊，”他说道，“查利·哈普哥德正是一个他们所说的步步高升的年轻人——有个人就是这么对我讲的。这也都是实情。死前他闹不定还能当州长呢，这谁说得准？也许，他还能进合众国参议院哩。”

“你这么看待他是出于什么理由呢？”摩斯夫人问道。

“我听过他的一次竞选演讲。他的措辞巧妙，但内容乏味无聊，缺乏真知灼见，不过却又令人信服，难怪上司觉得他沉稳、值得信赖。他说的那套陈腐的话与普通选民的观念相差无几——这样来形容吧：如果你为某人整理好他的思想，再呈献给他，肯定会赢得他的欢心。”“我倒觉得你是在妒忌哈普哥德先生。”露丝插话说。

“没有的事！”

马丁脸上憎恶的表情一下子惹火了摩斯夫人。

“你的意思是不是想说哈普哥德先生是个愚材？”她冷冰冰地责问道。

“和普通的共和党人差不多，”马丁针锋相对地说，“也和普通的民主党人八九不离十。他们都是些没有心计的笨蛋，而有心计的只是凤毛麟角。明智的共和党人仅仅是那些百万富翁及其头脑清晰的跟随者。他们知道哪些事对自己有利，并了解其中的奥秘。”

“我是个共和党人。”摩斯先生淡淡地说道，“请问，把我归于哪一类呢？”

“哦，你是一个不知不觉服从于他人的随从。”

“随从？”

“是呀。你没有工人阶级的主顾，也不接手刑事诉讼，而专为大公司打官司。你不是靠受理殴打妻子的纠纷和盗窃案子维生，而是从那些社会主子手中领取报酬。谁提供钱，谁就是主人，所以说，你是一位随从。你的宗旨是服务于财团，增进财团的利益。”

摩斯先生脸色有些涨红。

“老实讲，先生，”他说道，“你的言谈活像一个流氓社会主义者。”

就在这时，马丁说出了上面提到过的那段话：

“你痛恨和害怕社会主义者，可这是为什么呢？你可是既不熟悉他们又不了解他们的信条呀。”

“你的言论让人听起来的确像是社会主义。”摩斯先生回答说。露丝担心地望望这个，又忧虑地瞧瞧那个，而摩斯夫人却高兴得满脸放光，因为这下总算激起了她丈夫的对抗之心。

“我说共和党人是蠢材，认为自由、平等和博爱已化为泡影，但这并不等于我就是社会主义者。”马丁笑了笑说，“我对杰斐逊以及那些影响了他的思想的不讲科学的法国人[6]提出疑问，也不能说明我是社会主义者。请相信我的话，摩斯先生，你比我离社会主义要近得多呢，因为我是社会主义的死敌。”

“你可真爱开玩笑。”摩斯先生无以对答，只有这样说道。

“一点也不是玩笑，我说的全是心里话。你一方面相信平等，一方面又为大公司效劳，岂不知那些大公司一天天、一点点地在埋葬平等。你称我为社会主义者，就因为我不承认平等，因为我点明了你们实际所奉行的原则。共和党是反对平等的，尽管他们高喊平等的口号，却干着与平等背道而驰的事情。他们打着平等的旗号，却在消灭平等。所以，我把他们称作蠢材。至于我本人，我可是个个人主义者。我相信的是‘胜者王侯败者寇’。这条道理是我从生物学当中学来的，起码我是这么认为的。正如我所说的那样，我是个人主义者，而个人主义世世代代以至永远，都是社会主义的敌人。”

“可你常去参加社会主义者的集会。”摩斯先生挑战似的说。

“的确如此，但那和探子深入敌营是一个道理。不然，怎么能够了解敌情呢？话又说回来，我倒是很喜欢参加他们的集会哩。他们个个是出色的战士，不管对还是错，全都饱读书卷。对于社会学以及所有其他的学科，他们当中任何一个人的知识都比普通的工业巨头渊博得多。不错，我参加过六七次他们的集会，但这并不能使我成为社会主义者，就像听听查利·哈普哥德的演讲不能使我成为共和党人一样。”“话虽这么讲，”摩斯先生有气无力地说，“可我仍认为你有社会主义的倾向。”

马丁心里想道，天啊，他不知道我在说什么，恐怕连一个字也没听懂。他把自己学的东西都丢到哪里去啦？

就这样，马丁在自己的思想发展过程当中，迎面遇到了由经济基础所决定的伦理观，或者说由阶级地位所决定的伦理观。这种伦理不久就变成了狰狞可怕的怪物出现在他面前。就他个人而言，他是一个明智的伦理学者，讨厌夸夸其谈和陈词滥调，但更讨厌周围那些人的伦理观点，因为他们的伦理观是一个千奇百怪的大杂烩，里面有经济的成分和形而上学的见解，也包含有多愁善感及机械的模仿。

有一次，他尝了一口这种奇特的大杂烩，受到了很大的刺激。他的妹妹玛丽安结交了一位勤奋的年轻技工，那人属于德国血统，在精通了修自行车的技术之后，自己开了一家修理铺。同时，他还取得了低档自行车的经销权，生意十分兴隆。不久前，玛丽安登门来看望马丁，说她已经订了婚。她还顽皮地为马丁看手相，替他算命。第二次，她把赫尔曼·冯·施米特也带了来。马丁热情地接待他们，对他们表示祝贺，说话随随便便且精于辞令，先使妹妹的那位满脑子农民意识的恋人有几分不快。接着，马丁把自己为纪念玛丽安上次来访所写的六七段诗歌朗诵了一遍，这就使对方的印象愈加糟糕。这是一首社交诗，笔调活泼、神妙，他为之取名为《手相专家》。朗诵完之后，他发现妹妹的脸上没有丝毫喜悦的表情，不由感到意外。只见玛丽安以不安的目光紧盯着自己的未婚夫。马丁顺着她的目光望去，看到那位了不起人物的不对称的面部阴云笼罩，一副不赞成的神色。这件事发生之后，两位客人早早地便告辞了。马丁一时想不通，世上竟然有个女人，甚至还是工人阶层的女子，听到别人为她写的诗，非但不感到受宠若惊，还感到不高兴，但他事后又把所发生的一切忘了个干净。

几天后的一个晚上，玛丽安又来看望他，这次是独身一人。她二话没说，直截了当地责怪他不该那样做，语调很是伤心。

“得了吧，玛丽安。”他愤怒地呵斥道，“听你的口气，你好像为有我们这样的亲人感到丢人，或者为有我这样的哥哥觉得羞耻。”

“我是觉得难为情。”她脱口说道。

马丁见她眼里饱含着委屈的眼泪，一下子为难起来，不管怎样，她的心里可是认真的呀。

“玛丽安，我为我自己的亲妹妹写首诗，你的那位赫尔曼有什么可吃醋的呢？”

“他不是吃醋。”她抽泣着说，“他说你的诗写得粗俗和下流。”

马丁难以相信地吹了一声又长又低的口哨，随后定下神来，把抄写的一份《手相专家》又看了一遍。

“我找不出来。”他最后这样说道，把稿子递给了她，“你自己看吧，把你认为下流的地方指给我看。他用的是‘下流’这个词，我没搞错吧？”

“他是这样说的，而且他知道是怎么回事。”她说着，一把将稿子推开，满脸厌恶的表情，“他说你必须把手稿撕掉，还说他绝不允许这样写自己的妻子，供世人耻笑。他说这样做丢人透顶，使他无法容忍。”

“你听我说，玛丽安，他简直是在无理取闹。”马丁话刚出口，却突然改变了主意。

他看到眼前的这位姑娘非常伤心，知道要想说服她或她的丈夫，都是枉费心机。尽管这一切都显得荒唐可笑，但他还是决定屈服于对方。

“好吧，就依你。”他说着，把手稿撕成六七片，扔进了废纸篓里。

但他心中却在得意地想着，他的那份用打字机打出的原稿此时正放在纽约一家杂志社的编辑部里呢，这是玛丽安和她的丈夫永远都不会知道的。那些无害于人的美丽诗句有朝一日刊载出来，他自己、玛丽安夫妇乃至整个世界，都不会因此蒙受什么损失。

玛丽安伸手正欲取废纸篓里的稿子，但半路却停了下来。

“可以吗？”她以央求的口气问。

他点点头，若有所思地打量着她，看着她把撕碎的稿子敛到一起，放入衣袋里——显然是想拿回去证明她胜利地完成了自己的任务。他从她联想到了丽茜·康诺莱，另一位工人阶层的女子。她虽然不像他见过两次的那位姑娘具有炽热的激情和绚丽多彩的生命力，但她们俩的衣着和举止却如出一辙。他突发异想，幻想着她们俩当中的一个出现在摩斯夫人的客厅里的滑稽景象，不由笑了。但随着笑意的消失，他产生了一股强烈的孤独感。他的这个妹妹以及摩斯家的客厅，是他人生旅途当中的两块里程碑。如今，他把这两块里程碑全都抛到了身后。他亲切地望了望旁边的几本书，现在，他只剩下这几位伙伴了。

“哦，你说什么？”他醒过神来，惊异地问道。

玛丽安把自己的提问又重复了一遍。

“我为什么不去工作？”他哈哈大笑了起来，但笑得有些勉强，“这是你的那位赫尔曼讲的话吧？”

她摇了摇头。

“不许骗我。”他厉声说道，而对方只好点头承认他的猜测是对的。

“那好，请转告你的那个赫尔曼，叫他少管闲事；我把他的姑娘写进诗里，他干涉干涉是可以的，但除此之外，就叫他少放些屁。明白吗？”

“如此看来，你认为我当不成作家，对吧？”他继续说道，“你觉得我一无所长，自甘堕落，给家里人带来了耻辱，是吗？”

“我认为你如果找个工作，情况会好得多。”她语气坚定地说，让他看得出她讲的都是真心话，“赫尔曼说——”

“叫赫尔曼见鬼去吧！”他按捺住胸中的怒火嚷嚷道，“我想知道的是你们什么时候结婚。还有，你问问你的赫尔曼，看他愿不愿意屈尊俯就，允许你接受我的结婚礼物。”

待她走后，他把这件事又前后思量了一番，有一两次还发出了苦笑声。他看到自己的妹妹及其未婚夫，看到他那个阶层以及露丝那个阶层的全体成员都按照褊狭的模式过着狭隘的生活——他们是些合群的动物，聚居在一起，依照彼此的看法规范着自己的生活，缺乏个性以及真正的生命力，因为那些幼稚的模式在束缚着他们的一言一行。那些人像幽灵一样排着队在他的眼前闪动：伯纳德·希金波森和勃特勒先生胳膊挽着胳膊，赫尔曼·冯·施米特跟查利·哈普哥德肩并着肩；他对他们一个个鉴定，一对对评判，然后把他们打发走——鉴定时依据的是他从书中学到的智能及伦理标准。他茫然地问自己，那些伟大的灵魂、伟大的须眉丈夫和巾帼英雄今在何处？出现在他的幻觉里，出现在这间斗室里的那些无忧无虑、庸俗愚蠢的人当中，找不到伟人的身影。他厌恶他们，也许就像瑟茜[7]厌恶那些猪一样。等到把幻觉中的最后一位人物打发掉，他满以为只剩下自己一个时，却有一位不速之客出其不意地闯了进来。马丁打量着他，看到眼里的是硬边帽、剪裁得规规整整的双排扣上衣和一双摇摇晃晃的肩膀——这是他过去的模样，一个十足的小流氓。

“你和别人没什么两样，小伙子。”马丁嘲讽自己，“你的伦理观以及知识并不比他们高明。你并不是独立地思考问题，独立地行动。你的观点与你身上的衣服一样，都是别人为你准备好的；你的行动受到大众的意见制约。你是流氓团伙的头目，因为其他人拥戴你，认为你是块好料。你跟别人打架，统治着那个团伙，这倒不是因为你喜欢那样做——你明知自己打心底里厌恶——而是因为其他的流氓怂恿你那样做。你打败了干酪脸，是因为你不肯认输，而不肯认输的原因部分是由于你是沉沦的野兽，另外一部分是由于你和周围的每一个人一样，坚信衡量男性强弱的标准是伤害及摧残他人肉体时所显示出的嗜血性和凶狠性。唉，你真卑鄙，甚至还抢别人的女朋友，倒不是因为你喜欢她们，而是因为你周围的狐群狗党操纵着你的伦理观，他们的骨髓里都蕴藏着野雄马及公海豹的本能。啧，一闪过去了许多年头，现在你是怎么看待这些问题呢？”

就像是回答这种提问似的，他的幻觉蓦地发生了剧变。硬边帽和那件剪裁得四四方方的上衣不见了，取而代之的是比较顺眼的服饰；那张面孔上的凶狠表情不见了，眼里冷酷的神色也消失了；由于受到美和知识的熏陶，他现在的面孔变得温文尔雅、神采奕奕。这幅幻象与现实中的他十分相似。他凝神观察着，看到写字台的灯光把那道幻影照得通亮，而那道幻影却在读书。他瞧了瞧书名，原来是《美学》。接着，他一头钻入幻象之中，调了调灯光，把《美学》继续阅读了下去。

[1]　19世纪英国新浪漫主义流派作家，《金银岛》的作者。

[2]　19世纪英国诗人兼批评家。

[3]　美杜莎是希腊神话中的女蛇怪，目光所及之处全化为石头。

[4]　17世纪法国唯心主义哲学家。

[5]　此处指牛津主教威尔勃福斯。

[6]　杰斐逊是美国第三任总统，曾受过法国启蒙主义思想的影响。

[7]　希腊神话中的女巫，经常把路人变成猪。

第三十章

在一个晴朗的秋日，马丁向露丝朗读了他的《爱情组诗》。这一天和他们一年前相互表述爱情时一样充满了融融的暖意。下午，他们和以往一样，一道骑车子深入群山，登上那座深受他们喜爱的山丘。她时不时高兴得惊叹出声，打断他的朗读。末了，他终于读完了，把最后一页稿纸与其他的稿纸放到了一起，等待着她的裁判。

她迟迟不说话，临到说话时也吞吞吐吐，不愿痛痛快快把心里刻薄的看法讲出来。

“我觉得这些诗写得很美，非常美，”她说道，“但就是卖不出去，对吧？你明白我的意思，”她说道，几乎用的是一种央求的口气，“你从事写作是不现实的。有些事情行不通——也许是稿子卖不出去的问题吧——这就使你无法靠写作为生。亲爱的，你可千万别误解我的意思。这些诗都是为我而写的，真让我感到幸福和自豪，让我觉得受宠若惊——否则，我就算不上一个真正的女人了。然而，咱们不能靠这些诗结婚呵。难道你还不明白吗，马丁？不要把我看成一个追求金钱的人。我所操心的是咱们的爱以及咱们的未来。自从咱们彼此了解了对方的真情后，整整一年过去了，但结婚的日子仍遥遥无期。不要以为我一谈结婚就是沉不住气，应知道我的感情以及我本人都在水深火热之中。你既然迷恋于写作，为什么不到报社找个工作呢？为什么不当记者呢？至少，暂时当当记者行吗？”

“那会破坏我的风格。”他回答道，声音低沉而单调，“你不知道为了培养自己的风格我付出了多少心血。”

“可短篇小说呢？”她反驳道，“你把它们称为糊口的作品。这种东西写了不少，难道它们就不破坏你的风格吗？”

“不，这可是两码事。那些短篇小说是在我创作了一整天独具一格的作品之余，在极端疲倦的情况下写出来的。而记者从早干到晚都是为了糊口，糊口是他们生活中唯一的宗旨。那是一种旋风似的生活，一种过眼烟云般的生活，既无过去又无将来，根本不考虑什么风格，只顾及记者的文体，所以绝不能算作文学创作。目前我的风格正在形成和具体化，如果去当记者，就等于文学上的自杀。说实在的，我所写的每一篇短篇小说以及每篇小说当中的每一个字，都违背了我的心愿、有损于我的自尊，都亵渎了我对美的敬重。告诉你吧，我心里感到厌恶，也感到内疚。当小说卖不出去的时候，即便我的衣服又送进了当铺，我还暗自高兴哩。但撰写《爱情组诗》却给我带来了喜悦，那是极为崇高的创作喜悦！所有的遗憾都从中得到了补偿。”

马丁不知道，露丝对所谓的“创作喜悦”是不感兴趣的。她倒是提到过这个词——他第一次正是从她口中听到的。上大学的时候，为了获得文学学士的学位，她学习过创作、研究过创作。但由于缺乏个性和创造性，她的文化修养的全部表现只不过是把别人的话重复来重复去。

“编辑修改你的《海洋抒情诗》，难道会有错吗？”她问道，“别忘了，一个编辑必须有真才实学，否则就当不上编辑。”

“这种观点和那些顽固的正统派唱的是一个调子。”他说道，出于对编辑们的仇恨，有些控制不住自己了，“现存的事物不仅是正确的，而且还是最出色的。不管什么东西，只要存在，就足以证明它适合于存在，不但能存在于现有的条件下，还能存在于其他所有条件下——请注意，这是一般人下意识的观念。他们正是由于愚昧才相信这套道理——他们的愚昧不折不扣地表现在威宁格尔[1]所形容的那种幼稚的思维方式上。他们是一些缺乏思想的人，但他们却自认为有头脑，主宰着少数真正有思想的人的生活。”

他打住了话头，强烈地感觉到他的话已超出了露丝的理解范围。

“老实讲，我不知道威宁格尔是个什么人。”她反驳道，“你说话太笼统，让我理解不透。我刚才谈的是编辑的特点——”

“那就让我来告诉你吧。”他打断她的话说，“对百分之九十九的编辑而言，主要的特点是失败。他们在创作上没有取得成功。别以为他们不愿享受创作的喜悦，而喜欢编辑部那枯燥的工作，喜欢当销售量以及业务经理的奴隶。他们也曾试过笔锋，然而却以失败告终。可恶的矛盾正在此处。在文学界，所有通向成功之路的大门都被这些看门狗、这些文学上的失败者把守着。杂志社以及出版局的大多数，或者几乎所有的编辑、副编辑、助理编辑和审稿人，都想从事写作，可是却遭到了失败。而正是这些天底下最没有资格的人，在决定着哪些稿件可以出版，哪些不可以。经过证明，他们没有独创性，缺乏天赋的灵感，可他们却能够对不落窠臼的天才进行裁决。除了他们之外，还有评论家呢，那些人也是失败者。别以为他们对创作诗歌或小说没抱过幻想、没试过身手；他们全都尝试过，但全都失败了。唉，评论文章一般都味同嚼蜡，比吃了鱼肝油还让人觉得恶心。你了解我对评论家以及那些所谓批评家的看法。伟大的批评家确有其人，但他们寥若晨星。假如我当不成作家，就到编辑界找口饭吃。怎么说也可以挣来面包、牛油和果酱。”

露丝反应敏捷。她不赞成恋人的观点，一下子就在他的话里发现了矛盾。

“可是，马丁，如果情况真是这样，如果真像你所断言的那样，所有的大门全都关闭着，怎么还有人可以成为伟大的作家呢？”

“他们把不可能的事情转变成了现实，才取得了成功。”他答道，“他们的业绩辉煌灿烂，似燃烧的火焰，将那些挡道的人都化成了灰烬。他们创造了奇迹，战胜了那些占绝对优势的敌人。他们大功告成，因为他们是卡莱尔[2]笔下的那种伤痕累累但永不屈服的巨人。我必须向他们学习，必须把不可能变为可能。”

“可你要是失败了呢？你应该为我想想，马丁。”

“我要是失败了？”他把她打量了一会儿，就好像她说的话简直不可想象。随后，他的眼里露出了理解的神色。“我要是失败了，就去当编辑，而你就当编辑夫人。”

听到他开玩笑的话，她皱起了眉头，样子又可爱又动人，使他忍不住把她拥入怀中亲吻，一直待她将眉头舒展开。

“好啦，够了。”她说着，凭借意志的力量挣脱了他那令人心醉的有力臂膀，“我跟我的父母谈过。以前我可从来没和他们这样较过劲呀。我逼着他们听我讲话。说来我真是个不孝的女儿。他们看不上你，这你知道；可我向他们一遍又一遍地申明我对你的爱是不会改变的。最后，家父妥协了，说如果你愿意，可以马上到他的事务所工作。他主动提出要付给你可观的薪水，好让咱们结婚，找幢小房子安顿下来。我认为他的心肠真是太好了——你觉得呢？”

马丁心口隐隐作痛，于绝望之中伸手去取烟叶和纸（其实，他身上已不再装这些东西了），想卷支烟抽，嘴里还喃喃不清地说着什么。而露丝却自顾自地朝下讲着。

“我想坦率地告诉你一句话，好让你知道你在他心中确切的位置，你听了可别伤心。他不喜欢你的偏激观点，还认为你好逸恶劳。我当然是了解真实情况的，我知道你工作得很努力。”

马丁心里嘀咕着，自己到底有多努力，恐怕连她也不知道。

“那么，你是怎么看待我的观点呢？你觉得我的观点很偏激吗？”他问道。

他紧紧盯住她的眼睛，等待着回答。

“依我看，你的观点很让人不安。”她答道。

他听完答话之后，感到生活灰蒙蒙一片，压得他透不过气来，竟然忘记了她曾试探性地提议过让他去工作。而她也只敢做到这一步了；想等到有机会再旧话重提，听听他的答复。

她没等多久，机会就来了。马丁也有一个问题需要问她，他想弄清楚她对他到底有多大的信心。结果，一星期之内双方的问题都得到了解答。事情是由马丁向露丝朗读《太阳的耻辱》而引起的。

“你为什么不愿当记者呢？”待他朗读完后，她问道，“你这么爱写东西，我相信你一定能够成功。你可以在新闻界平步青云，扬名于天下。有许多伟大的特派记者拿着高薪，把整个世界作为自己的活动舞台。他们走遍各个角落，像斯坦利[3]一样被派往非洲的腹地，或者去采访教皇，以及奔赴神秘的西藏去探险。”

“如此看来，你不喜欢我的这篇文章喽？”他颇为抵触地说，“难道你认为我在新闻写作上露出了头角，而在文学创作上碌碌无为吗？”

“不，不。我喜欢这篇文章。文章听起来蛮不错的，但恐怕你的读者看不懂。起码，我就不懂。它听上去倒是很悦耳，可就是让人理解不了。你的科学术语简直把我搞糊涂了。你要知道，亲爱的，你是一个极端主义者。你以为明了的东西，到了我们这儿就不一定明了了。”

“依我看，让你感到麻烦的是哲学术语吧。”他一时无话可讲，只好这样说道。

他刚刚朗读完这篇表达了他最成熟思想的文章，心里正燃烧着火焰，谁料她竟说出那等话，真让他承受不了。

“不管文章写得有多糟，”他执拗地说，“难道你就找不到一点可贵之处吗？我指的是思想内容方面。”

她摇了摇头。

“找不到。这篇东西和我所看过的作品迥然两样。我看过梅特林克的作品，理解他——”

“他那套神秘主义，你也能理解吗？”马丁脱口问道。

“是的。可你的这篇用来抨击他的文章，却让我难以理解。当然，如果要论独到的见解——”

他不耐烦地摆摆手，切断了她的话，可自己又不开口。待他清醒过来时，才突然发现她仍在讲话，而且已经讲了好一会儿了。

“总之，你把写作当作玩耍一样看待。”她说道，“这种游戏你玩的时间已经够长的了，应该认真面对生活了——面对咱们俩的生活，马丁。在这之前，你仅仅顾及自己的生活。”

“你是想让我去工作？”他问道。

“对，家父提供——”

“这些我全明白，”他截住她的话说，“我想知道的是，你是不是对我丧失了信心？”

她目光暗淡，无言地紧紧握了握他的手。

“是对你的写作失去了信心。”她末了这样压低声音承认道。

“你看过我的许多作品，”他粗暴地说，“你认为怎么样呢？一点希望都没有吗？和别人的作品比起来，你觉得怎么样？”

“他们的作品能卖出去，可你的——你的却卖不出去。”

“还没回答我的问题呢，你认为我不该选择文学生涯吗？”

“好吧，我来答复你吧，”她硬着头皮说，“我觉得你不是块搞写作的料。请原谅，亲爱的，这可是你逼着我说出来的。你很清楚，在文学方面我比你了解得多。”

“是的，你是个文学学士，”他若有所思地说，“按说你应该比我了解得多。”

“不过，我还有话要补充呢。”双方痛苦地沉默了一会儿之后，他继续说道，“我清楚自己的能力，这一点没有人比我更清楚了。我知道我一定会取得成功。我绝不会被压倒的。我心里有一团东西似火焰在燃烧，需要用诗歌、小说和散文把它表现出来。对此，我不要求你抱有信心，也不要求你对我本人以及我的写作抱有信心。我所要求你的是爱我，对爱情要有信心。

“一年前，我请求给我两年的时间。现在，只剩下一年了。我以自己的荣誉和灵魂担保，在这一年当中，我定能获得成功。记得很久以前你曾讲过，我要写作就得先当学徒。听了你的话，我当了学徒。我惜时如金，一分钟当成两分钟用。有你在前边等着，我从未动摇过。你要知道，我已经忘掉了睡安稳觉是什么滋味。我只觉得，几百万年之前我曾经想睡多长时间就睡多长时间，睡足了便自然而然地醒来。现在，我总是被闹钟叫醒。我拨闹钟的时间，得根据入睡的迟早而定；待到上好钟、熄掉灯，我便进入无知无觉的沉睡。

“一旦觉得困的时候，我就把手头难懂的书拿开，换上一本轻松些的书。当睡意泛上来的时候，我就用指关节敲打脑袋，以驱赶睡魔。我读过吉卜林的一篇作品，里面讲到一个怕睡觉的人。那人弄来一副马刺，困倦的时候，便把赤裸的身子靠在铁刺上。想想吧，我也是那样做的。我看着钟表，一直要坚持到深夜一点、两点或三点，才肯把马刺取开。这样，在马刺的监督下，我要看书看到预定的钟点才睡觉。一月复一月，马刺伴着我入睡。我孤注一掷，分秒必争，睡五个半小时也觉得太奢侈。现在，我每天只睡四个小时。我简直太想睡觉了。有时候，由于缺乏睡眠，我感到头晕目眩，而能给人带来休憩和长眠的死亡对我倒成了一种诱惑。这时，朗费罗的诗句会在我的脑际盘桓：

深奥的大海寂静无澜，

海里的万物在它怀中睡眠；

趋前一步，一切全完；

一个跳跃，一个水泡，

就会与死神相伴。

“当然，这全是一派胡言，全是由于紧张和用脑过度产生的荒诞念头。可问题在于，我为什么要这样做呢？那是为了你啊！是为了缩短学徒期，争取早一日取得成功。如今我总算期满出师了。我了解自己的情况。我敢说，我一个月学的东西比普通大学生在一年中学的还多。告诉你吧，对这一点我是有把握的。要不是渴望得到你的理解，这些话原本是不打算跟你讲的。这绝非自我吹嘘，因为我可以用书来衡量我取得的成绩。如今，要是拿我以及我的知识作为比较对象，你的弟弟仅仅是孤陋寡闻的野蛮人。当我从书本中挖掘知识的时候，他们却在睡大觉。很久以前我渴望成名，而现在已不在乎成不成名了。我想的是你。我对你的渴慕超过了对衣食以及名利的追求。我梦想着把头靠在你的怀里，美美地睡上它几天。用不了一年的时间，这个梦想肯定会变为现实。”

他的力量似一股股浪潮冲击着她；两人的意愿愈是对抗，她就感到对方对自己的吸引力愈强烈。他身上总是向她散发出一种力量，而现在这股力量涌动在他那慷慨激昂的声音里和闪闪发亮的眼睛里，化为生命的活力及智慧在他的体内冲撞。在这一瞬间，她一下子发现自己的信念产生了裂缝——透过那道裂缝，她看清了真正的马丁·伊登，出类拔萃、不可战胜。就像驯兽师有时怀疑自己的本事一样，此刻的她似乎也在怀疑她是否能够驯服这个人的野性。

“另外还有一点，”他滔滔不绝地说着，“你爱我，可你为什么会爱上我呢？我心里有一种东西在督促我写作，而正是这种东西吸引了你的爱。你爱我，因为我与那些你所认识的、也可能会爱上的男人有点不同。我不是当编辑和会计的料，也不善于做斤斤两两的小生意以及为诉讼案与人辩论。如果硬让我干这种事，让我跟那些人学，做他们所做的工作，呼吸他们所呼吸的空气，形成他们所形成的观点，那你就抹杀了我们之间的区别，葬送了我，毁掉了你所爱的东西。我的创作欲望，是我身上最具活力的东西。倘若我仅仅是个平庸的人，我就不会产生写作的欲望，你也就不会愿意嫁给我为妻了。”

“但你可别忘了，”她突然想出了一个能与之类比的例子，于是便插话说，“有些古怪的发明家，在家里人忍饥挨饿的情况下，还异想天开地研制什么永动机。毫无疑问，他们的妻子爱他们，跟他们同甘共苦，这倒不是‘因为’而是‘尽管’他们对永动机着了迷。”

“不错，”马丁说，“但也有些发明家并不是怪人，他们饿着肚子研制实用的东西；有时候，这些人能够获得成功，这是有案可查的。当然，我并不企求干一些不可能办到的事——”

“你不是说过‘要把不可能变为可能’吗？”她切断他的话，问道。

“我那样说是打个比喻。我要做的是前人做过的事情——写作，并靠此为生。”

她没作声，而她的沉默刺激着他朝下说。

“照你的看法，我的目标跟永动机一样荒诞不经吗？”他责问道。她紧紧握了一下他的手——像一位母亲对自己受委屈的孩子表示怜爱一样——，使他从中得到了答案。这会儿，在她看来，他正是一个受委屈的孩子，一个鬼迷心窍，妄想实现不可能实现的目标的人。

谈话临近尾声时，她又一次告诫他，说她的父母对他抱着敌视态度。

“你爱我吗？”他问道。

“我爱！我爱你！”她喊叫了起来。

“我也爱你，而不是他们，所以不管他们怎么样，都不会让我感到难过，”他以一种激动的声音说道，“我坚信你的爱，因而不害怕他们的敌视。世间凡事都可能走错道，唯有爱情不会迷失方向。爱情绝不会误入歧途，除非它是苍白无力的爱情，半路发起晕，自己栽倒在地。”

[1]　19世纪奥地利思想家。

[2]　19世纪英国作家，宣扬“英雄史观”。

[3]　19世纪英国探险家，年轻时曾在美国当记者。

第三十一章

在百老汇大街上，马丁无意中碰到了他的姐姐葛特露——这原来是一次非常幸运的巧遇，可是却让他感到窘迫万分。她在街拐角等电车，先瞧见了他，注意到了他那张饿出了皱纹的脸上急切的表情，以及他眼里绝望和阴郁的神色。他刚去找过当铺老板，想凭着已当出的自行车再弄点钱来，但结果一无所获。泥泞的秋季，马丁早就当掉了自行车，只留下了那套黑色西装。

“你还有一套黑衣服嘛，”当铺老板对他的每笔财产都了如指掌，便这样回答他说，“你可别说你把它已当给了那个犹太人李普卡。因为你如果真的——”

老板显出一副威胁的表情，慌得马丁急忙申明：

“不，不，衣服还在我这儿。不过，我有正经事，要留着穿呢。”

“好吧，”榨人血汗的老板平静地说，“我这是做生意，你把衣服拿来，我才能给你钱。你以为我这一行是干着玩的吗？”

“可我的车子一点毛病都没有，价值四十块钱呀。”马丁辩驳道，“你只给了我七块钱。不，连七块也不到，而是六块两毛五，你把利息预先扣下了。”

“再想要钱，就取衣服来。”对方的一句答复把马丁打发出了那间密不透风的肮脏小屋。马丁绝望的心情流露在脸上，引起了姐姐的怜悯。

姐弟俩刚见面，电报大街的电车便开了过来，停下来运载那些下午出来购物的人。他搀着姐姐的胳膊上车，而希金波森夫人从他的搀扶中觉察到他不打算跟她一道上车。于是她在踏板上转过身来，低头望着他那张憔悴的面孔，心里又感到一阵隐痛。

“你不上来吗？”她问道。

说着话，她就下了车，站到了他身旁。

“我步行——你知道，这是一种锻炼。”他解释说。

“那么我就陪你走几段街区吧，”她宣称道，“也许这对我有好处。这些日子我老是感到四肢无力。”

马丁打量了她一眼，便知道她说的是真话。只见她浑身上下一副邋遢相，肥胖得有些不健康，耷拉着肩膀，疲倦的脸上布满了松弛的皱纹，沉重的脚步缺乏弹性——看她的步态，像是在模仿一个无忧无虑、心情愉快的人走路，可又模仿得丑态百出。

“你最好还是在这儿等下一趟车吧。”他见姐姐走到头一个街角便停了下来，于是这样对她说道。

“老天呀！瞧我已经累得不行了！”她气喘吁吁地说，“不过，你穿着这种鞋，我照样能陪你走下去。你的鞋底薄得跟纸一样，走不到北奥克兰，早早就会磨穿的。”

“家里还有双好的呢。”马丁答道。

“明天来吃晚饭吧，”她前后不接茬地邀请道，“希金波森先生不会在家的。他要到圣莱安德罗办事去。”

马丁摇了摇头，可是一听到邀请他吃饭，他的眼睛里便无法遏制地闪现出一副饿狼似的神色。

“你身无分文，马特，所以才步行锻炼吧！”她原打算轻蔑地哼一声鼻子，可末了仅仅抽噎了一下，“等等，让我找找看。”

她在手提包里摸索了一阵，把一枚五块钱的金币塞进了他手中。“瞧我，把你上次的生日给忘了，马特。”她语无伦次地喃喃着。

马丁的手本能地握住了那枚金币，但与此同时，他觉得自己不该收下金币，于是犹豫不决，被弄得痛苦万分。这枚金币意味着食物、生命、体力和脑力，还有——谁说得准呢？——也许他真能写出一篇佳作，挣来许多枚金币哩。在他的幻觉中，清清楚楚地闪现出他刚刚写完的两篇论文的手稿。他看到它们被扔到了桌下，搁在那堆给人家退了回来但他无钱买邮票寄出的稿件上。他看到了它们的题目——那是他用打字机打出来的：《神秘的祭司长》和《美之发祥地》。这两篇文章还从未投出去过呢。它们与他在这方面所写的其他文章相比毫不逊色。要是有邮票就好啦！他心中涌起最后必胜的信念，而这种信念与饥饿感结成有力的联盟，督促他飞快地将金币装进了自己的口袋。

“我会还你的，葛特露，还你一百倍的钱。”他哽咽了一下说，喉头发痛发紧，眼睛一下子有些湿润。

“请记住我的话！”他不连贯地以一种自信的口吻叫嚷道，“不出一年的时间，我就会把整整一百枚黄灿灿的金币放到你的手上。我并不要求你相信我。你就等着瞧吧。”

说实在的，她的确不相信他的话。她心中的疑虑搅得她很是不安，可又拿不出办法来，于是这样说道：

“我知道你在挨饿，马特。你浑身上下都露出一种饿相。你随时可以来家里吃饭。希金波森先生一出门，我就打发孩子去叫你。另外，马特——”

他等着她朝下说，不过，他心里明白她要端出什么话来，因为他对她的思维方式了解得一清二楚。

“你不觉得现在该找个工作干干吗？”

“你认为我这样做无出头之日吗？”

她摇了摇头。

“除了我自己，没有人对我抱有信心，葛特露。”他带着激烈的反抗情绪说，“我写出了许多优秀作品，早晚有一天会卖出去的。”

“你怎么知道是优秀作品呢？”

“因为——”他的脑海里翻腾着壮阔的文学及文学史的画面，使他觉得无法向她解释清他为什么有自信心，于是便迟疑了一下，“因为杂志上刊出的文章，百分之九十九都不如我写的好。”

“真希望你能听听别人的劝告，”她说话的语气软，但看法不可动摇，坚信自己正确地诊断出了他的痼疾，“真希望你能听听别人的劝告。”她又重复了一遍说，“明天来家里吃晚饭吧。”

马丁把她抉上电车后，便匆匆赶到邮局买邮票，五块钱花掉了三块。就在当天去摩斯家的路上，他又折进邮局，把好多又长又厚的信封放在秤上称了称，将邮票全都贴了上去，只剩下了三张两分的。

后来才发现，这个晚上对马丁来说十分重要，因为用过餐后，他结识了勒斯·勃力森登。马丁不知道这个人是怎么钻进摩府来的，也不知他是谁的朋友，或者哪位熟人把他带来的。他也无心去向露丝打听此人的情况。简而言之，马丁一开始只觉得勃力森登萎靡不振、蠢头蠢脑，所以根本没把他往心上放。过了有一小时，他发现勃力森登还是个缺乏礼貌的人，只见他从一个房间转到另一个房间，痴呆呆地望着那些画，要不就从桌子上或书架上取书及杂志看。勃力森登是头一次来摩斯家，可是他不与其他人接触，自己坐在一张宽敞的莫里斯安乐椅上，蜷起身子，从口袋里掏出一本薄薄的书，泰然自若地看了起来。他一边出神地看书，一边用手指轻柔地梳理着头发。这天晚上，马丁再没有去注意他，除了一次，他看到勃力森登在和几位年轻姑娘打情骂俏时倒显出一副志得意满的样子。

说来也巧，马丁离开时，在小道上撵上了勃力森登，此刻勃力森登已经快走到了街上。

“喂，你好啊！”马丁说。

对方仅仅没礼貌地哼了一声，算是作为回答，不过却调过身来同他走到了一起。马丁没再主动地找话说，于是两人默默无语地朝前走了几段路。

“真是个高傲的老混蛋！”

这一声嚷嚷又突兀又恶毒，吓了马丁一跳。他感到莫名其妙，同时愈加讨厌对方了。

“你跑到这种地方来干什么呢？”两人默默地又走了一段路之后，对方突然发问道。

“那你呢？”马丁反问道。

“不知道，我一点也不明白。”对方回答，“不过，我这样轻率可是头一次。一天有二十四个小时，好歹总得打发掉啊。走，跟我喝一杯去。”

“好吧。”马丁答道。

他欣然答应了对方，可紧接着就感到为难起来。回到家，他上床之前得写几个小时卖钱的作品，而上床后还有一部魏斯曼的作品在等着他，就更别提和激动人心的小说一样充满了离奇曲折情节的赫伯特·斯宾塞的《自传》了。他心想，何必要把时间浪费在一个他不喜欢的人身上呢？可是，真正叫他感兴趣的不是身旁的这个人，也不是喝酒呀，而是喝酒时的气氛——雪亮的灯光、镜子，以及一排排耀眼的酒杯、热情洋溢和容光焕发的面孔、人们大声的喧闹。对，正是这样，他感兴趣的是鼎沸的人声——那些人是乐天派，散发出成功的气息，花钱买酒气度不凡。他孤苦寂寞，这就是问题的所在。所以，一旦有人邀请，他就会一口答应下来，活似一条鲣鱼，紧紧咬住钩上的诱饵不放。他和乔在雪莱温泉旅馆喝过酒，后来又跟那位葡萄牙食品商喝过一回，但自那以后他再没下过酒吧饮酒。脑力上的劳累与体力上的劳累不一样，不会激起饮酒的欲望，因此他没感到过有喝酒的必要。但这会儿，他心里却升腾起了喝酒的欲望，或者不如说，他渴望在卖酒和饮酒的气氛中陶醉一番。而“洞穴”酒吧正是这样一种地方——他和勃力森登坐在酒吧里的大皮椅子上，呷着威士忌和苏打水。

他们交谈着，谈话的内容涉及面很广。两人轮流做东，依次叫酒。马丁酒量惊人，瞧见对方也是海量，不由感到诧异，他还常常放下酒杯，不无意外地倾听对方的高谈阔论。不大一会儿，他就发现勃力森登无所不晓，觉得他是自己遇到的第二个智力超群的人。而且，他还发现勃力森登具有一些考德威尔教授所缺乏的东西——即炽热的感情、敏锐的眼光和洞察力，以及灿烂奔放的天赋。生动的语言潺潺流淌出勃力森登的口中。他的两片薄嘴唇恰似机器的冲模，冲出的词语又尖锐又刻薄；有时，这两片薄嘴唇微微噘起，发出委婉动听的声音，讲出温柔悦耳的话语，以及闪闪发光的优美词句，美得令人难以忘怀，还吐露出深不可测的生活之谜；有时，这两片薄嘴唇就像号角一样，吹出宇宙间的冲撞和混战声，那些词句如银铃样清越、似星空般皎洁，不仅概括了科学的结论，还讲述了更多的道理——那是诗人的精神、超自然的真理，如此扑朔迷离，无法用语言表达，只能靠微妙而不可捕捉的深奥词句来传意。他具有神奇的眼力，可以根据经验看到最遥远的地方，看到语言所不能够描述的地方，可是他却创造了奇迹，用黄金语言，把未知的意义赋予已知的词汇，将一般人所无法接受的信息输送给马丁的大脑。

马丁忘掉了起初对他的厌恶感。此刻，书本所能够提供的最优秀的东西变成了现实。眼前就是一个智囊，一个活生生的他所敬仰的对象。“真让人佩服得五体投地啊！”他在心里一遍遍念叨着。

“看来你是研究生物学的。”他意味深长地说出了声。

令他感到意外的是，勃力森登竟摇了摇头。

“可是你所阐明的真理只有生物学才能够论证呀，”马丁坚持着说，而对方漠漠地瞪着他瞧，“你的结论一定与你看的书是一致的。”

“听到这话真让人高兴。”勃力森登说，“我仗着一星半点的知识走捷径找到了真理，想起来就使我感到宽慰。就我本人而言，我从不关心自己正确与否，因为那是毫无价值的。人类永远都不可能彻底地了解真理。”

“原来你是斯宾塞的信徒！”马丁欢喜地叫嚷道。

“我只是在青少年时期看过他的书，而且仅仅看了一本《教育学》。”“但愿我也能像你一样轻松随便地积累知识。”半小时之后马丁这样说道。他刚才一直在仔细分析勃力森登的智力。“你真是一个武断的人，而这正是你的绝妙之处。你以武断的观点，说出了科学家们靠着归纳和推理才论证出的最新事实。你一下就得出了正确的结论。你完全抄的是一条近路啊。你以光的速度，凭着某种超理性的方法找到了真理。”

“是啊，这一点过去曾让约瑟夫神甫以及德登修士感到头痛。”勃力森登答道，“噢，不，”他接着又说道，“我算不上什么。我只是凭着幸运，才进了天主教大学接受教育。你的知识是从哪里学来的？”马丁回答的时候，不住眼地打量着勃力森登，从他那又瘦又长贵族式的面庞、耷拉的肩头，一直打量到他那放在旁边椅子上的大衣以及被许多书塞得鼓鼓囊囊的衣袋。勃力森登的脸以及纤细的长手都被太阳晒得发黑——马丁觉得未免太黑了。这种晒出的黑肤色叫马丁感到担心。很显然，勃力森登不属于户外活动的人，那他怎么会受到阳光的蹂躏呢？马丁心想，这种黑肤色有点病态，其中必有缘故，同时他又开始端详那副面孔——那张脸颧骨高耸、两颊深陷，长着一个马丁前所未见的典雅端庄的鹰钩鼻。那双眼睛倒没有什么特别的，大小适中，呈现出一种难以形容的棕色；不过，眼睛里燃烧着一团烈火，或者更确切些说，隐藏着一种既奇特又矛盾、双重意义的表情。那双眼睛闪射出坚强不屈的挑战光芒，甚至显得严厉过度，但同时又惹人怜悯。马丁对他顿生怜悯之心，虽然当时并不知为什么，可马上便了解了其中的原因。

“噢，我染上了肺结核病，”过了一会儿，勃力森登先说自己来自亚利桑那州，继而随口这样宣称道，“那儿气候不错，我到那儿待过两三年。”

“这里的气候不怎么样，难道你就不怕发病吗？”

“怕发病？”

他在重复马丁所用的词语时虽没着意强调，但马丁从他那张苦行者的脸上看得分明，他是无所畏惧的。勃力森登的眼睛眯起来，活像雄鹰的眼睛，马丁留意到他的鹰钩鼻和胀大的鼻孔是那样富于好斗性，那样咄咄逼人和肆无忌惮，差点都喘不过气来了。他暗暗叫好，同时热血沸腾，不由出口朗诵道：

命运给了我当头一棒，

打得我头破血流，

但我的脑袋依然高扬。

“你喜欢亨利的诗，”勃力森登说，表情迅速变得和蔼温柔起来，“当然，这也是意料之中的事，啊，亨利，一个勇敢的战士！他在当代诗人中——在那些杂志诗人中，可谓鹤立鸡群，活似太监群里站立着的一个角斗士。”

“你不喜欢杂志吗？”马丁低声责问道。

“你喜欢吗？”对方冲着他咆哮道，口气粗野得吓了他一跳。

“我嘛——我为杂志撰稿，或者只是想为杂志撰稿罢了。”马丁支支吾吾地说。

“这就好。”对方的口气软了下来，“你想为它们撰稿，可是没有得志。正因为你一败涂地，我才尊敬你和钦佩你。我知道你写的是什么样的文章。我闭着眼都看得出，你的文章当中有一样东西使你处处吃闭门羹。那就是有胆有识的观点，杂志社是不需要这类货色的，它们所需要的是空洞无聊的垃圾。上帝很清楚，它们登的就是这种文章，所以才没有你的立足之地。”

“我并非不肩写平庸的文章。”马丁反驳道。

“恰恰相反——”勃力森登打住话头，傲慢地望了望马丁的穷酸相，从他那破旧的领带、毛了边的衣领和油光发亮的上衣袖子一直望到略微有些磨损的袖口，接着把眼光上移，最后落到了他那深陷的脸颊上，“恰恰相反，平庸之作你还高攀不上呢。你差着十万八千里，永远也别指望能写好。听着，伙计，我只消请你去吃饭，就可以激怒你。”

马丁觉得脸上的血一个劲朝上涌，火辣辣的。勃力森登得意地哈哈大笑起来。

“吃饱了肚子的人接到这样的邀请，就不会恼火。”他断言道。

“你是个魔鬼。”马丁怒气冲冲地叫嚷道。

“瞧你，我又没邀请你。”

“你没那个胆量。”

“嗬，这倒说不定。我现在向你发出邀请。”

勃力森登说着从椅子上半欠起身来，好像准备立刻上饭馆吃饭去似的。

马丁攥紧拳头，太阳穴里的血管嗵嗵地跳着。

“波斯科！他可以把活蛇一口吞下！把活蛇一口吞下！”勃力森登模仿着当地一位著名吞蛇人招徕生意的腔调喊叫了起来。

“我也可以将你生吃活剥。”马丁说，一边用无情的目光扫视着对方那遭到疾病摧残的身躯。

“可惜我不值得让你吃。”

“其实，”马丁思考着说，“你不值得小题大做。”他突然开怀大笑了起来，笑得又舒畅又痛快，“老实讲，你在出我的洋相，勃力森登。你知道我在挨饿，可这没什么大惊小怪的，也没什么丢人的。按说，我瞧不起的就是人们那褊狭的世俗观念；你随口说了一句尖锐的话，一句大实话，我立刻就被褊狭的观念所左右了。”

“你恼火了。”勃力森登一口咬定说。

“我刚才的确是恼了，这是出于小时候养成的偏见。我接受了那些陈旧观念，我后来学的东西都被它们庸俗化了。它们是我心里见不得人的东西。”

“现在你把它们视如敝屣啦？”

“当然喽。”

“真的吗？”

“真的。”

“那好，咱们吃点东西去。”

“让我清账吧。”马丁这样说道。他想用那两块钱中花剩下的一点零钱付刚才喝的威士忌和苏打水，可勃力森登硬是逼着侍者把零钱放回到了桌子上。

马丁扮了个鬼脸，将钱塞进了口袋，接着感到勃力森登把一只手亲切地搭在了他的肩上。

第三十二章

紧跟着，在第二天下午，玛丽亚见又有一位贵宾来看望马丁，不由激动万分。不过，这次她可没有惊慌失措，而是把勃力森登请进华丽、体面的客厅入座。

“我不期而至，让你讨厌了吧？”勃力森登启口问道。

“不，不，哪里的话！”马丁说着，跟他握握手，招呼他坐到仅有的那张椅子上，而自己在床沿上落了座，“你是怎么知道我住在这里的？”

“我给摩斯家挂了个电话，是摩斯小姐接的，所以我就来啦。”他把手伸进外衣口袋，掏出一本薄书扔到了桌子上，“这本书是一位诗人写的，你留着看吧。”他见马丁一味客气，便又说道，“我要书有什么用呢？今天早晨我又吐了血。有威士忌吗？啧，当然不会有喽。请稍等一下。”

他立起身朝外走去。马丁目送他那颀长的身影下了门外的台阶，望着他转过身来想关上大门，不无痛心地留意到他那曾经一度宽阔的肩膀如今已凹入萎缩下陷的胸部。马丁取来两只大酒杯，然后开始看那本诗集——亨利·沃恩·马罗的新作。

“没有苏格兰威士忌，”勃力森登回来时说道，“那穷小子只卖美国酒，我打了一夸脱[1]。”

“我叫孩子去买些柠檬来，咱们做甜酒喝。”马丁建议说。

“不知这本书能给马罗带来多少稿酬？”他把那本诗集举起来，接着说道。

“大概五十块钱吧。”对方回答，“其实，只要不赔钱，哄着出版商冒风险把书印出来，就已经是万幸的了。”

“如此看来，靠写诗是无法维持生活喽？”

马丁的口气及神色都显得十分沮丧。

“当然是不行的，只有傻瓜才抱那种指望。靠写打油诗，倒还可以。譬如，布鲁斯、弗吉尼亚·斯普林，还有塞奇威克，就干得相当出色。可是，写真正的诗歌就不行了。你知道沃恩·马罗是怎么度日的吗？他在宾夕法尼亚的一家私立男生小学校里教书，那儿可是天底下最糟糕的地方。就是让我再活上五十年，我也不愿同他交换位置。然而，他的作品比现代打油诗人的劣作要强到了天上，简直像是拿红宝石和胡萝卜相比。可评论家把他说得一钱不值！他妈的，那帮家伙全都愚不可及！”

“不会写文章的人偏偏要评论会写文章的人，他们写的东西满世界都是。”马丁颇有同感地说，“评论史蒂文森及其作品的糟粕文章，多得让人吃惊。”

“那是一群欺世盗名的坏蛋！”勃力森登咬牙切齿地说，“对，我了解那些杂种——他们得意地揪住那封为达米恩神甫写的辩护信[2]不放，挑史蒂文森的毛病，对他分析来衡量去——”

“全是用他们自己的那种可悲的自私自利标准对他衡量。”马丁插进来说。

“对，说得好，正是这样。那些家伙满口的‘真善美’，简直是在糟蹋人，末了还要在他背上拍一拍，说什么‘好样的，费多’。呸！难怪理查德·拉尔夫[3]临终的那天晚上称他们为‘叽叽喳喳的小人’。”

“他们是在挑星尘[4]的毛病，”马丁捡过话头，充满激情地说，“是在挑灿若朗星的伟人的毛病。我曾经写过一篇讽刺短文，抨击那些批评家——更确切些，那些评论家。”

“容我拜读一下。”勃力森登恳求道。

于是，马丁找出一份《星尘》的复写本。勃力森登看着看着，不由笑出了声，还搓着双手，竟然忘掉了喝他的甜酒。

“我觉得你自己就是一点星尘，落入了一个小人的世界，他们用毛巾蒙住眼睛，什么都看不见。”勃力森登读完文章后，这样评价道，“稿子一投出去，肯定就被杂志刊用了吧？”

马丁翻了翻投稿记录簿，说道：“遭到了二十七家杂志社的退稿。”

勃力森登原想开怀大笑一场，可是却剧烈地咳嗽了起来。

“不用说，你也写过诗。”他气喘吁吁地说，“拿几篇让我瞧瞧。”

“现在别看了吧。”马丁带着央求的口气说，“我想和你交谈呢。我为你捆扎好，你拿回去看。”

勃力森登辞别时，带走了《爱情组诗》以及《仙女与珍珠》。次日来时，他一见马丁的面就说：

“我想再看几篇。”

他坚信马丁是个真正的诗人，而马丁发现他也是位诗人。马丁对他的诗作大为佩服，当得知他从未做过发表的努力时，不由十分吃惊。

“愿天火烧掉所有的编辑部。”当马丁自告奋勇要为他的诗作找个出版的地方时，勃力森登这样说道，“你应该为了美而爱美，”他劝告说，“不要再向杂志社投稿了。马丁·伊登，我建议你回到轮船上去，回到大海上去。城市里到处都是病态和堕落的人，你有什么可留恋的呢？在这里，你为了迎合杂志的口味每一天都在出卖美，简直等于自杀。那天，你对我引用了一句什么话来着？——啊，对，‘人呀，最后诞生的蜉蝣。’请问，你这个最后诞生的蜉蝣要名有什么用呢？一旦得到了名，它反而会害了你。你太单纯、太朴实、太富于理性，我看你靠这种空洞的东西发不了迹。希望你永远也别向杂志出卖自己的半行诗作。你应该只效忠于美，为它尽心竭力，让功名利禄统统见鬼去吧！哼，狗屁成就！如果你的那首比亨利的《幽灵》还高明一等的似史蒂文森风格的十四行诗，以及《爱情组诗》和海洋诗算不上成就的话，那么，成就到底是什么呢？

“并非在大功告成时获得欢乐，而是在追求中寻觅喜悦。你不必说明，我非常清楚，你自己也明白。美对你来说是一种痛苦，一种没完没了的痛苦，它像永不愈合的伤口，似烧得火红的刀子。何必与杂志纠缠不清呢？让美作为你的目的吧。何必把美铸造成金币呢？反正你也做不到；所以我没必要为此而感到不安。你把杂志看上一千年，从中找到的价值也抵不上济慈[5]的一行诗句。不要再计较名利了，明天就到船上找份工作，返回大海去吧。”

“我追求的不是名，而是爱情。”马丁笑着说，“爱情在你的宇宙里似乎无存身之地，可在我的宇宙里，美只是爱情的使女。”

勃力森登望着他，目光中既有怜悯又包含着羡慕。“你这么年轻，小马丁，如此地年轻。你想展翅高空，但你的翅膀是用最薄的纱织成，上面涂着最华丽的色粉。小心别烧焦了你的翅膀。啧，事实是它们已被烧焦。难道《爱情组诗》非得是为了讴歌女人吗？这话让人觉得脸红。”

“它讴歌爱情，也讴歌女人。”马丁哈哈大笑道。

“疯人的哲理。”对方回敬道，“抽了大麻烟，游历于梦境时，我才会这么想。劝你还是小心为妙。这种资产阶级味十足的城市会毁掉你的。就拿我跟你相遇的那个市侩窝而言吧，说它‘腐败透顶’还太客气了些。在那种气氛中无法保持神志清醒。真是堕落啊。他们当中，无论男女，没有一个不堕落。他们腹中装着蛤肉，从蛤蟹那儿获取高度理性及艺术的灵感——”

他突然停了下来，打量着马丁。接着，他猛地恍然大悟，明白了过来，脸上的表情变得又诧异又惊恐。

“你的那首美妙绝伦的《爱情组诗》原来是写给她——一个苍白、干瘪的女人！”

一眨眼的工夫，马丁刷地伸出右手，一把紧卡住他的脖子，使他透不过气来，摇得他上下牙直打架。可是马丁在他的眼睛里看不到恐惧的表情，只有一种惊异和嘲讽的神色。马丁觉得自己这样做不对，于是便揪住勃力森登的脖子，把他按倒在床上，同时松开了手。

勃力森登痛苦地喘了会儿粗气，而后咯咯笑了起来。

“你要是真把我摇死了，到了黄泉之下我还得感激你呢。”他说。

“这些日子我的脾气太糟糕，一触即发，”马丁道歉说，“希望没伤着你。来，让我为你掺一杯甜酒喝。”

“嘿，你这棒小伙子！”勃力森登说，“不知你是不是为你的身体感到自豪。你强壮得很哩，简直是一只小豹，一头幼小的雄狮。可老天知道，你必须为这副好身板付出代价。”

“这话是什么意思？”马丁把酒杯递给他，不解地问，“来，把酒喝了，别再胡言乱语了。”

“因为——”勃力森登呷了口酒，满意地笑了笑，“因为女人呗。她们会纠缠你，一直把你缠死。她们已把你缠得够呛，我又不是昨天才出生的小孩，哪能不知道。你大可不必再卡我的脖子了，我反正要把话说出来的。毫无疑问，你们之间产生了年轻人的爱情；可是，看在‘美’的分上，下次可得把对象选好啊。你为什么要跟一个资产阶级的小姐儿女情长呢？算啦，别跟她来往了。劝你挑个感情奔放、不贪生、不怕死、一爱到底的伟大女子吧。世上是有这样的女子的，她们的爱也可以像娇生惯养、羞怯的资产阶级小姐的爱那样缠绵。”

“怎么是羞怯？”马丁不服地问。

“对，正是羞怯。她们满口谈的都是褊狭的伦理观，那是别人灌入她们脑子里去的。她们惧怕真正的生活。她们也许会爱上你，但她们更爱自己褊狭的伦理观。你需要的是无拘无束的生活和自由自在的精神，需要的是绚丽多彩的蝴蝶，而非灰色的小飞蛾。唉，你要是没死的福分，残留于人世的话，你对她们也会感到厌倦的，厌倦所有的女人。不过，你会死去的。你绝不会搭乘轮船重返大海，而是继续逗留在这些满世界都是害虫的城市里，直至骨朽肉烂，一命升西。”

“你可以给我上大道理，我不想跟你拌嘴。”马丁说，“不管怎样，你的观点是由你的性格决定的，而我的观点也同样不可动摇。”

在爱情方面、为杂志撰稿方面以及许多其他的事情上，他们两人意见不统一，可他们彼此喜欢对方；马丁对勃力森登的感情是非常深的。两人天天见面，但勃力森登顶多只在马丁那密不透风的房间待上个把钟点。他每次来都随身带着一夸脱威士忌，上街吃饭时，他把威士忌和苏打水从头喝到尾。两人的饭钱总是由他清付，马丁在他的邀请下吃到了美味佳肴，第一次喝到了香槟酒，还品尝上了莱茵葡萄酒。

可是，勃力森登始终都叫人琢磨不透。尽管他看上去像是个苦行者，尽管他脸无血色，但他一味地纵酒狂饮。他不怕死，对一切事物都抱着仇视和愤世嫉俗的态度；可是在苟延残喘之际，他却显得热爱生活，热爱生活的每一个细节。他怀着一种疯狂的劲去咀嚼生活和寻求刺激，正如他曾经说过的那样“我来到凡尘世间，就应该索取我的一点小小的空间”。他吸过毒，干过许多离奇古怪的事，为的是寻求新的刺激和感受。有一回他告诉马丁，说他曾经一连三天不喝水，而且是有意这样做，为的是体会一旦喝水后渴感消除时的那种妙不可言的欢乐。

他究竟是何人，或怎样一个人，马丁始终都没弄清楚。他是一个没有过去的人，他的将来是近在眼前的坟墓，而他的现在是一种痛苦和狂热的生活。

[1]　1夸脱=1.101升。

[2]　达米恩于1873年自愿赴麻风病区为患者服务，死后遭到诽谤。史蒂文森发表了《给海德神学博士的一封公开信》，伸张正义。

[3]　19世纪美国诗人。

[4]　此处比喻杰出人物。

[5]　19世纪英国著名浪漫派诗人。

第三十三章

马丁在拼战当中一输再输。随他怎样精打细算，卖作品得来的钱都不够和支出保持平衡。感恩节来临之际，他把黑西装送入了当铺，这下不能应邀到摩斯家赴宴了。他推辞的理由叫露丝很不高兴，由此把他逼到了山穷水尽的地步。他跟露丝说，他一定去赴宴；还说他要到旧金山去，找《横贯大陆月刊》索要他那五块钱的稿酬，然后把西装赎回来。

早晨，他问玛丽亚借了一角钱。他原来想向勃力森登借钱，可那个行踪不定的家伙不见了踪影。马丁已经两个星期没见他的面了，绞尽脑汁也没想出自己到底是哪些地方得罪了他。马丁用借来的这一角钱搭渡船来到旧金山，边在市场街上走，边思想着万一要不到稿酬，自己的处境将会多么艰难。到了那时，他连奥克兰也回不去了，因为他在旧金山一个熟人也没有，没办法再借到一角钱。

《横贯大陆月刊》编辑部的房门微微开着，马丁正要推门进去，里边传来一阵大喊大叫，使他猛地收住了脚步。只听有人嚷嚷道：“可问题不在这里，福特先生。”（马丁从收到的信件中知道，福特是那位编辑的名字。）“问题在于，你打算不打算付钱？——我是说付现金，马上付清。对于《横贯大陆月刊》的前景以及你来年的打算，我不感兴趣。我只想拿到我的工钱。现在跟你把话说清楚，除非我拿到钱，否则《横贯大陆月刊》的圣诞号就别指望排印。再见，有钱的时候再去找我吧。”

房门猛地开了，那人怒容满面，嘴里骂骂咧咧，紧攥着拳头，冲过马丁身边，顺着甬道走了。马丁决定不马上进去，就在门口徘徊了有一刻钟的时间，然后才推开门走了进去。这是一种新鲜的体验，因为他以前从没踏入过编辑部的门槛。在这个编辑部显然不需要名片，只见一位杂役跑入里间屋通报有人要见福特先生。杂役出来时，隔着半间屋子召他过去，把他引入密室——编辑的私室。马丁产生的第一印象就是：屋里乱七八糟，没一点秩序。紧接着，他注意到一位长着络腮胡子但很面嫩的人正坐在一张活动盖面的写字台旁，好奇地打量着他。马丁见他神态安详，不禁觉得纳闷，跟印刷商的争执看来并没有影响他平静的心绪。

“我——我叫马丁·伊登。”马丁启口说道。（他真想直言：“我要取回我那五块钱的稿费。”）

然而，这是他见到的第一个编辑，在这种情况下他不想一下子就把编辑吓坏。令他感到意外的是，福特先生一跳老高，说了声“怎么不早说！”，紧接着就用双手握住马丁的手，热情地摇着。

“你不知道，我见到你有多高兴，伊登先生。我一直想知道你到底长得什么样子。”

说着，他伸直胳膊，把马丁稍微推开一些，用一双欣喜的眼睛打量着马丁的那身次一等的衣服——也是马丁的末等衣服，破旧得已无法修补，不过裤缝线倒是笔挺，那是他用玛丽亚的熨铁精心熨出来的。

“老实讲，我没想到你会这么年轻。你的小说写得雄浑、有力、成熟、深刻，是一篇杰作，我刚读了六七行就看出来了，让我来讲讲头一次拜读大作时的感受吧。噢，不，还是先介绍你跟我的同仁认识一下吧！”

福特先生边说，边把他领进了大办公室，将他介绍给副编辑怀特先生，一个又瘦又小的人儿，手冰得出奇，就好像正在患冷病，稀稀拉拉的小羊胡子如丝一般光滑。

“还有，这位是恩兹先生，伊登先生。恩兹先生是我们的业务经理。”

握手时，马丁发现对方目光古怪，脑袋谢了顶，大半个脸都被雪白的胡须遮盖着，但从能看得到的一小部分脸蛋判断，那人倒是显得相当年轻。那胡须是由对方的妻子在星期日仔细修剪出来的，而且，他的妻子还同时为他刮颈后的汗毛。

三个人围住马丁，七嘴八舌说着钦慕的话，让马丁觉得他们似乎在比赛看谁讲得快。

“我们常常感到纳闷，弄不清你为什么不到敝社来。”怀特先生说。

“我没有买车票的钱，而且我住在海湾对面。”马丁单刀直入地答道，目的是想表明自己迫切需要拿到那笔稿酬。

他心想，光凭我这身破旧的衣服，就足以说明我的困难境地了。一有机会，他就暗示他的来意，暗示了好几次，可他的钦慕者却像聋子一样。他们夸奖着他，述说着他们看到他的那篇小说时的第一感受以及后来的感受，述说着他们的妻子和家里人的感受，但他们绝口不提付稿费的事情。

“我跟你讲起过我初次拜读你的那篇小说时的情景吗？”福特先生说，“显然，我没跟你谈起过。当时，我正乘车从纽约西行。列车停在奥格顿站时，新接班的乘务员把一份刚刚出版的《横贯大陆月刊》带上了车。”

我的上帝啊！马丁心想，你们可以乘坐普尔门豪华列车旅行，却抠着我那可怜的五块钱稿费不放，让我忍饥挨饿。他觉得《横贯大陆月刊》对他太不公平，不由清楚地回忆起自己数月来无望的等待、与饥寒相伴的悲惨情形。此时此刻，他肚里的饥火升腾起来，痛苦地折磨着他，这使他想起自己前天只吃了一丁点食物，而自那以后粒米未进。一时间，他怒不可遏。这些畜生不仅仅是强盗，还是一群鬼鬼祟祟的小偷。他们出尔反尔，把他写的小说骗到了手。好么，他要让他们瞧瞧他的厉害。他心里暗暗下定了决心：拿不到钱，绝不离开编辑部。他想起，如果要不回稿费，他就无法返回奥克兰了。他使劲控制着自己的情绪，但脸上却露出了一副凶相，吓得他们惊慌了起来。

他们讲得越发滔滔不绝了。福特先生又在讲他第一次拜读《嘹亮的钟声》时的情形，而恩兹先生却抢着复述他的那位在阿拉米达当教师的侄女对《嘹亮的钟声》的赞誉之辞。

“我讲讲我的来意吧，”马丁终于说道，“我来拿你们全都非常喜欢的那篇小说的稿酬。记得你们曾答应过，一刊出就付给我五块钱。”福特先生那表情多变的脸上立刻露出一副欣然同意的神色，伸手就去掏口袋，可半截却猛然把身子转向恩兹先生，说他把钱忘到家里了。这话显然叫恩兹先生很生气；马丁见他抽搐了一下胳膊，像是保护他的裤兜，便明白钱就放在那里。

“很抱歉，”恩兹先生说，“刚付过印刷商的账还不到一个小时，他把我手头的钱都拿走了；那笔账其实还不该付，可那印刷商硬是要求立即交预付款，真是出乎人的意料。”

两个人一齐把期待的眼光投向怀特先生，可那位先生哈哈大笑，耸了耸肩膀，反正他是问心无愧的。他来《横贯大陆月刊》原是想学习杂志文学，谁知学到的却主要是关于金钱的学问。《横贯大陆月刊》欠了他四个月的薪水，他明白先得满足印刷商，然后才轮到副编辑。

“伊登先生，瞧瞧我们这副样子，真是太不成体统了。”福特先生以一种轻松的口气说道，“老实讲，这全是粗心大意造成的。不过，我要告诉你我们应该怎么做，明天早晨第一件事就是把支票给你寄去。你有伊登先生的地址吧，恩兹先生？”

恩兹先生说他有马丁的地址，并答应明天早晨一定寄支票。马丁对银行的支票之类的事情懵懵懂懂，可他觉得他们没理由非得等到第二天再把支票给他，认为今天给他也是一样的。

“那就一言为定，伊登先生，我们明天把支票寄给你，好吗？”福特先生说。

“我今天就要拿到钱。”马丁斩钉截铁地回答。

“事情很不凑巧，如果你换一天来的话。”福特先生那温文尔雅的话语刚说到此处，就被恩兹先生打断了。后者发起了脾气，一双古怪的眼睛愈发显得古怪了。

“福特先生已把情况解释清楚了，”他粗暴无礼地说，“我也讲明白了。支票会寄给——”

“我也把话说清了，”马丁打断他的话说，“我讲过，今天就要拿到钱。”

业务经理的无礼使他的脉搏跳动有些加快。他警惕地注视着对方，因为他猜想《横贯大陆月刊》的现金就装在那位先生的裤兜里。

“真是过意不去。”福特先生开口说道。

就在这当儿，恩兹先生不耐烦地转过身去，像是要不辞而别。说时迟，那时快，马丁扑上前去，一把扼住他的喉管，使他那依然整齐得无可挑剔的雪白的山羊胡子成四十五度角朝天翘起。怀特先生和福特先生看到他们的业务经理被抖得像一条阿斯特拉罕[1]羔羊地毯一样，不由惊恐万状。

“把钱掏出来，你这刁难才华初露的年轻人的老混蛋！”马丁威吓道，“快掏，不然我就把钱从你身上抖出来，即便全是硬币也可以。”随后，他又冲着旁边的那两个吓得半死的人喊道：“别到跟前来！如果谁敢插手，就叫他受点伤。”

恩兹先生喘不过气来，直到卡住他喉管的那只手松开，他才能够表示愿意掏钱。掏了几次，他从裤兜里总共拿出了四块一毛五分钱。

“把口袋翻出来！”马丁喝令道。

结果，裤兜里又掉出一角钱。马丁把搜出的钱连数了两遍，生怕弄错。

“该你了！”他冲着福特先生叫喊道，“再交出七角五分钱。”

福特先生毫不迟疑地把口袋都搜了个遍，结果掏出了六角钱。

“真的就这么一点？”马丁把钱拿到手，威胁地问道，“你的背心口袋里装的是什么？”

为了表示诚意，福特先生把两个背心口袋翻了个底朝天。一张硬纸片从一个口袋里掉到了地板上。他把硬纸片捡起来，正要放回口袋，却听马丁叫喊道：

“这是什么？——是轮渡票吧？把它给我。这张票值一角钱，就记在我的账上吧。算上这张票，我总共拿到了四元九角五分钱。还差我五分钱。”

他恶狠狠地拿眼睛去瞧怀特先生，看到那个脆弱的家伙正把一枚五分钱的硬币递过来。

“谢谢你们，”马丁冲着他们全体说，“再见啦。”

“强盗！”恩兹先生冲着他的背影咆哮道。

“小偷！”马丁回敬说，出去时砰的一声摔上了门。

马丁高兴得发疯，一想起《大黄蜂》刊用了他的《仙女与珍珠》，欠他十五块钱的稿酬，当下就决定去要钱。可是，办《大黄蜂》杂志的是一伙油头粉面、魁梧强壮的年轻人，他们是明目张胆的强盗，见钱就捞，见人就抢，相互之间也尔虞我诈。办公室的家具被打坏了几样。可最后那位编辑（大学时代的运动健将）在业务经理、广告人以及杂役的大力协助下，终于把马丁搡出了办公室，并猛一用力将他推下了第一段楼梯。

“下次再来吧，伊登先生；随时都欢迎你莅临。”他们居高临下地站在楼梯顶端，冲着马丁哈哈笑着说。

马丁站起身来，咧嘴笑了笑。

“呸！”他喃喃地回敬道，“《横贯大陆月刊》那帮人是雌山羊，可你们这些家伙全是职业拳击手。”

这话又引起了一阵笑声。

“我承认，伊登先生，”《大黄蜂》的编辑冲着下边喊道，“作为一个诗人，你自己也很有两下子。请问，你的‘右勾拳’是从哪里学来的？”

“是从你学到‘扼颈’的那个地方学来的，”马丁答道，“等着吧，总有一天我会揍你个鼻青脸肿。”

“但愿你的脖子还能够动弹。”编辑关心地说，“咱们大伙儿出去喝一杯——当然不是为了庆祝你的脖子，而是为了庆祝这次小小的战斗，你看怎么样？”

“喝不过你们，钱就由我出。”马丁赞同地说。

于是，强盗们和受害人一起开怀痛饮，并和和气气地做出了决定：根据“强食弱肉”的原则，《仙女与珍珠》的十五块钱稿费理应属于《大黄蜂》编辑部的成员。

[1]　俄国一城市，因产羔羊皮而出名。

第三十四章

阿瑟留在院门口，而露丝登上了玛丽亚屋前的台阶。她听到了咔嗒咔嗒的打字声，待马丁开门迎她进屋后，发现他正在打印一页稿件。她来是想落实他是否到她家赴感恩节宴会；可是未等她提出这个话题，马丁倒先急切地端出了自己正在忙碌的事情。

“来，让我给你念念这篇文章。”他嚷嚷道，把复写的副本一页页揭掉，将稿纸一张张整理在一起，“这是我的最新作品，与以前写的东西都不一样。它是那样不同凡响，简直叫我有些害怕，可我心里有一种隐约的感觉，这是一篇佳作。你来评判一下吧。这是一个关于夏威夷的故事，我给它起名叫《维基-维基》。”

他心怀创作的喜悦，满脸奕奕闪光，可她却在寒气逼人的房间里打着哆嗦，而且刚才握手时她就觉得他的手冷冰冰的。她侧耳倾听他朗读，而他时不时地发现她脸上只有不满的表情，可是在读完之后他还是问道：

“坦率地说，你觉得怎么样？”

“我——我说不出来。”她答道，“你认为——你认为这篇文章能卖出去吗？”

“恐怕卖不出去，”对方诚实地说，“对杂志而言，它太激烈了。可它是真实的，我保证是真实的。”

“你明明知道卖不出去，可你为什么偏要写这类东西呢？”她毫不留情地说，“你写作的动机是为了谋生，不对吗？”

“对，正是这样；可是这段悲惨的故事迷住了我。我欲罢不能，非得把它写出来才能心静。”

“可你笔下的那个叫‘维基-维基’的人物，说出的话为什么那样粗俗呢？这肯定会触怒读者，当然，这也是编辑拒绝接受你的作品的原因。”

“因为真正的维基-维基就是那样讲话的。”

“这样写难登大雅之堂。”

“这是生活，”他率直地说，“是有血有肉真实的生活。我必须按自己看到的情况描写生活。”

她没吱声，两人都感到很窘，于是相对无语干坐了一会儿。他爱她，所以不能够彻底地了解她，而她不能够理解他，是因为他过于巍峨高大，超出于她的天地之外。

“唔，我从《横贯大陆月刊》拿到了稿费，”他试图换一个较为愉快的话题，便这样说道。一想到那三个络腮胡子被迫交出四元九角五分钱和一张轮渡票的情景，一想到最后看到的他们的那副样子，他哑然失笑。

“这么说，你一定去喽！”她高兴地喊了起来，“我来这儿的目的就是为了落实这件事。”

“去？”他心不在焉地喃喃道，“去哪儿？”

“去赴明天的宴会呀。你知道，你曾说过一拿到那笔钱就把衣服赎回来。”

“这我可全忘了。”他低声下气地说，“事情是这样的，今天早晨牲畜管理员扣下了玛丽亚的两条母牛和一头小牛——唉，玛丽亚碰巧手头没钱，所以我只好替她把牛赎了回来，《横贯大陆月刊》的那五块钱都花在了这上边——《嘹亮的钟声》的稿酬进了牲畜管理员的腰包。”“那你不去赴宴啦？”

他低头看了看自己身上的衣服。

“去不成了。”

失望和责备的泪水在她那蓝色的眼睛里闪亮，可她什么也没说。

“明年感恩节我和你将会在德尔摩尼哥饭店[1]设宴，”他乐呵呵地说，“要不就到伦敦去，到巴黎去，或者到你想去的任何地方去。这一点我是胸中有数的。”

“几天前我在报上看到，”她猛不愣丁地说，“铁道邮递处在当地录用了几名员工。考试时你曾名登榜首，是不是这样呢？”

他只好承认说，他曾接到过录用通知，但他谢绝了。“我当时对自己充满了信心——现在仍然如此。”他最后说道，“从现在起再过一年的时间，我的收入将会超过铁道邮递处员工十几倍。你等着瞧吧。”

待他把话说完，她仅仅唉了一声，然后站起身朝上扯了扯手套。“我得走了，马丁，阿瑟在等我呢。”

他把她搂在怀里吻，可她却是一副消极被动的样子。她的躯体没有绷紧，胳膊没有去拥抱他，接吻时嘴唇缺乏往日的活力。

他从门口返回时，认定她在生他的气。但这是为什么呢？糟就糟在牲畜管理员扣下了玛丽亚的牛。可那是天降的横祸，谁也怨不成。他根本想不到自己完全可以采取另外一种态度。接下来，他思忖着自己有一些理该责怪之处，因为他谢绝了铁道邮递处的通知书。再说，她不喜欢《维基-维基》。

他登上台阶顶端时转过身来，迎住了下午来送信的邮差，他接过一捆长信封，那种周而复始的狂热期望又袭上了心头。有一封信用的不是长信封。这一封又短又薄，外面印着《纽约眺望》的通讯处。他正要拆信，却半截停下了手。这不可能是录稿通知书，因为他没给那家杂志社投过稿。也许——一经产生这种不着边际的念头，他的心脏几乎停止了跳动——也许这是向他约稿呢；但随即他便推翻了这种猜测，认为这是绝对不可能的。

这是一封由现任编辑署名的正规短函，信上仅仅告知他随信附来了一封他们收到的匿名信，并让他放心，说《纽约眺望》编辑部无论在任何情况下都不会理睬匿名信件。

马丁发现附来的那封信由印刷体书写，写得很蹩脚。这封信杂乱无章、文理不通，把马丁大骂了一顿，一口咬定向杂志兜售短篇故事的“所谓的马丁·伊登”根本就不会写作，实际上只会从旧杂志上剽窃文章，用打字机打好后充当自己的作品寄出。信封上盖的是“圣莱安德罗”的邮戳。马丁不用多想，就知道是谁写的了，通篇显而易见的是希金波森的文法、希金波森的口头语、希金波森的怪点子和思维方式。马丁在字里行间看到的不是意大利人[2]的那种娟秀的笔体，而是他那位食品商姐夫拙劣的墨迹。

可这是为什么呢？他百思不得其解。他哪一点得罪了伯纳德·希金波森呢？这件事真是蹊跷异常、荒唐透顶，连一点道理都讲不通。一星期之内，有十几封类似的信从东部各杂志社的编辑那儿接二连三地转到了马丁手中。马丁觉得那些编辑表现得非常出色。他和他们素昧平生，可他们当中有些人甚至对他表示同情。显然，他们讨厌匿名信。他看得出，那妄图败坏他名誉的恶人已遭到了失败。其实，即便匿名信产生了影响，那也一定是好的影响，因为他的名字至少引起了部分编辑的注意。也许，他们在收到他投的稿件时，会想起他就是匿名信中提到的人。也许，这种记忆会改变他们的看法，使其稍微偏向对他有利的一边，这谁能说得准呢？

差不多就是在这段时间，马丁在玛丽亚心目中的威望却一落千丈。一天早晨，他看到她在厨房里痛苦地呻吟着，虚弱得脸上直淌泪，想把一大堆衣服全都熨好，可又力不从心。他立刻断定她患了流感，便让她喝了杯热威士忌（那是勃力森登的酒瓶子中剩下的），吩咐她躺到床上去。可玛丽亚硬是不肯，说必须把衣服熨出来，当晚就送去，否则明天就没有东西可给那七个饿着肚子的小西尔瓦吃。

她不无吃惊地看到马丁·伊登从炉子上抓起熨斗，将一件花哨的女式衬衫扔在了熨衣板上（后来她老爱提起这件事，直至死的那一天）。那是凯特·弗拉纳根最体面的一件衬衫，而弗拉纳根又是玛丽亚的圈子里要求最苛刻、穿着最讲究的一个女人。况且，弗拉纳根小姐特别叮咛过，必须当晚就把衬衫送去。众所周知，她跟铁匠约翰·柯林斯打得火热。玛丽亚还暗地里了解到，弗拉纳根小姐和柯林斯先生第二天要到金门公园去。玛丽亚原想把衬衫抢过来，可没能做到。在马丁的搀扶下，她摇摇晃晃坐到了一把椅子上，鼓着眼睛从那儿观看他干活。她见他很快就把衬衫平平安安熨好了，这活让她干得花四倍的时间。她必须承认，马丁熨烫的本事一点都不比她差。

“如果你的熨斗再热一些，”他解释道，“我可以干得更快。”

在她看来，他使用的熨斗已经比她胆敢使用的要热得多了。

“你喷水的方法全是错误的，”他接下来说道，“啧，让我来教你怎样喷水吧。关键的一点是要用力。如欲熨得快，就得用力喷。”

他从地下室的柴堆那儿弄来一只木箱，在上面安了个盖，然后用西尔瓦家的孩子收集来准备卖破烂的废铁做了配件。把刚喷好水的衣服放入箱子，盖上盖，拿熨斗压住，这套装置就算大功告成，可以投入使用了。

“你瞧着我做给你看，”他说着，脱下身上的衣服，只剩下一件汗衫，一把抓起他称之为“真正热”的熨斗。

“他熨完了手中的活，就洗毛料品。”玛丽亚后来这样叙述道，“他说：‘玛丽亚，你真笨到家了，我来教你怎么洗毛料品吧。’说完，他给我示范了一通。他用了十分钟的时间，制造了一台机器——一只大桶、一个轮毂、两根杆子，就这么多部件。”

马丁的这套装置是在雪莱温泉旅馆从乔那儿学来的。旧轮毂安装在一根垂直杆的一端，当作冲板用。再把这冲板固定在弹簧杆上，然后将弹簧杆安在厨房的椽子上。这样，轮毂便可以冲压桶中的毛料，用一只手操作就能够干得非常出色。

“我再没有洗过毛料品。”玛丽亚回忆往事时总以这样的话作为结尾，“我让孩子们操纵那杆子、轮毂和大桶。伊登先生真是个聪明人。”可是，正由于他洗熨技巧娴熟，而且帮她改造了厨房里的洗衣设备，他在她心目中的地位才一落千丈。她一向在想象中给他披上一层绚丽的传奇色彩，而今了解到了残酷的事实，知道他曾经当过洗衣工，这种色彩便烟消云散了。他的那些书，那些乘着马车或怀揣无数瓶威士忌前来看望他的贵客，全都失去了价值。他只不过是一个工人，与她共处同一阶级、同一阶层。他比以前更富有人性，更平易近人了，但他已经不再是个神秘人物。

马丁和家里的亲戚愈来愈疏远。继希金波森先生无缘无故对他进行攻击之后，赫尔曼·冯·施米特先生也露出了狰狞面目。由于幸运地卖掉了几篇短篇故事、几首幽默诗和几则笑话，马丁钱囊充盈，一下子阔绰起来。他不仅还清了部分欠款，手头仍很宽余，足可以赎回黑西装和自行车。自行车上的脚踏杆扭歪了，需要修理，他想和未来的妹夫套近乎，就把车子送进了冯·施米特的修理铺。

当天下午，一个小男孩就把车子送了回来，这叫他感到很高兴。他觉得这是对他的一种非同寻常的恩惠，因为修好的车子一般都得自己去取，于是便认定冯·施米特也想和他亲近。但他一检查，却发现车子根本就没有修。隔了一会儿，他给妹妹的未婚夫打了个电话，方才知道对方不愿同他有“任何种类、任何方面、任何形式”的交往。

“赫尔曼·冯·施米特，”马丁以轻松的语气说，“我真想去揍扁你那猪鼻子。”

“你敢踏进我的铺子，”对方答道，“我就报警，我要让你吃不了兜着走。哼，我了解你这号人，你可别想在我跟前逞强。我不愿和你这种人有任何来往。你是个二流子，就是这么回事，我可没有看错人。别以为我要娶你的妹妹，你就能揩我的油。你为什么不去找份工作，老老实实挣钱过日子呢？你说呀！”

马丁的人生观此刻发生了作用，打消了他心中的怒火。他又诧异又好笑，长长地吹了声口哨，放下了听筒。但随着这种好笑的感觉旋即而至的是另外一种感觉——一种孤独感压上了他的心头。除了勃力森登，没有人理解他，没有人喜欢他，可勃力森登销声匿迹了，只有上帝才知道他去了哪里。

暮色垂降时，马丁出了果品店，捧着买好的东西朝家走去，在街角处，一辆电车停了下来，他看到一个熟悉的瘦削身影下了车，高兴得心儿直跳。那是勃力森登！电车启动之前，马丁飞眼瞧见他的两个外衣口袋鼓鼓囊囊的，一个装的是书，另一个装着一夸脱威士忌。

[1]　纽约的一家著名饭店。

[2]　此处指专干敲诈、勒索的黑手党人。

第三十五章

勃力森登绝口不提自己为何长时间不露面，马丁也没有追问。透过甜酒杯中散发出的热气，能看到朋友那张灰白的面孔，他已经心满意足了。

“我也没有闲混日子。”听马丁如数家珍地列举了自己撰写的作品之后，勃力森登这般宣称。

他从上衣里边的口袋取出一份手稿，递给了马丁，而马丁一瞧题目，便诧异地抬起头来。

“不错，就是这么回事，”勃力森登哈哈笑着说，“题目起得非常妙，对吧？《蜉蝣》——就这两个字。这还得感谢你呢，因为你曾说过人是一种始终直立的、有生命的无机物，是最后诞生的蜉蝣，是一种有体温的生物，在温度计那弹丸之地上还要昂首阔步。我当时就产生了想法，非得写出来才能安心。请讲一下你的看法吧。”

马丁先是脸上泛红潮，但把文章看下去，面色便转为苍白了。这是一篇十全十美的艺术佳作。形式战胜了内容（如果这能称其为“战胜”的话），可是内容的每一点一滴都在无懈可击的结构中给表现了出来，叫马丁高兴得头发昏，激动得眼里涌出泪水，只觉得背上发冷，像有条小虫爬上爬下。这是首六七百行的长诗，是那样奇特、神妙和超尘脱俗。真是美得令人不可思议，可它白纸黑字就在眼前。它描写的是人类以及人类最高形式的心灵探索，描写人类是怎样探索茫茫无际的太空，寻找最遥远的恒星和彩虹光谱的明证。这是一个垂死之人头脑中闪现出的狂放和疯狂的幻想，此人低声饮泣，从衰弱心脏的一阵猛烈跳动中汲取灵感。这首诗以庄严的韵律，随着冷澈的星球之间的混战、万千星辰的冲撞、寒气袭入的恒星的碰击以及黑暗的太空中星云的焚烧抑扬起伏；而透过这一切，回响着人类那隐隐约约、不绝如缕的尖细、微弱的声音，似银梭的嗖嗖声，于行星的呼啸和星系之间的碰撞声中，这就宛若一声哀鸣。

“这在文学作品中是绝无仅有的。”马丁最后终于能够说出话来了，“真是妙啊！——太了不起了！它使我感到兴奋，使我陶然若醉。这是一个既伟大又无限渺小的问题——我无法把它排出我的思想。人类的那种探求真理、长久连绵的微弱哀鸣声，现在仍在我的耳边回荡。它活似吼狮啸声中一只蚊虫发出的凄惨鸣叫。它诉说着人类那微不足道的欲望还没有得到满足。我知道自己在说傻话，可这篇东西叫我着了迷。你实在——我不知道你是怎样一个人——但你真是了不起，就是这么回事。你是怎么写成的呢？到底是怎么写的呢？”

马丁打住了狂热的话头，但片刻之后又滔滔不绝讲了起来。

“我从今往后再也不写作了。我的作品拙劣，只是胡涂乱抹，而你让我看到了真正艺术巨匠的手笔。不愧为天才！你比天才还天才，是超天才的天才。你讲的是四海皆准的真理，句句都真实可信。朋友，不知你意识到这一点没有，你这个武断者，科学可以证实你的话。这是愤世嫉俗者的真理，从黑铁板似的宇宙冲压出来，与壮丽的音律交织在一起，汇成一幅灿烂辉煌的美景。现在，我一句多余的话都不想再说了。我激动得难以自禁。对，我也要付诸行动。让我来把你的作品推向市场吧。”

勃力森登咧嘴笑了。“在基督教世界，没有一家杂志社敢登这篇作品——这你是知道的。”

“我并不知道。我只知道，在基督教世界，没有一家杂志社不会抢着登哩。这样的作品可不是天天都能够见得到。这不仅仅是今年最杰出的诗作，也是本世纪最出类拔萃的诗篇。”

“我敢说你一定会碰一鼻子灰。”

“你不必愤世嫉俗，”马丁规劝道，“杂志社的编辑并非全都是白痴。这我知道，我敢跟你打这个赌。跟你赌什么都行，我敢说《蜉蝣》第一次投稿或第二次投稿，就会被刊用。”

“只是有一条原因使我不能跟你打这个赌。”勃力森登停顿了一会儿，“这是篇伟大的作品——是我所撰写的最伟大的作品。这我是清楚的。它是我的绝笔，我为之感到十分自豪。我崇拜它，认为它比威士忌还要美妙。当我还是个单纯的青年、心怀甜蜜的梦幻及纯洁的理想时，就梦想着要写出这种伟大、完美的东西。如今，我总算如愿以偿，把它写了出来。我可不愿把它交给一群笨蛋糟蹋和玷污。不，我不打这个赌。它是我的，是我创作的，只跟你一道欣赏。”

“可你也得考虑考虑全世界的人呀，”马丁不赞同地说，“美的作用在于给人以欢乐。”

“这是我创造的美，我想怎样就怎样。”

“别太自私了。”

“我并非自私。”勃力森登不动声色地咧嘴一笑——每当为自己的两片薄嘴唇即将说出的话感到得意时，他总是这副表情，“我的无私无异于一只饥肠辘辘的猪。”

马丁再怎样劝，都无法使他改变自己的决定。马丁告诉他说，他对杂志的仇恨既偏执又盲目，这种行径比那个放火烧掉以弗所的狄安娜神庙的青年[1]做出的事情还要可鄙一千倍。面对暴风骤雨般的指责，勃力森登悠然自得地呷着甜酒，承认对方的话句句真实，只是除了对杂志编辑的看法。他恨编辑恨得咬牙切齿，抨击他们时比马丁的言辞还为激烈。

“希望你能用打字机为我把它打出来。”他说，“论打字，你比哪个速记员都可以强上一千倍。现在，我想给你提点建议。”他从上衣外边的口袋里掏出厚厚一叠手稿，“这是你的《太阳的耻辱》。我看了不是一遍，而是两三遍，足见我对你是极为钦佩的。听过你针对《蜉蝣》说的那番话后，我只好保持沉默了。不过有一点我要说明：《太阳的耻辱》一经问世，必将引起轰动。它将引起一场论战，单就广告价值而言就值千金呢。”

马丁笑了。“大概你接下来就会建议我把它投给杂志社吧。”

“千万别那样做——就是说，如果你想让它出版的话，该把它交给第一流的出版社。也许某个审稿人会头脑发疯或喝醉了酒，对它提出好评。你博览群书，而你马丁·伊登的大脑从书中提炼出精华，倾注在《太阳的耻辱》一文中。总有一天，马丁·伊登会出名，而他的名声主要靠的是这部佳作。所以，你必须为它找个出版商——愈快愈好。”

这天夜里，勃力森登回去得很迟。他刚踩上电车的第一级踏板，便猛然转过身来，将紧紧揉在一起的一个小纸团塞到马丁的手里。

“拿上吧，”他说，“今天我去赌赛马，押对了注。”

铃儿叮当响了一声，电车开走了，抛下马丁一个人，顾自寻思手里握着的那团皱巴巴、油腻腻的东西到底是什么。回到自己的房间后，他把那团东西展开一看，原来是张一百块钱的钞票。

他毫不迟疑地就把钱用了。他知道自己的这位朋友手头总是有许多钱，也十分肯定地知道，自己一旦成功，就能够把钱还回去。次日早晨，他清付了每一笔债务，预付了三个月的房钱给玛丽亚，还去当铺把当掉的东西全赎了回来。接着，他为玛丽安买了结婚礼品，还买了些较为简单的礼物，适宜作圣诞礼物用，准备送给露丝和葛特露。最后，他带着剩下的钱，把西尔瓦全家领到了奥克兰去。他迟了一年才履行去年冬天许下的诺，但他的话总算兑现了，让西尔瓦全家，包括最小的孩子以及玛丽亚本人，都得到了一双鞋子。另外，还有喇叭、洋娃娃和各种各样的玩具、大包小包的糖果及坚果，使西尔瓦一家每个人的怀里都捧得满满的。

这支古里古怪的队伍尾随在他和玛丽亚的身后，浩浩荡荡开进一家糖果店，想买一根最大的棒棒糖。正是在这种状况下，他碰上了露丝母女。摩斯夫人大为震惊。连露丝也感到伤心，因为她毕竟有点爱面子。她的恋人和玛丽亚紧挨在一起，统领着一群衣衫褴褛的葡萄牙小孩，让人看起来着实不雅。但更叫她伤心的是，她看得出来他缺乏自爱和自尊之心。另外，通过这一番情景，她看得十分清楚，他不可能让人忘掉他那工人阶级的出身。这种出身本来就够丢人了，可偏偏还要不知羞耻地在世人面前——在她这个阶层的人面前招摇过市，岂不太过分了些。虽然她和马丁的婚约秘而未宣，但他们长期以来的密切交往肯定惹人说闲话。单说这个店铺里吧，就有她的几个熟人在偷眼瞧她的恋人以及他身后的那帮孩子哩。她没有马丁那般随和，也不如他宽宏大量，不能够无视于环境的压力。她伤心到了极点，敏感的天性使她羞愧得浑身打哆嗦。鉴于这种情况，马丁当天到她家去的时候，没把给她的礼物从胸前口袋里掏出来，准备以后选个比较合适的机会再给她。露丝流出了眼泪——那是伤心、愤怒的眼泪——，实在让他意想不到。他见她痛苦万状，便觉得自己太残酷，可他心里却云里雾里，弄不清到底是怎么回事。他从来就没想到过该为自己所认识的人感到羞耻，也绝想不到带西尔瓦一家去购买圣诞礼物会叫露丝丢面子。可是，待露丝把话挑明之后，他明白了她的观点。他把这看作女性的弱点，所有的女人都在所难免，连出类拔萃的女子也包括在内。

[1]　狄安娜神庙相传是“世界古代七大奇迹之一”，被以弗所青年希罗斯特拉都斯放火烧掉。

第三十六章

“走，我要让你看看真正的精英。”元月里的一天傍晚，勃力森登对他这样说道。

他们一道在旧金山吃了饭，来到渡口，准备返回奥克兰时，他突发奇想，要引着马丁去见见“真正的精英”。他转身飞快地跑过沙滩，消瘦的躯体上披的那件外套上下飘动着，马丁跟在一边紧赶慢赶。在一家批发酒商店里，他买了两坛一加仑装的红葡萄老酒，一手拎起一坛，到米森大街上了电车，而马丁提着几瓶一夸脱装的威士忌，紧随其后。

他一边想着露丝此时见到他将会出现怎样一幅情景，一边想着那些“真正的精英”是些什么人。

“闹不定那儿连个人影也没有呢。”当他们下了电车，向右拐入市场街南边工人区的中心时，勃力森登说道，“要是真没有人，那你就失去了一次等待已久的机会。”

“到底是些什么人呢？”马丁问。

“是聪明的人，他们可不是我在那个商人窝里看到你结交的那种胡言乱语的笨蛋。你读了些书，就发现自己孤傲不群。今天晚上我要让你见见另外一些读书人，这样你就不会再感到寂寞了。

“这倒不是说我对他们那种没完没了的讨论感兴趣，”走过一个街区之后，他说道，“我对书本上的哲学缺乏兴趣。不过，你会发现他们与资产阶级的蠢猪不同，而是些有头脑的人。但你得留点神，因为不管你谈什么样的话题，他们都非要争得让你无以对答不可。

“但愿诺顿能在场，”隔了一会儿，他一边推辞着不让马丁帮他拎那两坛酒，一边气喘吁吁地说，“诺顿是个唯心论者——哈佛大学毕业生，记忆力好得惊人。唯心主义观点引他走上了无政府主义道路，家里人把他赶了出来。做父亲的是一家铁路公司的总裁，资产超过百万富翁许多倍，可为儿子的却在旧金山忍饥挨饿，编一份无政府主义的报纸，每月收入二十五块钱。”

马丁不熟悉旧金山，对市场街南面更是一无所知，弄不清勃力森登要带他到哪儿去。

“接着讲啊，”他说道，“先把他们的情况介绍一下。他们是靠什么为生的？怎么会跑到这种地方来？”

“希望汉密尔顿也能在场。”勃力森登收住脚步，歇了歇手，“他叫斯特朗-汉密尔顿——要知道，名字中间还有连字符呢——，出身于南方的一个古老世家。他是一个流浪汉，是我所见到的最懒的人。他在一家社会主义合作商店里当店员，或者说竭力当店员，一星期挣六块钱，可他积习难改，叼空就进城游荡。一次，我见他在一条长凳上坐了一整天，一口东西也没吃，晚上我请他下馆子——到饭馆只消走两段街区——，谁知他却说：‘太麻烦了，老伙计，还是给我买盒烟算啦。’起先他跟你一样，是斯宾塞的信徒，后来克拉斯使他信了唯物一元论。如有可能，我要让他谈谈一元论。诺顿也是一元论者——只不过他否定一切，仅强调精神的作用。他辩论起来，可以叫克拉斯和汉密尔顿难以招架。”

“克拉斯是何人？”马丁问。

“咱们这就是到他家去。他在大学里当教授，后来被解雇——也是因为那缘故。他才思敏捷，可为了糊口什么都干。据我所知，他穷困潦倒之时，便走上街头行骗，一点廉耻都不顾。诸如扒死人的衣服，他什么事情都干得出来。他和资产阶级的区别在于，他敢抢敢骗，不想入非非。他喜欢谈尼采、叔本华、康德，什么都谈，但在这个世界上，他甚至对他的玛丽都漠不关心，唯有一元论才真正让他感兴趣。海克尔[1]是他崇拜的偶像。只有抨击海克尔，对他才是奇耻大辱。

“这儿就是他们聚会的地方。”上楼之前，勃力森登在楼梯口放下酒坛歇手。这是一幢很普通的街角二层楼，楼下开着一家酒馆和一家食品店。“那帮人都住在这里，他们把楼上的房间全包了。不过，只有克拉斯一人占的是两间房。随我来吧。”

楼上的过厅里没有点灯，可勃力森登自如地在漆黑一团中穿行，活似一个熟门熟路的幽灵。这时只见他停下来跟马丁说话。

“还有一个叫史蒂文斯的人，他是个神智学者，一开口便语惊四座。眼下他在一家餐馆当洗碟工，喜欢抽高级雪茄，一次我见他吃饭时只肯花一角钱，饭后却花五角钱买雪茄抽。我口袋里装着几支雪茄，他要在就送给他。

“另外还有个叫帕里的家伙，他来自澳大利亚，是个统计学家，恰似一部包罗万象的百科全书。随你问他一九○三年巴拉圭的粮食产量，一八九○年英国向中国出口床单的数量，吉米·布里特和巴特灵·尼尔逊的那场拳击赛是哪个量级的，或者美国一八六八年次重量级拳击冠军为何人，你都会得到准确无误的答案，而且像自动售货机一样迅捷。再者，还有个叫安迪的石匠，凡事都有自己的看法，且下得一手好象棋。另一个叫哈里的面包师，狂热地推崇社会主义，是个坚定不移的工会会员。顺便提一句，你可记得那次厨师和侍者的大罢工吗？工会组织人以及罢工筹划者就是汉密尔顿，事先他就是在这里——在克拉斯的房间里运筹帷幄的。他那样做只是为了取乐，后来由于人太懒惰，没有和工会一道坚持到底。不过，他要是有意往上爬，完全可以如愿。他懒得没法提，要不然，他定会前途锦绣、鹏程万里。”

勃力森登在黑暗中行进着，直至瞧见一线光亮，来到一处门槛前。他敲敲门，里边应了一声便把门打开了。马丁发现和自己握手的克拉斯是个皮肤微黑的英俊男子，牙齿白得耀眼，一抹黑髭两端下垂，两只乌黑的眼睛又大又亮。玛丽是个金发少妇，正在小套间里洗碟子，那个套间既做厨房又充为餐厅。外间屋又当卧室又为客厅。一星期来洗的衣物挂在头顶，如彩饰般低垂，使得马丁没能一下子看到有两个人在角落里谈话。那两人瞧见勃力森登和他的两坛酒，便欢呼了起来。经介绍，马丁得知他们俩就是安迪和帕里。他跟他们坐到一起，聚精会神地听帕里描绘头天晚上看的一场拳击赛。这当儿，勃力森登得意扬扬地调制了一杯甜酒，接着便把葡萄酒、威士忌和苏打水一杯杯朝上端。他吩咐去把大伙儿都叫来，于是安迪就出去挨着房间请人。

“很幸运，他们多半都在家。”勃力森登低声对马丁说，“那两位是诺顿和汉密尔顿；走，去见见他们。听说，史蒂文斯出去了。我要想办法让他们谈谈一元论。他们几杯酒落肚，就会打开话匣子。”

起初，大家扯东拉西地闲谈着，但马丁仍然能够看得出来，他们的思路非常敏捷。他们的观点虽然常常相互冲突，可他们的确有独到的见解。他们妙语连珠，诙谐幽默，同时又不肤浅。马丁很快就发现，无论谈任何话题，他们当中的每个人都能够旁征博引地运用自己的知识，并且对社会及宇宙有着深刻、完整的看法。他们的观点并非别人为他们准备好的；他们全都是反叛者，不过类型不同罢了，他们的口中吐出的没有一丝一毫的陈词滥调。在摩斯的府内，马丁从未听到过涉及面如此广泛的谈话。若非时间的关系，他们的话题范围似乎会无边无际。他们从亨弗莱·华德夫人[2]的新作谈到萧伯纳最近的剧本，从戏剧的前途扯到对曼斯斐尔德[3]的怀念。他们对晨报上的社论或赞美或讥讽，话题从新西兰劳工的状况一下子就跳到亨利·詹姆士[4]和勃兰德尔·马修斯[5]那儿，接着转向德国对远东的觊觎以及“黄祸”[6]引起的经济问题，还对德国的选举和倍倍尔[7]最近发表的演说争论不休，最后谈到了当地的政局、劳工党组织的最新举措以及党内的丑闻，谈到了海员大罢工的幕后操纵势力。马丁见他们掌握着如此多的内幕消息，不由感到吃惊。他们对那些报纸上从不登载的东西无所不晓——诸如秘密事件和操纵傀儡活动的幕后人物。叫马丁觉得意外的是，那个叫玛丽的年轻女子也加入了讨论，而且显露出超群的智慧，这在他所结识的女性当中是绝无仅有的。他们在一起谈论斯温伯恩和罗塞蒂[8]，随即，她把马丁引向一个陌生的天地，谈起了法国文学。待她站在梅特林克一边说话的时候，他寻到了报复的机会，把《太阳的耻辱》一文中精心构思的论点搬出来向她实施攻击。

其他的几个人也加入了辩论，屋子里烟雾缭绕、空气混浊。这时，勃力森登挥起了挑战的红旗。

“这下，你又有了新的目标了，克拉斯，”他说，“一个似白玫瑰般纯洁的年轻人，怀着一腔对赫伯特·斯宾塞的热爱。看你能不能把他变成海克尔的信徒。”

克拉斯如梦方醒，眼睛里像有块磁性金属一样闪闪发光。而诺顿同情地瞧了瞧马丁，脸上挂着女性的甜蜜的微笑，似乎在宣布他要全力保护马丁。

克拉斯端直开始向马丁发起攻击，诺顿则步步干涉，到了后来，他们俩针锋相对地辩论了起来。马丁听着听着，真想揉揉眼睛看到底是怎么回事。这简直不可能是真事，更不用说发生在市场街南边的工人区里啦。书本上的知识在这些人的心中活跃着。他们的话语热烈，充满了激情，智慧的力量在刺激着他们，就像他见过烈酒和愤怒刺激得有些人热血沸腾一样。他听到的可不是书本上那种干巴巴的哲学理论，也不是康德及斯宾塞那班半偶像式的神话人物笔下的言辞。这是一种有血有肉、富于生命力的哲理，体现在这两个人的身上，使他们的面部表情激动异常。别的人不时也插进去几句，大家都带着全神贯注的神情倾听着这场辩论，手中的香烟熄灭了也全然不顾。

唯心论从未引起过马丁的兴趣，可这种理论一落入诺顿的手中，就变成了叫人耳目一新的东西。唯心论在逻辑上似乎是合乎道理的，深深打动了他的心，可克拉斯和汉密尔顿好像就看不到这一点，他们嘲笑诺顿是形而上学者，诺顿也嘲笑他们是形而上学者。“现象”和“本体”这两个名词被抛来抛去。他们谴责他妄图用意识本身解释意识。他则谴责他们在玩文字游戏，说他们的推理方式不是从事实到理论，而是从字眼到理论。一听这话，他们都呆了。他们推理的基本模式，正是从事实出发，再给这些事实冠以名称呀。

当诺顿谈到康德的错综复杂的理论时，克拉斯提醒他说，微不足道的德国哲学流派一旦失势，就都跑到了牛津去。过了一会儿，诺顿提出了汉密尔顿的“节俭律”[9]，而他们则声称他们的每一个推理过程都运用的是这条定律。马丁抱着膝盖，听得乐不可支。可诺顿并非斯宾塞的信徒，十分想影响马丁的哲学观，所以讲话时一方面针对自己的两个敌手，一方面针对他。

“要知道，贝克莱[10]提出的问题从来就没有人解答过，”他用眼睛直勾勾地望着马丁说，“相比较而言，赫伯特·斯宾塞离答案最近，但还近得不够。就连斯宾塞最忠实的信徒也不敢再朝前迈一步。一天，我看了萨利倍[11]的一篇论文，他至多只能说，赫伯特·斯宾塞几乎解答了贝克莱的问题。”

“你们知道休谟[12]都说了些什么吗？”汉密尔顿问道。

诺顿点了点头，可汉密尔顿为了让别人也知道，还是说了出来。“他说贝克莱的问题既不可能解答，又不可能让人信服。”

“那是休谟自己的观点。”对方回敬道，“休谟的看法与你们的如出一辙，所不同的是，他还算聪明，承认贝克莱的问题不能够解答。”

诺顿又敏感又兴奋，可是却不慌乱，而克拉斯和汉密尔顿则像两个冷酷无情的野蛮人，专门寻找薄弱环节下手。天色渐晚，诺顿见对方老是指责他是一个形而上学者，不由恼火起来，用手紧紧抓住椅子才不至于跳起身来，灰色的眼睛喷发着怒火，姑娘般的面孔变得严厉和坚毅，随即对敌阵发起了全面进攻。

“好吧，你们这些海克尔的信徒，就算我推理起来像个医生一样，那么请问，你们是怎样推理的呢？你们这些不讲科学的武断者，连一点根据都没有，只会把你们的那套实证理论往不适当的地方安。早在唯物一元论学派兴起之前，所谓的基础就毁于一旦了，所以再不可能有根据可言了。那是洛克的作为，他叫约翰·洛克[13]。两百年前——甚至比这还要早一些呢——他曾在《悟性论》一书中论证天赋观念是压根不存在的。最为可笑的是，这正是你们所强调的理论。今天晚上，你们一遍又一遍地宣称天赋观念是不存在的。

“这说明了什么问题呢？这说明你们永远都不可能了解基本的实在。你们生下来时，大脑空空如也。通过五官，你们的大脑只能够掌握事物的表层或现象。出生时，你们的大脑里没装事物的本体，以后也没法了解——”

“我否认——”克拉斯企图插嘴。

“请等我把话说完。”诺顿吼道，“通过五官的接触，你们对力与物质之间的作用和反作用也只能了解一二。要知道，为了顺利辩论起见，我情愿承认物质的存在；我要做的是用你们自己的论点驳倒你们。我只能采取这种方法，因为你们俩天生就无法理解哲学上的抽象概念。

“请问，根据你们自己的实证理论，你们对物质有哪些了解呢？你们只了解物质的现象和表面。你们只知道物质的变化，或者说，只知道那些在你们的意识里引起变化的物质的内在变化。实证理论只涉及现象，可你们笨得意想当本体论者，拿物质的本体当研究对象。不过，根据实证理论的定义来看，科学只涉及事物的表象。有一位人士曾这样说过，从现象中获得的知识绝不可能超越现象本身。

“即便将康德驳得体无完肤，你们也解答不了贝克莱的问题。可是你们又非得假定贝克莱是错的，因为你们要强调科学已证明上帝是不存在的，或者换句同样确切的话来说，已证明了物质的存在。——要明白，我承认物质的存在，只是为了让你们能听懂我的论点。你们如果愿意，那就当你们的实证理论家吧。不过，本体论在实证学科是没有地位的，所以就别把它搬出来了。斯宾塞的不可知论是正确的，可如果他——”

该搭最后一班渡轮回奥克兰去了，勃力森登和马丁蹑手蹑脚溜出了房门。而诺顿仍在高谈阔论，克拉斯和汉密尔顿则像一对猎犬一样，只等他一讲完就扑到他身上去。

“你让我看到了人间仙境，”马丁在渡轮上说，“能结识这样的人，才不枉活一世。我的大脑感到非常兴奋。以前我从不赞同唯心观，现在我对它也无法接受。你知道我永远都将是一个唯实论者，大概这是我的天性。不过，我真想回敬克拉斯和汉密尔顿几句，而且我认为自己对诺顿也有微词可言。依我看，斯宾塞的观点仍未被驳倒。我激动得真像一个头一次看马戏的孩子。看来，我还得多读些书。我要掌握萨利倍的论点。我还是认为斯宾塞的观点不容置疑，下次我要给他们露一手。”

可是，勃力森登吃力地喘着气，已经睡着了，只见他的下巴埋在围巾里，抵在凹陷的胸脯上，身子裹在长大衣里，随着螺旋桨的振动而颤抖。

[1]　19世纪德国生物学家，唯物一元论者。

[2]　19世纪英国著名小说家。

[3]　19世纪美国著名演员。

[4]　19世纪美国小说家。

[5]　19世纪美国评论家，对剧坛影响颇大。

[6]　白人种族主义者害怕东方黄种人强大起来，称其为“黄祸”。在当时的美国，尤指工资低廉的黄种人对白种工人构成的所谓“威胁”。

[7]　德国社会民主党领导人。

[8]　19世纪英国诗人兼画家，拉斐尔前派的领导人。

[9]　逻辑学上的一条定律，苏格兰19世纪的形而上学者威廉·汉密尔顿曾在《形而上学》一书中做过阐述。

[10]　17世纪的一位爱尔兰主教，唯心主义哲学家。他否认物质世界的存在，认为“存在即被感知”。

[11]　19世纪英国优生学家兼社会学家。

[12]　18世纪苏格兰经验派哲学家，著有《人性论》一书。

[13]　17世纪英国经验派哲学家，其名著为《悟性论》。

第三十七章

第二天早晨，马丁做的头一件事便与勃力森登的建议和叮咛背道而驰。他把《太阳的耻辱》装进信封，邮给了《卫城》。他坚信自己能够找到机会在杂志上发表，认为一经杂志扬名，便会赢得书籍出版社的青睐。而且，他把《蜉蝣》也塞进信封，给一家杂志寄了去。尽管勃力森登对杂志持有十分强烈的偏见，可马丁觉得这首伟大的诗篇应该得到发表。不过，他并无意于在没得到对方允许的情况下把它刊登出来。他的计划是先让一家高品味的杂志把这篇诗稿收下，他便可以此为根据和勃力森登死缠硬磨，最终征得他的同意。

这天上午，马丁开始动手写一篇小说。几个星期之前他就拟出了小说的提纲，自那以后这篇小说就不断地干扰着他的生活，非要他付诸笔端不可，显而易见，这是一篇精彩的海洋小说，一篇二十世纪的冒险传奇性小说，描写的是真实世界中在真实的情况下的真实人物。但在跌宕起伏的故事情节下还隐藏着另外一种东西——只看表面意思的读者是永远也分辨不出来这种东西的，可话又说回来，它也绝不会使读者感到乏味，削弱小说的趣味性。正是这种东西，而非故事本身，在督促着马丁操笔写作。说起来，历来都是这种伟大、广阔的主题使他构思出故事情节。找到了这样一个主题，他才考虑该用哪些特点的人物，以及在哪些时空条件下的哪些特定的地点，来表现这种广阔的主题。他决定用《逾期》作标题，认为小说的长度不应超过六万字——这对具有旺盛创作精力的他来说，只是区区小事。头一天动笔，他就感到自己已掌握了语言工具，并感到由衷的高兴。他再不用担心那锋利的工具会出错，破坏他的作品了。长期的艰苦磨炼和钻研结出了硕果。如今，他能够胸有成竹地描绘心里构思出的伟大事物了。他写了一个钟点又一个钟点，觉得自己对生活以及生活中的种种事情都有了可靠和全面的了解，这在以前是从没有过的。《逾期》将是一篇忠实地反映特定人物和特定事件的小说；而且，他深信它讲述的还将是伟大不朽的事物，适合于任何时代、任何海洋和任何生活——他把身子从桌旁挪开，朝后靠了一会儿，心里想着这全都归功于赫伯特·斯宾塞。是啊，得感谢赫伯特·斯宾塞，感谢斯宾塞放入他手中的那把万能钥匙——进化论。

他心里清楚自己正在写一篇伟大的作品。“一定能轰动！一定能轰动！”——这句话一遍遍鸣响在他的耳畔。毫无疑问，这篇作品将一炮打响。他终于要写出能叫杂志界趋之若鹜的作品了。整篇故事如道道闪电出现在他的眼前。他丢下稿纸，把一个章节写进了笔记本。这将是《逾期》的结尾篇；他在大脑中已把整部小说构思得点滴不漏，所以他在尚未结尾之时，就可以提前几个星期把结尾篇写出来。他把这篇未完稿的小说跟那些海洋作家的作品做一比较，觉得它不知要精彩多少倍。“只有一个人的作品能与之媲美，”他喃喃出声道，“那就是康拉德[1]。这部小说甚至叫他也会震惊，使他握着我的手说：‘写得好啊，马丁，我的孩子。’”

他写了整整一天，最后才想起自己要到摩斯家吃晚饭。多亏勃力森登给了他钱，他赎回了黑西装，现在又有资格参加晚宴了。他在市中心下了车，跑进图书馆去寻找萨利倍的著作。他把《生命的周期》借到手，上了电车后将书翻到诺顿提起过的那篇关于斯宾塞的文章。他愈读愈生气，只见他咬牙切齿、脸色涨红，不由自主地把拳头攥紧了又松开，然后又攥紧，仿佛刚刚抓住了一个可恶的人似的，非把对方扼死不可。下了电车后，他沿着人行道大步流星走去，那步态让人一看就知道是个气得发疯的人。来到摩斯家，他按响了门铃，铃声使他清醒过来，意识到了自己的境况。他觉得自己很可笑，于是便脸上堆起笑容，和蔼可亲地走了进去。然而刚一踏入门槛，他的心头就袭上了一阵深深的忧郁感。在这一整天里，他扇动着灵感的翅膀凌空飞翔，而现在却跌入了尘埃。“资产阶级”、“商人的窝”——勃力森登给这儿冠以的名称又浮现在他的脑海之中。不过，这又怎么样呢？他愤怒地责问道。他要娶的是露丝，而不是她的家庭。

他觉得，他以前从没见过露丝这般美丽、这般脱俗、这般幽雅，同时又这般健康。她双颊带着红晕，两汪秋水一次次吸引着他——起初他就是在这两汪秋水里看到了什么是不朽性。近来他已把不朽性抛到了脑后，因为他读的科学著作与不朽性唱的是反调。可是在这里，在露丝的眼睛中，他看到了一种无言无语的论证，而这超越于一切用语言表述的论证。他在她的一双秀目中看到了一种令所有的辩驳之辞都敬而远之的力量，因为他在那里看到了爱情。他自己的眼睛里也有着爱情的倩影，而爱情是无可辩驳的。这就是他深信不疑的原则。

入席之前，他跟她在一起待了半个小时，这使他感到无限幸福，对生活感到心满意足。然而一坐到饭桌旁，辛苦劳作的一天所带来的无法避免的衰弱和疲倦感便开始折磨他。他觉得眼皮发沉，心情烦躁。记得就是在这张他现在所鄙视和经常感到厌倦的饭桌旁，他曾经有生第一次在一种他自以为是高度文明和幽雅的气氛中，跟一群文明人一起就餐。他又看到了很久以前那个可怜巴巴的自己，那个自惭形秽的野人，痛苦不安得每个毛孔都在冒汗，给叫人为难的分门别类的餐具弄得不知所措，被一个可怕的仆人折磨得痛苦不堪，妄图跃上令人目眩的社会高度，过上流人的生活，可最后却决定保持自己的本来面目，没知识就不装有知识，没修养不装有修养。

他瞧了一眼露丝寻找安慰，活像一位乘客，一想到轮船很可能沉没，便猛然惊慌起来，拼命想弄清救生圈在何处。这下好啦，总算找到了——那就是爱情和露丝。所有的一切都经不起书本知识的考验，唯有露丝和爱情能经得起。他从生物学的角度为这两者寻觅到了证据。爱情是生活最崇高的表现形式。造物主像对待所有普通的人一样，不断地塑造着他，使他能够去爱。创造工作花去了造物主一百万年的时间——不，是一千万年，一亿年的时间，而他则是造物主的最佳杰作。造物主使他心中燃起最强烈的爱火，以赋予他想象，使爱情的力量加强千百万倍，随即便把他送入人间，在这里寻求刺激、柔情和配偶。他把手伸到桌下，握住了身旁露丝的那只手，这一握使一股暖流在两人之间奔涌。她飞眼瞧了瞧他，目中异彩闪闪、柔情缱绻。他激动万分，眼睛也情意缠绵。岂不知，她多半是由于看到了他眼里的神情，两汪秋水中才闪出异彩和涌出柔情。

当地高级法院的勃朗特法官就坐在他的斜对角，位于摩斯先生的右侧。马丁见过这个人几次，但并不喜欢他。此人正和露丝的父亲谈论工会运动、当地的局势以及社会主义，而摩斯先生就社会主义这个话题想把马丁挖苦一通。最后，勃朗特法官隔着饭桌投来慈祥的目光，显露出父辈的怜悯之情。马丁心里觉得好笑。

“年轻人，你会成熟起来的，”法官安慰道，“治疗这类年轻人的通病，时间是最好的良药。”他又转过脸来对摩斯先生说：“我认为，对这种病例，讨论是无济于事的，因为它只会让病情更加顽固。”

“的确如此，”对方以严肃的口吻承认说，“不过，常常提醒一下病人，让他了解自己的病情，也是有好处的。”

马丁乐得笑了起来，但笑得很吃力。这一天太长了，而写作时又太紧张，所以他现在筋疲力尽，感到痛苦不堪。

“毫无疑问，你们俩都是高明的医生。”他说，“不过，如果你们肯听听病人的看法，他会告诉你们，你们的诊断实在糟糕。你们以为在我身上发现了疾病，其实那是你们俩的通病。至于我，是具有免疫力的。你们俩血管里涌动的那种半生不熟的社会主义病毒，并没有感染我。”

“高明，真高明，”法官嘟哝着，“对于辩论实在技高一筹，一下就能反守为攻。”

“有些话是你亲口说过的。”马丁眼里直冒火，但他控制住了自己，“要知道，法官，我听过你的竞选演讲。遵循着巧妙的逻辑——哦，我喜欢用‘巧妙’这个词，此处别人并不理解其含义——你按照巧妙的逻辑，一方面自欺欺人地信仰竞争制度和强者生存的原则，一方面却又不遗余力地采取一切措施削弱强者的实力。”

“我的年轻人——”

“别忘了，我听过你的竞选演讲。”马丁又提醒道，“一切都是有案可稽的。你主张控制州际贸易、铁路托拉斯和美孚石油公司，提倡保护森林资源，还赞成采取千百种限制性措施，这些完全都是社会主义者的论调。”

“你是不是想告诉我，你认为不应该限制种种滥用权力的现象？”

“这不是问题的所在。我想告诉你的是，你对我的诊断是错误的。我想告诉你，我没有受到社会主义病毒的感染。我想告诉你，被这种病毒蹂躏得衰弱无力的正是你自己。而我，怀着刻骨仇恨反对社会主义，也坚决反对你们的那种杂牌民主思想，因为你们的民主完完全全是拿空话做外衣的伪社会主义，那套空话经不住词典的考验。

“我是一个反动分子——一个彻头彻尾的反动分子。你们无法理解我的立场，因为你们眼前罩着一层关于社会秩序的由谎言织成的薄纱，而你们目光不够敏锐，看不透这层薄纱。你们假装信仰‘强者生存’和‘强者治人’的原则，可我却真的信仰。这就是区别。不久之前，几个月以前，我相信的正是这种原则。你们以及你们亲友的见解曾一度给我留下过深刻印象。可商人充其量只是怯懦的统治者；他们整日在钱堆里打滚，沾满了铜臭味，所以恕我冒昧，我倒赞成恢复贵族统治。在这间房屋里，唯独我一个是个人主义者。我对国家一无指望，仅指望一位强者，一位马背上的英雄把国家从一事无成的腐败状态中拯救出来。

“尼采的话是对的。我不愿费口舌解释尼采是何许人，只想说他是对的。世界属于强者——这种强者也是高贵的，他们绝不会浸泡在臭气熏天的买卖人的圈子里。世界属于名副其实的贵人，属于伟大的‘金发野兽’[2]，属于绝不妥协的人，属于‘敢说敢干者’。你们这些社会主义者既害怕社会主义又自以为是个人主义者，他们会把你们生吞活剥的。你们那一套逆来顺受、唯唯诺诺的奴隶伦理，绝对挽救不了你们。——唉，我知道这些话你们听不懂，所以我再不用这话让你们心烦了。但有一点可别忘了——马丁·伊登是位个人主义者，而这样的人在奥克兰屈指可数。”

他表示不愿再辩论下去，把身子转向了露丝一边。

“我今天太激动了。”他压低嗓门说道，“我想要的是爱情，而不是高谈阔论。”

他没理睬摩斯先生，而对方却说道：“我还是不服。社会主义者都是诡辩家。这是鉴别他们的方法。”

“尽管如此，我们还是要把你改造成一个出色的共和党人。”勃朗特法官说。

“不等你们如愿，马背上的英雄便会来到。”马丁幽默地回敬了一句，又掉回头来跟露丝谈话。

可摩斯先生却不肯就此罢休。他这位未来的女婿懒惰成性，不肯脚踏实地干正经的工作，这叫他很不高兴，再说，他瞧不起对方的见解，理解不透对方的性格。这时，他将话头转到了赫伯特·斯宾塞的身上。勃朗特法官在一旁一唱一和地敲着边鼓。一提起那位哲学家的名字，马丁的耳朵便竖了起来，听着法官以严肃和得意的言辞在讽刺斯宾塞。摩斯先生时不时地望一眼马丁，似乎在说：“哼，小子，知道厉害了吧。”

“真像叽叽喳喳的乌鸦。”马丁低声咕哝了一句，随后又继续跟露丝和阿瑟说话。

可是，整整写作了一天，昨天晚上又见到了一帮“真正的精英”，这一切都对他产生了影响；另外，在电车上读的那篇叫他气愤的文章，此刻仍在烧灼着他的大脑。

“你怎么啦？”露丝见他拼命地在控制自己，不由吃了一惊，便突然问道。

“世上没有上帝，只有不可知论，而赫伯特·斯宾塞则是它的先知。”此刻，只听勃朗特法官这样说道。

马丁把目光转向了他。

“庸人之见。”他不动声色地说，“我头一次听到这话是在市政厅公园，那是出自一个狗屁不通的工人之口。以后常听人引用，那哗众取宠的腔调叫我作呕。你应当为自己感到羞愧。那个伟大高尚的名字经你的嘴讲出来，就像是一滴甘露落入了污水池。真令人恶心。”

这段言语像是晴天霹雳一般。勃朗特对他怒目而视，脸色似中风一般难看，四周鸦雀无声。摩斯先生暗自高兴。他看得出女儿的内心十分震惊。这正是他所希图的——让这个他不喜欢的人暴露出粗野的本性。

露丝把手伸到桌下，恳求地握住马丁的手，可他气愤得热血沸腾。那些身居高位的人们不学无术、装腔作势的态度激怒了他。哼，亏他还是高级法院的法官呢！仅仅在几年之前，他还从泥沼里仰望这些荣光披身的人物，把他们奉为天神呢。

勃朗特法官恢复了镇静，还想继续下去，佯装出一副礼致彬彬的样子跟马丁讲话，这让马丁觉得对方全是为了顾及有女士在场的缘故。这一来，马丁的怒火就更旺了。这个世界上难道就没有诚实可言吗？“你不配跟我谈论斯宾塞，”他高声说道，“你对斯宾塞的了解比不上他自己国家的同胞。不过，我承认这并非你的过错。这只是一个卑鄙、愚昧的时代留下的一个侧影。今晚来这儿的路上，我遇见了一个实例。我读到了萨利倍的一篇攻击斯宾塞的文章。你应该看一看。那文章随处可见，你可以到书店买，也可以从公共图书馆借。你把自己对那位高尚人物的诋毁，跟萨利倍在这方面收集到的材料一比较，就会觉得自己是多么贫乏和无知，不害臊才怪呢。萨利倍的文章是一段可耻的记录，会使你在可耻的程度上自叹弗如。

“有个学究型的哲学家，连给斯宾塞提鞋都不配，却把斯宾塞称为‘半文明人的哲学家’。依我看，你所读过的斯宾塞的作品不会超过十页，可有些据猜想比你有文化，但读过的斯宾塞的作品并不比你多的批评家，却公开向斯宾塞的信徒们挑战，让他们从他——斯宾塞所有的作品中理出一条中心思想，岂不知，斯宾塞在科学研究和现代思想的整个园地里都留下了天才的烙印；他是心理学的鼻祖；他改革了教育学，所以当今的法国农民子弟才能够根据他制订的原则学到‘读写算’。一群蚊虫般的小人，一边不折不扣地把他的思想付诸实践以获取实利，一边又毁坏他的名声。他们大脑中唯一一点有价值的知识，主要都归功于他。我敢说，如果没有他，他们亦步亦趋学来的知识当中就不会有多少正确的成分。

“像牛津大学的校长费尔班克斯这样一个人——一个论地位比你还高的人，勃朗特法官——，他竟然声称后人不会把斯宾塞看作思想家，而会将其视为诗人及梦想家。那伙人简直是胡言乱语、满嘴放屁！他们当中有个人曾说：‘《第一原理》不能说一点也不具有某种文学的因素。’另外一些人却说，斯宾塞与其说是一个有独到之见的思想家，倒不如说是位孜孜不倦的务实主义者。一派胡言！一派胡言！”马丁倏然收住了话头，随即便是一片死一般的寂静。露丝一家尊敬勃朗特法官，把他看作一个有权势、有成就的人，现在听到马丁的一顿抨击，都感到惶恐不安。接下来，这顿饭吃得就像办丧事一样。法官和摩斯先生两人只顾自己谈话，而其他的人则东拉西扯地闲聊。后来，当露丝和马丁单独在一起时，他们俩闹了一场。

“你让人无法忍受。”她哭着说。

而他的怒火尚未完全平息，只听他不住地喃喃着：“这群畜生！这群畜生！”

她硬说他侮辱了法官，他则还嘴道：

“难道就因为揭露了他的真面目吗？”

“我不管你说的话是否属实，”她固执己见地说，“反正总得讲礼貌和懂分寸呀，你没权利侮辱任何人。”

“那么，勃朗特法官凭什么权利攻击真理呢？”马丁责问道，“我敢说，攻击真理，和侮辱法官那种人微不足道的人格相比较，是一种更为严重的罪行。他不仅攻击真理，还玷污一个已经辞世的伟大、高尚人的名声。呸，畜生！畜生！”

他那起因复杂的怒火又燃烧了起来，露丝对他感到害怕。她从未见他发过这样大的火，在她看来，这通火发得莫名其妙，不合情理。然而，尽管她惊恐万状，那股曾经吸引过她的魔力，此刻仍在把她朝他跟前拉——这种魔力曾经诱使她靠入他的怀里，诱使她在那个如痴如醉的时刻将自己的手搭到他的脖颈上。她为刚才发生的事情感到既伤心又气愤，可她还是躺在他怀里，哆嗦着身子听他一遍遍喃喃着：“畜生！畜生！”她仍躺在那里，听他这样说道，“我再也不来你们家吃饭了，亲爱的。他们不喜欢我，所以我不应该闯到这里来惹他们讨厌。再说，我也讨厌他们。呸！他们真叫人恶心。我真是鬼迷心窍，当初还天真地认为那些身居高位、住着漂亮房子、受过教育并有银行存款的人，全都是出类拔萃的呢！”

[1]　19世纪英国小说家，原籍波兰，其作品多以海洋生活为题材。

[2]　根据尼采的超人哲学，金发碧眼的北欧原始民族为优秀的理想人种，后来喻指强者。

第三十八章

“走，咱们到地方分会去。”

勃力森登说着话，感到一阵眩晕，因为他半个小时前刚吐过血——在三天的时间里，这是第二次吐血了。他端着长年不离手的威士忌酒杯，指头发着颤，把酒一饮而尽。

“我和社会主义有什么相干的呢？”马丁责问道。

“党外人士可以发表五分钟的讲话。”这位病恹恹的人怂恿道，“你可以站起来直抒己见，跟他们说你为什么不欢迎社会主义。跟他们谈谈你对他们以及他们的那套贫民道德观持什么样的看法。你要把尼采的思想灌入他们的大脑里，并准备迎接他们的攻击，好好跟他们干一场。这对他们是有好处的。他们喜欢辩论，而这也是你的希求。要明白，我真希望在辞别人世之前看到你成为一位社会主义者。将来你会遇到失意的时期，那时只有社会主义可以挽救你。”

“我怎么也弄不懂，为什么别人不是，而偏偏你是个社会主义者，”马丁沉思道，“你讨厌芸芸众生。自然，贫民中没有什么可以赢得你的那颗爱美之心。”他见对方又在斟酒，便责怪地用手指着威士忌杯子说，“社会主义似乎并不能挽救你。”

“我已经病入膏肓，”对方回言说，“而你则不同。你身体健康，具有远大的前程，所以不管怎样你都必须受到生活的约束。至于你弄不懂我为什么是个社会主义者，我会告诉你的。这是因为社会主义是不可避免的；因为现今的腐朽和不合理的制度已日薄西山；因为你的那种马背英雄的时代已一去不复返。奴隶们已无法容忍。他们人多势众，会强行地把所谓的马背英雄拖下来，不让他横刀跃马。你斗不过他们，只好忍气吞声地接受全套奴隶哲理。我承认，这滋味不好受。但事情已成定局，迫使你必须接受。你信奉尼采的理论，思想有点古旧。过去的已经过去，谁要说历史可以重演，那他就是在撒谎。当然，我是不喜欢芸芸众生，但一个可怜虫又能做些什么呢？马背英雄不能重登历史舞台，可不管什么样的人当政，也比现在掌权的那些怯懦的猪猡强。不管怎么说，你还是去吧。我已经喝足了酒，再在这儿坐下去，准会醉的。你知道医生是怎样叮咛的——让医生见鬼去吧！我会骗过他的。”

这是星期日的夜晚，他们发现小礼堂里挤满了奥克兰的社会主义者，其中大多数都是工人阶级的成员。发言的是个口齿伶俐的犹太人，他让马丁觉得反感，但同时也赢得了马丁的钦佩。此人弓腰曲背、肩膀狭窄、胸脯塌陷，这说明他真正是在人烟稠密的贫民区里长大的。马丁由此而想到，弱小、可怜的奴隶与一小撮贵族老爷进行了历史悠久的斗争，这些老爷们一直统治着他们，而且还将永远地统治他们。在马丁看来，眼前的这个枯草人儿就是一种象征。他代表着可怜、软弱和无能的芸芸众生，这些人生活境遇悲惨，根据生物学的规律，势必遭到淘汰。他们虽然有一套精湛的哲理，又像蚂蚁一样喜欢合作，但他们不适于生存。造物主瞧不起他们，而宠爱杰出的人物。多产的造物主创造了芸芸众生，可是只选用最优秀的人。人类依样画葫芦，在养种马和种黄瓜时也采用同样的方法。当然，作为宇宙的造物主，完全可以想出一个比较完美的方法来；可这个宇宙里的人类目前必须顺应这种方法。说实在的，他们在消亡之际可以挣扎一番，就像台上的那个演讲人以及台下满脸冒汗的听众现在挣扎的那样，他们可以聚在一起商讨新招，以减轻生存的痛苦，用智慧战胜宇宙。

马丁是这么想的，当勃力森登怂恿他登台亮相时，他也是这么说的。他听从了对方的建议，按照规矩走上讲台，跟主席打了个招呼；他压低嗓门、慢条斯理地讲着，把刚才听那位犹太人发言时脑子里涌出的思绪整理在一起。在这种聚会上，每个发言的人只有五分钟的时间；可五分钟过后，马丁正讲得起劲，对他们的信条所实施的攻击才完成了一半。他引起了大家的兴趣，听众高声喊叫，要求主席延长他的时间。他们很欣赏他，认为他是一个值得一听的有才智的敌手，于是便全神贯注地倾听，连一个字也不错过。他讲得慷慨激昂、振振有词，直言不讳地攻击奴隶、奴隶的伦理观和斗争策略，并坦率地指出台下的听众就是他所提到的奴隶。他引用了斯宾塞以及马尔萨斯的语录，阐述了生物学的发展规律。

“因此，”结尾时，他突然地这样总结道，“凡是由奴隶型的人组建的国家都不能够延续下去。古老的发展规律如今依然在产生着作用。在为了生存所进行的斗争当中，正如我以上讲的一样，强者以及强者的后裔将生存下去，而弱者和弱者的后裔会被击败，继而消亡。结果，强者和强者的后裔生存了下来，于是，只要竞争持续下去，人类的力量便会一代一代加强。这就是进化法则。可你们这些奴隶——我承认，当奴隶很不是滋味——你们这些奴隶却梦想建立一个社会，在那里，进化的法则将失去效用，弱者和无能者都可以生存下去，每个无能的人想吃多少就吃多少，一天要吃几餐就吃几餐，不管强者还是弱者都可以娶妻生子。其结果会怎么样呢？每一代人的力量和生命价值不但会停止增长，反而将降低。这就是对你们那套奴隶哲学的报应。到时候，你们的奴隶社会——奴隶所有、奴隶所治、奴隶所享的社会——势必会随着其生命力的衰弱和崩溃而走向衰弱和崩溃。

“别忘了，我阐述的是生物学原理，而非夹带感情的伦理学。凡是由奴隶组建的国家都不能——”

“那么美国呢？”听众中有个人喊道。

“是啊，美国的情况怎么样呢？”马丁反问了一句，“十三个殖民地推翻了它们的统治者，建立了一个所谓的共和国。奴隶们当家做主了，再没有靠武力统治的主子了。可是，没有某种主子是不行的，于是便产生了一种新型的主子——他们不是伟大、雄健的贵族，而是一群精明狡诈的商人和债主。他们又开始了对你们的奴役——不过，他们不是像名副其实的贵族那样靠铁腕的武力公开地奴役，而是靠阴谋诡计、欺骗和谎言，用见不得人的方法进行奴役。他们收买你们的奴隶法官，腐蚀你们的奴隶立法机关，强迫你们这些奴隶的子女过比奴隶生活更可怕的生活。如今，你们有两百万个孩子在这个由商人寡头操纵的美国拼命地干活。有一千万个奴隶住不上适意的房子，吃不上适意的食品。

“话又说回来。我已经对你们讲明，但凡奴隶社会就不能持续下去，因为论其本质，这种社会必须取消发展规律。一个奴隶社会一经建立，腐化堕落便会接踵而至。你们高谈废除这种发展规律并不困难，可是，到哪儿去寻找新的发展规律来维持你们的力量呢？那你们就制订它吧。是不是已经制订好了呢？说说看呀。”

马丁在一片叫嚷声中回到了位子上。二十几个人站了起来，向主席高声喊叫着要求发言。他们在声震屋瓦的喝彩鼓舞下，一个接一个对马丁进行反击，言辞慷慨激昂，兴奋地挥动着手臂。这是一个疯狂的夜晚——但仅仅是才智上的疯狂，是一场思想的交锋。一些人偏离了主题，然而大多数发言的人都直截了当地对马丁进行还击。他们以他所不熟悉的思路使他感到震惊；他们叫他看到的不是新的生物学规律，而是旧有规律的新式应用方法。他们过于认真，有时显得很不客气，主席非止一次捶桌子维持秩序。

碰巧听众席上坐着一位初出茅庐的新闻记者。他原是由于这一天无新闻可采才被派到了这里来，可他心里却急切想挖掘到耸人听闻的消息。这位记者并不精明，仅仅是能说会道而已。他的大脑过于愚钝，听不懂这场大辩论。可他心里却自鸣得意，自以为要比这些喋喋不休的工人阶级的疯子高明得多。而且，他对那些身居高位、为国家及新闻界制订方针政策的人极其尊敬。再者，他还心怀抱负，那就是达到一个完美的境界，当一名优秀记者，善于无中生有，甚至大肆渲染。

他不知道大家在讲什么，反正也没这个必要。诸如“革命”这一类字眼给了他提示。就像古生物学家能够根据一块化石骨把整副骨骼的结构都复制出来一样，他可以根据“革命”一词杜撰出一篇讲话稿。他当天夜里就这么干了，而且干得非常出色。由于马丁引起的轰动最大，他便把所有的一切都安在马丁的头上，将他描绘成这出戏里的无政府主义魁首，把他那套反动的个人主义理论改头换面，变成了最恐怖、最激烈的社会主义言论。这位名不见经传的记者是个艺术家，大笔一挥给文章涂上了特定的地方色彩——在场的人目光疯狂、披头散发，属于神经衰弱、颓废堕落的类型，激动得声音发着抖，把握紧的拳头举到空中，而为这一幕做背景的是愤怒的人群所发出的咒骂、咆哮以及沙哑的吵闹声。

第三十九章

次日早晨，马丁在自己的那间斗室里边喝咖啡边看报纸。他发现他的名字上了标题，而且登在第一版，这可是前所未有的事情；他还不无诧异地从报上看到，自己成了奥克兰社会主义者最臭名昭著的领袖。他把那位小记者为他杜撰的措辞激烈的演讲稿匆匆浏览了一遍，起初还为记者的无中生有感到愤怒，但最后却大笑一声，丢开了报纸。

当天下午，勃力森登来访，无精打采地一屁股坐到了仅有的那把椅子上，只听马丁坐在床沿上说道：“那位记者不是喝醉了酒，便是恶意中伤。”

“这有什么可耿耿于怀的呢？”勃力森登说，“你总不会希望那些看报纸的资产阶级猪猡赞同你的观点吧？”

马丁略加思忖，然后说道：

“是的，我的确不在乎他们赞同不赞同，一点也不在乎。可是，这很可能会使我和露丝家的关系有些尴尬。她父亲一直认为我是一个社会主义者，这篇晦气的文章将让他更加深信不疑。这倒不是我在乎他对我的看法——他怎么看又有什么要紧的呢？我想把今天写的东西念给你听。当然还是《逾期》喽，我才写了有一半的样子。”

在他朗读之际，玛丽亚猛地推开门，引进一个衣着光鲜的小伙子，来客飞眼扫了一下四周，看了看那只油炉和屋角的“厨房”，随后把目光移到了马丁身上。

“请坐。”勃力森登说。

马丁在床沿上挪了挪身子，给小伙子让出点地方，然后便等他说明来意。

“我昨晚听了你的演讲，伊登先生，今日登门采访。”小伙子启口说道。

勃力森登放声大笑起来。

“这位也是社会主义者吧？”记者问道，同时飞快地打量了勃力森登一眼，估量着这位面色苍白的垂死之人有多大的新闻价值。

“那篇报道就是他写的，”马丁低声说，“看起来还只是个毛孩子！”

“为什么不揍他一顿呢？”勃力森登问，“要是能让我的肺病痊愈，哪怕是五分钟，我都情愿出一千块钱。”

小记者有一些困惑不解，因为这通谈话没有直接冲着他，但却以他为中心，以他为目标。他的那篇关于社会主义者大聚会的报道写得很精彩，受到了表扬，他因此而受命来采访对社会造成威胁的那个组织的领袖，马丁·伊登。

“你不反对给你照张相吧，伊登先生？”他说，“我们报社的一位摄影师等在外边，他说最好马上为你拍照，不然太阳要落山了。照完后咱们再谈话。”

“还来了个照相的，”勃力森登若有所思地说，“揍他，马丁！揍他！”

“我大概真是老了，”马丁答道，“我明明知道该揍他，可就是没那份心思，像是无所谓一样。”

“看在他母亲的分上，揍他一顿。”勃力森登怂恿着。

“这倒值得考虑，”马丁说，“可是，花那么大的气力似乎有点划不来。你知道，要打人总得使力气呀。再说，揍他一顿又管什么用呢？”

“对，这样考虑问题才是正确的。”小记者嘴上说得很轻松，但眼睛却已经开始担忧地朝门外望了。

“可他净扯谎，文章中没有一句话属实。”马丁又说道，同时只把目光盯在勃力森登身上。

“从大体上来看，那只不过是篇描写文嘛。”小记者壮着胆子说，“再说，那是很好的广告。价值就在此处。这可是为你涂金抹彩呀。”

“那是很好的广告，马丁老伙计。”勃力森登一本正经地也这样说道。

“这是为我涂金抹彩——真是感激不尽！”马丁也凑趣道。

“让我想想——你是在哪儿出生的，伊登先生？”小记者换上一副专注和期待的表情，这样问道。

“他连笔记也不做，”勃力森登说，“他全都记在心里。”

“这一点我是可以做得到的。”小记者尽量不表露出内心的不安，“正儿八经的记者是不需要笔录的。”

“昨天晚上——你就做得不错嘛。”可勃力森登毕竟不是寂静教[1]的信徒，这时只见他的态度来了个一百八十度大转弯。“马丁，你要是不揍他，我可要亲自动手了，即便过后马上倒毙也在所不惜。”

“打一顿屁股可以不可以？”马丁问。

勃力森登慎重地考虑了一下，然后点了点头。

一眨眼的工夫，坐在床沿上的马丁便把小记者脸冲下地扳倒在他的膝上。

“喂，你可别咬人啊，”马丁警告道，“如若不然，我就打扁你的脸。这张脸这么俊俏，打烂了就太可惜了。”

他举起手，一起一落地打了起来，又快又有节奏。小记者扭动着身子，挣扎和咒骂，但就是不敢咬马丁。勃力森登沉着脸在一旁看着，不过有一回却激动了起来，抓起那只威士忌酒瓶，恳求道：“嘿，让我也来一下吧。”

“很遗憾，我可是累了，”马丁最后终于住了手，说道，“手都打麻了。”

他把小记者扶起来，让他坐在床上。

“你打人，我要让你蹲监狱，”小记者号叫了起来，孩子般使着性子，泪水顺着他那涨红的脸直朝下流，“我要让你吃苦头。你就等着瞧吧！”

“多漂亮的小伙子，”马丁说道，“他却不明白自己在走下坡路呢。像他那样造别人的谣，是一种不诚实、不光明正大的行为，缺乏男子汉的气味，而他自己还意识不到呢。”

“这得由咱们来告诉他。”勃力森登乘着对方停顿的当儿插嘴说。

“是啊，我得教导教导他，因为他对我进行过恶意中伤。以后，食品店肯定再也不会让我赊账了。最为糟糕的是，这可怜的孩子再这样干下去，就会堕落成一个头号新闻记者，同时也是头号无赖。”

“不过，事情还来得及。”勃力森登说，“谁说得来着，也许你会成为挽救他的得力工具呢。刚才你为什么不让我也揍他一下呢？我也想贡献自己的一份力量。”

“我要叫人把你们俩都抓起来，你们这些大……大……大……大坏蛋。”执迷不悟的小记者抽泣着说。

“不行呀，他的嘴巴太漂亮、太娇嫩了，”马丁故作悲伤地摇头晃脑地说，“恐怕我是白白把手打麻了。这位小伙子反正改不了啦。他将来一定会成为一个伟大和有成就的新闻记者。他是没有心肝的。单凭这一点，他就可以成为伟人。”

这时，小记者溜出了房门，心里一直怀着恐惧，生怕勃力森登用手中紧攥的那只酒瓶从背后给他一下。

第二天早晨，马丁从报上又看到了许多叫他感到新奇的有关于他自己的情况。“我们与社会不共戴天，”一栏采访记把这样的话安到他头上，引用说，“我们不是无政府主义者，而是社会主义者。”文章的作者指出，这两种主义之间似乎没有什么区别，据说马丁耸了耸肩膀，表示默认。根据文章的描绘，他的脸两侧生得不对称，而且身上还显露出别的种种堕落痕迹，其中尤为醒目的是他那双暴徒的手以及他那布满血丝的眼睛里闪射出的凶光。

报上还写到，他每天晚上都在市政厅公园向工人们发表演讲，而且，他在那些煽动人们思想的无政府主义者和鼓动家当中，吸引的听众最多，言辞也最激烈。小记者还花重墨描绘了他那寒碜的斗室、斗室中的油炉以及仅有的那把椅子，描绘了那个跟他做伴的死尸般的浪人，说那个浪人就好像是在某个城堡的地牢里被单独监禁了二十年，刚刚放出来一样。

小记者是个勤奋的人。他东奔西跑，打听到了马丁的家世，还搞到一张希金波森零售店的照片，而伯纳德·希金波森本人就站在店门外。报道中说，这位先生是个明智、体面的生意人，他无法容忍小舅子的社会主义观点，也无法容忍小舅子本人，说他是一个懒惰成性的窝囊废，给他工作他不愿干，早晚都得蹲班房。玛丽安的丈夫，赫尔曼·冯·施米特也受到了采访。他把马丁称作家里的害群之马，跟马丁断绝了来往。“他企图揩我的油水，可我当即就跟他彻底一刀两断，”冯·施米特告诉记者说，“他总算识相，不再来纠缠了。要让我说，一个人不愿工作就不是个好人。”

这一回，马丁真的生气了。勃力森登把这件事视为精彩的玩笑，可他安慰不了马丁，因为马丁知道自己将很难向露丝说得清。马丁还知道，她的父亲一定会为所发生的事情大喜过望，还会利用这次机会解除他们的婚约。具体会利用到什么程度，很快就能知晓。当天下午，邮差送来了一封露丝写的信。马丁拆信时有一种不祥的预感，索性站在他刚从邮差手中接过信的那扇敞开的大门旁读了起来。读着读着，他不由自主又像往日抽烟时一样，伸手到口袋里去取烟叶以及卷烟用的棕色纸。却不知口袋里是空的，也觉察不到自己在用手取卷烟用的东西。

信中没有热情的词句，也不见发泄愤怒的话语。可是，从第一句始到末一句终，通篇都响彻着一种伤心和失望的调子。她说，她原以为他已经克服了少年时的疯狂劲，以为她对他的爱值得珍惜，使他认认真真、正正派派过日子。现在，她的父母采取了坚决的态度，要他们解除婚约。她不得不承认他们有理由这样做。他们俩的关系绝不可能美满，从一开始就是不幸的。她在全信中只写了一段遗憾的话，而这段话使马丁感到非常痛苦。“早先你如果谋个职业，努力发展自己，事情就不会是这样的了，”她写道，“但偏偏出现了现在的结果。你过去的生活太狂放，太不正统了。我知道这不能怪你。你只能按自己的天性，根据早年的教养做事情。所以，我不责怪你，马丁。请你记住，这只是一个错误。我父母认为咱们俩不般配，说幸亏发现得不算太迟，咱们应该感到高兴。”……“你不用再来找我了，”她在临近结尾时这样说道，“再见面，只会让你我以及我的母亲不快。我觉得，我实际上已经给她老人家带来了许多痛苦和忧虑。这伤口得花好长时间才能弥合。”

他把信又从头至尾仔细看了一遍，然后坐下来写回信。他把自己在社会主义者大会上的发言概括地复述了一下，指明他所说的话与报纸硬安在他头上的那通言论在各个方面都是截然相反的。在信尾，他以一种狂热的恋人口气，苦苦哀求对方爱他。“请回信，”他写道，“在你的回信中，你必须告诉我一点——你是不是爱我！别的都不重要——只要你回答这一个问题。”

可是，第二天和第三天都没有见到回信。《逾期》放在桌子上，他一碰也不去碰，桌下的退稿一天一天愈积愈多。他的酣睡头一次受到了失眠的打搅，他辗转反侧，熬过了一个个漫长而烦躁的夜晚。他到摩斯家去了三次，但每一次都被听到门铃声前来开门的仆人支走。勃力森登在旅馆里卧床不起，身子虚弱得不能出来走动，马丁倒是常去陪他，却不愿讲出自己的心事让他不安。

对马丁而言，麻烦事的确很多。那位小记者的报道所产生的后果之严重，甚至超出了马丁的预料。那位葡萄牙食品商拒绝再赊账给他，而那位身为美国人并以此感到自豪的水果商则称他为“祖国的叛徒”，不愿再同他打交道，并且彻底贯彻爱国主义原则，把他欠的账一笔勾销，不许他再抱有还账的企图。街坊邻里的谈话中也反映出同样的情绪，对马丁抱着极大的愤慨。谁都不愿和一个叛逆的社会主义者来往。可怜的玛丽亚半信半疑，给吓坏了，可她仍对马丁忠心耿耿。附近的孩子们忘掉了曾经来找马丁的华贵马车给他们带来的敬畏感，现在隔着老远喊他“浪子”和“无业游民”。然而，西尔瓦家的孩子忠实地捍卫他，为了他的荣誉打了不止一次激烈的战争，于是，青紫的眼睛和淌血的鼻子成了家常便饭，这加重了玛丽亚的困惑和担忧。

一次，马丁在奥克兰的街上遇到了葛特露，从她嘴里听到了一件他知道势必会发生的事情——希金波森为他让全家人当众出丑感到非常恼火，禁止他再上门去。

“你为什么不离开这里呢，马丁？”葛特露央求道，“你走吧，到别的地方找个工作安顿下来。等风头过去之后，可以再回来嘛。”

马丁摇了摇头，一句解释的话也没说。叫他怎么解释呢？他痛心地看到自己跟家人之间，在思想上横着一道万丈鸿沟。他永远无法跨过这道鸿沟，无法跟他们解释自己的观点——即尼采关于社会主义的理论。要让他们理解他的态度和行为，英语的词汇是够用的，别的语种也一样。他们认为他应该找个工作，这是他们所能想得到的正确行为。他们自始至终只会说这一句话，因为这是他们思想宝库中的唯一内容。找个工作！去干活吧！当他的姐姐在一旁讲话的时候，他的心里却在为这些可怜、愚昧的奴隶惋惜。难怪这个世界属于强者，奴隶总摆脱不了被奴役的命运。一份工作对他们就是金身神像，叫他们顶礼膜拜。

尽管他明知自己当天就得去当东西，但葛特露要给他钱时，他却又一次摇了摇头。

“眼下可别靠近伯纳德。”她告诫他说，“过上几个月，待他的火气消了之后，如果你愿意，可以为他工作，赶马车去送货。一旦需要我，就叫人捎个口信，我会来的。可别忘了。”

她出声地哭泣，走掉了。望着她那沉重的躯体和笨拙的步态，他不由感到一阵悲哀。目送着她远去，他觉得尼采的理论大厦在颤抖，有点摇摇欲坠。以抽象的理论谈论奴隶倒真是无所谓，可一联系到自己家里的人，就不那么叫人痛快了。不过，只要有一个奴隶被强者践踏到脚下，那就是他的姐姐葛特露。一想到自己的矛盾心理，他便露出了野性的微笑。亏他还是一个杰出的尼采主义者呢，竟然一触动情思和感情，就让思想观念受到动摇——唉，受到奴隶伦理观的动摇，因为这实际上是由于他对姐姐的怜悯而致。真正高贵的人是不屑怜悯和同情的，怜悯和同情产生于处于底层的奴隶营中，无非是那些拥挤在一起的可怜人及弱者的苦难和血汗的产物。

[1]　17世纪一种基督教的神秘主义教派，主张“清静无为”。

第四十章

《逾期》仍然不被理睬地放在桌子上。他寄出去的每一份稿件现在都退了回来，堆放在桌下。只有一份稿子他还在一次次往外寄，那就是勃力森登的《蜉蝣》。他的自行车和黑西装又进了当铺，而打字机行的人又在为租赁费担忧。但他已经不再关心这类事情。他正在寻找一种新的方位，在未找到之前，他的生活得处于静止状态。

几个星期之后，他所等待的事情终于发生了。他在街上遇见了露丝。事实是，她由弟弟诺曼陪伴着。他们竟然对他视而不见，诺曼还想挥挥手把他赶开。

“要是再缠我姐姐，我就喊警察。”诺曼威胁说。

“如果你非要喊警察，你就喊吧，到时候你的大名会上报纸的。”马丁执拗地答道，“快滚到一边去，随你去找警察吧。我要同露丝谈谈。”

“我想听你亲口讲清。”他对她说。

她脸色苍白，浑身打着哆嗦，但她还是收住了脚步，投来询问的目光。

“我想让你回答我信中提的那个问题。”他提醒道。

诺曼不耐烦地想干涉，但马丁飞快横了他一眼，制止了他。

她摇了摇头。

“你都是出于自愿吗？”他责问道。

“是的。”她的声音低沉、坚决，而且显得很慎重，“我是出于自愿。你让我丢乖露丑，无颜见朋友。我知道，他们都在议论我呢。我跟你没有别的可说了。你使我伤透了心，我永远也不想再见到你。”

“什么朋友、议论以及报纸上的谣言！这种事情与爱情相比就微不足道啦！我只能认为，你从来就没爱过我。”

一阵红晕涌上来，遮盖住了她脸上的苍白色。

“难道以前我没爱过你吗？”她以微弱的声音说，“马丁，你不知道自己在说些什么。我和一般人是不一样的。”

“你也看到，她不愿同你再有任何关系。”诺曼脱口说道，拉起她就走。

马丁闪身放他们过去，一边不知不觉地伸手到外衣口袋里去取根本就不存在的烟叶以及卷烟用的棕色纸片。

回北奥克兰得走很长一段路，但直至步上台阶，进入自己的房间，他才发现自己已走完了这一程路。他坐到床沿上，痴呆呆地望了望四周，犹如一个刚刚苏醒的梦游病患者。他看到了放在桌上的《逾期》，于是便拉过那把椅子，伸手去拿钢笔。他生性喜欢有始有终，干事情非得干完不可。眼前正有件事情尚未完成。为了去完成另一件事情，才耽搁了这件事。而现在那件事已经完成，得全力以赴干这件事了，直到把它干完。至于以后再干什么，他心中没个数。他只知道他的生活已经发生了重大的转折。前一个阶段的生活已经结束，他现在正以勤奋的工作为那个阶段画句号。他对前途漠不关心。他很快就能知道等待自己的是什么。随它是什么，都已经无所谓了。他觉得好像什么都无所谓了。

五天来，他深居简出、闭门谢客，而且很少进食，一个劲地写《逾期》。第六天早晨，邮差送来一封《巴特农》编辑写的薄薄的信。他把信一看，就晓得《蜉蝣》被采用了。“敝社将诗稿送交卡特莱特·勃鲁斯先生过目，”编辑在下文中写道，“鉴于彼方评价颇高，我自不忍释手。今当奉告，该诗稿拟于八月一期刊出，因七月版业已排就。敝社发表该诗作所感之欣喜，由此可见一斑。烦劳君向勃力森登转告敝社之荣幸及谢意。回函务附彼之小照和简史。若不满于敝社之稿金，烦立即电告，言明几多为当。”

由于对方开的稿酬是三百五十块钱，马丁觉得没必要拍电报还价了。下来，就是要征得勃力森登的同意了。事情还真是让他说着了。这不，有个杂志编辑就是识货的，懂得什么是真正的诗。即便对这部本世纪的伟大诗作来说，对方出的价也算相当高了。而且，马丁知道，卡特莱特·勃鲁斯是唯一能够引起勃力森登几分敬意的评论家。

马丁乘电车到闹区去，眼睛望着一座座房屋和一条条横街飞闪而过，心里却生出了几分遗憾，因为他对朋友的成功以及他自己的非凡胜利并不感到十分高兴。美国的一位杰出的评论家称赞了这部诗作，这证明他的说法是对的，只要文章好，就能在杂志上发表。可是，他已经丧失了往日的那股激情，觉得自己并非急于报喜，而是渴望见到勃力森登。《巴特农》采用了《蜉蝣》，这让他想起自己在这五天当中只顾埋头写《逾期》，没听到过勃力森登的消息，甚至连想也没想过他。马丁这才发现自己的精神恍恍惚惚的，竟然把朋友也忘了，这让他感到惭愧。就是这种惭愧的感觉也不十分强烈。除了创作《逾期》的艺术冲动，他对别的感觉全都麻木了。在干别的事情的时候，他都像在做梦一样。拿现在来说，他就如临梦境。电车风驰电掣，而周围的景物显得十分虚无缥缈，如果旁边的那座教堂庞大的石头尖塔突然崩塌，劈头盖脸砸下来，他也不会注意到，更不用说感到惊慌了。

一到旅馆，他便匆匆上楼去了勃力森登的房间，后来又匆匆下了楼，因为房间里空着，一件行李也没有。

“勃力森登先生留下什么地址没有？”他问服务员道，而对方用诧异的目光把他打量了几眼。

“你难道不知道吗？”那人问。

马丁摇了摇头。

“各家报纸都登了这消息。他死在了床上，是自杀，子弹穿过了头部。”

“尸体已经埋掉了吗？”提这个问题时，马丁觉得自己的声音像是从别人的口中发出，来自于遥远的地方。

“没有。验过之后，他的遗体被运到了东部。这些事情都是他家里的人委托律师办的。”

“依我说，他们可真够快的。”马丁评价道。

“哦，快不快我倒不清楚。事情已过去五天啦。”

“过去五天啦？”

“是的，那是在五天之前。”

马丁嗳了一声，便掉过头走了。

来到街角处，他走进西部联合电报局，给《巴特农》发了封电报，让他们发表勃力森登的那部诗稿。由于口袋里只有五分钱，回家还得乘车用，于是他便注明由对方付费。

回到自己的房间后，他又开始写了起来。昼去夜来，一连数日他坐在桌旁一个劲地写着。除了当铺，他哪儿也不去，也不锻炼。肚子饿了，有东西煮的时候，他就一顿顿吃，没东西可煮的时候，他则饿了一顿又一顿。这篇小说提前便一章一章打好了腹稿，可是他又设想了一个开头，虽说得增加两万字，但可以提高表现力。这倒不是因为十分有必要把文章写得锦绣生华，而是因为他的艺术创作原则在要求他这样做。他精神恍惚地写个不停，奇怪地脱离了周围的世界，觉得自己像是一个受人驱使的鬼魂，用文字描绘昔日的生活。记得有人说过，所谓鬼就是死人的灵魂，这个人虽已死去，但他自己却恍恍惚惚，意识不到。马丁停下手中的笔，思量了一会儿，怀疑自己已经死去，只是还没意识到罢了。

终于有一天，《逾期》完稿了。打字机行里的人来取打字机，坐在床上等候，而马丁坐在仅有的那把椅子上打着结尾篇的最后几页。在结束的地方，他以大写体打下了“完”字，而对他来说这件事的确完结了。他怀着一种如释重负的感觉看着打字机被人搬出去，然后走到床跟前，一屁股坐了下去。他饿得浑身无力。他已经有三十六个小时粒米未进了，而且也从没考虑到要吃东西。他仰面躺着，闭着双眼，脑子里什么都不去想，任凭茫然和昏沉的感觉逐渐在心头积聚，蚕食他的意识。就是在这种半昏半迷的状态中，他出声地念起了一首无名诗的诗句，那些诗句都是勃力森登喜欢引用的。玛丽亚在门外担心地听着，被他那沉闷的语调弄得惶恐不安。诗句本身她倒是听不明白，她所忧虑的只是他念诗时的腔调，以及那反复出现的诗句——“我已经唱够”

我已经唱够——

将琵琶搁置一旁。

歌声瞬间消失，

犹如轻轻掠过的光影，

隐入红苜蓿丛中。

我已经唱够——

将琵琶搁置一旁。

我曾经像只报晓的鸟儿，

高歌于蒙露的枝头；

现在我却不作一声。

宛若一只筋疲力尽的红雀，

我已唱不出歌；

我曾经引吭高歌，

而今已经唱够，

将琵琶搁置一旁。

玛丽亚再也忍不住了，于是快步跑到炉灶前，用碗盛了一夸脱汤，又拿长柄勺兜着锅底一舀，把锅里大部分的碎肉和菜都盛到了碗里。马丁打起精神，强坐起身子，一边一匙一匙地喝着汤，一边让玛丽亚放心，声称自己没说梦话，也没有发烧。

待她离开之后，他耷拉着肩膀，郁郁寡欢地坐到床沿上，用一双缺乏光泽的眼睛四下里瞅着，可什么也看不到。后来，一本邮差早晨送来的杂志，像一道闪光照进了他那漆黑一团的大脑。杂志的封套已经撕破，却无人问津地放在那里。他心想，这是份《巴特农》杂志，八月刊的《巴特农》，上面一定登载了《蜉蝣》。勃力森登要是在跟前看看就好啦！

他把杂志翻开，却突然停了下来。《蜉蝣》被作为特稿处理，标题上装饰着美丽的图案，四边绘着皮德斯莱[1]式的花纹。标题图案的一边是勃力森登的照片，另一边登着英国大使约翰·瓦留爵士的照片。编者前言中引用约翰·瓦留爵士的话说，美国根本没有诗人，而《巴特农》这次刊出《蜉蝣》，就等于在说：“瞧，这是什么，约翰·瓦留爵士！”卡特莱特·勃鲁斯被描绘成为美国最伟大的评论家，前言引用他的话说，《蜉蝣》是美国有史以来最优秀的诗作。最后，编者前言以这样一段话作为结尾：“对于《蜉蝣》的价值，我们尚未完全定论，也许我们永远都无法定论。不过，我们读之再三，对诗作中的遣词造句惊叹不已，弄不清勃力森登先生从何处得此佳词，不知他是怎样把它们连缀成章。”接下来刊登的便是那首诗。

“幸亏你已经死了，勃力斯[2]老兄。”马丁喃喃地说着，听凭杂志从两个膝盖之间滑落到了地上。

这件事既浅薄又庸俗，让人作呕。可马丁感情淡漠，发现自己并不十分厌恶。他真希望自己会勃然大怒，只可惜他没这份精力。他的感觉太麻木了。他的热血已经变冷，不会再沸腾，产生汹涌澎湃的愤怒情绪。不过，这又有什么关系呢？这件事与勃力森登所谴责的资产阶级社会里的所有现象还不都是一个样子。

“可怜的勃力斯，”马丁心想，“他绝不会原谅我的。”

他硬撑起身子，取过一个以前用来装打字纸的盒子，在里面翻了翻，拣出十一首朋友写的诗。然后，他把诗稿竖一撕，横一撕，扔进了废纸篓里。撕的时候他无精打采，撕完后便坐在床沿上，目光空洞地望着前方。

他不知在那里坐了有多久，直到最后，他的那双原本什么都看不到的眼睛瞧见了一条长长的水平白线。真是奇怪。那条白线逐渐变得清晰起来，他看出那是一座珊瑚礁，在太平洋白色的浪花丛中冒着水蒸气。紧接着，他看到在那起伏的浪涛里有一只小独木舟，那是一只外边带支架的独木舟。舟尾部有一个腰缠红布、紫铜色皮肤、天神一般的年轻人，正在荡动银色的桨。他认出那人是酋长塔蒂的小儿子摩蒂，而此处是塔希提岛，在那座冒着水蒸气的珊瑚礁后面便是美丽的帕帕拉陆地，酋长的茅草屋坐落在河口。此刻已近黄昏，摩蒂打完鱼正欲还家。他等待着海中翻起大浪，好乘着浪峰越过那道珊瑚礁。马丁觉得自己像过去一样，也坐到了独木舟上，操着一把桨，只等身后翻起青绿色的冲天大浪，只等摩蒂的一声令下，他就会拼命划舟。他不再是一个旁观者，自己也上了独木舟。只听摩蒂大喝一声，他们俩使出吃奶的力气荡桨，驾着浪峰冲向天空。舟首下的海水嘶嘶作响，像是喷气嘴发出的声音，空中满是飞溅的浪花，随着一阵震耳欲聋、久久不散的轰隆声，独木舟来到了环礁湖平静的水面上。摩蒂哈哈一笑，抖掉眼角上的咸水，两人合力荡桨，向珊瑚碎石铺成的海滩划去，在那儿的椰子林里，塔蒂的茅草屋沐浴着落日的余晖，闪射出金光。

随着幻景的消逝，他眼前又浮现出自己那间零乱和肮脏的斗室。他希望能再次看到塔希提岛，可是这愿望却落了空。他知道那片椰子林里有歌声，有少女翩翩起舞于月光之下，只可惜他不能亲眼看见。他仅可以看得到那张堆满杂物的写字台，看得到曾经放过打字机的那片空地方以及那脏乎乎的窗玻璃。他呻吟一声，合上眼睛沉沉睡去。

[1]　19世纪英国装饰画家，风格纤巧、细腻。

[2]　勃力森登的简称。

第四十一章

他一动也没动，沉睡了一整夜，第二天早晨邮差来送信才起床。他身体疲倦，情绪消沉，漫无目的地翻动着信件。有一封薄薄的信，是一家强盗杂志社寄来的，里面装着一张二十二块钱的支票。这笔钱他催了有一年半的时间，现在看到了，却无动于衷。昔日在接到出版商的支票时那种激动的心情，现在已一去不复返。这张支票与以前的支票不一样，里面不包含有希望，也不预示伟大的前程。这在他看来仅仅是张二十二块钱的支票，用这点钱可以买点东西吃。

这批信件里还有一张支票，是纽约的一家周刊寄来的。这是几个月前刊登的一首幽默诗的稿酬，总共十块钱。他突然产生了一个想法，随后便冷静地考虑了一番。他不知该干些什么，而且也不急于干什么事情。可是，总得活下去呀。再说，他还欠别人许多钱呢。如果花一笔钱买邮票，把桌下堆积如山的稿件再寄出去，这笔投资划得来吗？也许一两份稿件会被采用，那会有助于他维持生活。最后，他决定投入这笔钱，于是便跑到奥克兰银行兑换了支票，买了十块钱的邮票。一想到回去在自己的那间密不透风的斗室里做饭，他就觉得腻味。他不愿再去考虑那些债务，这对他来说可是第一次。他明明知道只花十五至二十分钱就可以做一顿丰盛的早餐，可他偏偏跑到福伦咖啡馆花两块钱去吃饭。他还给了侍者两角五分钱的小费，又用去五角钱买了一包埃及香烟。自从露丝求他戒烟以来，他这可是第一次抽烟。他现在觉得没必要再戒烟了，再说他很想过过烟瘾。花点钱有什么关系呢？本来，他花五分钱就可以买一包达勒姆烟叶和一些棕色卷烟纸，用这些能卷四十支烟——可这又怎么样呢？如今，除了能买些手头用的东西，钱对他来说毫无意义了。他没有航海图，也没有船舵，不想到任何港口停泊，只是随波逐流，尽量地躲避生活，因为生活伤透了他的心。

光阴一天天流逝，他每天夜里都睡足八个钟点。他一方面等待着寄支票来，一方面还要到日本餐馆吃饭，每顿饭花十分钱，消瘦的身子逐渐有了肉，凹陷的脸颊也日趋丰盈。他不再折磨自己，不再缩短睡眠时间、超负荷工作和学习。他既不动笔写东西，也不看书，倒是经常散步，到山里游玩，或者在寂静的公园里长时间地溜达。他没有朋友，没有熟人，也不想去结交。他没这份心思。他在等待着某种动力使他静止的生活重新活跃起来，可他不知这股动力将来自何处。目前，他的生活依然处于停顿状态，显得漫无目的、空虚和懒散。

一次，他到旧金山去找那些“真正的精英”。可是在最后的那一瞬间，当他迈入楼上的大门时，却缩了回去，转身就朝拥挤的工人区跑去。一想到自己会听到哲学大辩论，他便恐惧万分，偷偷地飞速逃走，生怕碰上一位“真正的精英”，认出他来。

他有的时候翻翻杂志和报纸，想看看《蜉蝣》究竟被糟蹋成了什么样子。《蜉蝣》引起了轰动。但那是怎样的一种轰动！每个人都读过这首诗，每个人都讨论它到底是不是诗。当地的报纸也在讨论这问题，天天都刊出一栏栏的学术性评论、滑稽可笑的社论以及读者一本正经的来信。海伦·德拉·德尔玛（被大吹大擂地封为美国最伟大的女诗人）拒绝让勃力森登和她一道骑木马[1]，写了许多公开信，声明他根本就不是诗人。

《巴特农》制造了这次轰动一时的事件，在下一期上自称自赞了一番，一边嘲笑约翰·瓦留爵士，一边从生意的角度出发，毫无心肝地利用勃力森登的逝世大做文章。一家自称销量达五十万份的报纸刊出了一首海伦·德拉·德尔玛凭灵机一动而写出的标新立异的诗，她在诗中把勃力森登挖苦、嘲笑了一通。另外，她还带着讽刺的态度，模仿勃力森登的笔调写了一首诗。

马丁非止一次为勃力森登的死感到庆幸。勃力森登生前对芸芸众生恨之入骨，而今他心中一切美好和最神圣的东西却在被芸芸众生任意糟蹋。肢解“美”的工作每天都在进行。国内的每个蠢材都乘机在报上大出风头，借着伟大的勃力森登的光，把他们那枯萎、渺小的自我在公众面前显露显露。一份报纸上刊出了这样一段话：“前不久，我们收到一位先生的来信，说他写了一首类似的诗，比勃氏的诗还要优秀。”另一份报纸则以极其严肃的口吻责难海伦·德拉·德尔玛用模仿的笔调写的讽刺诗，说道：“毫无疑问，德尔玛小姐写这首诗时，带着一种揶揄的目的，而并非完全怀着崇敬的心情，这种崇敬是一个诗人对另一个诗人，也许是最伟大的诗人所应有的。不管德尔玛小姐对《蜉蝣》的作者是否嫉妒，有一点是肯定的：她像成千上万的人们一样，被他的作品迷住了，也许有那么一天，她会试笔写他这样的诗篇。”

牧师们开始在布教时抨击《蜉蝣》。有个牧师由于坚决拥护这首诗的大部分内容，竟被冠以拥护异端邪说的罪名，逐出了教会。这部伟大的诗篇给世人带来了娱乐。喜剧诗作家和漫画家欣喜若狂，紧紧抓住这个题材不放，而社交周刊的人物动态栏目登载了许多这方面的笑话，说什么查利·弗莱沙姆曾交心地告诉阿契·吉宁斯，一个人只消把《蜉蝣》看上五行，就会动手揍一个跛子，看上十行就会跳河。

马丁却不觉得好笑，也没有气得咬牙切齿，他对眼前的现象感觉到的只是一种深深的悲哀。他的整个世界以及处于这个世界巅峰的爱情已经崩溃，与之相比，杂志界和尊贵的公众之崩溃，就算不上什么了。勃力森登对杂志的看法是完全正确的，而他马丁却苦苦探索，白白浪费了许多年头才明白过来。杂志界的内幕跟勃力森登所说的一模一样，甚至还要更糟糕些。他的一切都已经结束，他以此安慰着自己。他曾经想入非非，立下了冲天壮志，到头来却摔到了瘟疫横行的沼泽地里。塔希提的幻景——洁净、可近的塔希提——出现在他眼前的次数愈来愈多。另外还有平坦的帕乌莫土群岛以及高耸的马克萨斯群岛[2]；他时常想象着自己搭乘贸易帆船或轻巧的小船，趁黎明时分溜出帕皮提[3]的环礁，开始漫长的航程，穿过产珍珠的珊瑚岛群，直上奴加希伐岛[4]和泰奥海伊湾[5]，他知道，塔马利会在那儿杀猪欢迎他，而塔马利的那些戴着花环的女儿们则会抓住他的手，又唱又笑地为他戴上花环。南洋在召唤他，他知道自己迟早都会应召而去。

在这段时间里，他听之任之地生活着、休息着。在知识王国里走了那么远的路，而今可要恢复恢复体力了。待《巴特农》把三百五十块钱的支票寄给他，他便转手交给了勃力森登家在当地雇的那个为勃力森登料理后事的律师。他转交过支票后，拿到一张收据，同时他又为勃力森登给他的那一百块钱写了张借据。

没过多久，他就不再光顾日本餐馆了。正当他放弃战斗的时候，却时来运转啦。不过，这种转折来得太迟了些。他拆开《千年盛世》寄来的一封薄薄的信，看到一张数额为三百块钱的支票时，心里一点也不感到激动。他留意到，这笔钱是《冒险》的稿酬。他的所有欠款，包括欠那家重利盘剥的当铺的钱，总共不足一百块钱。待他把债务都清理干净，又把一百块钱交给勃力森登的律师，抽回借据，口袋里还剩下一百多块钱。他到裁缝铺做了一套衣服，还三番五次到全城最好的餐馆吃饭。他虽然仍住在玛丽亚家的那间斗室里，但邻里的孩子们看到他身着新装，就不再站在柴房顶上，或者把脑袋探过屋后的篱笆，管他叫“浪子”和“无业游民”了。

《沃伦月刊》花两百五十块钱买下了他的那篇夏威夷题材的短篇小说——《维基-维基》。《北方评论》采用了他的论文《美之发祥地》，《麦金托许氏杂志》采用了《手相专家》——他写给玛丽安的那首诗。编辑和审稿人已经度完暑假归来，稿件处理得很快。马丁摸不着头脑，不知他们到底抽了哪根筋，竟然都采用起两年来一直被他们坚决拒之门外的稿件来。他过去没出版过什么东西呀。别的地方没有人知道他的名字，即便在奥克兰，那几个自以为认识他的人，也只会把他视为声名狼藉的无政府主义者和社会主义者。所以，没法解释为什么大家都突然要起了他的货。这完全是命运在捉弄人。

《太阳的耻辱》遭到数家杂志社的退稿之后，他采纳了勃力森登生前的建议，把它寄给出版社，让它在出版社之间兜圈子。又遭到几次退稿之后，最后辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司接受了它，答应秋季出版。马丁要求预支版权税，可他们写信说这不是他们的惯例，还说这种性质的书一般都保不住本。他们怀疑，他的书销量不会超过一千本。马丁根据这个销量开始计算这本书能给他带来多少钱。零售一块钱一本，按百分之十五的版税率计算，他总共可以拿到一百五十块钱。他心想，如果能从头做起，他一定专门写小说。《冒险》的字数只有其四分之一，但《千年盛世》所付给他的稿酬却多出一倍。如此看来，他在报纸上很久以前看到的那段文章是千真万确的喽。一流杂志的确是一用稿就付酬，而且酬金丰厚。《千年盛世》给他的稿费还不止每字两分钱哩，而是每字四分钱。他们见了好的文章就不惜重金，买他的作品不就是一例吗？想到这一点，他咧嘴笑了。

他写信给辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司，提出想把《太阳的耻辱》的版权以一百块钱的价格卖给他们，可对方却不愿冒这个险。这时，他并不缺钱花，因为他有几篇后期写的小说被采用，并且付了稿费。他无债一身轻，竟然在银行开了个户头，存了好几百块钱。《逾期》遭到数家杂志社的退稿之后，最终在梅瑞迪斯-罗威尔出版公司寻到了归宿。马丁想起葛特露曾给过他五块钱，想起自己曾打算以一百倍的数额偿还她；于是，他写信要求预支五百块钱的版权税。令他感到意外的是，收到的回信中果然附着这个钱数的支票，另外还有一份合同。他把支票兑换成了许多五块钱一枚的金币，然后打电话给葛特露说要见见她。

她风风火火赶来，累得气喘吁吁，上气不接下气。来时她生怕出了什么事，便把身边仅有的几块钱塞进了手提包里；她满以为弟弟遭了大难，此刻只见她跌跌撞撞跑上前来，哭泣着倒入他怀里，同时默默无语地把手提包塞给他。

“我原来想到你那儿去，”他说，“可我不想跟希金波森先生吵架。我真去了，情况肯定会那个样。”

“过一段时间他就会想开的。”她一边安慰马丁，一边却在纳闷，不知他究竟遇到了什么麻烦，“不过，你最好找份工作，安顿下来。伯纳德喜欢的是踏踏实实工作的人。他的火气都是让报上的那篇文章激起来的，以前从没见过他发这么大的脾气。”

“我不打算找工作干，”马丁笑嘻嘻地说，“你可以把这话转告给他。我不需要谋差事，这就是证明。”

他把手一抖，那一百枚金币便倾入了她的衣兜，宛若一条金光闪闪、叮咚作响的小溪。

“还记得有一次我没钱乘车，你给过我五块钱吗？这是还给你的钱，外加九十九个年龄不同但个头相等的兄弟。”

如果说葛特露来时心怀不安，那么此刻她则吓得六神无主。她深感恐惧的是，事情得到了证实。她已经不再是怀疑了，而是深信不疑。她惊恐地望着马丁，粗壮的腿儿直朝后缩，就好像那条金色的小溪烫手似的。

“全是你的了。”他笑着说。

她热泪盈眶，悲伤地念叨着：“可怜的孩子！可怜的孩子！”

他先是不解，随后猜出了令她不安的原因，便把随支票一道寄来的梅瑞迪斯-罗威尔出版公司的那封信递给了她。她结结巴巴读着信，不时停下来擦眼泪，读完之后说道：

“这就是说，这钱是正道得来的？”

“比中彩票还正当，是我挣来的。”

她慢慢地相信了，把信又仔细看了一遍。他花了很长时间才向她解释清这笔钱是通过什么样的渠道挣来的，花了更长的时间才让她明白这钱真的属于她，因为他不需要。

“我替你把钱存到银行里。”她最后说道。

“千万别这样做。这钱是你的，愿买什么就买什么。如果你不愿要，我就给玛丽亚，她知道怎么花。我劝你把钱收下，雇个用人，你自己好好休息休息。”

“我要把这事讲给伯纳德听。”她离别时说。

马丁听了一愣，但随后咧嘴笑了。

“那你就告诉他吧，”他说，“这一来，也许他又会请我吃饭了。”

“是的，他一定会——我敢肯定他准会的！”她一边激动地嚷嚷着，一边把他拉到跟前，又是亲吻又是拥抱。

[1]　希腊神话中的飞马，象征着诗人的灵感。此处喻指诗坛上的一席之地。

[2]　这两组群岛都处于南太平洋。

[3]　在塔希提岛西北端，为社会群岛首府。

[4]　马克萨斯群岛中的第一大岛。

[5]　马克萨斯群岛的首府所在地。

第四十二章

一天，马丁感到十分寂寞。他身强体壮，然而却无事可做。自从停止写作和读书，自从勃力森登逝世后，自从与露丝分道扬镳以来，他的生活显得异常空虚；他不愿过下馆子、抽埃及香烟那种养尊处优的日子。南洋的确在召唤他，可他觉得他在美国的戏还没有收场。两本书即将出版，还有更多的书也很可能问世。这些书可以为他带来金钱，他要等着把钱袋装满再到南洋去。他知道在马克萨斯群岛有一座峡谷和一个海湾，花一千块智利大洋就能买到手。那座峡谷从陆地环抱的马蹄形海湾边一直延伸至白云缭绕、望之令人目眩的高山之巅，大概有一万英亩的面积。峡谷里长满了热带果树，到处可见野鸡和野猪，偶尔还有野牛群出入其间，高山的群峰之间，野羊成群结队，它们时常遭到野狗的袭击。那儿杳无人迹，四处荒蛮。而他花上一千块智利大洋，就能把那峡谷和海湾买下。

他记得，那个海湾是个美丽的地方，水深得足可以泛起最大的舟船。那儿十分安全，《南太平洋指南》一书介绍说，它是方圆几百英里最理想的船只检修地。他要买一艘大帆船——一种像游艇一样的船只，外面包着铜皮，驾驶起来得心应手——周游列岛，贩椰干和采珍珠。他要把峡谷和海湾作为大本营，盖一幢酋长式的茅草屋，像塔蒂的那幢一样，还要雇一群黑皮肤的仆人，在家中、峡谷里以及帆船上干活。他要在那儿款待驻泰奥海伊的商务代办、来往商船的船长以及南太平洋游民里的头面人物。他将敞开家门，如王子般迎四方来客。他要把自己看过的书以及虚幻的世界忘个干净。

如欲实现这一理想，就得在加利福尼亚耐心等待，把钱袋装满。如今，金钱已经开始源源流入。倘若一本书打响，就可以把堆积如山的稿件卖光。而且，他还可以把那些小说及诗歌收集成册出版，这样管保能买下那峡谷、海湾和帆船。他再也不动笔写作，对此他已拿定了主意。可眼下等着出书，他得有点事干才成，总不能沉浸在无忧无虑的迷梦里，浑浑噩噩地混日子呀。

一个星期天的早晨，他听说砌砖工人当天要在贝冢公园举办野餐会，于是便寻了去。昔日，他不知参加过多少次工人阶级的野餐会，了解那儿会有什么样的情形。一步入公园，往年的那种感受便一齐涌上了他的心头。这些劳动人民毕竟是他的同类。他在他们中间出生，在他们中间生活，虽然离别了一段时间，可现在又回到了他们中间，难免叫他激动。

“真是马特不成！”他听到一个人说道，紧接着，一只手亲热地搭在了他的肩上，“这么长时间，你到哪儿去啦？出海去了吗？来，跟我们喝一杯。”

他又回到了往日的那些伙伴中间——还是那一群人，只不过少了几个故人，添了几张新的面孔。这些伙伴并非砌砖工人，可他们就像过去一样，什么样的星期日野餐会都参加，来跳舞、打架和寻欢作乐。马丁跟他们一起饮酒，觉得自己又成了一个真正的人。他心想，他真是个傻瓜，竟然半途离他们而去；他深信不疑，如果他始终跟这些人在一起，没去攻读那些书，没去结交那些上流社会的人，他此时的心情会欢快得多。然而，啤酒却似乎不如以前那样醇香了，喝起来不似往年那样有味道。他认定是勃力森登破坏了他对生啤酒的爱好，同时，他怀疑那些书也会作祟，毁掉他跟这些少年时期伙伴的友谊。他觉得自己绝不能受书本的影响，于是便挪动脚步向帐篷舞厅走去。在那里，他见管子工吉米正和一个高挑的金发女郎在一起。那姑娘看到他，立刻撇下吉米，迎了上来。

“啧，还是跟过去一个样。”吉米对伙伴们说道。大家见马丁和那个金发女郎迈着华尔兹舞步走远了，便一齐嘲笑起了他。“我才不在乎呢。看到他回来，我高兴都来不及呢。瞧见他们跳华尔兹了吗？舞步多么轻盈。你们说，我能责怪那姑娘吗？”

不过，马丁跳完后又把金发女郎还给了吉米。他们三个和六七位朋友在一起，望着场中一对对翩翩起舞的人们，哈哈大笑着，彼此打着趣。看到马丁又回到他们身旁，大伙儿都很高兴。他们才不管他的书出版不出版呢，也不在乎他创作的价值。他们喜欢的是他本人。他觉得自己活似一位流亡归来的王子，孤寂的心田里注入了温馨的热流。这一天，他纵情娱乐，玩得昏天黑地。他口袋里装着钱，跟过去带着薪水从海上回来时一样，又放开手花了一通。

有一回，他在舞池里看见丽茜·康诺莱被一个工人小伙子搂着从他身旁舞过；后来，他绕着帐篷闲转，碰见她正坐在一张茶点桌旁。两人都感到意外，寒暄了几句，过后，马丁便把她带到了花园里，在那儿说话不用提高嗓门去压音乐声。他刚一开始说话，就赢得了她的倾心。这他看得出来。她那既高傲又谦卑的眼神，她那神气十足的躯体所做出的每一个柔媚的举动，以及她专心致志听他讲话的神态，无一不表明这一点。她已经不是他过去所认识的那个小姑娘了，而成了一位女人。马丁发现她的那种狂野和倔强的美更加完善，尽管没有丧失一丝一毫的狂野，但倔强和火辣辣的劲儿却似乎有所收敛。“真是个美人，一个十全十美的尤物。”他低声赞叹了一句。他明白她的芳心在他身上，他只消招呼一声，她便会跟随他走遍天涯海角。

就在这念头掠过他的脑海时，有人重重一拳砸在了他的脑袋侧面，差点将他击翻在地。挥拳的是位怒火中烧的男子。那人原是想揍他的颚部，由于太性急，才打错了地方。马丁摇摇晃晃扭过身来，瞧见那拳头又野蛮地向自己砸来。他本能地一躲闪，那拳头便落了空，使挥拳的人身子失去了重心。马丁弯起左肘，使出浑身的力气砸在那个失去重心的人身上。那人斜着倒在地上，但他又一跃而起，发疯似的冲了过来。马丁见他气歪了脸，真不知他为什么要发这么大的火。他心里一边纳着闷，一边又使出浑身的力气，把左拳直直甩了出去。那人仰面倒了下去，身子缩作一团。吉米和伙伴们跑了过来。

马丁激动得热血沸腾。昔日的那种跳舞、打架和寻欢作乐的情景完完全全回到了眼前。他一边谨防着自己的敌手，一边扫了丽茜一眼。姑娘家在小伙子们打架的时候，一般都会尖叫起来，可丽茜却没有尖叫。她屏住呼吸观战，身子微微前倾，怀着极浓的兴致，一只手按在胸口上，脸蛋泛着红晕，眼睛里流露出十分惊奇和异常钦佩的神情。

那人站起身，拼命挣扎着想摆脱那几只抓住他的手。

“她在等我回来呢！”他冲着在场的人嚷嚷道，“她在等我回来，可这家伙却插了一杠子。你们放开我，让我收拾这家伙。”

“你吃了熊心豹子胆啦？”吉米帮着众人扯住那小伙子，问道，“这家伙是马丁·伊登，拳脚厉害得很。告诉你吧，你再跟他胡闹，他会活剥了你的皮。”

“不能让他就这么把她从我的身边抢走。”对方插嘴说。

“他打败过‘荷兰鬼’[1]，你应该知道他的手段，”吉米继续规劝道，“他们只战了五个回合。你跟他交手，恐怕一分钟也支持不下来。你明白吗？”

这一信息对怒气冲天的小伙子似乎起到了威慑作用，使他瞪着眼睛把马丁端详了半天。

“他看起来没那么厉害。”他冷笑着说，可他的冷笑失去了冲劲。

“‘荷兰鬼’当初也是这么想的。”吉米语气坚定地说，“走吧，咱们离开这里。天下的姑娘多的是。随我走吧。”

小伙子由他带着乖乖地到帐篷那边去了，其他的人也跟着走了。“他是谁？”马丁问丽茜道，“这到底是怎么回事？”

昔日的那种热烈和持久的打架的激情，如今已烟消云散，他发现自己太喜欢自我分析，无法再过那种寻衅滋事的原始生活了。

丽茜把脑袋朝后一仰。

“哦，他是一个小人物，”她说，“只不过跟我做做伴而已。”

“你知道，这也是迫不得已，”她停了一会儿，然后解释道，“我感到非常孤独。不过，我始终都没忘记你。”她的声音愈来愈低，目光直视前方，“为了你，我随时都可以将他抛开。”

马丁望着她那移开的面孔，心里明白自己只消伸出手去，就可以得到她。他不知道自己所学的温文尔雅、合乎语法规范的英语到底有什么价值。他沉湎于遐想，竟然忘了同她对话。

“你杀尽了他的威风。”她嫣然一笑，试探性地说。

“不过，那小伙子倒是挺壮的，”他大度地承认说，“他要是不被拉走，很可能让我穷于应付。”

“那天晚上我看到你和女朋友在一起，她是谁呢？”她突然问道。

“哦，一个普通的女朋友。”他回答说。

“时间过去许久了，”她沉思着喃喃道，“像是有一千年了。”

对这件事马丁不愿深谈，把话题又引到了别的方面。两人在餐馆里吃了饭，他点了美酒和佳肴。饭后，他跟她跳舞，而且只跟她跳，直到她喊累方休。他是个出色的舞伴，她随着他打旋，舞来舞去，欢天喜地地把头靠在他肩上，希望永远这样下去。到了下午，他们钻进树林，按着古老的习惯，由她席地而坐，而他仰面朝天躺下，脑袋枕在她的膝上。他躺在那儿打盹，她却抚弄着他的头发，低头望着他紧闭的双眼，心里充满了一往情深的爱意。他猛然抬眼一瞧，看见了她脸上含情脉脉的表情。她把眼皮一合，随后又睁开，带着柔情和倔强望着他的双目。

“这些年我一直循规蹈矩。”她说话时，声音低得简直成了耳语。

马丁心里清楚，这虽然是个奇迹，但也是事实。他心中升腾起一种强烈的欲望，恳求他去满足。他有能力给她带来幸福。他自己不要幸福，为什么就不能把幸福给她呢？他可以娶她为妻，把她带到马克萨斯群岛去，住在干草打墙的城堡里。这种愿望非常强烈，但他的本性所发出的专横命令却更强硬，不许他那样做。不管怎样，他仍然忠实于爱情。过去的那种放浪形骸的生活一去不复返了。他无法把那种生活拉回来，也无法回到那种生活中去。他变了——直到此刻他才发现自己的变化是多么大。

“我不是个打算结婚成家的人，丽茜。”他柔声说。

抚弄他头发的那只手突然停了下来，但随后又抚弄了起来，而且仍是那么温柔。他注意到她绷紧了面孔，可那是下决心时的表情，因为她的脸蛋仍散发着柔和的光，因为她依旧容光焕发、含情脉脉。

“我没那意思——”她刚启口，便迟疑了起来，“或者说，我不在乎！”“我不在乎。”她又重复了一遍，“能做你的朋友，我感到自豪。为了你，我任何事情都肯干。恐怕我生就这种脾气。”

马丁坐起身，握住她的手。他显得很庄重，带着一片温柔，但却缺乏激情；这种温柔叫她心寒。

“算啦，别谈这个了。”她说。

“你是一个伟大、高尚的女性，”他说，“我为能结识你感到骄傲。是的，我感到非常自豪。你对我来说就是漆黑一团的世界当中的一线光明。我对你必须规矩才好，因为你一直都是一个循规蹈矩的人。”

“你对我规矩与否，我全不在乎。你愿把我怎么样就怎么样。你可以把我摔倒在尘埃中，从我身上踩过去。世间只有你一人可以这样做。”她神色超然地说道，“自小我就注意保护自己，看来没有白费力气。”

“正是因为这一点，我才不能够越轨。”他柔声细语地说，“你如此大度和体贴人，使得我也必须体贴人。我不打算结婚，也不能胡搞乱来，尽管我过去放纵过自己。今天我真不该到这里来，和你相会于此。现在再说也没有用了，我怎么也想不到会有这样的结局。

“你请听着，丽茜。我无法表达自己有多么喜欢你。我不仅仅是喜欢，还崇拜和敬重你。你美丽动人，是那样超尘脱俗。可光动嘴皮子又有什么用呢？我想为你做点事情。你一直过的是困苦的生活，我要让你的日子轻松些。”（她眼中闪出了喜悦的光芒，但随即又消失了。）“过不了多久，我肯定能拿到一笔钱——数目挺大。”

在这一瞬间，他舍弃了购买峡谷、海湾、干草打墙的城堡和华丽白帆船的计划。这又有什么关系呢？他可以像以前经常做的那样，随便登上一条船，胡乱去个地方嘛。

“我想把钱给你用。你一定有些打算——如上学念书，或者进商学院。你也许想通过学习当一名速记员。我可以为你做出安排。或者，你的父母双亲还在世——我可以为他们开个食杂店什么的。你想要什么，只需说出来，我就能为你搞到。”

她一声不吭地坐在那儿，目光呆视着前方，眼睛里没有一滴泪水，身子一动不动，但是喉头却在发痛，马丁深深地觉察到了她的感觉，自己的喉头也痛了起来。他为自己刚才的一番话感到后悔。他给她的只是钱，与她奉献给他的东西相比，显得那样庸俗。他的礼品是无关痛痒的身外之物，而她所奉献的则是她本人，以及她的自尊、名声、人格和一切美好的愿望。

“不谈这个啦。”她的声音有些哽咽，但她咳嗽了一声，想掩饰过去。最后，她站起了身。“走，咱们回去吧，我累得不行啦。”

这天的盛会已经结束，寻欢作乐的人们几乎已散尽。可是，马丁和丽茜从树林里走出来时，却发现那帮人在等他们。马丁立刻明白是怎么一回事——一场风暴正在酝酿之中。那帮人是来保护他的。他们走出公园的大门时，身后散散漫漫地跟着另一帮人，那是丽茜的男伴纠集来的朋友，小伙子失去了自己的女人，打算报仇雪恨。几个警察和特警巡官料到要出乱子，便尾随而来制止，把两班人马分别赶上了开往旧金山的火车。马丁对吉米说，他要到第十六大街下车，然后搭电车去奥克兰。火车驶入第十六大街车站时，可以看到一辆电车等在那里，售票员正不耐烦地摇着铃。

“就坐那辆车，”吉米提议说，“你们跑过去，我们拦住他们。快去，到电车上去！”

敌对的那一方没料到这一招，一时茫然不知所措，但随后便跳下火车，追了上来。坐在电车上的那些矜持、稳重的奥克兰人几乎都没留意到有个小伙子和一位姑娘跑上电车，在前边靠外的座位坐了下来。他们不知道这两位与吉米的关系，只见吉米跳上踏板，冲着司机吆喝道：

“打开电开关，老伙计，快离开这里！”

紧接着，吉米猛地转过身去，乘客们看见他一拳打在了一个飞奔而来、企图攀上电车的人脸上。整个电车上都能见到拳头与面孔的撞击。吉米和他的一帮人排列开，站在又长又低的踏板上，迎击着对手的进攻。叮当当一阵铃响，电车启动了，吉米一伙人击退了敌人的最后进攻，他们自己也跳下车去展开决战。电车冲向前方，把混乱的战场远远抛在了后边。吓得目瞪口呆的乘客们做梦也想不到，坐在拐角靠外的座位上的那个表情从容的年轻人和那个漂亮的女工，竟是引起这场恶斗的罪魁祸首。

起初，马丁心中重新涌起了昔日的那种战斗激情，非常欣赏刚才的战斗场面。但那种激情很快就消失了，他感到一阵深深的悲哀。他觉得自己老态龙钟，比昔日的那些粗鲁莽撞、无忧无虑的年轻伙伴要老上几百岁。他走得太远了，远得已经回不去了。他们的生活方式曾一度与他的如出一辙，而今却叫他厌恶。他对一切都感到失望，他和以前判若两人。生啤酒喝到口里淡而无味，而他们的友谊也同样叫他觉得淡而无味。他离开他们太远了，成千上万本打开的书像一道鸿沟横在他与他们之间。他使自己过着流放生活。他漫游于辽阔的知识王国之中，最后无法再返回家园。不过，他毕竟是个人，需要满足自己那种寻求伙伴的要求。只是他还没有找到新的家园。那帮朋友不理解他，家里的人不理解他，资产阶级不理解他，坐在他身旁的这位他十分敬重的姑娘也不理解他，还不理解他对她的尊崇。他仔细思考着，悲哀中又添了几分痛苦。

“跟他和好吧。”分手时，他劝丽茜道。此刻，他们站在六马路和市场街附近的一幢工人房屋前——这儿是丽茜的家。他所指的就是那个这天被他篡夺了位置的小伙子。

“不可能——现在已不可能了。”她说。

“嗨，无稽之谈，”他语调轻松地说，“你只要吹声口哨，他就会飞奔而来。”

“我不是那意思。”她简短地说。

他知道她话中的意思。

当他正欲道晚安的时候，她把身子靠了过来。不过，她在倾身时，既不强求，也不是挑逗，而是怀着一腔热望，显得十分恭敬。他的心被感动了，胸中涌起博大、宽厚的情绪。他把她搂在怀里，亲吻着她，同时心中很清楚印在自己嘴唇上的吻是男人所能够得到的最真情的吻。

“上帝啊！”她抽泣着说，“我愿为你死去！我愿为你死去！”

她猛地挣出他的怀抱，跑上了台阶。他觉得自己的眼睛一下子湿润了起来。

“马丁·伊登啊，”他在心里说道，“你并不是一个不通情理的人，而是一个可怜的尼采信徒。如果可能，你一定会娶她，让她那颤抖的心房充满幸福。但这不可能，你办不到。真他妈丢人。”

“‘一位可怜的老流浪儿在抨击腐败现象时说，’”他想起了亨利的一段语录，不由喃喃出声道，“‘我认为生活犯了大错，是一种耻辱。’是啊，生活的确犯了大错，的确是一种耻辱。”

[1]　吉米捏造出的人物，作为恐吓。

第四十三章

《太阳的耻辱》于十月份出版了。马丁割断快递邮包上的绳子，出版商赠送的六本样书掉落到了桌子上，可他心中此刻感到的却是一阵深深的悲哀。他暗忖，如果这发生在短短的几个月前，他一定会欣喜若狂，于是他不由把应该有的那种喜悦与眼下自己的淡泊和冷漠做了一番比较。这是他写的书，他出版的第一本书，可是他脉搏的跳动一丝一毫都没有加快，心里只有悲哀。现在，这对他已失去了意义，充其量只能给他带来一些钱，可是他对金钱一点也不在乎呀。

他拿着一本书来到厨房里，把它送给了玛丽亚。

“这是我写的，”他解释道，希望能打消对方的疑团，“就是在那间小屋里写的。依我看，你送去的那几夸脱菜汤也在中间起了作用。收下吧，书是你的了。全当我的一件纪念品吧。”

他不是在炫耀和卖弄，心里唯一的动机就是让她高兴，让她为他感到骄傲，并且向她证明，她长期以来对他抱有的信念是正确的。她走进前厅，把书放到了家用《圣经》上。她家的房客撰写的这本书是一件圣品，是友谊的象征。他当过洗衣匠一事曾给她以沉重的打击，而今这本书减弱了她的痛苦。书中的内容她一句也看不懂，但她认为里面的每一个句子都是伟大的。她是一个单纯、实际和勤劳的女性，然而却崇拜杰出的人才。

他对《太阳的耻辱》一书的出版无动于衷，在阅读剪报公司每周寄来的书评时也同样无动于衷。他的书引起了轰动，这是显而易见的。这意味着他的钱袋里可以装入更多的金币。他可以为丽茜做点安排，可以兑现他所有的许诺，之后还能剩下足够的钱建造干草打墙的城堡。

辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司小心翼翼地一版印了一千五百本；他们看到第一批书评，二版又印了三千本；这批书还未发出去，第三版便接到了五千本的订单。伦敦的一家出版公司拍来电报，商谈在英国出书，接踵而来的是法国、德国以及北欧都在翻译该书的消息。这本抨击梅特林克派的书出版得再合时宜也不过了，引发了一场激烈的论战。萨利倍和海克尔持拥护的态度，为《太阳的耻辱》进行辩护，这两人总算在一次论战中站到了同一边。克罗克斯[1]和华莱士[2]则站在反对的一边，而奥列佛·洛其爵士[3]根据自己的那套宇宙学说，企图提出一种折中的看法。梅特林克的信徒们团结在神秘主义的旗帜周围。切斯特顿[4]就这个问题连篇累牍写了一些被公认为不偏不倚的论文，逗得全世界都捧腹大笑；后来，乔治·萧伯纳的一顿炮火，把所有的一切，包括这场论战以及参加论战的人，几乎全都轰到了阴沟里。不用说，战场上还有一群群的牙将，真是灰尘蔽日，喊杀声连天，煞是热闹。

“哲学性的论文集竟和小说一样畅销，实在是天大的奇迹。”辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司在给马丁的信中说，“你的选题恰到好处，所有的一切都异常顺利。不说你也明白，我们正在抓住有利时机。四万余册书在美国和加拿大销售一空，新版两万册已付印。为了满足市场的需求，我们加班加点地工作。不过，这种需求是我们自己创造的，光广告费就花了五千块钱。这本书一定会打破以往的纪录。

“我们冒昧地附上一份合同书的副本，向你预约第二部书稿。恭请注意，我们把版权税提高到了百分之二十，这是一个稳重的出版社所敢于提出的最高版权税。如果你对我们的条件感到满意，请将书名填入‘书名’一栏。我们对书的内容不做规定，什么样的题材都可以。倘若你手头有完稿的作品，那就更好。眼下是最佳时机，万不可坐失。

“收到你签过的合同书后，我们愿预支给你五千块钱的版权税。我们对你是有信心的，打算大张旗鼓地干一场，我们还想同你商量签订一份长期合同，譬如说以十年为期，凡是你写的书，都由我们独家刊行。详情容以后再谈。”

马丁放下信，在心里列了个算术题，算出一角五分乘六万的得数是九千块钱。于是，他签了那份新合同，在书名栏填上了《欢乐的烟雾》，寄还给出版商，还寄去二十篇短篇小说，那是他在尚未找到报刊小说公式之前撰写的。只隔了美国邮政一来一回所需的那么长时间，辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司就寄来了一张五千块的支票。

“今天下午两点钟左右，我想请你跟我一道进城去，玛丽亚。”马丁早晨收到支票后，这样说道，“要不这样吧，你两点钟到第十四大街和百老汇大街的拐角处等我。到时候，我去找你。”

按着约定的时间，她赶到了那里。她那困惑的脑袋瓜所能想到的唯一东西就是买鞋子，所以，当马丁领着她从一家鞋店门前走过，钻进一家不动产事务所时，她流露出了一种诧异和失望的表情。随后发生的事情似梦一般，使她一辈子都忘不了。几位体面的先生一边冲她和蔼地微笑，一边跟马丁讲话，他们自己之间也谈上几句；打字机啪嗒啪嗒响了一阵；大家在一份很正规的文件上签了字；她的房东也在，也签了名字；待一切手续办完，她走到街上时，房东对她说道：“喂，玛丽亚，这个月的那七块半钱的房租不用交啦。”

玛丽亚一下子惊得说不出话来了。

“下个月，下下个月，以及下下下个月，都不用交房租了。”房东又说道。

她结结巴巴道了谢，像受了人家的恩惠似的，直至回到北奥克兰的家中，找自己圈里的人商量了一下，还请那位葡萄牙食品商调查了一番，她才算真正明白过来。原来，她住的这幢小屋，这幢她交了多年房钱的小屋，现在归她所有啦。

“为什么不买我的东西啦？”这天晚上，马丁下了电车，葡萄牙食品商走出来迎住他，问他道。马丁解释说，他现在不自己做饭了。随后，他应邀走进店里，喝了杯酒。他留意到，那是食品店里存的最好的酒。

“玛丽亚，我要和你分手了。”马丁当天夜里宣布道，“不久，你也会离开这里的。到时候你可以把这房子租出去，当当房东，你不是有个哥哥在圣莱安德罗或海华滋做牛奶生意么。我要你把人家的衣服都退回去，不要洗了——懂吗？明天你就到圣莱安德罗或海华滋什么来着，去找你的那个哥哥，让他来见我。我住奥克兰的都市饭店。他懂行，知道什么样的牛奶场好。”

就这样，玛丽亚当上了房东，还成了一个牛奶场唯一的主人，她雇了两个人为她干活，在银行里有了存款。尽管家里的孩子都穿上了新鞋，并到学校里念书，她的存款依然持续增加。有人梦到神话中的王子，然而却无人亲眼见到过；辛勤劳动、讲求实际的玛丽亚从未梦到过神话中的王子，可是却收一个曾经当过洗衣匠的王子当了房客。

这个时候，世人开始发问：“这位马丁·伊登是何许人？”马丁拒绝向出版商提供自己的履历材料，但报界就不好对付了。奥克兰是他的家乡，于是记者们一下就发掘出了几十个能够提供情况的人。凡是关于他的情况，无论是真实的还是虚构的，凡是他干过的事情以及许多他没干过的事情，全都登载出来供公众欣赏，并附着快照和相片——相片是当地的一个摄影师提供的，此人曾为马丁照过相，这时即刻为他的相片弄到版权，推向市场。起初，马丁对新闻界和资产阶级社会的做法十分厌恶，反对它们的宣传；可最后他终于屈服了，因为屈服比反对省力气。他觉得自己无法将远道而来的特派记者拒之门外。再说，一天的时间这么长，既然不再埋头写作和读书，总得有点事情做以打发这些钟点。于是，他便逆来顺受，由着一时的兴致，允许采访，并对文学和哲学发表看法，甚至还接受资产阶级的邀请去赴宴。他的心情处于一种古怪而舒畅的状态。他对什么都不计较，对所有的人都宽恕，甚至宽恕了那个曾经把他描绘成暴力分子的小记者。他允许小记者为他写了一整版采访记，还登了特摄的照片。

他偶尔也和丽茜见见面。很明显，她不愿让他有这么显赫的名声，因为这加宽了他们之间的距离。也许是抱着一种缩短距离的希望，她听从了他的劝告，上夜校和商学院读书，并让索价昂贵的高级裁缝为她做时装。她每天都有显著的进步，后来马丁竟然怀疑起自己的决定是否正确，因为他知道她的依从和努力全都是为了他。她竭力使自己在他眼中有价值——有那种他看起来似乎十分重视的价值。然而，他不给她以指望，像哥哥一样对待她，而且很少去看她。

趁着他声名鹊起之际，梅瑞迪斯-罗威尔出版公司急忙把《逾期》推上了市场。由于这是部小说，销路甚至比《太阳的耻辱》还好。每个星期的畅销书目中，他的两本书都名列榜首，这是史无前例的高尚荣誉。《逾期》不仅受到小说读者的青睐，《太阳的耻辱》的热情读者也被这部海洋小说深深地吸引住，从中可以欣赏到他博大精深的写作技巧。首先，他抨击了神秘主义文学，而且干得非常出色；接着，他成功地端出了自己所提倡的文学观，这证明他是一个罕见的天才，集评论家和创作家的素质于一身。

金钱滚滚而来，名声愈来愈大；他宛如一颗彗星，猛地在文坛上散发出光彩，可他对自己引起的轰动却不感兴趣，反而觉得好笑。有一件事让他想不通。那是一件小事，如果叫世人知道了缘由，他们会感到困惑的。他把那件小事看成天大的事，但别人不会为那件事困惑，而只会为他想不通感到困惑。勃朗特法官请他去吃饭。就是这么件小事，或者说，开始时这是件小事，但它很快就会演变为大事。他曾当面羞辱过勃朗特法官，态度十分恶劣，可勃朗特法官在街上碰到他，竟邀请他去吃饭。马丁心想，他在摩斯府上屡次遇见勃朗特法官，对方从未请他吃过饭，为什么偏偏现在就请他吃饭呢？他问自己。他人没有变，仍是那个马丁·伊登。问题在哪里呢？是因为他写的东西在书上发表了吗？可那是早已完稿的作品呀，又不是后来才写的。当勃朗特法官抱着普通人的那种看法，讥笑斯宾塞的学说以及他的观点时，这些作品已经完成了呀。如此看来，勃朗特法官请他吃饭并非为了某种真正的价值，而是看重于某种虚幻的价值。

马丁笑了笑，接受了邀请，同时又为自己的心安理得感到诧异。六七位达官贵人带着他们的女眷参加了宴会，马丁发现自己成了中心人物，勃朗特法官由汉威尔法官起劲地帮着腔，私下劝他加入冥河俱乐部——那是个极端严格的俱乐部，其成员不仅仅要有钱，还必须有成就。马丁谢绝了，心里愈加想不通了。

他忙得焦头烂额，把那堆手稿朝外卖。编辑们求稿的信弄得他难以应付。人们发现他是个讲究风格的作家，而且讲的是货真价实的风格。《北方评论》刊载了他的《美之发祥地》后，写信来又要六篇同样性质的论文。原来可以从稿件堆里挑六篇给他们寄去，可是《勃顿氏杂志》出于投机的心理，先一步问他要五篇论文，每篇愿出五百块钱的稿酬。他回信说愿意满足他们的要求，但每篇论文要一千块钱。他记得这些稿子以前正是被这几家杂志社退了回来，可现在他们又趋之若鹜地来要稿。他们的退稿单冷酷无情，机械而千篇一律。他们让他吃过苦头，而今他也要让他们吃吃苦头。《勃顿氏杂志》按他要的价买走了五篇论文，剩下的四篇被《麦金托许氏杂志》以同样的价格抢了去，而《北方评论》太穷，竞争不过别人。就这样，《神秘的祭司长》、《奇迹梦想家》、《衡量自我的尺度》、《错觉论》、《天神与血肉之躯》、《艺术与生物学》、《批评家和试验管》、《星尘》和《高利贷的尊严》相继问世，所引起的议论、哀叹和抱怨久久不能平息。

编辑们写信让他提自己的条件，他照办了，但拿出的总是现成的作品。他铁了心，不愿再写新作。一想到重新操笔耕耘，他就要发狂。他亲眼看见了勃力森登被读者们批得体无完肤的景象，所以那些读者尽管为他喝彩，他仍然余悸难消，无法对他们产生好感。他显赫的名声对勃力森登似乎是一种侮辱和背叛，这一点，叫他泄气，可他打定主意维持下去，非得把钱袋装满不可。

他收到的编辑来信中有这样的话：“约一年前，没能刊用你的爱情诗集，实乃敝社之大不幸。其实，我们对诗稿十分欣赏，只因出版计划已定，才没能采用你的稿子。假如大作仍在手头，恳请惠赐，我等将不胜欣喜，愿意把那些诗按你的条件全部刊出。敝社愿意提供最优厚的稿酬，并打算将诗作成册出版。”

马丁没寄爱情诗，却把无韵的悲剧诗收集在一起，寄了去。在邮寄之前，他把诗稿又看了一遍，深深觉得里边学生的幼稚腔调太浓，从各方面看都缺乏价值。可是，他把稿子寄出去了；诗作刊载后，才叫编辑抱恨终天。读者义愤填膺，狐疑满腹，认为这样蹩脚的劣作与马丁·伊登高标准的创作简直是天壤之别。人们一口咬定这绝不是他写的，而是杂志社拙劣的仿造品，要不就是马丁·伊登模仿大仲马[5]的做法，乘着自己功成名就之际，雇人捉刀代笔。后来他解释说这部悲剧诗是他初涉文坛的早期作品，那家杂志社非要不可，这么一解释惹得公众对杂志社的枉费心机大大嘲笑了一通，结果使杂志社换了编辑。马丁把预付的版权税装进了口袋，但悲剧诗始终未成册出版。

《考尔门氏周刊》花了近三百块钱，给马丁拍了一封冗长的电报，请他写二十篇文章，每篇愿付给他一千块钱的稿酬。他可以到美国各地旅游，费用全部报销，愿选什么样的题材就选什么样的题材，电文中虚拟了一些题目，目的是想向他表明他可以任意选择。对他的唯一限制是——他只能在美国国内旅游。马丁拍了回电，说自己很遗憾，不能接受，并注明电报费由对方支付。

《维基-维基》在《沃伦月刊》上一登出，立刻赢得了青睐。后来出了册书面边缘空得很宽、装帧十分精美的单行本，轰动了正在度假的读者，似野火般销开了。评论家们一致认为，这部作品可以和两位伟大作家的不朽作品——《瓶中妖魔》[6]及《驴皮记》[7]同享殊荣。

公众对短篇故事集《欢乐的烟雾》，却态度相当暧昧和冷淡。这些短篇故事辛辣而不落俗套，迎头痛击了资产阶级的道德及偏见。不过，法译本一经出版，就弄得巴黎的读者若醉似狂，美国和英国的读者也附庸风雅，拼命地购书。马丁趁机向沉稳谨慎的辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司施加压力，要他们把第三本书按百分之二十五的版税率付酬，第四本按百分之三十的版税率付酬。这两册书包含了他创作的全部短篇故事，有的已连载过，有的则正在连载之中。《嘹亮的钟声》和那些恐怖故事编成一册；另一册包括《冒险》、《罐子》、《生活的美酒》、《漩涡》、《拥挤的街道》以及另外四篇短篇故事。梅瑞迪斯-罗威尔出版公司抢走了他所有的论文集，而麦克斯密伦出版公司则买下了他的《海洋抒情诗》和《爱情组诗》。后来，《妇女家庭之友》付给他一笔可观的稿酬，又连载了《爱情组诗》。

马丁处理掉最后一部稿子，不由松了一口气，干草打墙的城堡和铜壳白帆船眼看就可以到手了。他总算弄清了勃力森登当初为什么要说真正有价值的东西上不了杂志。他的成功虽然表明勃力森登错了，可他有一种感觉，认为勃力森登的看法是千真万确的。他的成功，多是由于《太阳的耻辱》的问世，而不是因为他写了那些文章，那些文章只是次要的，它们屡次三番遭到杂志社的退稿。《太阳的耻辱》出版后，引起了一场论战，这才使他声名鹊起。没有《太阳的耻辱》，就不会引起轰动。没有《太阳的耻辱》创造出奇迹般的销量，他就不会出人头地。辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司目睹了这一奇迹。第一版他们只印了一千五百册，而且还怀疑是否能销完。他们是经验丰富的出版商，但随之而来的成功却令他们万分惊奇。他们觉得这的确是一个奇迹，写给他的每封信中都要怀着敬畏的心情回顾一番当初所出现的神秘现象。他们并不想解释那一现象，因为根本无法解释。它就是那么发生了。他们尽管经验丰富，可是却料所未及。

遐想之际，马丁对自己是否徒有虚名提出了疑问。购买他的书的是资产阶级，正是他们让金钱流入了他的钱袋。他对资产阶级有一星半点的了解，但他弄不清他们怎么能够欣赏得了或理解得了他写的东西。他作品当中内在的美和力量，对成千上万赞美他和购买他的书的读者来说，是毫无意义的。他只是暂时走红，是一个乘天神打盹攻上帕那萨斯山[8]的冒险家。成千上万的人捧读他的书，对他众口皆碑，但他们简直一点也不理解作品的内容，想当初他们攻击勃力森登的《蜉蝣》，将其批得体无完肤时，也同样茫然无知。而今，这些豺狼似的暴民却没有攻击他，却竭尽奉承之能事。攻击也罢，奉承也罢，其实都是一种机遇。有一点他十分肯定：《蜉蝣》比他的任何作品都要强到天上去，那可是数世纪以来最优秀的诗作。如此看来，暴民们对他的称颂实在可悲，因为正是这么一批人把《蜉蝣》打入了十八层地狱。他深深叹了口气，同时也感到心满意足。他高兴的是最后一部稿件已经脱手，他很快就可以一了百了啦。

[1]　19世纪末20世纪初的英国化学家兼物理学家。

[2]　20世纪初的英国博物学家。

[3]　20世纪初的英国物理学家。

[4]　20世纪初的英国评论家。

[5]　19世纪法国著名小说家，曾请人为他草拟故事梗概，然后由他本人加工成稿。

[6]　史蒂文森的中篇小说。

[7]　巴尔扎克《人间喜剧》中的一部小说。

[8]　希腊神话中缪斯女神的住处，此处喻指文坛。

第四十四章

摩斯先生在都市饭店的前台见到了马丁，不知是为了别的事碰巧到了那里，还是专门请他吃饭来的。马丁心里可吃不准，不过他倒倾向于第二种假设。不管怎样，请他赴宴的是摩斯先生——露丝的父亲，一个曾经禁止他上门、解除了他和露丝婚约的人。

马丁没有生气，甚至连架子也没有摆。他原谅了摩斯先生，但心里却感到纳闷，不知对方如此低三下四究竟是怎么一种滋味。他没有直接拒绝邀请，而只是用含糊不清、模棱两可的话搪塞了一下，并问候了他家里的人，特别是摩斯夫人和露丝。他非常自然、毫不迟疑地说出了露丝的名字，但未免有点吃惊，因为他的心不颤不抖，没有像昔日常有的那样脉搏加速跳动、热血奔涌。

请他吃饭的人络绎不绝；他只接受了其中一部分人的邀请。有些人为了能请他吃饭，特意托人介绍跟他认识。对于这样一件愈演愈烈的小事，他一直都想不通。伯纳德·希金波森也请他去吃饭，这让他越加困惑。他不由想起，在他饿得死去活来的那些日子，没有一个人请他去吃饭。那时他多么需要有顿饭吃啊！由于肚中无食，他手足无力、头昏眼花，饿得皮包骨头。世间的事真是矛盾。当他想吃饭的时候，没有人发出邀请，而现在他能买得起成千成万顿饭，食欲一天不如一天，请他吃饭的人却纷至沓来。到底是为什么？这其中无道理可言，也不是因为他本人的价值。他还是从前的他，甚至连他所有的作品都是在那段时期创作的。摩斯夫妇曾责怪他游手好闲、逃避工作，还借露丝之口要他到事务所当个职员。他们明明知道他在写东西呀，因为露丝把他的一份份稿件都交给他们过目了呀。正是由于那些稿件，他的名字才上了所有的报纸，而正是因为他的名字上了所有的报纸，他们才请他去赴宴。

铁的事实是：摩斯夫妇当初看不上他或他的事业，所以不愿请他吃饭。因此，现在请他也不可能是看上了他或他的事业，而是看上了他的名声，因为他是个人尖尖——不请他请谁呢？——还因为他手里握着约十万块钱。这正是资产阶级社会衡量一个人的标准，难道还能指望着他们用别的标准去衡量吗？不过，他是有自尊心的，鄙夷这样的标准。他渴望别人看重的是他本人，或者是代表着他本人的作品。这是丽茜衡量他的标准。她把他的事业甚至看得一钱不值，而只看重他本人。管子工吉米以及那些老朋友也是拿这种眼光看待他的。跟他们在一起厮混时，这一点已被反复证实过——那个星期天在贝冢公园就是一个例子。他的事业是个狗屁。他们所喜欢并愿意为之而战的是马丁·伊登这个人——一个老伙伴和好朋友。

那么，露丝的态度呢？她喜欢他本人，这是无可置疑的。可尽管她喜欢他本人，她更喜欢的还是资产阶级衡量人的标准。他认为，她反对他写作主要是因为凭写作赚不来钱。她对他的《爱情组诗》就提过这样的意见。她也曾催促他去找工作。不错，她用的是“职业”这样一个高雅的字眼，但意思都一样，印在他脑海中的还是原来的那个名称。他给她念他的所有作品——诗歌、故事、论文——《维基-维基》、《太阳的耻辱》等等。可她总是一个劲地催他去找份工作。天啊！为了能配得上她，他拼命少睡觉，耗尽了精力写作。但这好像就不是工作似的！

于是，这件小事愈变愈大。他身体健康、精神正常，按时吃饭，睡眠充足，然而这件愈变愈大的小事却沉重地压在他的心头。他的脑海中不断闪出这样一个词语——“已完稿的作品”。一个星期天他来到希金波森零售店的楼上，坐在伯纳德·希金波森的对面吃一顿丰盛的晚宴时，他费了很大的劲才克制住自己，没有喊出这样的话：

“那些都是已完稿的作品呀！现在你请我来吃饭，可那时你看着我挨饿，不准我进你家的门，并诅咒我，还不是因为我不愿去找工作干。岂不知那些作品已经完稿，全都写得停停当当。而今我说话时，你心里尽管有自己的想法，却硬是不说出口来，随我说什么你都恭恭敬敬地聆听。我说你们这些人庸俗透顶，全是市侩小人，你非但不勃然大怒，反而嗯嗯呃呃地承认我的话大有道理，原因何在？因为我出了名，口袋里有的是钱，而不是因为我是马丁·伊登——一个非常好的人，一个有点头脑的人。如果我说月亮是生乳酪做成的，你也会同意我的看法，至少不会持否定的态度，还不是因为我有许多许多的钱。那些作品早已完稿；告诉你吧，正当你唾弃我，视我如粪土的时候，那些作品就已经写完啦。”

马丁虽然没有喊出声来，但这些念头却在咬啮着他的大脑，不停地折磨着他。不过，他面挂微笑，显出一副宽容大度的样子。他的话愈来愈少，而伯纳德·希金波森粉墨登场，滔滔不绝讲了起来。他说自己也取得了成就，并为此感到自豪。他是个无师自通的人才，没有人帮助过他，所以他不欠任何人的情。作为一个公民，他尽到了自己的责任，养活了一大家子人。希金波森零售店是一个纪念碑，说明了他的勤奋和能力。他爱希金波森零售店，就像有些人爱自己的妻子一样。他对马丁推心置腹，说他耗费了大量的精力和心力才建起了这个商店。对于这座零售店，他是有远大抱负的。眼看着该地区飞速发展，店面的确显得太小了些。如果地方再大些，他可以提出一二十种省力省钱的改进方法。他早晚都会如愿以偿的。他正在尽一切努力，指望着有一天能把旁边的地基买下来，盖一幢两层的木板房。他可以把楼上的房间租出去，而两幢房的底层都可以充当希金波森零售店的店面。当说到将会有一块新招牌横贯两幢房的门面时，他眼中散发出了闪亮的光彩。

马丁忘了听对方讲话。“已完稿的作品”这个短语在他的大脑中轰鸣着，淹没了对方的唠叨。那轰鸣声叫他发狂，他真想摆脱那声音。

“你刚才说需要多少钱？”他突然问道。

他的那个正在详细讲解该地区生意经的姐夫收住了话头。他刚才没提需要多少钱，但他心里清楚，因为他已经盘算过好几十遍了。

“按眼下木料的价格，四千块钱就够了。”他说道。

“招牌也包括在内吗？”

“这我可没有算进去。房子一盖好，招牌是少不了的。”

“还有地基呢？”

“再加上三千块钱吧。”

他把身子前倾，望着马丁签支票，舌头舔着嘴唇，激动地将手指头一张一合，当他接过支票时，用眼一瞟，发现上面的数目是七千块钱。

“我——我顶多只能付六厘的年息。”他沙哑着声音说。

马丁真想大笑一场，可是没笑出声，却这样问道：

“那有多少利息呢？”

“让我算算。按六厘的利息率——六乘七——总共四百二十块钱。”

“每月三十五块钱，对吧？”

希金波森点了点头。

“那好，如果你不反对，咱们这样做吧。”马丁说着望了一眼葛特露，“倘若你每个月用这三十五块钱雇人做饭、洗衣服和擦地板，你可以把这笔本金留着自己支配。假如你能保证葛特露不再干杂务，这七千块钱就属于你了。愿意不愿意？”

希金波森先生觉得十分委屈。让他的妻子再也不干家务，这对他的节俭精神简直是一种侮辱。眼前的礼物是裹着糖衣的药丸，是一枚苦涩的药丸。想想吧，让他的妻子不干活！这真是叫他作难。

“那好吧，”马丁说，“我每个月出三十五块钱，这张——”

他隔着桌子伸手去拿支票。可伯纳德·希金波森抢先用手把支票按住，嚷嚷道：

“我同意！我同意！”

待登上电车时，马丁感到又厌烦又疲倦。他抬起眼睛望了望那块刺眼的招牌。

“畜生，”他痛苦地咕哝着，“畜生，实在庸俗。”

《手相专家》附着白蒂埃的装饰画以及威恩的两幅插图，由《麦金托许氏杂志》推出后，赫尔曼·冯·施米特竟忘了自己曾把这篇作品称为下流诗。他声称是自己的妻子给了作者以灵感，并让这消息传到了一个记者的耳朵里。而后便接受了一位专栏作家、专栏摄影师和专栏画家的采访。结果，星期日增刊用整整一个版面登载了玛丽安的照片和理想化的画像，登载了许多关于马丁·伊登及其家里人的生活私事，还得到《麦金托许氏杂志》的特别恩准，以大号铅字重新全文刊出了《手相专家》。街坊邻里一下子热闹了起来，那些认识这位伟大作家妹妹的幸运主妇们都感到非常自豪，而那些不认识的也急忙凑上来培养感情。赫尔曼·冯·施米特在自家的小修理铺里暗自高兴，决定再添置一台新机床。“这比登广告强，”他对玛丽安说，“而且一分钱也不用花。”

“最好请他来吃顿饭。”玛丽安建议说。

马丁来赴宴时，对那位肥头大耳的肉食批发商和更为肥胖的批发商夫人和颜悦色——他们可是重要人物哩，赫尔曼·冯·施米特这样一个正在发迹的年轻人很可能会用上他们。然而，吸引他们到家里来，非得用他的这个伟大的小舅子作诱饵不可。席间还有一位也吞下了同样的诱饵，此人便是阿萨自行车公司太平洋沿岸经销处的总负责人。冯·施米特极想巴结讨好这个人，因为从他手中可以得到奥克兰地区自行车的经销权。赫尔曼·冯·施米特觉得有马丁这样一位小舅子，就等于拥有一笔可观的财产，可他心里却弄不懂这到底是怎么回事。更深人静，待妻子睡着了的时候，他把马丁出的书和诗集胡乱翻阅了一通，心想世上的人真蠢，竟花钱买这种东西。

马丁心明如镜，把这一切都看了个透。他向后仰着身子，得意地凝视着冯·施米特的脑袋瓜，想象着自己挥起拳头，在又狠又准地猛击，一拳一拳揍得这个呆头呆脑的荷兰佬屁滚尿流。不过，有一点他倒是挺满意的。冯·施米特虽然不富裕，而且有着发财的决心，但他还是雇了个用人，不让玛丽安干繁重的家务。马丁和阿萨经销处的总负责人进行了交谈，饭后把他跟赫尔曼拉到一旁，说自己愿意出资在奥克兰为赫尔曼建一个最出色的、设备齐全的自行车行。这还不算，他在跟赫尔曼私下谈话时，要他留心物色一个汽车经销处和修理厂，因为完全可以两件生意一块做，照样能做得很好。

分手时，玛丽安眼里噙着泪水，用胳膊勾住马丁的脖子，述说着自己是多么爱他，而且始终爱着他。不过，正当她振振有词讲话的时候，中途却出现了明显的停顿，于是她又是流泪，又是亲吻，又是语无伦次地喃喃，想借此掩饰过去。马丁却认为她这是在恳求原谅，因为她当初对他缺乏信心，硬让他去找份工作干。

“我敢肯定，他绝对攒不住钱，”赫尔曼·冯·施米特事后对妻子推心置腹地说，“我一提利息，他就生气。他说让本金见鬼去吧，假如我再说见外的话，他就拧下我的荷兰脑瓜。这可是他说的——要拧下我的荷兰脑瓜。不过，尽管他不懂生意，他还是满不错的。他好就好在给了我机会。”

宴会请帖似雪片飞来，可请帖愈多，马丁就愈困惑。他以贵宾的身份参加过亚登俱乐部的宴会，在座的都是些他过去时常听人提起、在报上常常看到的名人雅客；那些人对他说，当他们拜读到《横贯大陆月刊》登载的《嘹亮的钟声》以及《大黄蜂》刊出的《仙女与珍珠》时，他们就看出他一定能走红。上帝啊！他心想，当时的我可是饥肠辘辘、衣衫褴褛呀！那时你们为什么不请我吃饭呢？那可正是时候呀。那些作品已经脱稿。如果你们现在请我吃饭是由于我的作品的缘故，那么，当我需要食物的时候，你们为什么不请我呢？《嘹亮的钟声》以及《仙女与珍珠》只字都未更改过呀。不，你们现在请我吃饭，并非看重我的作品，而是由于所有的人都在请我吃饭，是因为请我吃饭是一种荣誉。你们现在请我吃饭，是因为你们是合群的动物，是因为你们是芸芸众生当中的一员，是因为世人的脑子里目前都有一个盲目、机械的念头，那就是宴请我。他伤心地问自己，马丁·伊登以及马丁·伊登写的作品，跟这些有什么关系呢？然而，他还是站起了身，以机警俏皮的话答谢别人机警俏皮的祝酒词。

事情就是这样，无论他到哪里去——不管是在记者俱乐部、红木俱乐部，还是参加名流茶话会以及文学讨论会——别人总跟他回忆起《嘹亮的钟声》和《仙女与珍珠》最初发表时的情景。马丁总是非常生气，心里责问着：你们当初为什么不宴请我？那都是些早已完稿的作品呀。《嘹亮的钟声》和《仙女与珍珠》从未有过一丝一毫的更改呀。它们的艺术性以及价值，那时和现在都是一样的啊。显然，你们现在宴请我并非为了这两篇作品，也不是为了我的其他任何作品，而是因为请吃饭是一种时髦，因为芸芸众生都发了狂似的想宴请马丁·伊登。

在这种场合，他时常会突然看到一个身穿方下摆衣服，头戴史特逊硬边帽的小流氓出现在人群里。一天下午，他到奥克兰的加利纳协会去，就见到了这幅情景。当他从椅子上站起身，趋步走向台前时，他看到那个身穿方下摆衣服、头戴史特逊硬边帽的小流氓穿过大厅后端宽敞的门昂首挺胸地踱了进来。马丁全神贯注，目不转睛地望着，引得五百位衣着时髦的女士都回过头来，看他究竟在望什么。然而，她们看到的只是一条空荡荡的中央甬道。他却见那个小流氓沿甬道摇摇晃晃地走来。他心里思量着，不知那家伙会不会摘掉那顶从未见离开过脑袋壳的硬边帽。那家伙顺着甬道径直走上前来，登上了讲台。一想起自己的遭遇，马丁真恨不得对着自己青少年时的幻影痛哭一场。那幻影大摇大摆走到台前，来到马丁跟前，消失在他的内心深处。五百名女士戴着手套轻轻鼓起了掌，为这位应邀而来的难为情的伟人打气。马丁忘掉脑海中出现的幻象，笑了一笑，开始讲起了话。

年老的学校总监在街上叫住马丁，想起了他是谁，不由回忆起当马丁因打架被学校开除时，他曾在办公室里召开过几次会议。

“很久以前，我在一份杂志上拜读过你的《嘹亮的钟声》，”他说，“写得跟坡[1]的作品一样棒。真了不起！我当时就说那是篇杰作！”

马丁差点没说出声，在后来的那几个月里你在街上碰到我两回，可是你视而不见，跟我擦肩而过。那两次我都是饿着肚子，到当铺里典东西。我的作品那时已经脱稿，可你对我不理不睬。为什么现在却理起我来啦？

“那天我还对妻子说来着，想请你改天去吃顿饭，”对方说，“她完全同意我的建议，说那是好主意。是啊，她完全赞同。”

“吃饭？”马丁说话的声调十分凶狠，简直像是在咆哮。

“哦，是的，是的，是吃饭——跟我们一起吃顿便饭。我可是你过去的学监啊，捣蛋鬼。”他不安地说道，并用手戳了马丁一下，想以这种随便的方式表示亲热。

接着，马丁恍恍惚惚在街上走着，最后在街角处停了下来，茫然地朝四下望了望。

“这我敢肯定！”他末了咕哝了一句，“那老家伙害怕我。”

[1]　爱伦·坡，19世纪美国著名小说家兼诗人。

第四十五章

一天，克拉斯来找马丁——这个克拉斯是那帮“真正的精英”当中的一员。马丁带着一种轻松感接待了他，听他绘声绘色地详细讲述一项计划。那是一项相当富于刺激性的计划，引起了马丁的兴趣，但不是投资者的兴趣，而是小说家的兴趣。克拉斯讲到半截停顿了好一会儿，评论说他的《太阳的耻辱》中的大部分看法都是痴人之见。

“不过，我来这儿的目的并非为了宣传哲学观，”克拉斯接着说道，“我是想来问你一声，你愿意不愿意对这项计划投一千块钱。”

“不愿意，因为我还没痴呆到那种程度，”马丁回答道，“不过，我可以告诉你，我将要做些什么。我一生中最伟大的一个夜晚是你恩赐给我的，你对我的恩赐是金钱无法买到的。如今我有了钱，而金钱对我算不上什么。鉴于你曾赐给我一个无价的夜晚，我情愿把我所不稀罕的金钱拿出一千块送给你。你需要钱，而我的钱多得花不完。你想得到钱，所以来求我，可也没必要设计骗取。你把钱拿走好啦。”克拉斯一点也不显得惊奇，把支票折好放进了衣袋里。

“按这种价格，我很愿意跟你签份合同，多提供一些那样的夜晚。”他说。

“太迟了，”马丁摇了摇头说，“那对我来说是唯一的一个灿烂的夜晚，让我觉得如处仙境。我知道那是你们司空见惯的夜晚，可对我则不然。我的生活再也达不到那样高的境界了。我跟哲学已断了缘分，再也不想听到一句有关哲学的话。”

“这是我有生以来靠哲学赚到的第一笔钱，”克拉斯走到门口时，停下脚步说，“可接下来，市场就垮了。”

有一天，马丁在街上碰见摩斯夫人乘车经过。她冲他笑笑，点了点头。他还了一个微笑，把帽子朝上抬了抬。这件事没有给他任何感触。要是发生在一个月前，他也许会产生厌恶，或者感到困惑，会不由自主地去揣摩她当时的心情。如今可一点刺激性也没有，他想也没有去想它。转身就把它忘了个干净，就像他一走过中央银行大楼或市政厅，就会把它们忘掉一样。然而，他的大脑却超乎寻常地活跃，繁杂的思绪没完没了地兜圈子。处于圈子中心的是“作品早已脱稿”这句话；它像一条永不死亡的蛆虫咬啮着他的脑髓。他早晨一醒来就想到这句话，而夜间在梦里折磨他的还是这句话。周围的一切事物，只要一经过他的感官，立刻就跟这句话挂上了钩。他沿着一条残酷无情的逻辑进行推理，最后得出结论：他是一个不值得一提的小人物。小流氓马丁·伊登和水手马丁·伊登是真实的他，而著名作家马丁·伊登是根本不存在的。著名作家马丁·伊登只不过是公众心里产生的幻象，由着公众的意念硬是安到了小流氓和水手马丁·伊登的躯体上。但这蒙骗不了他，他知道自己绝不是那个公众所崇拜，并用宴席祭祀的太阳神。

他在杂志上阅读有关他的文章，仔细留意那些文章是怎样描绘他，后来简直无法把自己跟那些描绘对上号。他曾经活得潇洒，活得刺激，而且坠入过爱河；他性情随和，以宽厚的态度对待生活中的种种缺憾；他当过水手，随船浪迹异国他乡，过去还带人打过群架；第一次到公共图书馆时，他面对浩瀚的书海惊诧不已，但后来学会了在书海中遨游，直至掌握书本里的知识；他挑灯夜读，睡觉时床上还放着马刺，最后终于写出了自己的书。这些描绘尚有踪可寻，但有一点却是无中生有——说他胃口大得惊人，求食于诸家百姓。

杂志界还有些现象令他啼笑皆非。各家杂志社均声称他是自己发现的。《沃伦月刊》在寄给订户的广告中说，他们一向致力于发现新作家，如马丁·伊登就是他们引荐给读者的。《白鼠》、《北方评论》以及《麦金托许氏杂志》都抢着要戴这顶桂冠，后来《环球》得意扬扬地出示了一个合订本，才塞住了他们的口，因为那部被改得面目全非的《海洋抒情诗》就隐没在里边。《少年与时代》躲过了债务之后，又重新还了阳，这当儿也声称马丁是他们最先发现的，可惜的是这番言辞只有农家的孩子能读得到。《横贯大陆月刊》义正词严、有根有据地讲述了他们是怎样最先发现马丁·伊登的，不料却遭到了《大黄蜂》激烈的驳斥，后者还展示了《仙女与珍珠》一文，辛格尔屈利·达恩莱出版公司那不太响亮的声明被淹没在了这一片喧闹中。再说，这家出版公司没有自己的杂志，没法把话说得响亮些。

报界对马丁的版权税进行过统计。几家杂志曾付给他优厚稿酬这一事实，以某种方式泄露了出去。于是，奥克兰的牧师带着友好的态度前来登门求见，而他的邮件堆里开始有了专业团体请求捐款的信件。但比这更糟糕的是女人的纠缠。他的照片被登出来，传播面很广，而专栏作家则利用他那坚毅的紫铜色面孔、身上的伤疤、结实的肩膀、清澈安详的眼睛以及苦行者似的微微凹陷的脸颊大做文章。看到这些，他会回忆起狂放的少年时代，生出几丝微笑。和女人们在一起时，他时常会发现她们当中有人用眼瞟他，对他进行估价和挑剔。他暗自发笑，想起勃力森登的警告，他又是一笑。女人是绝对毁不了他的，这一点可以肯定，因为他早已过了那个阶段。

有一回，丽茜在他的陪伴下到夜校去，途中发现一位衣着考究、花容月貌的资产阶级女子朝他瞟了一眼。那一瞟时间太长了些，意味太深远了些。丽茜明白其中的含义，不由气得浑身发紧。马丁看在眼里，知道里边的缘由，便告诉她说，他已经对这种目光习以为常，一点也不往心上放。

“你应该往心上放才对。”她目光逼人地说，“你有病，问题就在这里。”

“我还从来没有这么健康过呢，体重比以前增加了五磅。”

“不是指你的身体，而是指你的大脑。你的思维机器出了故障，这连我这个微不足道的小人物都看得出来。”

他在她旁边走着，陷入了沉思之中。

“只要你能恢复过来，叫我干什么我都愿意。”她感情冲动地说，“女人用那样的眼光看你，像你这样的男人是不应该漠不关心的。这不正常。换上女里女气的男人倒还说得过去，可你不属于那种人。说实话，要是有个合适的女子前来唤醒你的心，我会为你感到高兴的。”他把丽茜送到夜校，就回到了都市饭店里。

回到自己的房间，他便一屁股坐到一把莫里斯安乐椅上，呆呆地望着前方。他没有打盹，也没有思考，脑子里空空荡荡的。不过，每隔一会儿，就会有记忆中的场景出现在他的眼皮底下，色彩绚丽、光芒四射。他看得到这些场景，然而却几乎意识不到它们的存在，就好像它们是梦境似的。不过，他又没有睡着。有一回，他打起精神望了望手表，看到才八点钟。他无事可做，上床睡觉又太早。后来，他的大脑又变成了空白，一幕幕场景在他的眼皮底下忽隐忽现。这些场景没有什么特别突出的地方，老是一簇簇树叶和灌木似的树枝，枝叶间透洒着火热的阳光。

一声叩门惊愣了他。他并没有睡着，听到叩门声，脑子里立刻想到是有人来送电报、信件，要不就是服务员从洗衣房取回了洗净的衣服。他心里在想着乔，想着乔现在不知身处何方，嘴里却说了一声：“请进。”

他仍在想着乔，没有扭过头望门那儿，只听到房门轻轻地闭上了。接着便是长时间的沉寂。他忘记了有人敲过门，依旧目光茫然地望着前方。正在这时，他听到了一声女人的抽泣。那抽泣是不由自主突然发出的，随后便强行压抑住了——待他觉察到这些，便转过了身去。紧接着，他霍地跳起了身。

“露丝！”他叫了一声，显得又惊异又慌乱。

她脸色苍白，神情紧张。她紧靠在门边，一只手撑在门上，另一只手垂到身旁。她可怜巴巴地向他伸出双手，走了过来。当他牵住她的手，把她引到莫里斯安乐椅跟前时，他觉得那双手冷冰冰的。他又拉过来一把椅子，坐在了宽大的把手上。他慌乱得说不出话来。在他的心里，他和露丝的事已经结束，已经加了封印。他此刻的感觉，就好像雪莱温泉旅馆的洗衣房把整整一个星期的活突然送到了都市饭店来，让他马上洗干净。他几次想说话，但每一次都迟疑着没说出口。“我来这里没人知道。”露丝以微弱的声音说，同时动人地笑了笑。

“你说什么？”他问。

他听到自己的声音，颇觉意外。

她把刚才的话又重复了一遍。

“噢。”他支吾了一声，随后就再也想不出有什么话可说的了。

“看到你进来，我在外边又等了一会儿。”

“噢。”他又支吾了一声。

他的舌头还从来没有如此僵硬过。其实，他心里根本就不知道说什么好。他感到既困窘又难堪，但就是要了他的命他也想不出可说的话。雪莱温泉旅馆的洗衣房来送脏衣服，也比这好应付些。那时他可以挽起袖子，干活就是了。

“后来你就进来啦。”他终于说了这么一句。

她点了点头，带着几分调皮的神情解开了脖子上的围巾。

“最初我是在马路对面看见你的，当时你和那个姑娘在一起。”

“噢，是的，”他简短地说，“我送她到夜校去。”

“见到我你不高兴吗？”两人又沉默了一阵之后，她问道。

“高兴，高兴，”他急忙说，“不过，你到这里来是不是有点冒失？”

“我是溜进来的。没有人知道我来这里。我想见见你。我想对你说，我当初真是太傻了。我来是因为我再也不能不来了，因为我的心在催促着我，因为——因为这是我的愿望。”

她从椅子上立起身，向他这边走过来。她把手搭在他的肩上，急促地喘着气，随后投入了他的怀里。他豁然大度，生性随和，不愿意伤害别人的感情。他心里清楚，如果拒绝了她的献身，就等于给了她一个女人所能承受得了的最严重的伤害。于是，他用胳膊把她抱住，紧紧地搂住她。然而，他的拥抱缺乏温情，只有接触，没有一丝一毫的爱抚。她投入了他的怀里，而他抱住了她，就是这么多。她紧偎在他怀中，后来换了个姿势，把手朝上摸去，搭在了他的脖子上。可这双手摸到的不是火焰一般的肌肉，这时的他觉得既尴尬又不舒服。

“你怎么抖得这么厉害？”他问，“是冷了吧？要我生炉子吗？”

他移动了一下想脱出身去，可她却偎得更紧了，浑身似筛糠般颤抖着。

“只不过是有点激动而已，”她上下牙打着架说，“一会儿就会安静下来的。瞧，我已经好些了。”

她慢慢地就不再发抖了。他仍然搂着她，心里却不再感到纳闷了。现在他已经知道她的来意了。

“我母亲当时想让我嫁给查利·哈普哥德。”她说道。

“查利·哈普哥德就是那个满口陈词滥调的家伙？”马丁咕哝了一句。随后他又说道：“而今，你母亲大概想让你嫁给我吧。”

他这话不是以提问的方式说出来的，而是带着肯定的语气。随即，他的版权钱数排成队伍在他的眼前飞舞了起来。

“对此她不会反对的，我心里有数。”露丝说。

“她认为我有资格吗？”

露丝点了点头。

“可是拿现在跟她解除咱们婚约的那个时候相比，我的资格一点都没有增加。”他若有所思地说，“我没有变，仍是从前的那个马丁·伊登，只不过稍微堕落了些——我现在开始抽烟了。你从我嘴里闻不出来吗？”

她没有答话，仅伸展手指按在他的嘴唇上，动作既优雅又顽皮，指望结果跟从前的历次一样，他会吻她的手指。可是马丁的嘴唇连一点亲热的反应也没有。他等着对方把手指移开，然后又说了下去。

“我没有变，仍然没有工作。我现在不找工作，而且将来也不会找。我依旧认为赫伯特·斯宾塞是一位伟大高尚的人，而勃朗特法官是十足的笨蛋。那天晚上我跟他吃了顿饭，所以不会搞错。”

“可是你却未接受家父的宴请。”她责怪地说。

“原来这事你也知道？是谁派他来的？是你的母亲吧？”

她没有吭声。

“原来真是她指派他来的，我当时就这么想过，我想这次你也是她派来的。”

“我来这里没人知道，”她反驳道“，你以为我母亲会允许这种事吗？”

“我只知道她会允许你嫁给我。”

她尖声叫了起来。“啊，马丁，别太绝情了。你还一次也没吻过我呢，就像一块冷冰冰的石头。你想想我冒了多么大的风险。”她战栗了一下，朝四下里望了望，不过她的目光里有一半是好奇，“你想想，我所来的是什么地方。”

“我愿为你死去！我愿为你死去！”丽茜的话在他的耳朵里回响。

“以前你为什么不敢冒险呢？”他刻薄地问，“当我没有工作，饥肠辘辘的时候，你为什么不敢冒险呢？现在的我跟从前一模一样，还是那个人，那个艺术家，那个马丁·伊登呀。多日来，我一直在心里提这样的问题——这不仅仅涉及你的态度，也涉及大众的态度。你看得出我没有变化，可是我那猛然倍增的身价却在不断地迫使我承认自身的变化。我骨头上还包着那些肉，身上还长着那十个手指和脚趾。我还是从前的我，没增长新的力量，没培养新的美德。我的大脑还是从前的大脑，甚至对文学或哲学也未产生新的看法。我本身的价值跟没有人理睬我的那个时候一样，可他们现在却开始理睬我了，这真让我想不通。显然，他们关心的并非我本人，因为我仍然是以前他们不理不睬的那个我。由此看来，他们感兴趣的是另外一种东西，一种我身外的东西，一种不是‘我’的东西！想听听那究竟是什么吗？那是我所获得的名声。可名声并非我本人，它仅存在于他人的心目中。另外还有我已经挣到的以及正在挣的钱。但钱也不是我本人，它存在银行里，装在某某人的口袋里。你现在来找我，难道就图这些，图我的名声和钱吗？”

“你的话叫我心碎。”她抽泣了一声说，“你知道我爱你，正是因为爱你，我才到这里来的。”

“恐怕你没听懂我的意思，”他温和地说，“我的意思是，如果你一直爱我，那么，现在的爱为什么会比以前强烈得多？当初的爱为什么那么软弱，使你竟然抛弃了我？”

“忘掉往事，原谅我吧。”她充满激情地大声说，“我曾经爱了你那么长时间，你可不能忘本啊。而今，我来到你跟前，投入了你的怀抱。”

“我大概算得上一个精明的生意人，总是盯着秤星，想称称你的爱有多少分量，弄清那是什么种类的爱。”

她从他的怀里抽出身，坐得笔直，用探询的目光把他打量了好半晌。她正要说话，半途却停了下来，没有说出口来。

“你瞧，我是这样看的，”他继续说道，“那时的我跟现在的我毫无两样，可是除了我本阶层的人，好像谁都不喜欢我。我的书那时全都写出来了，可看过手稿的人似乎就没有一个喜欢的。其实，正是由于我的作品，他们反倒愈加不喜欢我。因为我写了那些作品，就好像我干了什么——至少说是降低身价的事情吧。人人见了我都说：‘找份工作吧。’”

她动了动，想说反对的话。

“是的，是的，”他说，“除了你一个人，因为你劝我谋个职位。‘工作’这个俗里俗气的词，就像我的作品一样叫你反感，让你觉得不舒服。我可以告诉你，当我认识的人就像劝一个浪子改邪归正一样劝我找工作时，我也觉得这个词让人不舒服。再回到刚才的话题上——我的作品一出版，公众一开始青睐于我，就使得你的爱发生了质的变化。当初的马丁·伊登虽然已经把那些作品全部写出，你却不愿嫁给他。那时你对他的爱不够强烈，所以你不能嫁给他。可现在你的爱却强烈了起来。我不得不做出这样的结论：你的爱情力量来自于我作品的发表和公众的青睐。对于你，我就不提版权税了，不过我敢肯定正是那些钱使你父母的态度发生了变化。自然，这一切都让我感到不高兴。但最为糟糕的是，这些使我对爱情，对神圣的爱情产生了怀疑。难道爱情如此庸俗，必须用出版的书籍和公众的青睐培育吗？看来是这么回事。我一直坐着思考这个问题，头都眩晕了。”

“可怜的脑袋呀，真够你呛的。”她伸出手，用手指抚慰地理着他的头发，“不要让你的脑袋再眩晕了。让咱们重新开始吧。我一直都是爱你的。我知道自己不该太软弱，屈从于母亲的意志。我真是不应该呀。我常听你以宽厚的态度说，人免不了会犯错误，会有缺点。把你的宽厚也给我一点吧。我错了，请原谅我。”

“哦，我原谅你，”他急忙说，“当实际上没有什么可原谅的时候，原谅别人是不难的，你做的事情没有一桩需要得到原谅。人是按照自己的世界观行事的，不必强求。这就像我不必因为自己没有去找工作而请求你原谅一样。”

“我当时是出于好意，”她抗辩道，“这你是知道的。我不可能一方面爱着你，一方面却不怀好意。”

“不错。可你的那片好意会毁掉我的。”

“是啊，是啊，”他见她要反驳，便抢着说道，“你可能会毁掉我的写作和我的事业。现实主义适合于我的天性，可资产阶级的精神和现实主义是相互抵触的。资产阶级是懦夫，他们害怕生活。你所做的一切是让我也害怕生活。你希望能塑造我，把我塞进一个狭小的生活框架里，那里的价值是空洞的、虚伪的和庸俗的。”他觉得她不服气地动弹了一下，“庸俗——彻头彻尾的庸俗，依我看是资产阶级教养及文化的基础。正如我说的那样，你希望能塑造我，用你们的阶级理想、阶级价值和阶级偏见把我改造成你们那个阶级当中的一员。”他伤心地摇了摇头，“即便现在，你也不理解我在说什么。你在我的话中所理解的，并非我想表达的意思。我的话在你看来荒诞不经，可对我却是实实在在的。你很可能会感到有些不解，会惊奇地想，这个野小子，刚从荒蛮的泥沼中爬出来，竟然对我的阶级评头论足，说我的阶级庸俗。”

她无精打采地把头靠在他的肩上，由于情绪不安，身子一阵阵抖动着。他等了一会儿不见她说话，便又管自说了下去。

“你现在却想重温旧情，想得到我，和我结百年之好，不过，我可会说，如果我的书没有打响，我倒还会是现在这个样，而你却不会来找我。全都是因为他妈的那些书——”

“别说脏话。”她打断了他的话。

她的责备先是吓了他一跳，可接着他便刺耳地哈哈笑了起来。

“瞧，又来啦，”他说，“在此关键时刻，正当你终身幸福危若累卵之际，你又像过去一样害怕起了生活——害怕生活，害怕朴实的脏话。”

他的话把她一激，使她意识到自己的言行是多么的幼稚。不过，她觉得他过分地夸大其词，于是心里有些气愤。他们好半天默默无言地坐着，她绝望地思索着，而他则在追忆着他的那份逝去的爱。他现在才发现，他没有真心爱过她。他所爱的是一个理想化的露丝，一个他一手创造的天仙，爱的是他的爱情诗当中所描绘的那个金光闪闪、灿烂耀目的精灵。这个满身资产阶级的缺点，脑子里无可救药地装满了资产阶级思想的真正的资产阶级的露丝，他却从来都没有爱过。

她突然开口说了话。

“我知道你的这番话是有道理的。我害怕生活，过去对你爱得不够，可现在我已经学会了怎样去爱。我爱你的现在，爱你的过去，甚至还爱你成长的道路。我爱你与那个被你称为我的阶级的不同之外，爱你的那些我虽然不理解，但相信一定会理解的观点。我将全力以赴去了解你的信仰。连你抽烟和说脏话我也要爱，因为它们是你的一部分。而且，我还可以学嘛。在刚才的十分钟里，我已经学到了不少东西。我敢冒风险来这里，就证明了我学习的成果。啊，马丁！——”她抽咽着，紧偎在他身上。

这一回，他才怀着怜悯之心温情地拥抱了她，而她感激涕零，高兴地晃动了一下身子，脸上散发出异彩。

“为时太迟了。”他说着，想起了丽茜的那席话，“我已患病在身——啊，病的不是我的躯体，而是我的心灵，我的大脑。我好像对什么都不看重，对什么都无所谓了。如果几个月前你能像现在一样，事情就会不同，如今太迟了。”

“还不算太迟。”她叫喊道，“我会让你看到的。我要向你证明我的爱已经加深，这份爱对我来说已经超越了我的阶级，超越了我所珍重的一切。资产阶级所珍重的一切都会遭到我的蔑视。我不再害怕生活。我要离开父母，不在乎我的朋友怎样嘲笑我。我愿立时就搬到这里来。如果你愿意，咱们可以同居。和你在一起，我会感到自豪和幸福。假如说我曾经背叛过爱情，那么现在为了爱情，我将背叛以前使我产生背叛行动的所有人。”

她站在他面前，两眼闪闪发光。

“我在等待，马丁，”她低声说，“等着你接受我。你瞧瞧我。”

他瞧了瞧她，心里赞叹不已。她补偿了自己过去的欠缺，终于挺直了腰杆，成为一个真正的女人，摆脱了资产阶级习俗铁的桎梏。她是那样了不起和出类拔萃，又是那样不顾一切。可是，他到底怎么啦？她的所作所为并没有引起他的激情或打动他的心。他只是从理智上觉得她了不起和出类拔萃。在这个应该迸发出火一般热情的时刻，他却在冰冷冷地对她进行评估。他心里没有受到感动，觉察不到一丝一毫对她的欲望。这时，他又想起了丽茜的话。

“我病了，病得很重，”他绝望地摆了摆手说，“直到现在我才知道自己病得这么严重。有样东西从我的心里消失了。我素来不害怕生活，但做梦也想不到会对生活感到餍足。我的心里被生活填充得严严实实，对任何事情都不会再产生欲望了。如果我的心里还有空地方，现在我一定会接受你的。你看得出我病得有多么厉害。”

他把脑袋朝后一靠，合上了眼睛；像一个哭泣的孩子，透过瞳孔上蒙着的一层模糊的泪水，一望到阳光便忘了内心的悲哀，马丁看见眼睑里出现一丛丛草木，看见火热的由光穿过枝叶发出耀眼的光芒，便忘掉了自己的病，忘掉了露丝的存在和所有的一切，那绿茵茵的草木并没有给人以宁静感。那阳光太强烈、太灿烂，看了让人觉得眼痛，可他还是在望着，自己也不知这是为什么。

门把手咔嗒一声响，使他清醒了过来，只见露丝站立在门边。

“我怎么出去呢？”她泪水汪汪地问，“我感到害怕。”

“哦，实在对不起，”他大声说着，跳起了身子，“瞧，我病得多厉害，竟然忘了你在这里。”他用手摸了摸头，“你知道，我的脑子有点不正常。我送你回家去。咱们从服务员的门出去，没有人会看到的。你把面纱拉下来，一切都会平安无事的。”

她紧挽住他的胳膊，穿过灯光黯淡的甬道，走下了狭窄的楼梯。

“现在没事啦。”他们一上了人行道，她就这么说道，同时想把手从他的胳膊上抽回来。

“不，不，还是让我把你送到家吧。”他回复道。

“请别送了，”她不同意地说，“没这个必要。”

她又想把手移开，这让他一时觉得奇怪。她这会儿已脱离了危险，却仍然一副害怕的样子。她惊慌失措，只要甩掉他。他想不出原因来，于是便把这归结于她太紧张的缘故。他拉住她的那只往回抽的手，陪着她继续朝前走。一段马路才走了一半，他瞧见一个身穿长大衣的男子缩进了一个门洞里。从旁边经过时，他朝门洞里望了一眼，尽管那人把衣领高高地翻起，但马丁认出他就是露丝的弟弟诺曼。

一路上，露丝和马丁都很少开口说话。她惊慌得魂不守舍，而他心灰意冷。有一回，他提了提自己要远走他乡，回到南海去；还有一回，她请求他原谅，说她不该来找他。除此之外，两人再没有别的话。到了她家门口，分手时平平淡淡。他们握了手，道了晚安，而后他把帽子朝上抬了抬。大门关上了，他点起一根烟，转身回旅馆去。当走到刚才看见诺曼缩进去的那个门洞前时，他停住了脚步，心里沉思着往里边望了望。

“她是个骗子。”他出声地说，“她明明知道那个送她来的弟弟在外边等着领她回去，却要我相信她冒了很大的风险。”他忍不住放声大笑起来，“呸，这些资产阶级呀！当我一贫如洗的时候，说我不配跟他的姐姐在一起。当我在银行有存款的时候，他却把她送上了门。”他扭过身来就走，一个跟他走同一方向的流浪汉在后边问他讨钱。

“喂，先生，能给我半角钱让我找个过夜的地方吗？”那人说。

那人的声音勾得他回过了头来。一眨眼工夫，马丁就和乔握起了手。

“还记得咱们在温泉旅馆分手时的情形吗？”对方说，“我当时就说咱们还能见面，因为我打心里能感觉得到。这不，咱们又相遇了。”“你看起来气色很好，”马丁羡慕地说，“你比以前还胖了些。”

“当然喽，”乔满脸喜气地说，“直到开始流浪，我才懂得了什么是生活。我体重增加了三十磅，感觉棒极啦。唉，在过去的那些日子里，我累得筋疲力尽。流浪生活非常适合我。”

“可你还不是要找过夜的地方，”马丁不屑地说，“今天晚上可真够冷的。”

“呃？找过夜的地方？”乔刷地把手伸进臀部口袋，掏出一大把零钱来，“这比干活强吧，”他得意地说，“我是看你像阔佬，才想敲你竹杠。”

马丁哈哈笑了笑，算服了他。

“这钱够你美美喝上几杯了。”他揶揄道。

乔把钱又放回了口袋里。

“再不喝了，”他宣称，“我可不想喝个烂醉。没有什么能阻止我饮酒，只不过我不愿喝罢啦。跟你分手后，我喝醉过一次，当时空着肚子，但没料到会醉。像牲口一样干活时，就像牲口一样开饮。当我过上人的生活，我就像人一样喝酒——兴致来了就偶尔喝上一杯，情况就是如此。”

马丁约好第二天与他见面，然后便径直回饭店了。他在前台停了停，查了查船期表。马利波萨号五天后驶往塔希提。

“明天打电话为我订个房舱，”他吩咐服务员说，“不要甲板上的，而要甲板以下的，要上风舷的——左舷，别忘了，要左舷。你最好写下来。”

回到自己的房间，他爬上床，像个孩子一样悄然入睡了。今天晚上发生的事情没有给他留下什么印象。他的大脑麻木得已经不能够接受印象了。他跟乔见面时突发的热情瞬间便逝，一转眼他便厌烦了那个从前的洗衣匠，觉得同他谈话十分勉强。五天之后，将乘船奔赴心爱的南海，这件事也引不起他的兴趣了。他闭上眼睛，正正常常、舒舒服服地一觉睡了八个小时。他睡得很安宁，没有变动姿势，也没有做梦。睡眠可以叫他忘掉一切。每天醒来，他都有一种遗憾的心情。生活使他烦恼、厌倦，而时间给他带来的是痛苦。

第四十六章

第二天早晨，他一见到自己以前的工友便说：“听我说，乔，第二十八大街有个法国人。他赚了许多钱，眼下要回法国去。他有家呱呱叫的、设备齐全的小规模蒸汽洗衣店。如果你想安顿下来，就拿这家店做个开端吧。这些钱你拿去买套衣服，十点钟到这个人的办公室去，洗衣店是他替我物色的，让他带你去那儿看看。如果你看中了，觉得价钱也合适——总共一万两千块钱——，只消跟我说一声，它就是你的了。你快去吧，我还忙着呢。咱们回头见。”

“你竖起耳朵听着，马特，”对方一字一板地说，同时心里的怒火直朝上冒，“今天早晨我是来看望你的。明白吗？我可不是来要什么洗衣店的。我是看在老朋友的面子上来和你聊聊，可你却把一家洗衣店施舍给了我。让我告诉你怎么做吧。你可以和那家洗衣店一道下地狱。”

他说完就想冲出屋子去，却被马丁一把扳住了肩膀，使他转回了身。

“你也给我听着，乔。”他说，“如果你再这么不懂事，我就揍你的脑袋瓜。正因为咱们是老朋友，我要狠狠地揍。明白吗？我会狠狠揍你的。愿意听话吗？”

乔猛地抱住他，想把他摔倒，而他拼命扭动着身子，想从乔的怀里挣出来，不让他占上风。两人搂抱成团在屋子里摔起了跤，最后哗啦一声倒在一把柳条椅上，把椅子压得粉碎。乔被压在下边，两条胳膊展开着被牢牢地按住，马丁用一个膝盖顶在他的胸口上。待马丁放开他的时候，他呼哧呼哧地直喘粗气。

“现在咱们可以谈谈啦，”马丁说，“你可别跟我对着干。我要你先把洗衣店的那桩事处理好，然后回来找我，那时咱们可以叙叙惜别之情。我说过我很忙。你瞧瞧。”

一位服务员送早班邮件，拿来一大堆信和杂志。

“我要看这许多东西，又要跟你谈话，这怎么能成呢？你去定洗衣店的事，回头咱们再谈。”

“好吧，”乔勉强地同意了，“原以为你会冷淡我呢，看来我猜错了。不过，要是正规打架，你可打不过我。我的拳头比你的硬。”

“那就让咱们改天见个高低吧。”马丁笑了笑说。

“当然好呀。我把洗衣店一安排好，咱们就较量。”乔说着，伸出了一条胳膊来，“看到这拳头了吗？它会打得你鬼哭狼嚎。”

待房门在这位洗衣匠的身后关上时，马丁如释重负地吁了口气。他对交往产生了抵触的情绪。他愈来愈觉得难以体面的态度待人了。有人在跟前他就不安，一与人谈话他就恼火。人们令他烦躁，于是他刚和人们接触，就想方设法要摆脱他们。

他没有看邮件，懒洋洋地在椅子上足足坐了有半个小时，什么事情也不干。只有些模糊和不完整的念头偶尔渗入他的意识，或者更确切地说，他那忽明忽暗的意识里只有这些隔很长一段时间才出现一次的念头。

后来他强打精神，开始翻阅信件。有十几封信是请求他亲笔签名的——他一看就知道；其中也有专业团体要求捐款的信；还有些是怪人寄来的信，其中有一个说他制作了一台永动机，还有一个说他能证明地球的表面下是一个空心的球体，另外有一个则请求他给予经济援助，说要买下加利福尼亚半岛，建立一个共产主义社会。有些信是女人写来的，想跟他结识。他看到其中的一封这样的信不由笑了起来。因为有个女人在信里附了张交付教堂座位费的收据，以此证明她的虔诚和高尚。

每天的邮件堆里总有编辑和出版商的信，前者低三下四地要他的文章，后者死乞白赖地要他的书稿——岂不知他在那几多凄风苦雨的日月里为了把这些可怜的、遭人鄙弃的手稿邮寄出去，当掉了自己所有的东西。邮件堆里也有意想不到的支票，有英国人购买连载权的钱，也有外国译本出版人预付的版税。他在英国的代理人通知他有三本书已经卖掉了出德译本的版权，并通知他瑞典文译本已经问世，但由于瑞典不是伯尔尼[1]会议的缔约国，他一分钱也拿不到手。此外，还收到俄国的来信，请求准许出俄译本——这是有名无实的，因为这个国家也不是伯尔尼会议的缔约国。

他回过头来看他的新闻代理人寄来的一大包剪报材料，看到他和他的作品已红得发紫。他创作的所有东西，全都似一股旋风出现在公众的眼前，看来这就是他的走红原因。他像吉卜林一样，风靡了读者群。正当他奄奄待毙时，公众却群情激昂，突然对他的书产生了兴趣。他忘不了，正是这些遍布全世界的读者曾经捧读吉卜林的作品，虽然一点也看不出个名堂，却为吉卜林高声喝彩，可是没过几个月，他们又猛扑到吉卜林身上，将他撕成碎片。想到这里，马丁苦笑了一声。他算老几，难道敢肯定几个月后不会有同样的遭遇？所以，他要捉弄一下公众。他要远走高飞到南海去，在那里盖草房、贩卖珍珠和椰子干，他将划着轻巧的独木舟越过珊瑚礁去捕鲨鱼和鲣鱼，将到泰奥海伊峡谷旁边的悬崖峭壁上猎野山羊。

想着想着，他便意识到自己已到了穷途末路。他清楚地看到自己正置身于幽灵峡谷。他的生命在消失、衰弱，走向死亡。他发现自己睡眠太多，睡觉的欲望过于强烈。过去他痛恨睡眠，因为睡眠夺去了他宝贵的生活时间。二十四小时里睡四个小时的觉，就等于少活四个小时。当时他是多么仇恨睡神啊！而现在他仇恨的却是生活。生活一点也不美好，在他看来一点也不甜蜜，有的只是苦涩。这是一个危险的信号。一个人如果不向往生活，就是在向生命的终点迈进，一种淡淡的求生的本能在他的体内蠕动，他知道自己必须离开这里。他在屋里朝四下望了一眼，觉得整理行李是个负担。也许，最好把整理行李放到最后去做。利用这段时间，可以去筹备一套行头。

他戴上帽子，走出房门，来到枪支店，用了半上午的时间购买自动步枪、弹药和渔具。做买卖的方式起了变化，他发现自己必须抵达塔希提后才能够订货。这也没关系，反正货物会从澳洲发来的。这样一来，他反倒高兴了起来。这件事他总算躲过去了，眼下无论干任何事情都叫他不快。他愉快地回到饭店，一想到那把舒适的莫里斯安乐椅在等着他，心里就有一种满足的感觉；可进了自己的房间，看到乔坐在那把莫里斯安乐椅上，他不禁暗自哼了一声。

乔对洗衣店十分满意，一切都已安排妥当，就等着第二天接管了。当他滔滔不绝讲话的时候，马丁闭着眼睛躺在床上。马丁的思绪飘得很远，远得他几乎都觉察不到自己在思索了。他几次都是很勉强地回答了对方的问话。这位可是他过去一直都很喜欢的乔啊。然而，乔过于热爱生活，这一点如汹涌的浪涛冲击着他腻烦的心灵，似钢针刺疼了他疲惫的神经，当乔提醒他说他们将来可以找个时间较量一下时，他差一点尖叫起来。

“别忘了，乔，你得根据你当初在雪莱温泉旅馆制订的那些章程管理这家洗衣店。”他说，“不许加班，不许开夜车，轧液机旁不用童工，别的地方也不能用童工，工资要公平合理。”

乔点了点头，掏出一个笔记本来。

“你瞧这个。这是我早饭以前拟出的章程。不知你意下如何？”

他把章程念了一遍。马丁都同意了，同时心里在嘀咕着，不知乔什么时候才肯离开。

待他醒来时，天色已近黄昏。他慢慢地回到了现实生活中来。他把屋里四下望了望。乔显然是在他昏然睡去后悄悄溜走的。他觉得乔还是怪能体贴人的。后来，他合上眼又睡着了。

后边的几天里，乔忙于筹划和接管洗衣店，不太来打搅他。直到启航的前一天，报纸上才宣布他要乘坐马利波萨号旅行。他那求生的本能又一次在他体内跳动，于是他去找医生检查了身体。他一点毛病也没有。医生说他的心和肺都非常健康。据医生的了解，他的每一个器官都很正常，功能没有任何异样。

“你一点毛病都没有，伊登先生，”医生说，“我肯定你没有任何毛病。你的健康状况极佳。老实说，我很羡慕你的身体，真是棒极啦。瞧瞧这胸脯。你之所以有着良好的体质，其秘诀都在你的胸膛里。像你这样的体格，可谓千里——万里挑一。要是不出意外，你可以活到一百岁。”

马丁情知丽茜的诊断是正确的。他的身体没有毛病，出故障的是他的“思维机器”，除了到南海去，别无灵丹妙药。麻烦在于，正值即将启程的节骨眼上，他却不想去了。南海和资产阶级文明一样，对他失去了吸引力。在想到要出发的时候，他没有一丝热情，出去旅行这件事使他惊慌，因为那会叫他的肉体感到劳累。如果已经上了船，已经扬帆启航，他倒会感觉好受些。

最后一天像受刑一样让人痛苦。从早报上得知了他将乘船旅行的消息后，伯纳德·希金波森和葛特露带着全家，以及赫尔曼·冯·施米特夫妇都赶来话别。另外还得料理事务、清付账单，以及应付纷至沓来的记者。他到夜校的门口跟丽茜·康诺莱匆匆道了别，便急忙走开了。回到饭店里，他发现乔在等他。乔忙了一整天洗衣店的事，此刻才脱出身来。马丁觉得这最后的时刻实在难熬，但他抓住椅子的把手，又是听又是说，足足有半个小时。

“你要知道，乔，”他说，“你不必把自己死死绑在洗衣店里。那儿可没有绳子捆你。你随时都可以卖掉洗衣店，把得来的钱花掉。什么时候你厌倦了，又想过流浪生活，那你就退出，反正你怎么高兴就怎么来。”

乔摇了摇头。

“谢谢你的好意，我可是再也不想流浪了。流浪生活倒是挺不错，就是有一点不足——找不到姑娘。这就让人受不了，因为我这人就喜欢女人，离了女人是不行的。可当了流浪汉就得清心寡欲，有时候路过举办舞会和聚会的人家，听到女人的笑声，从窗口看到女人的白裙子和笑脸——嗨，那滋味真是痛苦极啦。我非常喜欢跳舞、野餐和在月光下散步等娱乐。我愿意开洗衣店，活得排排场场，口袋里大洋叮当叮当响。我已经交上了女朋友，虽然是昨天才交的，但我真恨不得马上跟她结婚。一想到这件事，今天我就高兴得直吹口哨。她长得很美，有一双温柔的眼睛，说话和蔼可亲。我一定娶她，你等着瞧吧。我问你，你有这么多钱，为什么不结婚呢？你能得到天下最好的姑娘。”马丁笑着摇了摇头，内心里觉得奇怪，不明白一个男人为什么要结婚。结婚好像是一种莫名其妙，叫人无法理解的事情。

快开船的时候，他从马利波萨号的甲板上望见丽茜·康诺莱站在码头上，躲在前几排人丛中。他产生了一个念头，想带她一起走。这可是轻而易举之事，她一定会大喜过望。这个念头刹那间几乎对他形成了诱惑，但紧接着他就恐慌了起来。他内心的想法让他感到惊乱，他的那颗疲倦的心大声地发出了抗议。于是，他呻吟一声，从栏杆那儿扭过身去，喃喃地说：“伙计，你病得太厉害了，病得太厉害了。”

他逃进船舱，在那儿一直躲到轮船离开码头。中午在餐厅里吃饭的时候，他被安置到贵宾席位上，坐在船长的右首。他很快就发现自己成了船上了不起的人物，但再了不起也没有给他一丝一毫称心如意的感觉。下午，他躺在甲板躺椅上，闭着眼一个劲打盹，晚上早早就上了床。

第二天一过，晕船的都复原了，所有的旅客都露了面，可是他跟他们接触得愈多就愈讨厌他们。他知道这样看待他们是不公正的。他强迫自己承认他们是些善良的好人，而就在承认的当儿又得出这样的结论——他们虽善良，但与所有的资产阶级是一样的，具有褊狭的心理和空洞的思想。和他们交谈让他厌腻，因为他们那卑鄙和浅薄的大脑里简直是一片空白；而年轻一代那兴高采烈的情绪和过分旺盛的精力却使他颇为惊讶。他们从来不肯安分，一刻不停地在甲板上掷绳圈，抛铁环，来回溜达，要不，闹嚷嚷地涌到栏杆边观看水里跃起的海豚和第一批出现的飞鱼。

他的觉睡得很多。一吃过早餐，他就拿上一本永远也看不完的杂志往甲板躺椅上坐。那些铅字让他疲倦。他想不通人们怎么有这么多的素材可写，想着想着就在躺椅上打起盹来。午饭的铃声响时，他不得不起来，这让他又气又恼。他一点也不愿意醒着。

有一回，他想摆脱这种昏昏欲睡的状态，便打起精神到水手舱去找水手们。然而，这些人似乎跟他当水手时的同伴不一样。他觉得自己和这些面孔呆板、思想愚鲁、缺乏理性的人之间没有任何相通之处。他陷入了绝望之中。在上层社会，喜欢他的人当中没有一个喜欢的是他马丁·伊登本人，而现在他又无法再回到过去曾喜欢过他的那个自己的阶层中去。他不喜欢他们，无法容忍他们，就像他无法容忍头等舱里的那些愚蠢的旅客以及那些吵吵嚷嚷的年轻人一样。

他觉得自己是一个病人，而生活像一道强烈的白光刺得他那疲倦的眼睛发疼。在有知觉的每一秒钟里，都有生活的火光在他的周围、在他的身上闪耀，照得他难受，使他痛不欲生。他这辈子还是头一回乘坐上等舱。以前航海时，他不是住水手舱、三等舱，就是在黑洞洞的煤舱深处搬煤。在那些日子里，他攀着铁梯爬出闷热的船舱时，常常看到乘客穿着凉爽的白衣服，悠闲自得地什么也不干，头上张着帆布篷遮挡阳光和风，把唯命是从的服务员指挥得跑来跑去，当时他觉得他们身处仙境，过的是天堂里的生活。现在他自己成了船上了不起的人物，成了人们心目中的中心人物，坐在船长的右首，可他偏要回到水手舱里去徒劳无益地寻找失去的天堂。他非但未发现新的天堂，也未找到旧的天堂。

他想振作起来，找点能引起兴趣的事做。于是，他到船员餐厅里去吃饭，但待在那里只让他不高兴。他和一位下了岗的舵手进行了交谈，那人生性聪敏，马上对他展开社会主义宣传，把一叠传单和小册子塞进了他手里。马丁听那人讲解奴隶的道德观，听着听着便倦怠地思索起了自己的那一套尼采哲学。这一切都有什么价值呢？他记得尼采说过一句疯话，疯狂地怀疑真理。谁说得准呢？也许尼采是对的，任何事物都无真理可言，连事实里都没有真理——根本就不存在真理这回事。他的大脑很快就累了，很想回到椅子上打盹。

船上的日子已经够难熬了，可他偏偏又产生了新的苦恼。到了塔希提后会怎么样呢？那时他得上岸去，得定购货物和乘帆船到马克萨斯群岛去，得干一千一万件想起来都让人害怕的事。每当他硬着头皮思索的时候，就会发现自己身处极其危险的境地。实际上，他已走进了幽灵峡谷，他的危机就在于他一点儿也不害怕。假如他感到害怕，他肯定会逃生的。正因为无怯意，他才一步步向谷底走去。在过去所熟悉的事物中，他找不到一点乐趣。马利波萨号正顶着东北贸易风行驶，那美酒般的风儿吹拂在他身上，却让他气恼。他挪开椅子，想躲避这过去日夜陪伴着他的同伴那热情洋溢的拥抱。

马利波萨号驶入赤道无风带的那天，马丁更加苦恼了。他睡得过多，再也睡不着了，于是只好醒着忍受生活那白炽火光的照耀。他走来走去，烦躁不安。空气黏糊糊、湿漉漉，暴风雨也没有给人带来凉爽。生活使他痛苦。他在甲板上四处溜达，实在受不了就在椅子上坐坐，然后起来再转悠。最后，他强迫自己看完了那本杂志，又从船上的图书室里挑了几本诗集。但这些诗集引不起他的兴趣，于是他又踱起了步。

晚饭后他在甲板上待了很长时间，然而这也无济于事。回到舱里，他还是无法入睡。连这种短暂的休息他也享受不到，这叫他无法忍受。他打开电灯，想看会儿书。有一本诗集是斯温伯恩的著作。他躺在床上翻阅了起来，翻着翻着突然来了兴趣。他把一个章节看完，还想朝下看，可不由又翻了回来。他将书反扣在胸口上，陷入沉思。答案就在这里，这就是答案。奇怪，以前他怎么就没想到过！所有的一切都在此不白自明；他的漫游一直都走的是这个方向，而今斯温伯恩向他指明这就是痛快的出路。他渴望安息，而归宿就在这里。他望了望敞开的舷窗，看到那儿倒是挺宽敞。几个星期以来，他第一次有了喜悦的心情，因为他终于找到了治疗自身病疾的良方。他捧起诗集，慢慢地朗诵那一节：

放弃了对生活的热恋，

摆脱恐惧、告别希望，

我们虔诚地祈祷，

感谢冥冥的上苍，

幸喜生命终有尽期；

死去的不复站起；

纵使疲倦的河流蜿蜒曲回，

总会平安归向海洋。

他又望了望那舷窗。斯温伯恩提供了答案。生活是一场噩梦，或者更确切地说，它变成了一场噩梦，化为叫人无法忍受的东西。“死去的不复站起！”这一诗行深深打动了他，令他感激涕零。这可是天地之间唯一叫人向往的事情。当生活充满了痛苦，令人厌倦的时候，死亡会哄你沉沉入睡、长眠不醒。还有什么可犹豫的呢？该走啦！

他立起身，抱头探出舷窗，低头望着那浑浊的浪花。马利波萨号满载着旅客，吃水很深，用两手抓住窗子，便可以把脚伸进水里。他可以无声无息地钻入水里，谁都听不见，一朵浪花飞溅起，打湿了他的面孔。他的嘴唇发咸，那味道很是不错。他想着是否应该写一篇绝笔，但随即便一笑置之。已经没有时间了，他迫不及待地要赴黄泉之路。

他熄掉舱里的灯，免得暴露行踪，然后把脚先伸出了舷窗，不料肩膀却被卡住了，于是他抽回身，将一条胳膊紧贴在身旁，再次朝外钻。船体的摆动帮了他的忙，他借力钻出，用手抓紧窗子。双脚一触到海水，他就松了手，落入浑浊的泡沫里。马利波萨号的舷体似一堵黑墙从他身边擦过，星星点点的舷窗里亮着灯光。轮船向前疾驶，几乎未待他清醒过来就把他甩到了后边。他慢慢地在泡沫飞溅的海面上游着。

一条鲣鱼在他白皙的身子上咬了一口，惹得他笑出了声。他身上掉了一块肉，疼痛感才使他想起了投海的目的。他刚才过于忙碌，竟忘了自己的目标。马利波萨号上的灯光在远方愈来愈模糊，而他却在这儿满怀信心地游着泳，就好像一门心思要游到千里开外的最近的陆地似的。

这是一种不由自主地求生本能。他停止了游泳，但一觉得海水漫过嘴，便又猛然伸手划水，让身子朝上浮。他心想这是求生的意志，随即便轻蔑地哼了一声。哈，他还有意志——坚强的意志！只消最后一用劲，这意志就会毁于一旦、烟消云散。

他变变姿势，直立起来，抬头望望静悄悄的群星，同时吐净了肺里的空气。他猛然手脚并用，狠劲划水，将肩膀和半个胸脯都露出水面。这样做是为了能在潜水时多一份冲力。接着，他放松身子，一动不动地朝下沉，似一尊白色雕像没入海中。他有意识地深深吸一口海水，就像一个人服麻醉剂一样。他感到窒息，可这时他的胳膊和腿却乱划一气，把他托出水面，使他又清楚地看到了群星。

他竭力不让空气进入他那快要破裂的肺里，但却徒劳一场。他不肩地心想这是求生的意志在作祟。看来，必须重新换一种方法。他把空气吸进肺里，让里边充得满满的，这样便可以潜得深一些。他转过身，头朝下用出全身的力气和全部的意志往底层游去。他愈潜愈深，睁眼望着那磷光闪闪、幽灵般冲来冲去的鲣鱼群。他一边游，一边希望那些鱼不要来咬他，因为那样会摧毁他紧绷的意志。幸好那些鱼没有咬他，于是他充满了感激之情，感谢生活赐给他这最后一点好处。

他不断地往下游，累得四肢发酸，几乎动弹不得。他知道自己已到了深处。他的耳膜被海水挤压得发痛，脑袋嗡嗡作响。他的耐受力正在崩溃，可他拼命划动四肢把自己朝更深处送，直至意志动摇，肺里的空气猛然喷射出来。一串串气泡朝上泛起，似小气球般跳动着，摩擦着他的脸颊和眼睛。旋踵而至的便是疼痛和窒息。他眩晕的大脑里闪过这样一个念头：这不是死亡，因为死亡没有痛苦。他还活着，这是生存的痛苦，是一种可怕的令人窒息的感觉。这是生活所能给予他的最后一击。

他那倔强的手脚开始击打水，间歇地，有气无力地划动。他愚弄了它们，愚弄了驱使它们击打和划动的求生意志。他游得太深了，它们已无法把他送到海面上去了。他似乎懒洋洋地漂浮在梦境的海洋里。五彩光环包裹着他、沐浴着他，浸透了他的身体。那是什么？好像是一座灯塔。其实，那东西仅存在于他的大脑中——是一道耀眼夺目的白光，闪动得愈来愈快。随着长长的一声轰隆巨响，他觉得自己滚下了非常长的一条宽楼梯。到了底层，他跌入黑暗之中。他明白自己坠入黑暗的世界。就在他明白这一点的瞬间，他的感觉停止了。

[1]　1886年在瑞士首都伯尔尼召开的会议，缔结了国际版权公约。

第一章　是什么让你疲惫，如何应对疲惫

这里有个重要而惊人的事实：单纯地进行脑力劳动并不会使你疲惫。这听起来似乎很荒唐，不过几年前科学家曾试图了解人类大脑工作多久后会“降低工作效率”——疲惫的定义。科学家们惊讶地发现，大脑在持续活动时，经过大脑的血液丝毫没有留下疲惫的痕迹！如果你从体力劳动者的动脉中抽取一滴血液，你会发现其中充满了“疲劳毒素”和其他因疲劳产生的物质。但如果你从爱因斯坦的动脉中抽取一滴血，则不会发现任何疲劳毒素。

目前看来，大脑在工作八小时甚至十二个小时后依然如新。大脑的耐疲劳性无与伦比……那么究竟是什么让你疲惫呢？

精神病学家宣称，大多数疲劳来自我们的精神状态和情绪。英国最显赫的精神病学家A．A．布里尔博士的观点更绝对：“百分之百脑力劳动者的疲劳都来自精神因素，也就是情绪。”

那么，何种情绪因素会使脑力劳动者感到疲惫呢？愉悦？满足？不！绝不是！感觉无聊、愤恨、不被赏识、徒劳、匆忙、焦虑才是使人感到疲惫的情绪因素，这些情绪还会使人易患感冒，效率降低，因头痛而不得不提早下班。没错，坏情绪使身体紧张，因此我们才会疲惫不堪。

大都会人寿保险公司在一张宣传画上指出：“努力工作这件事本身所制造的疲惫，如果可以睡个好觉或是好好休息，就能得到大大的缓解。只有忧虑、紧张和不良情绪才是造成疲惫的三大原因。往往在人们归罪于体力和脑力劳动时，事实上，这些因素才是罪魁祸首。请记住，紧张的肌肉便是工作着的肌肉。学会放松些！把精力留给重要的任务。”

现在请停下来做一下自我检查。当你阅读这几行文字时，你是否皱着眉头？你的双目之间是否是紧绷的？你感觉自己的坐姿放松吗？你的肩膀是否耸起？你脸上的肌肉紧张吗？如果你的整个身体不像旧娃娃一样松弛，那么此时此刻你正在制造着神经和肌肉的紧张，也就意味着你制造着神经和肌肉的疲劳！

为何在进行脑力工作时会产生不必要的紧张呢？丹尼尔·W．乔斯林说过：“我发现最主要的原因是一种几乎普遍存在的意识，即认为努力工作需要卖力，否则这件事就做不好。”所以我们在聚精会神时会不由自主地紧锁眉头、耸起肩膀。我们命令肌肉做出努力的姿态——而这并不会帮助大脑进行工作。

精神疲劳的解药是什么？放松！放松！放松！一定要记住，学会在工作时放松！

这听起来似乎很容易，但事实上很难。因为你可能需要改变一辈子养成的习惯，但努力是值得的——它有可能给你的人生带来一场革命！威廉·詹姆斯在《放松宝典》一文中说过：“美国人的过度紧张、躁动、急促以及表达方式的夸张和强烈，都只不过是坏习惯而已。”紧张是一种习惯，放松也是一种习惯。而我们可以改正坏习惯，养成好习惯。

怎样才能放松呢？从心理开始还是从神经开始？都不是。要记住，永远先从肌肉开始！

让我们来试试吧。让我们先从眼睛开始，展示如何放松。请通读此段，当你读到此段结尾时，后背向后倚，闭上眼睛，默默对自己说：放松，放松，不要紧张，不要皱眉……放松，放松……慢慢地重复一分钟。

你是否察觉眼部的肌肉在几秒钟后开始听话了？是否感觉到有双无形的手抚走了紧张？就是如此神奇，你在一分钟内已经尝试了放松艺术的全部诀窍和秘密。你也可以用同样的方法放松你的下巴、脸颊、脖子、肩膀以及全身，但最关键的器官还是眼睛。芝加哥大学的埃德蒙·雅各布森博士甚至说过，如果能彻底放松眼部肌肉，你就能忘掉所有烦恼！眼睛之所以对于缓解神经紧张发挥着如此重要的作用，是因为它们占用了身体精神能量总消耗的四分之一。这也是为什么视力完美的人也会出现眼部疲劳的现象，都是眼部的紧张造成的。

著名小说家维姬·鲍姆说，她小时候遇到了一位老人，并从他那里学到了最重要的一课。有一次，她摔倒了，膝盖和手腕都受了伤，这时老人过来把她扶了起来。这位老人曾经在马戏团演过小丑，他一边拍去她身上的尘土一边说：“你受伤是因为你不懂如何放松自己。你得想象着自己就像只软塌塌的袜子，又柔弱又软和。来吧，让我教给你如何做。”

后来，那位老人还教给维姬·鲍姆和其他的小孩们如何奔跑、如何翻跟斗。他总是反复强调：“想象着自己柔软得像只皱巴巴的旧袜子，自然就可以放松了！”

你可以在任何奇怪的场合进行放松，只要你不刻意地、夸张地去放松。放松意味着抹去一切紧张和压迫，感受从容与自在。从想象眼睛与脸部的肌肉开始学习放松。反复对自己说：放松……放松……放松……感受能量从脸部肌肉流向身体中心，想象着自己像婴儿一样没有丝毫的紧张感。

伟大的女高音歌唱家嘉丽·库契就是这样做的。海伦·杰普森告诉我，她常常看到嘉丽·库契在演出前坐在椅子里，慢慢放松脸部肌肉，她的下巴放松得简直就像要坠下来了一样。这是个很好的习惯，这样会使她在上台前避免过于紧张、防止疲劳。

下面是帮助你放松的四个建议：

1．随时随地放松。尽量让你的身体像旧袜子一样松弛。我在办公桌上放了一只褐红色的袜子，提醒着自己应该如此松弛。如果你没有袜子，一只猫也行。你是否曾经抱起过在阳光下睡觉的猫？放松就是猫那种像湿报纸一样耷下来、软绵绵的感觉。就连印度的瑜伽修行者都说过，若想掌握放松的艺术就要研究猫。我从来没见过疲惫、神经崩溃或者是失眠、忧虑、得胃溃疡的猫。你如果能学会像猫一样放松，那么或许也能避免被这些症状所困扰。

2．工作时尽可能地选用舒服的姿势。记住，身体上的紧张会导致肩膀疼痛和神经疲劳。

3．每天自我检查四五次，问自己：“我是否努力过头了？我是否在用与工作无关的肌肉？”这会帮助你养成放松的习惯。就如大卫·哈罗德·芬克博士所说：“最懂心理学的人都知道这是事半功倍的习惯。”

4．一天结束前再做一次自我检查，反省自己：“我究竟有多累？如果感觉累，那不是因为脑力劳动本身，而是我进行劳动的方式不对。”丹尼尔·W．乔斯林说：“我不以每天的疲劳程度来衡量自己的成就，而是以轻松的程度来衡量。一天下来如果我感觉特别疲劳，我便知道，这一天的工作在数量和质量上毫无疑问都是低效的。”如果美国的所有商业人士都懂得这个道理，那么高血压死亡率一定会一夜间骤减的，我们的疗养所和精神病院也不会出现因疲劳和焦虑而崩溃的病人们了。

第二章　告别不良情绪，重返好心情

疲惫的首要原因便是厌烦。让我们用爱丽丝的故事来举例说明。爱丽丝是住在某一条街上的一个企业小职员。有一天她精疲力竭地回到家，她的一举一动中都显露出她很疲惫。她头痛，后背也痛，连晚饭都不想吃，只想直接去睡觉。她的母亲苦苦劝说她才坐到了饭桌边。这时电话铃响了，是男友打来的，邀请她去跳舞。她的眼睛里忽然有了光芒，精神也振奋了。她跑到楼上，换上了最适合她的蓝色长裙就跑去跳舞了，直到凌晨三点才回来。回来后她一点都不累。实际上她兴奋得一夜睡不着觉。

八小时前的爱丽丝看似十分疲惫，但她真的是累了吗？也许当时是真的。她很累，因为工作令她厌烦，或许生活也使她厌烦。世界上有无数个爱丽丝，你或许就是其中之一。

众所周知，情绪因素比生理因素更会使人疲惫。几年前，约瑟夫·E．巴尔马克博士在《心理学档案》中发表了一篇实验报告，报告中论述了厌烦的情绪是如何导致疲劳的。巴尔马克博士让一组学生完成一系列他们不感兴趣的测试。结果，学生们不仅感到又疲劳又困乏，还抱怨感到头痛、眼睛不适、心情不好等症状。有些人甚至连胃都不舒服了。这些都是学生们幻想出来的吗？当然不是。他们还对这些学生做了新陈代谢的测试，结果显示当他们感觉厌烦时，体内血压和耗氧量都会降低。而一旦他们产生了兴趣和喜悦，整个新陈代谢的速度都会立刻加快！

在做有趣、刺激的事时，我们很少会感到疲惫。比如说，最近我在加拿大洛基山脉的路易斯湖附近度假。我一连几天都在珊瑚溪边钓鳟鱼，试图越过比我还高的树丛、木桩、倒塌的树木，然而这样的八个小时过后我一点也不累。为什么？因为我很兴奋、激动不已。钓到六条凶猛的鳟鱼，让我很有成就感。但如果我在钓鱼的时候感到无聊，你觉得我又会有怎样的感受呢？我肯定会因在海拔七千尺的高度做着如此费劲的工作而感到精疲力竭。

即便是在爬山这样令人劳累的活动中，厌烦的情绪依然比体力消耗本身更令人感到疲惫。明尼阿波利斯农业与机械储蓄银行总裁S．H．金曼先生曾跟我说起过一件事，这件事完美地证实了上述观点。1953年7月，加拿大政府要求加拿大登山俱乐部为威尔士亲王的皇家园林卫队提供登山培训，金曼先生就是被选中的培训者之一。他告诉我，他和其他指导员——几个四十二到五十九岁的男人，是如何带领这支年轻团队徒步穿过冰天雪地，以及依靠绳子越过了四十尺高的、几乎没有落手落脚之处的悬崖的。他们登上了迈克尔峰、副总统峰，以及加拿大洛基山脉小约赫山谷里的其他不知名山峰。经过十五个小时的攀岩后，这些身体素质处于顶峰的年轻人个个都已经精疲力竭了（在此之前，他们刚刚完成了六周艰苦的突击训练）。

是攀岩用到了突击训练时未练结实的肌肉而导致了疲惫吗？任何经历过突击训练的人都会鄙视这个可笑的问题！不，他们之所以感到极度劳累是因为他们认为爬山非常无聊，他们疲惫到连饭都没吃就睡着了。但是那些指导员，年龄是年轻士兵两到三倍的人，他们难道就不感觉累吗？不，他们当然也很累，但还没到精疲力竭的程度。他们吃了晚饭，还继续聊了好几个小时的天，聊这一天的经历。他们并没有精疲力竭，因为他们对攀岩这件事感兴趣。

哥伦比亚的爱德华·桑代克博士曾经进行过一项关于疲劳的实验，他调动年轻人的兴趣而使他们连续一周不睡觉。经过大量调查及实验后，桑代克博士得出结论：“厌倦是工作效率降低的唯一原因。”

如果你是脑力工作者，使你疲劳的原因很少会是劳动本身，你或许是因为还剩多少没有做的工作而感觉疲劳的。比如上周某天你工作时总是受到干扰，该回的信一封都没有回；提前制定的日程都打乱了……你觉得处处都是麻烦。那天一切都不顺，你什么都没做成，却感觉疲惫不堪，头都快裂开了。

第二天却完全不一样，一切都进展得很顺利，你完成的工作是前一天的四十倍，然而一天下来你却神清气爽，到家时感觉就像一朵白色栀子花一样。你我肯定都有过那样的经历。

因此我们要学到的是：疲劳往往不是工作造成的，而是担心、焦虑和愤恨造成的。

撰写此章时，我去看了一部重排的音乐戏剧，杰罗姆·科尔恩的《演艺船》。剧中的棉花号上的安迪船长说了一句充满哲理的台词：“幸运的人能做自己所爱的事。”这些人是幸运的，因为他们有更多的精力和欢乐，而极少有焦虑与疲劳。兴趣在哪儿，精力就在哪儿。和满腹怨言的妻子或丈夫走一个路口要比和甜蜜爱人走十个路口累多了。

所以呢？你能做些什么？一位速记员是这样做的：她在俄克拉何马州塔尔萨市的一家石油公司上班。每个月中总有几天她都要重复一项再无趣不过的工作——往石油租约表格里录入数据。这项任务太单调枯燥了，以至于她下定决心为了自己的身心健康也要把它变得有趣起来。她是怎样做到呢？她决定每天都和自己竞赛，每天上午都要数清填好的表格数量，下午试图超越上午的工作量。她每天都算出填表总数，争取下一天填得更多。结果，这样做以后，她填的表格总数是部门中最多的。这一切能带给她什么？赞美？没有。感谢？也没有。升职、提薪？更没有。但是这帮助她避免了厌倦所导致的疲惫，给了她精神上的刺激。由于她尽力使无聊的工作变得有趣，她拥有了更多精力和热情，在闲暇时也获得了更多快乐。

我保证这个故事是真的，因为我娶了这个女孩为妻。

下面是另外一个速记女孩试图以工作为乐趣从而得到回报的故事。她曾经极度反感自己的工作，但现在不同了。她就是伊利诺伊州埃尔姆赫斯特市的瓦莉·G．格尔登小姐。她在信中讲到了自己的故事：

“我们办公室里一共有四个速记员，每个人都要处理来自不同主管的信件，有时我们会忙得不可开交。有一天，当某一位部门副总坚持让我重写一封信时，我一开始很抗议。我试图指出不必全部重写也能在信件上做出改动。然而他坚决地说：如果你不重写，我可以找别人做这份工作！我气得直冒烟。不过当我开始重新打字时，我忽然意识到，的确有很多人会争先恐后地做我这份工作，而且在做这件事时，我不是也拿到了薪水吗？这样一想，我感觉好多了。所以我决定尝试着去爱这份工作，或假装很爱——尽管事实并非如此。后来我有了一个重要的发现，如果我在做事时假装很爱这个差事，我就真的有可能在某种程度上喜欢上它。我还发现，当我喜欢做一件事时，速度也会提高，因此我现在很少需要加班了。这种新态度帮我赢得了好员工的名声。因此，当一个部门的主管需要私人秘书时，他就想到了我，想请我做这份工作，他说我总是超额完成任务还毫无怨言。观念转变所带来的力量对我来说是难以想象的。它简直有创造奇迹的能量！”

格尔登小姐的故事有力地印证了汉斯·费英格教授的“假设”哲学。他让我们在行动时假设自己是幸福的。

如果你假装喜欢自己的工作，那份“佯装”真的会提升你的兴趣，也就会减少你疲劳、紧张和焦虑的感受。

几年前，哈伦·A．霍华德做了一个改变他一生的决定，他发誓要把枯燥的工作变得有趣。他的工作也的确很枯燥，在高中午餐室刷盘子、擦台子、盛冰淇淋，而其他男孩不是在玩球就是在逗女孩。哈伦·霍华德讨厌他的工作，但为了生存不得不做，所以他决心研究冰淇淋。他想了解冰淇淋该如何制作、需要哪些配料以及为何有些冰淇淋更好吃。他认真地学习了冰淇淋的化学组成，也慢慢成了高中化学课上的奇才。他对食物化学产生了浓厚的兴趣，后来考上了马萨诸塞州立学院的食品技术系。纽约可可交易所举办了一个关于可可和巧克力的使用的有奖征集论文活动，猜猜是谁获胜并得到了一百美金的奖励？没错，正是哈伦·霍华德。

后来在找工作未果期间，霍华德把麻省阿默斯特市家中的地下室变成了他的私人实验室。不久后阿默斯特市通过了一项新的法律，要求牛奶上市前必须经过细菌量计算。霍华德很快便开始为十四家阿默斯特的牛奶公司计算细菌量，还雇了两名助手。

二十五年后他又会在做什么？这位经营食品化学技术公司的老板将退休或死去；那些积极、热情的年轻人会取代他的位置。二十五年后，哈伦·霍华德或许成了业界中的领袖，而与他一同卖冰淇淋的同学或许会失业，还会骂政府、抱怨自己从未得到过机会。霍华德若不是立志要使无聊的工作有趣起来，或许也不会得到任何机会。

几年前还有另外一个年轻人也在做着同样很枯燥的工作——在车床场生产螺丝钉，他叫山姆。山姆一直想辞职，但担心找不到其他工作。山姆告诉自己，既然他必须做这份工作，那么他要使工作变得有趣。所以他决定和旁边的技工比赛。一个人要把粗糙的一面抛光，而另一个人要把螺丝钉磨到合适的长度。他们偶尔交换机器，看谁能制造出最多的螺丝钉。组长对山姆工作的速度和精确度印象深刻，很快便给了他一份更好的工作。这仅仅是一系列晋升的开始。三十年后，山姆成了鲍尔温机车厂的厂长。但假如当初山姆没有立志把无聊的工作变得有趣，那或许他一辈子都将是一个普普通通的小技工。

著名广播分析家H．V．卡腾伯恩曾告诉我他是如何使无聊的工作变得有趣的。二十二岁时，他在一艘横渡大西洋的牲口船上喂牲口。后来，在骑自行车游览英国后，他饥肠辘辘、身无分文地来到了巴黎。他卖了相机，拿到五块钱，在巴黎版《纽约先锋报》上刊登了一则广告，找到了一份卖立体感幻灯机的工作。我还记得这种老式幻灯机，把它放在眼前看两幅一样的图片，看着看着，奇迹就发生了。幻灯机中的两个镜片把两张图片转换成了一张三维图片，我们看到了深度和惊人的立体感。

书归正传，卡腾伯恩开始在巴黎挨家挨户地推销这种幻灯机，而这个时候的他连法语都不会讲。不过他居然第一年就赚了五千美金的佣金，成了当年全法国薪水最高的销售人员之一。卡腾伯恩告诉我，这段经历给他带来的锻炼以及对成功特质的培养远远胜过在哈佛大学任何一年的教育。他十分自信地告诉我，这次经历后，他觉得自己有能力成功地向法国家庭主妇推销国会议事录。

正因为这段经历让他深入了解了法国的生活，也对他今后在广播中诠释欧洲大事件做出了极大的贡献。

那不会说法语的卡腾伯恩是如何成为销售专家的呢？他先让老板把推销时要说的话用纯正的法语写了下来，然后他全部都背下来。在推销前，他会按响某家的门铃，一位家庭主妇会来开门，然后他就开始背诵那一套推销词，他的发音又糟糕又滑稽。然后，他会给这位家庭主妇看图片。当她问任何问题时，他都回答：“一个美国人……一个……美国人。”然后摘下帽子指给对方看被他粘在帽子顶上的那段推销词。家庭主妇通常会被他逗得捧腹大笑，他也跟着哈哈笑——同时给对方看更多的图片。说到这些时，卡腾伯恩承认这项工作并不简单。他告诉我，让他挺下来的唯一原因只是：他想使工作变得有趣的决心。每天早晨他都要对着镜子给自己打气：“卡腾伯恩，如果你不想饿肚子就要做这份工作，既然你必须做这份工作，为何不享受它的过程呢？为何不在每次按铃时想象着自己是舞台角灯前的演员，面对的是观众？要是你正在做的事正如舞台上的表演一样滑稽，那么为何不投入热情去做好这件事呢？”

卡腾伯恩先生告诉我，正是凭着这每日训话的帮助，他把曾经惧怕的工作转为了给他带来丰厚回报的有趣刺激的活动。

我请他给渴望成功的美国年轻人提供一些建议。他说：“每天早晨激励自己。我们总会说起运动的重要性，运动能唤醒半梦半醒的人。然而我们更需要每天早晨进行精神与心灵的唤醒，让自己快速地投入行动。因此，每天都给自己打打气吧。”

这种每日自我训话的做法是愚蠢、肤浅而幼稚的吗？不，恰恰相反，这是心理健康的核心。“观念塑造生活。”这几个字在当今社会和在一千八百年前马可·奥勒留写下它们时同样是真理。

不断地给自己鼓舞士气，你便引导着自己拥有了勇气与幸福、力量与和平。时常告诉自己要感恩，心灵便会翱翔、会歌唱。

拥有了正确的思维，你便能使任何工作更加如意。你的老板当然希望你能对工作感兴趣，这样他才能赚更多的钱。但是让我们忘记老板们想要什么，只想想对工作感兴趣能带给自己什么。提醒自己，对一切充满兴趣能使生活中的快乐加倍。你醒着的一半时间都是在工作中度过的，如果你无法在工作中找到快乐，便也很难在其他地方找到了。一直提醒自己对工作产生兴趣，真的能让你忘掉焦虑。从长远角度讲，这很可能带来晋升和加薪。即便不能，也能使疲劳感降到最低，让你能更好地享受闲暇时光。

第三章　预防疲劳的四种良好工作习惯

良好工作习惯No．1　清除办公桌上除了手头需要的文件以外的所有纸张

芝加哥与西北铁路公司总裁罗兰·L．威廉姆斯曾说过：“桌上各类纸张堆积成山的人一旦清理了桌子，只留下解决手头问题所需的文件，就会发现做事轻松多了，也高效多了。我把这称为持家好习惯。这是提高效率的第一步。”

如果你参观过华盛顿的国会图书馆，你会看到顶部有诗人蒲柏的一句名言：“秩序是天堂的第一定律。”

秩序也应是商界的第一定律。不过现实中并非人人都遵守这个定律。人们的办公桌上常常堆积着几周都没碰过的文件。新奥尔良一家报社的出版人就告诉过我，有一次，秘书在收拾他的桌子时，竟然找到了丢失了两年的打字机！

仅仅看着桌上堆放得满满的未回复的信件、报告和备忘录，就足以产生困惑、不安和焦虑，但这还不是全部，这些文件时刻提醒着你：还有无数件事要做但时间远远不够。这一切不仅会令人不安与疲惫，还有可能导致高血压、心脏病和胃溃疡。

宾夕法尼亚大学医学院研究所的约翰·H．斯托克斯博士曾在美国医学会上宣读过他的论文，题目叫《与机体疾病并发的功能性神经症》。在论文中，斯托克斯博士提到了“从病人的精神状况中寻找什么”的主题并列出了十一个症状。第一个便是：

一种绝对的义务感或负担感——前方有无穷尽的事必须被完成。

但是收拾桌子、做决定这样的简单措施又怎么能帮你减压、减少负担感呢？知名精神病专家威廉·L．塞得勒博士提到过，他正是用这个简单办法治好了一个精神崩溃的患者。这个病人是芝加哥一家大公司的总裁，他刚找到塞得勒博士时紧张兮兮、满脸忧虑，充满了不安。他知道自己快挺不住了，但又不能离开工作，他只能寻求医生的帮助。

“就在病人给我讲他的故事时，我的电话响了。”塞得勒博士说，“电话是医院打来的。我一点儿也不拖延立刻就做出了决定，我尽可能地立即处理每一件事。刚挂电话不久，电话铃声又响起了，又是紧急事件，于是我花了些时间在电话里讨论问题。后来，第三次打扰出现了，我的同事进来咨询如何处理一个重病患者的情况。全部处理完之后我转向我的访客，为让他久等而道歉。然而他的心情却明快起来，脸上也露出了与进来时截然不同的神情。

“‘医生，不必道歉！’他说，‘在刚才的十分钟里，我觉得我知道自己的问题出在哪里了。我要回我的办公室，我要改变我的工作习惯。但是在我离开前，您介意让我看看您的办公桌吗？’”

于是，塞得勒博士打开了桌子的所有抽屉，里面除了办公用品以外没有其他的东西。病人问：“您没处理完的事项都放在哪呢？’”

“都处理完了！”塞得勒说。

“那没回的信呢？”

“都回了！”塞得勒告诉他，“我的规矩是：绝不拖延没回的信。我会在第一时间向秘书口述回信内容。”

六周后，这位总裁邀请塞得勒博士去他的办公室。他完全变了一个样，他的桌子也是。他打开办公桌抽屉，里面没有任何未处理的工作。“六周前，”这位总裁说，“我有两个办公室，三个办公桌，而且全都被各种文件盖得满满的。永远都有工作在等着我。与您见面之后，我一回来就清走了一车的旧文件。现在我只有一个办公桌，工作一来立马解决。我不再被堆积如山的工作所纠缠，也不再紧张、焦虑。然而最让我震惊的是——我痊愈了，所有的健康问题都消失了！”

前美国最高法院首席法官查尔斯·埃文斯·休斯说过：“人不会死于过量的工作，却会死于消耗与焦虑。”是的，精力的消耗及焦虑来源于看似永远无法完成的工作。

良好工作习惯No．2　按事情的轻重缓急排序

全国城市服务公司的创始人亨利·L．多尔蒂说过，不论开出多高薪水，同时具备以下两种能力的人都是极难找到的。

这两种无价的能力是：独立思考能力和按轻重缓急办事的能力。

查尔斯·拉克曼是一个白手起家，在十二年内攀升至白速得公司总裁，年薪十万美金并有百万其他收入的小伙子，他曾经说过，他的成功很大程度上源于亨利·L．多尔蒂推崇的极为难得的两个能力。查尔斯·拉克曼说：“从记事起我都是早晨五点起床，因为那是最适合我思考的时间。我在那时可以进行更好的思考，然后计划接下来的一天，安排做事的优先顺序。”

弗兰克·贝特格，美国最成功的保险销售人，他从不会等到早晨五点才起来制订计划。他会在前一个晚上为自己定下第二天的目标：要卖出的保险份额。倘若达不到，差额便会被加到下一天的销售额目标中，以此类推。

丰富的经验告诉我们，人们永远无法总按轻重缓急的顺序做事，但是我们也知道，制订出做事顺序的计划的确比“即兴演绎”要好得多。

如果萧伯纳没有制订严格的规定来控制做事的优先顺序，那么他或许也不会成为作家，而是做一辈子的银行出纳。他在那令人心碎的九年中强制自己每天写五页作品，虽然在这九年中他一共只赚了三十美金——差不多每天收入一便士。就连小说中的鲁滨逊·克鲁索都会按每小时该做什么来制订一天的计划。

良好工作习惯No．3　必要信息齐全时，立刻做决定，绝不拖延

已故的H．P．豪威尔——我以前的学生——曾经告诉我，他作为美国钢铁董事会成员参加董事会议时，发现会议总是拖拖拉拉的，讨论了很多问题却做不了几个决定，结果每个成员都要把很多报告带回家进一步研究。

最后，豪威尔先生说服了董事会，每次在会议上只着手解决一个问题、做一个决定，不拖延、不推迟。这个决定有可能是需要获取更多信息，有可能是做某事或不做某事，但不做出一个决定便不转移到下一个问题。豪威尔先生告诉我，这样子改变以后，效果是有效且惊人的：记事表清空了，日历干净了，董事会成员再也不用带一堆报告回家了。那种因问题永远解决不完而产生的焦虑完全消失了。

这条规矩不仅适用于美国钢铁董事会，对你我也会有所帮助。

良好工作习惯No．4　学着整合、委派和监督

很多商业人士正在过早地把自己送往坟墓，因为他们不懂得如何下放权责，总是包揽一切工作。结果呢？各种细节纠缠着他们。他们永远感觉不安、焦虑、紧张、匆忙。我知道，学会下放权责不容易。一开始对我来说也很不容易，困难重重。我也经历过把权责下放给错的人所造成的灾难。但不论如何，管理者必须学会下放权责，才能消除一些不安、紧张和疲惫。

很多不懂得整合、委派和监督的总裁五六十岁就患了心脏病——都是紧张和不安导致的。如果你认为这是危言耸听，那么看看报纸上的讣告便知真假。

若想减少不安和疲惫：

1．把桌子上与手头那项工作无关的纸张全部清理走。

2．按事情的轻重缓急排序。

3．必要信息齐全时，立刻做决定。

4．学会整合、委派和监督。

第四章　没人会去踢一条死狗

1929年芝加哥发生了一件轰动全国教育界的事，全美的学者都赶赴芝加哥见证此事。几年前，一个名叫罗伯特·哈金斯的年轻男子用当餐厅服务员、伐木工、家教和服装销售员赚来的钱供自己读完了耶鲁大学。八年后的他成了芝加哥大学的校长，这是美国第四大资源丰富的名校，而他只有三十岁！这简直不可思议！年长的教育家们纷纷摇头。无数的批评声向这个“神奇男孩”排山倒海地涌来，纷纷说他这不对、那不好，认为他太年轻、缺乏经验，教育理念太荒唐。就连报纸都加入了批评大军。

哈金斯就职那天，一个朋友对他的父亲说：“我很惊讶报纸竟然这样诋毁你的儿子。”

“是的，”老哈金斯回答，“这非常糟糕，但别忘了，没人会去踢一只死狗。”

没错，这只狗越重要，别人踢它时就越有满足感。后来成为爱德华八世的威尔士亲王也受到过这样的“待遇”。那时他在位于德文郡的达特茅斯学院就读——那是相当于美国安纳波利斯海军学院的一所院校，当时亲王大概有十四岁。一天，一名海军军官发现他在哭，就问他发生了什么。一开始他不肯回答，后来终于承认，海军学员们踢了他。学院的指挥官把那些男孩召集起来，首先说明亲王并未告状，但希望知道为何大家孤立他并如此粗暴地对待他。

男孩们支支吾吾，脚尖蹭来蹭去，很长时间后终于说了实话。他们希望有朝一日成为海军军官为国王效劳时就能跟别人说：我踢过国王！

所以当你被人踢、被人骂时请记住，那些人往往是想通过这种行为来感觉自己重要，这往往意味着你有所成就、值得被关注。很多人通过诋毁比自己学历高或更有成就的人来得到粗暴的满足感。比如说，我在撰写此章时收到了一位女士的来信，她在信中谴责了威廉·布斯将军——救世军组织的创始人。我曾经当众赞赏过布斯将军，但是这个女人写道，布斯将军挪用了八百万捐给穷人的款项。这种指控自然是莫须有的，但这个女人并不在意事实，她只想通过诋毁比她层次高的人来获取快感。我把这封可悲的信扔进了垃圾筐，并感谢上苍我没有娶这样一个女人。她的信中并没有提到多少有关布斯将军的信息，反倒让我看到她是怎样的人。叔本华数年前说过：“卑微的人总是从伟人的缺点和失误中得到极大的快感。”

很少有人认为耶鲁大学的校长会是卑微的人，然而耶鲁的一位前校长就曾把诋毁美国总统候选人作为极大的乐趣。这位耶鲁前校长警告大家，如果这个候选人当选总统，那么“我们的妻子和女儿或许会去卖淫，彻底地身败名裂，会虚荣肮脏、不知廉耻、没有道德、人神共愤”。

这听上去好像是在指责希特勒，不是吗？但并非如此。他骂的是托马斯·杰斐逊。哪个托马斯·杰斐逊？难道是那个千载扬名的托马斯·杰斐逊，《独立宣言》的起草者、民主的守护神？没错，就是他。

你猜猜还有哪位美国人被骂作“伪君子”“骗子”和“只比杀人犯好一点点”？而且在报纸上刊登的一幅漫画中，他趴在断头台上即将被斩首，游街示众时周围嘲笑声、嘘声一片。你猜这个人是谁？对，是乔治·华盛顿。

当然这是很久远的事了，或许人性已经进化了。那让我们再看一看海军上将佩里的例子吧。他在1909年4月6日乘着狗拖的雪橇到达了北极，这震惊了全世界。这是几个世纪以来，勇敢的人不畏痛苦、饥饿与死亡而试图实现的目标。不过，佩里本人也差点死于寒冷和饥饿，他的八个脚趾也因严重冰冻而不得不被切除。路上的重重灾难使他不堪重负，他一度曾担心自己会疯掉。他的上司——身在华盛顿的海军军官——看不惯佩里受到的极大关注和赞赏，于是指控他打着科学探险的旗号赚钱，并且“在北极无所事事”。可悲的是绝大多数人相信了，因为他们本就希望听到这些，所以很难不去相信。他们羞辱并阻挠佩里的决心是如此坚定，若不是麦金莱总统直接下命令，佩里在北极的事业便无法继续了。

如果佩里做的是坐在华盛顿海军部办公室里的工作，他还会被如此声讨吗？不会。那样的人不够重要，不足以引起嫉妒。

格兰特将军的遭遇比佩里上将还要糟糕。1862年，格兰特将军为北方赢得了一场伟大的胜利。这是一个下午就得来的胜利，是使格兰特将军一夜成名的胜利，即便在遥远的欧洲也反响巨大。从缅因到密西西比河岸的教堂都鸣起了钟声、燃起了篝火。然而胜利后的六周里，格兰特这个北方英雄就被拘捕了，他的兵权也被剥夺了。他在羞辱和绝望中哭泣。

为什么格兰特将军会在胜利高潮中被捕呢？很大程度上是因为他傲慢的上级心生妒忌。

在受到不公的批评干扰时，请记住：

不公的批评往往是变相的赞美。请记住，没人会去踢一条死狗。

第五章　不被批评所伤害

我曾经采访过斯梅德利·巴特勒少将，就是那个号称老“犀利眼”、老“地狱魔鬼”的巴特勒！还记得他吗？他是统帅过美国海军的将军中最多姿多彩、神气活现的一个。

他告诉我，他年轻时急切地渴望成为受欢迎的人，想给每个人留下好印象，所以在那段日子里，任何微小的批评都会刺痛他。不过他承认加入海军的三十年磨炼了他。“我曾经被责难、被侮辱。”他说，“我被骂成卑鄙懦弱、心如蛇蝎、臭名昭著的人，也曾被专家辱骂。所有不登大雅之堂的英文诅咒词汇都在我身上用过。哈！现在当我听到别人骂我时，我甚至不屑于回头看看那人是谁。”

或许老“犀利眼”巴特勒对于批评过于无动于衷了，但是有一件事是肯定的：我们大多数人把小小的嘲讽看得太过认真了。我记得几年前《纽约太阳报》有一名记者，他在参加我的成人教育班讲座后当众嘲讽了我和我的工作，当时我气坏了。我把它看作针对我本人的侮辱，我给《太阳报》执行委员会主席吉尔·霍吉斯致电，命令他发表一篇澄清文章，必须陈述事实而非嘲讽。我决心一定要讨个公道。

现在我为当时的举动感到羞愧。我知道买那份报纸的一半读者可能根本没有看到那篇文章，而看到的人中有一半只不过把它当作无足轻重的消遣而已，另一半幸灾乐祸的人不出几周便会把它忘得一干二净。

我现在明白了别人并不在意你和我，也不在意关于我们的舆论，他们只在乎自己的问题。在早饭前、早饭后、直到午夜过后的十分钟，他们关心自己轻微的头疼脑热要比你和我的死活多一千倍。

即便我们被骗、被嘲弄、被背叛、被暗算或者被最亲密的朋友出卖，也不该纵容自怜。相反，我们要提醒自己，这正是耶稣的遭遇。在耶稣最亲密的十二个朋友中，一个为了相当于今天十九美金的钱财而背叛了他，另一个在他受难时公然背弃了他，还三次宣称并发誓自己不认识耶稣。这是六分之一的比例！这就是耶稣的遭遇。那么你和我又凭什么期待更好的待遇呢？

几年前我发现虽然我不能阻止别人对我进行不公地批判，但我可以做更加重要的事：我可以决定是否允许自己被不公的指责所打扰。

当然，我并不是说要忽视所有批评的声音，我完全不是这个意思。我是说要忽视不公的批评。有一次我问艾莉诺·罗斯福，她是如何应付不公批评的——天知道她承受过多少不公平指责。她拥有的热忱朋友和残暴敌人的数量或许比在白宫生活过的任何一个女人都要多。

她告诉我，小的时候她很害羞，几近病态的害羞，惧怕人们的议论。她是如此害怕被批评以至于有一次她跑去向她的姑妈——西奥多·罗斯福的姐姐征求意见。她说：“百伊姑妈，我想做某某事，但是我怕被人议论。”

姑妈看着她的眼睛说：“只要你内心认为自己是正确的，就永远不要因别人的话而感到困扰。”艾莉诺·罗斯福告诉我，这条建议日后就像一块坚石一样守护着她在白宫的日子。她对我说，唯一避免评论的方法就是像德累斯顿瓷雕一样待在柜子里。“既然不论如何别人都会评判你，所以去做你内心觉得正确的事吧。因为做了会被谴责，不做也会被谴责。”这就是她的建议。

已故的马修·布拉在担任美国国际公司总裁一职时，我问他是否曾经对别人的评论敏感。他回答：“是的，早年非常敏感，那时我迫切地希望全公司的员工都认为我是完美的。我会首先试图讨好反对我的人，而这种举动又会激怒另一个人；当我处理与第二个人的问题时又捅了其他的马蜂窝。最后我终于意识到，我越是想安抚受伤的情绪从而逃避批评便树立了越多的敌人。所以最终我告诉自己：‘枪打出头鸟。习惯了就好。’这给了我极大的帮助。从那时起，我立下规矩：我会尽最大努力做事，然后撑起我那把旧雨伞，让议论之雨顺伞滑落，而不是灌入领口。”

蒂姆斯·泰勒做得更彻底。他让议论之雨灌入领口，然后大方地一笑而过。他在为每周日下午的纽约爱乐乐团的电台直播音乐会做中场休息讲解时，曾收到过一位女士的来信，信中称他为“骗子、背叛者、蛇蝎、恶魔”。后来泰勒先生在他的《人与音乐》一书中写道：“我怀疑她根本不关心谈论的内容。”然后在接下来一周的广播里他为千百万听众读了那封信。于是他再次收到那个女人的信，表达了她不变的观点。泰勒先生说：“在她的信中我依然是骗子、背叛者、蛇蝎、恶魔。”我们无法不敬仰能以这样的姿态面对批评的人，他平和、处事不惊，还颇具幽默感。

查尔斯·施瓦布在普林斯顿大学演讲时说到，他学到的最重要的一课是在施瓦布钢铁厂工作的一位德国老人给他上的。这位德国老人和其他工人陷入了激烈的争论中，被人扔进了河里。施瓦布先生说：“他走进我办公室时满身都是泥和水。我问他到底跟那些把他扔到河里的人们说了什么，他说：‘我只是一笑而过。’”

施瓦布强调他把德国老人的这句话当成了座右铭：“一笑而过。”当你是不公的批评的受害者时，这几个字尤其受用。你说的任何话别人都能反驳，但是人们能对“一笑而过”说什么呢？

如果林肯没有意识到扑面而来的刻薄谴责是多么的荒唐，或许他会垮在南北战争的重压下。他对如何应对此类谴责的描述也成了经典。麦克阿瑟将军在战争时期里把这些话打印出来挂在了指挥部办公桌的上方，丘吉尔把它镶在镜框中挂在了乡间别墅的书房里。林肯是这样说的：“如果我试图读完所有对我的攻击，那我就不用做其他事了，更别说一一回复。我只能竭尽所能把每件事做到最好，而且会一直做到底。如果结果是好的，对我的评价便无关紧要。如果结果是糟糕的，那么即便十个天使发誓说我是正确的也无济于事。”

当我们面对不公批评时，让我们记住：

竭尽全力地做事，然后撑开你的旧雨伞，不要让雨水灌入领口中。

第六章　你愿意用一百万的价格出售你的什么

我与哈罗德·艾伯特结识多年。他住在密苏里州的韦布城，曾经是我的演讲经理人。一天我们在堪萨斯城见面，然后他开车送我去我位于密苏里贝尔顿的农场。路上我问他是如何远离焦虑的，他给我讲了一个难忘的故事。

“我也曾经被焦虑所扰。”他说，“但1934年春天的一天，我走在韦布城西多尔蒂街上看到的景象，消除了我所有的焦虑。这一切是在十秒钟内发生的，但我在这十秒钟内学到的生活道理比过去十年还多。我在韦布城经营杂货店两年了，我不但用完了所有积蓄，还欠了要七年才能还清的债务。我的杂货店在前一周的周六关门了，我正要去商业与矿业银行贷款，这样我才能去堪萨斯城谋一份工作。我像一个失败者一样走着，我失去了所有的斗志和信念。忽然我看到迎面过来了一个失去双腿的人，他坐在用轮滑鞋的轮子和木板搭成的小车上，双手各持一根小木棍滑地前行。我看到他时，他刚滑过了马路，正把自己推上几寸高的人行道。当他把小木板翘起来时，我们的目光相遇了。他带着很灿烂的微笑，精神饱满地向我打招呼：‘早上好，先生！今天天气真好，不是吗？’当我站立着面对他时，我感觉自己很富有。我有双腿，我能走路。我为之前的顾影自怜而羞愧。我对自己说，如果他没有双腿都能快乐、积极、自信，那么我也一定能做到。我立刻感觉到很振奋。我之前准备向银行借一百美金，但现在我有勇气借二百美金了。我之前想对银行说，我要去堪萨斯找工作，而我现在要自信地宣布，我要去堪萨斯得到一份工作。我拿到了贷款，也找到了工作。

“我现在把这样一段话贴在了我家浴室的镜子上，每天早晨刮胡子时都要读一遍：

我没有鞋，所以沮丧。

直到有一天，我遇到了没有脚的人。”

艾迪·瑞肯贝克和同伴乘救生艇在太平洋迷失二十一天，我曾经问他从那次经历中学到的最重要的一课是什么。他说：“我从那段经历中明白的最重要的道理是：如果你有淡水喝、有食物吃，就不要抱怨任何事。”

《时代》周刊上刊登过一篇文章，讲的是一名警官的故事。他在瓜达康纳尔岛受了伤，子弹击中了他的喉咙，他接受了七次输血。他在小纸条上写字问医生：“我能存活吗？”医生说：“能。”他又写：“我还能说话吗？”医生再次给予了肯定的答复。然后他写道：“那我还有什么好担心的？”

此时此刻，为何不停下来问问自己：“我究竟在担心什么？”你或许会发现，那些你所担心的事情并不重要。

生活中90％的事是顺利的，而10％出了问题。我们若想快乐，只需要专注于90％的顺利，忽视10％的问题。如果我们想要忧心忡忡、苦楚不堪再得个胃溃疡，那就专注于10％的问题，忽视90％的顺利。

“思考和感恩”这五个字被刻在英国很多克伦威尔派的教堂中，这几个字也该被铭刻于我们的心中。我们应该思考所有值得感恩的事，感谢上天给予我们的恩惠和奖赏。

《格列佛游记》的作者乔纳森·斯威夫特可以说是英国文学界中最极端的悲观主义者。他为自己的出生感到遗憾，因此每到生日之际都会穿黑衣、行斋戒。然而，即便是这样一位绝望的顶级悲观主义者也赞美了快乐给身心带来的伟大力量。他宣称：“世上最好的医生就是均衡饮食、心平气和、心情舒畅。”

我们每天都能免费获得“心情舒畅医生”的服务。我们只需专注于我们拥有的财富，而这些财富远远大于阿里巴巴的宝藏。你会为了一百万而卖掉你的眼睛吗？双腿和双手呢？听觉呢？你的孩子？你的家人？把你的这些财富相加在一起，你会发现用洛克菲勒、福特和摩根的全部资产跟你换，你都不会愿意交换。

但我们对这些财富心怀感恩了吗？啊，没有。叔本华说过：“我们很少去想自己拥有什么，而总是在想缺少什么。”是的，这种心态是世上最大的悲剧。它所带来的悲痛或许比史上所有战争和疾病的总和还要多。

比如，它就曾让约翰·帕尔默从一个正常人变成了满腹牢骚的人，还差点毁了他的家。我知道这些因为这是他亲口告诉我的。

帕尔默先生住在新泽西州的帕特森市。他说：“我退伍后不久就开始做生意。我没日没夜地工作，一切都很顺利。后来麻烦来了。我找不到零件和材料，我怕不知哪天就要关门大吉了。我太担心了，以至于变成了一个爱发牢骚的人。我后来才察觉，那时的自己尖酸刻薄、脾气乖戾，差点就丢失了可爱的家。有一天，我的一个部下——一个年轻的残疾退伍军人对我说，‘约翰，你整天一副全世界只有你有麻烦的样子，你真该感到羞耻。就算你要把店关闭一阵子又能怎样？问题解决后你还可以再开张啊。你拥有很多值得感恩的东西，但你却总是在抱怨。天啊，我多希望拥有你所拥有的一切！看看我。我只有一个手臂，半边脸也被毁了，可我没有抱怨。如果你继续哀怨下去，你将失去的远远不止是一家店，而是你的健康、你的家庭和你的朋友！’

“听到那些话我愣住了，我意识到自己其实拥有很多。我当时立刻下决心改变，找回原来的自己，而我做到了。”

我的一个朋友露西尔·布莱克也是在即将陷入悲剧的边缘学会了感恩、快乐，而不是为缺失的东西而忧虑。

我几年前认识了露西尔，那时我们都在哥伦比亚大学新闻系学习短篇写作。几年前她的生活遭到了打击，那时她住在亚利桑那州图森市。她那时的生活……这是她的原话：

“我忙得团团转。我要在亚利桑那大学学习管风琴演奏，要在城里组织演讲培训班，还要在我居住的沙漠柳树农场教音乐欣赏课。晚间我还要参加各种派对、舞会、骑马的活动。某天早晨，我累得倒下了，我的心脏难受极了！医生说：‘你需要卧床整整一年来调整身体。’他不愿让我觉得自己还能恢复体能。

“卧床一年！那我就成了废物，可能还会死掉！我吓坏了！为什么这一切要发生在我身上？我做了什么坏事情，得到了这样的报应？我哭泣，我哀号。我充满愤恨、挣扎反抗。但我的确听从医嘱，卧床休息。我的邻居鲁道夫先生是一名艺术家。他对我说：‘你现在认为卧床一年会很悲惨，但实际上不会的。你将有时间思考并有机会认识自己。接下来的几个月里，你在精神上的成长将比之前所有的成长都要多。’听了这些话，我平静了许多，也试着去建立一套新的价值观。我读了引人深思的书籍。有一天我听到广播中的评论员说：‘人们只能表达存在于自身意识中的事物。’我之前也听到过无数类似的话语，但从未触及心灵，也没有在心中扎根。但从那时起，我决定只去思考那些我最重视的生活信条：喜悦、快乐和健康。我强迫自己每天早上醒来都默念一遍我要感恩的事物：身体没有疼痛、可爱的女儿、我的视力很好、我的听力很好、广播中好听的音乐、阅读的时间、好吃的食物、好朋友。我过得很快乐，还有很多的探望者过来看我，到最后医生不得不立一个牌子，要求只能在每天规定的时间段内接待一位访客。

“那是多年前的事了。现在的我过着充实、积极的生活。我非常感激卧床的那一年，那是我在亚利桑那州度过的最有价值、最快乐的一年。那时养成的每天早晨盘点幸福的习惯到现在还跟随着我。那是我最宝贵的财富之一。我很羞愧，因为直到我开始畏惧死亡时才真正学会了如何活着。”

我亲爱的露西尔·布莱克，你或许不知，你明白了塞缪尔·约翰逊博士在两百年前领悟的道理。约翰逊博士曾说过：“看到事物美好一面的习惯比每年赚一千英镑还可贵。”

我必须要提出，这些话不是职业乐观者说出的。说话者与焦虑、穷困和饥饿为伍二十年，最后终于成为那个时代最杰出的作家和空前绝后的雄辩家。

洛根·皮尔索·史密斯在短短一句话中注入了大量的智慧：“人生目标有二：其一，得你所想；其二，享你所得。只有最具智慧的人才能做到第二点。”

你想知道如何把洗碗变成有趣的事吗？如果答案是肯定的，建议你阅读伯格希尔德·道所著的非常励志的《我想看见》一书。

这本书是一个几乎失明了半个世纪的女人写的。“我只有一只眼睛。”她写道，“而它还布满伤疤，所以我只能从这只眼左部的一条缝隙里看世界。所以看书时，我要把书拿得离脸很近，还要尽可能地把眼球转向左边。”

尽管如此，她拒绝被怜悯，拒绝被他人当作“异类”。从小她就和其他孩子一起玩跳房子，但她看不见地上的标记，所以每当其他孩子回家后，她都会趴在地上，把眼凑到标记前牢牢记住。不久她就成了游戏高手。她在家读书，读的是大字书。她把书拿得离脸如此之近，以至于睫毛都碰到了纸张。她获得了两个文凭：明尼苏达大学的文学学士和哥伦比亚大学的文学硕士。

她一开始在明尼苏达州的小山村——双子山谷中教书，后来成了南达科他州苏瀑城奥古斯塔那学院的新闻和文学教授。她在此任教十三年，还在女子俱乐部演讲，在广播电台中谈书籍和作家。她写道：“在我的内心深处，总是有对全盲的恐惧。为了征服这恐惧，我选择用快乐甚至诙谐的态度面对人生。”

1943年，当她五十二岁时，奇迹发生了。著名的梅奥诊所为她做了手术，术后她的视力是之前的四十倍。一个崭新的美丽世界展现在她眼前，她现在觉得就连在水池边洗碗都是激动人心的事。“我开始玩洗碗盆里白色、蓬松的肥皂泡。”她写道，“我把双手伸进去，然后捧起来一团微小的肥皂泡。我在阳光下看它们，每个泡泡里都有一个微型彩虹，色彩斑斓。”

她向厨房水池上方的窗外看去，“一群麻雀正拍打着灰黑色的翅膀，穿越漫天雪花”。

为泡沫和麻雀深深着迷的她是这样为书结尾的：

“‘亲爱的上帝，’我轻声呼唤，‘我们天上的父，我感谢你。感谢你。’”

想象一下因为能在洗碗时看到色彩斑斓的泡沫和雪天中飞翔的麻雀而感谢上帝是怎样一番情景！

我们真该为自己感到羞耻。那些住在美丽童话世界里的每一天、每一年，我们却因盲目和贪婪而不曾看见、不曾体验。

如果你想停止忧虑、开始生活，请记住：

细数你拥有的恩惠而不是你遇到的麻烦。

第七章　发现自己，做回有个性的自己

请记住，在这个世界上你是独一无二的。

我接到来自北卡罗来纳芒特艾里的伊迪斯·奥尔雷德女士的一封信，信里面写道：

“儿时的我极度敏感、羞涩。我偏胖，而我的双颊使我看起来比实际还要胖。我有个思维很守旧的母亲，她认为穿好看衣服是愚蠢的。她常说：‘衣服大了能过，小了则破。’她也是依照这个理念打扮我的。我从来没参加过派对，也没做过什么有意思的事。我在校时从来没跟其他学生一起参加过课外活动，甚至连体育项目也没参加过。我的害羞是病态的。我认为自己和别人不一样，完全不受欢迎。

“长大后我嫁给了一个长我几岁的男人，而我却没有改变。我丈夫一家人是优雅而自信的，那是我长久以来所憧憬却没能成为的人。我想尽办法试图变成他们那样的人，但我做不到，让我改变的一切尝试都使我更深地钻进自己的壳里。我变得紧张易怒，我回避一切朋友。情况变得特别糟糕以至于我对门铃声都产生了恐惧。我知道自己很没用，也很怕我丈夫会发现这一点。所以每当我们在公共场合时我都强颜欢笑，夸张地扮演自己的角色。但我知道我演过头了，而之后的几天我都会在抑郁中度过。最后我变得非常不快乐，以至于我看不到继续存在的意义。我开始有了自杀的念头。”

那么，是什么改变了这个不快乐的女人的人生呢？只是不经意的一句话！

奥尔雷德女士继续说道：“一句话就这样改变了我的整个人生。有一天我婆婆讲起她如何培养孩子时说：‘不论在任何情况下，我都让孩子们做自己。’……‘让他们做自己。’就是这句话！瞬间我明白了自己一直以来都是自寻烦恼，我试图把自己塞进并不合适的模子里。

“一夜间我忽然变了一个人！我开始做自己，我开始学习了解自己，我试着找到自己的身份和优势。我尝试了一切可能的颜色和款式，找到了属于自己的穿着风格。我开始拓展自己的朋友圈，我还加入了一个社团，最早时是个小规模的。当他们让我参加一个节目时，我被吓傻了，但每次讲话后我都会增加一些信心。虽然这是个漫长的过程，但今天的我拥有了从前无法想象的快乐。现在当我教育自己的孩子时，我也时刻铭记着自己从苦楚经历中学到的一课：不论发生什么，永远做自己！”

不愿做自己真是个“有史以来就有的问题”。詹姆斯·戈登·吉尔其博士说过：“它就像生命一样普遍。”它也是很多神经症状、精神问题和其他复杂问题的病根。关于儿童教育问题，安吉洛·帕特里写过十三本书，诸多报纸也曾数千次登载过他的文章。他曾说过：“没有比想拥有别人的身体和头脑更悲惨的事了。”

在好莱坞，这种想成为别人的渴望更为强烈。山姆·伍德，好莱坞最知名的导演之一曾说过，年轻演员让他最头疼的事莫过于不愿做自己。他们宁可去当二流的拉娜·特纳或三流的克拉克·盖博。“观众已经知道那些风格了。”山姆·伍德不停地对年轻演员说，“现在观众想看些不一样的。”

山姆·伍德在拍《万世师表》《战地钟声》等电影之前从事房地产工作，这练就了他的销售技能。他认为商界的准则在电影界也适用。东施效颦、鹦鹉学舌是行不通的。山姆·伍德说：“经验告诉我，最安全的方法就是尽可能早地停用那些一味模仿他人的演员。”

我问过保罗·博因顿——当时他是一个大石油公司的招聘主管，人们应聘时所犯的最大错误是什么。他一定知道答案——他曾面试过六万多名求职者并写过一本名叫《求职六法宝》的书。他是这样回答的：“应聘者犯下的最大错误就是不表现真实的自己。他们往往不能坦诚，总是给你他们认为你想听到的答案。”可是这招无效，因为没人喜欢虚伪的人。没有人想要伪造的金币。

一位公交车司机的女儿付出了很大代价才学到这个道理。她梦想成为一名歌手，然而不幸的是，她嘴很大还长着龅牙。第一次在公开场合——新泽西的一个夜店演唱时，她尽量伸长上嘴唇试图盖住牙齿，她想表现得魅力四射。结果呢？她把自己弄得很可笑，这注定将失败。

不过夜店里的一位男士听到她的歌声后认为她很有天赋，于是直白地对她说：“是这样的。我一直观察着你的演出，我知道你想隐藏什么。你不好意思露出你的牙齿！”女孩很难为情，但男人继续说道：“那又怎样？长了龅牙又犯了什么罪吗？别试图藏起它们！张开嘴，当观众们看到你并不以此为耻时他们会爱你的。而且……”他机智地说，“你试图遮掩的牙齿或许还是你的财富呢！”

卡斯·戴莉听从了他的建议，抛下了对牙齿的顾忌。从那时起，她的脑中只有观众。她张大嘴巴，带着由衷的兴致与愉悦唱歌，后来成了电影和电台的大明星，一些喜剧演员还试图模仿她呢！

大名鼎鼎的威廉·詹姆斯谈到那些从未找到自我的人时说，一般人只开发了自身能力的10％。“与我们的潜能比较，我们只是半醒的人。我们只用了体能和智力资源的一小部分。概括地说，人类目前为止没有突破个人的局限性，他们拥有很多本领却没能加以运用。”

你和我都具备这样的能力，所以我们不要浪费一秒钟在烦恼上，因为我们不像那些人一样。你是世上的新生事物。有史以来，在你之前从未有过和你一模一样的人；从此之后的世世代代里也不会再有一个同样的你出现。遗传科学告诉我们，你是由父母各自遗传给你的二十三个染色体形成的。这四十六个染色体决定了你的全部基因。阿姆拉姆·善菲尔德说：“每个染色体中都有几十到几百个基因——而有时一个基因就能改变一个机体的整个生命。”的确，生命的形成是“令人畏惧而又奇妙”的。

在父母孕育的过程中，你成形的概率只有三百万亿分之一！也就是说，假如你有三百万亿个兄弟姐妹，没有一个会与你完全相同。这都是猜测吗？不，这都是科学事实。如果你想了解更多相关知识，请参考阿姆拉姆·善菲尔德所著的《你与遗传》一书。

在做自己这个话题上我坚定不移地支持，因为我感同身受。我知道自己在说什么——我付出了苦楚而巨大的代价。举个例子来说吧，当我第一次走出密苏里的玉米田来到纽约时，我报名加入了美国戏剧学院，我一心想成为演员。我以为自己的主意棒极了，这是一个成功的捷径，我好奇如此简单而又万无一失的想法怎么成千上万的有志之士都没有想到过呢？我的主意是这样的：我会学习约翰·德鲁、沃尔特·汉普登、欧提斯·斯金纳等当时知名演员的演技，然后模仿他们每个人的亮点，并把自己变成一个闪亮、成功的明星组合体。多么愚蠢！多么荒唐！我浪费了人生中几年的时间去模仿别人，最后我那厚厚的密苏里脑壳终于想通了：我应该做我自己——其实也根本无法做别人。

这令人沮丧的经历按说应该给了我深深的教训，但是没有。我太愚蠢了，于是又重蹈覆辙。几年以后，我准备写一本关于商界人士演说技巧的书，以为它会成为同类中最好的书。而对于这本书我犯了和当初想演戏时同样的错误：我想把所有同类书籍中的好想法全都借鉴进来，写成一本无所不包的书。所以我找到一大堆关于演说的书，用了一年的时间把里面的想法融汇到我的稿子里，然而我最终再次意识到我又做了愚蠢的行为。这种他人思想的大杂烩读起来既不自然又很无趣，没有商界人士会读完这样一本书。所以我把一年的心血丢进了垃圾桶，重新来过。这次我告诉自己：“你只能是戴尔·卡耐基，不论有怎样的缺点和局限性。你根本不可能成为其他人。”于是我不再试图成为其他人的混合体，我卷起袖管，做了从一开始就该做的事。我用自己的经历、观察以及身为演说技巧讲师所形成的观点写了一本关于演说的教科书。我永远都会记得（也希望自己做到如此）瓦尔特·罗利爵士带给我们的教诲：“我无法写出莎士比亚那样的书，但我能写属于我自己的书。”（这里的瓦尔特·罗利爵士不是把自己的外衣扔在泥地里以供女皇行走的那个人，而是1904年牛津大学的英文文学系教授。）

做自己，厄文·博林给晚辈乔治·格什温的忠告适合我们每个人。当博林和格什温初见时，博林已经名声大振，而格什温还是一个在锡盘巷(1)为了每周赚三十五美金而苦苦奋斗的年轻的歌曲创作者。格什温的才华给博林留下了深刻印象，于是博林邀请格什温担任他的音乐秘书，并开出了相当于之前三倍的工资。博林又建议道：“不过别接受这份工作，否则你会成为二流的博林。但你若坚持做自己，有一天你会成为一流的格什温。”

格什温一直把这个警告放在心上，后来逐渐成了美国那一代中最具影响力的作曲家。

查理·卓别林、威尔·罗杰斯、玛丽·玛格丽特·麦克布莱德、吉恩·奥特里等众多的人都得到了我在本章中一再强调的经验教训，也都像我一样付出了代价。

卓别林刚拍电影时，导演坚持要求他模仿一个德国著名喜剧演员，因而卓别林在决定演出自己的特色之前事业毫无进展。鲍勃·霍普也有类似的经历：他又唱又演了好几年都没有成绩，直到有一天开始说段子、做自己才走红。威尔·罗杰斯在歌舞杂耍表演中默默转绳子好几年，后来他发现了自己独特的喜剧天赋，凭着边转绳子边说话才出了名。

玛丽·玛格丽特·麦克布莱德刚上广播电台时曾试图表现成一名爱尔兰喜剧演员但不成功。而当她只去做自己——一个普通的密苏里乡下女孩时，她成了纽约最受欢迎的广播明星之一。

吉恩·奥特里想方设法掩饰自己的得克萨斯口音，并把自己打扮得像个纽约男孩，宣称自己是纽约人，人们都在背后笑话他的做法。而当他拨起班卓琴，唱起牛仔民谣时，他的职业生涯的大门打开了。他成了大银幕上和广播里闻名世界的牛仔。

你是世界上崭新的个体。记住这一点并为此高兴吧。最大限度地实现大自然赋予你的一切。归根结底，一切艺术都是自传。你只能以自己的角度唱歌、画画。你必定是你的经历、环境和基因塑造的。不论好坏，你必须培育自己的小花园，必须在人生交响乐中奏响自己的乐器。

爱默生一篇随笔《自助》中写道：“每个人在求知的过程中早晚会发现：嫉妒是无知，模仿是自我毁灭；他必须接受自己的好与不好，不论是怎样的比例；虽然大千世界物产富饶，但有营养的玉米只会长在自己辛勤耕种的田地里。每个人被赋予的能量都是崭新的，除了自己以外无人知晓你能做什么，若不尝试你也不会知道。”

而诗人道格拉斯·玛拉赫是这样说的：

如果你不能成为山顶上的一棵松，
那就做山谷中的一株灌木——
但要做溪边最好的那株小灌木；
做不成一棵大树，就做一株灌木。

如果你不能成为一株灌木，那就做一片草地，
把公路点缀出喜悦的色彩；
如果你不能成为狼鱼，那就做一条鲈鱼——
但要做湖中最活跃的那条鲈鱼！

我们不能都做船长，还要有船员，
每个人都有适合的岗位。
工作有大有小，
而必须完成的是眼前的事。

如果你不能成为高速公路，那就做一条羊肠小径。
如果你不能做太阳，那就做星星；
成功不在于大小，
而在于你是否做到最好。

为了培养平和、自由的心态，请记住：

让我们停止模仿他人。

让我们发现自己、做回自己。

————————————————————

(1) 译者按：19世纪末到20世纪初纽约曼哈顿流行音乐出版社和创作人的聚集地。

第八章　真诚之人，处处受欢迎

为什么要学习一本关于赢得朋友的书？为什么不学学史上最会交朋友的人有怎样的技巧？他是谁？或许明天走在街上你就会见到它。当你走到与它相距十英尺的距离时，它会开始摇尾巴。如果你停下来拍拍它，它几乎要从躯体中跳出来以展示它有多喜欢你。你知道在这种喜爱之情的背后没有任何隐藏的动机：它不想卖房子给你，不想和你结婚。

你有没有想过，狗是唯一不需要干活就能生存的动物？鸡要下蛋，牛要挤奶，金丝雀要唱歌。但狗什么都不用做，只需爱你就能生存。

我五岁的时候，父亲花了五十美分买了一只小黄狗。它是我童年的光芒与喜悦。每天下午大约四点半的时候，它都会坐到前院，美丽的眼睛坚定地盯着马路，一旦听到我的声音或看到我拎着饭盒穿过灌木丛，它都会像脱弓之箭一般一口气冲上小山坡迎接我，它快乐地上蹿下跳，狂喜般汪汪直叫。

五年来，提比是我形影不离的好朋友。后来在一个悲伤的夜晚，我永远也忘不了那个夜晚，它在我面前十尺之遥的地方被闪电击中。它的死是我童年的悲剧。

提比，你从未读过半本心理学书籍，你也不需要读。你凭那神圣的天性就懂得，真心在乎他人两个月比试图让别人对你感兴趣两年交到的朋友要多。我想再重申一遍：真心在乎他人两个月比试图让别人对你感兴趣两年交到的朋友要多。

然而你我都认识那些大张声势地试图让别人对他感兴趣、犯了一辈子这种错误的人。

这自然是行不通的。人们就是对他人不感兴趣。他们只对自己感兴趣，不论是早晨、中午还是晚上。

纽约电话公司做了一项电话对话的调查，意在找出人们最常用的词汇。你猜对了，那就是“我”。我、我、我……这个字眼在五百通电话中出现了三千九百次。

当你在看一张包括你在内的集体照时，首先找的是谁的身影？

如果我们只试图用让人刮目相看的方式赢得关注，将永远交不到一个真正真诚的朋友。真正的友谊不是这样形成的。

拿破仑试过了，而当他见约瑟芬最后一面时，他说：“约瑟芬，我曾比世界上很多人要幸运，然而在这一刻里，你是我唯一可以信赖的人。”不过史学家怀疑拿破仑是否连她都不能信任。

著名的维也纳心理学家阿尔弗雷德·阿德勒在《生活对你意味着什么》一书中说道：“那些对他人不感兴趣的人在生活中面对着巨大困难，也给他人带去最多的伤害。人类的一切失败都源于这样的人。”

你可以读一卷又一卷的深奥的心理学书籍，但对于你来说没有任何一句话比这句更重要。阿德勒的话意义深远，我再次强调：

那些对他人不感兴趣的人在生活中面对着巨大困难，也给他人带去最多的伤害。人类的一切失败都源于这样的人。

我曾在纽约大学上过一门短篇写作的课程。一位知名杂志社的编辑曾到我们班上进行讲座。他说他可以随意拿起一篇每天堆在他桌上的故事，只要读几段就能看出这个作者是否对他人感兴趣。“如果一个作者对别人不感兴趣，那么读者也不会喜欢他写的故事。”

这位犀利的编辑在说到如何进行虚构类写作时曾两度停下来讲道。他说：“我跟你们说，就如牧师会跟你们说的那样——记住，你一定要关心别人才能写出好故事。”

如果这对写小说有效，那你也可以确信，在面对面与人交往时亦是如此。

霍华德·萨士顿上次在百老汇表演时，我在后台待了一个晚上。萨士顿是公认的魔术大师，他四十年里去过无数国家，一次又一次地使用魔术手法去迷惑观众，使人目瞪口呆。超过六千万人曾掏钱看过他的表演，而他赚了差不多两百万美金。

我请萨士顿先生告诉我他成功的秘密。他的成功与他所受的学校教育肯定是无关的，因为他从小离家出走，过着流浪者的生活。他自己搭货车、睡草堆、挨家挨户乞讨食物，通过看车外的路标学会识字。

他对魔术有着更深层的知识吗？没有。他告诉我，关于魔术的书有上百本，会的魔术和他一样多的人也有一大群。而他有两样别人没有的东西。首先，他能在聚光灯下表现出自己的个性。他是一个表演大师，他懂得人性。他做的每一件事、每个动作、声音中的每个抑扬顿挫、眉梢的每次扬起都是设计过的，而这些表演精准到每一毫秒。此外，萨士顿还真正地对他人感兴趣。他说，很多魔术师在面对观众时心里会想：“坐在台下的是一群傻瓜，我肯定能把他们骗倒。”然而萨士顿的方式完全不同。他告诉我，每次在台上时他都对自己说：“我很感激这些来看我表演的人。是他们成全了我这颇受欢迎的谋生手段。我会为他们而尽全力表演。”

他宣称，他每次走上舞台之前都会对自己不断重复：“我爱我的观众。我爱我的观众。”这很可笑吗？很荒唐吗？你怎么想都行，我只是在向你转述大魔术师的成功秘诀。

宾夕法尼亚州北华伦市的乔治·戴克被迫关闭他开的休息站，提前退休，因为新建的高速公路将占用原休息站的地盘。退休的生活十分空闲，很快，他便感到无聊难耐，于是他拾起了那把旧的小提琴，用拉琴来打发时间。不久后，他开始四处游走、听音乐会，和不少颇有成就的小提琴手聊天。性格谦逊友好的他对遇到的每个音乐人的背景都打心眼里感兴趣。虽然他自己琴拉得不好，却结识了很多志同道合的朋友。他参加各种比赛，后来在美国东部乡村音乐爱好者中出了名，人们叫他“来自金爪郡的小提琴手乔治大叔”。我们听到乔治大叔演奏时，他已七十二岁，继续享受着生命的每分每秒。在大多数人认为不会再有作为的年纪里，他通过对别人的持续性关注为自己创造了新的人生。

这其实也是西奥多·罗斯福异常受人欢迎的秘诀。就连他的侍者都爱戴他。他的男仆詹姆斯·E．阿莫斯写了一本关于罗斯福的书，名叫《西奥多·罗斯福——仆人眼中的英雄》。在书中阿莫斯写到了这样一件引人深思的事：

我的妻子有一次向总统询问有关美洲鹑的事。她从来没见过美洲鹑，总统就对她描述了一遍。后来我们屋的电话响了（阿莫斯和妻子住在牡蛎湾罗斯福庄园的一间小屋里），我妻子接了电话，是罗斯福先生亲自打来的。他说他打电话是为了告诉我妻子，我们屋外现在就有一只美洲鹑，如果我们从窗口看出去就有可能看到。类似的小事使他散发着无穷魅力。每次他路过我们的房间时，即便看不到我们也会打招呼：“哦哦哦，是安妮吗？”或者“哦哦哦，是詹姆斯吗？”这就是他路过时的问候。

下属们怎会不喜欢这样的人呢？任何一个人都不可能不喜欢这样的人吧！

一天，塔夫脱总统和夫人都不在白宫里，罗斯福去白宫造访。他对白宫的每个侍者打招呼，并叫出他们的名字，哪怕只是对一个洗碗工。他对下人的真心喜爱就是这么表现出来的。

阿尔奇·巴特写道：“当他看见厨房女仆爱丽丝时，他问她是否还做玉米面包。爱丽丝说她有时会为下人们做，楼上是不吃的。

“‘他们品位太差。’罗斯福用他那浑厚的声音说，‘下次我见到总统时会亲自告诉他。’

“爱丽丝用盘子盛了一片给他，他就端到办公室里准备享用。一路上还不忘和园丁、劳工打招呼……

“他像以往一样和每个人打招呼。在白宫做了四十年守卫的艾克·胡佛含泪说：‘那是我们近两年来唯一的快乐日子，我们每个人都不会同意用一百美元换走这样的一天。’”

关心看似不重要的人也同样帮助新泽西查塔姆市的销售代表爱德华·M．塞克斯保住了一个客户。他说：“多年前，我为强生公司管理麻省的客户，其中的一个客户是欣厄姆市的一家杂货店。每次到这家店和经理谈话或接订单前，我都会与饮料贩卖员工和销售员工聊上几分钟。有一天，我走进去后经理让我离开，并告诉我不会再订强生的产品，因为他认为强生在食品和打折店搞的活动损害了杂货店的利益。我只得灰溜溜地离开，开着车在小镇里转了几个钟头。但最后我决定返回杂货店，至少要试着向经理解释我们的立场。

“当我回到店里时，照常跟饮料贩卖员工和销售员工打了招呼。当我走到经理面前时，他对我微笑并欢迎我回来，然后给了我双倍的订单。我惊讶地看着他，问这短短几个小时里发生了什么。他指了指饮料贩卖员，说我走后那个男孩告诉他我是那么多商家中唯一真诚地和他还有其他店员说话的人。他跟经理说，如果有任何商家值得他打交道，那就是我了。经理同意了，继续当我们的忠实客户。此后我永远记得，对于销售人员乃至每个人来说，对他人真诚的关心是最重要的品质。”

我的亲身经历告诉我，如果我们能展现对他人真诚的兴趣，便能从任何人那里得到关注、时间与配合，不论对方是多么德高望重。以下便是我的亲身经历。

几年前，我在布鲁克林艺术与科学学院办了一门文学写作课程。我们想邀请凯瑟琳·诺瑞诗、范妮·赫斯特、艾达·塔贝尔、阿尔伯特·佩森·特修和鲁珀特·休斯等著名又繁忙的作家来布鲁克林讲他们的经验，从而使学生更好地进步。所以我们给这些作者写信，说我们很仰慕他们的作品，对得到他们的建议并学习他们的成功秘诀有很深的兴趣。

每一封信都有150个学生的签名。我们在信中说知道对方很忙，或许忙到没时间准备演讲内容，所以我们随信寄去一系列他们可以准备的问题，都是有关作家本人及其工作方式的。这种做法受到了作家们的喜爱。谁又会不喜欢呢？所以他们离家来到了布鲁克林，给予我们充分的帮助。

我也曾用同样的方法成功说服了罗斯福内阁财政部长莱斯利·M．肖、塔夫脱内阁司法部长乔治·W．威克沙姆、威廉·詹宁斯·布莱恩、富兰克林·D．罗斯福等德高望重的人，请他们到我的那些演讲培训班为学生们讲话。

每一个人，不论是工厂工人、办公室员工还是当权的国王，都喜欢赏识自己的人。德国皇帝就可以作为例子。在第一次世界大战的末期，他大概成了这个地球上最被鄙视和憎恶的人了。连他自己的国家都把他当作敌人，所以他不得不逃亡到荷兰。人们对他的憎恨实在太强烈了，无数的人想把他撕成一片片或者绑在柱子上烧死。在这一片怒骂中，一个小男孩给皇帝写了一封简单、诚恳的信，信中充满了友好与尊敬。小男孩说，不论别人怎么想，他永远会把威廉当作他的皇帝，敬爱他。皇帝被这封信深深打动，并邀请小男孩来见他。小男孩来了，他的母亲也来了，后来威廉娶了她为妻。这个小男孩不必阅读有关赢得朋友、影响他人的书，他本能地懂得如何去做。

如果我们想交到朋友，就要甘愿为他人做事——做那些需要时间、精力、思虑和无私精神的事。当温莎公爵还是威尔士亲王时，他曾计划访问南美，而在走访之前，他花了几个月时间学习西班牙文，为的是能用那些国家的语言进行公开演讲。而南美人也因此十分爱戴他。

多年来我一直特意询问朋友的生日。我是怎么询问的呢？虽然我对占星术是一点都不信，但我会问对方是否相信生日与性格、性情的关系，然后让他们告诉我自己的生辰日期。假如对方说11月24日，我会在心里默念：11月24日，11月24日。等朋友一转身，我会马上写下来他的生日，回家后抄在一个生日簿上。每年伊始，我都会把这些生日抄到每日记事本上，这样我便能自动注意到朋友的生日了。当那天到来时，他们就会收到我的信或电报。每一次他们都会特别开心！我常常是唯一一个记得某些人生日的人。

如果想交到朋友，让我们热情洋溢地跟人打招呼。接电话时也是一样。说“你好”时要表达出你接到对方电话的喜悦。很多公司都训练他们的电话接线员用充满兴趣和热情的口吻接听每个人的电话，这样的话打电话的人会觉得这家公司在乎他。今后接打电话时请记得这一点。

表达对他人真诚的关心不仅能赢得朋友，还有可能培养起客户的忠诚度。在纽约的北美国家银行出版的刊物中印有这样一封来自储蓄者马德琳·罗丝黛尔的信件：

我希望贵公司知道我对你们的职员是多么的感激。每个人都那么彬彬有礼、乐于助人。在排了那么久的长队后，有那么热情的出纳员接待你是多么令人愉悦的事。

去年我的母亲住院五个月。每次我总是到出纳玛丽·佩楚奇罗那里办理业务，而她很关心我的母亲，常常询问她的近况。

毫无疑问，罗丝黛尔女士会继续和这家银行打交道。

纽约市一家大银行员工查尔斯·R．沃特斯被要求准备一份关于某公司的机密报告。他知道只有一个人拥有他正急切需要的信息，于是沃特斯先生去到了那位总裁的办公室里。这时一个年轻女人把头探了进来，告诉总裁今天她没有邮票可以给他。

“我在帮我二十岁的儿子集邮。”那位总裁向沃特斯先生解释道。

沃特斯先生讲了他此行的目的，然后就开始问问题，但总裁的话含糊、笼统而且模棱两可。他不想说话，并且看似没什么方法能让他说话。这次访谈简短而空洞。

沃特斯在班里讲这个故事时说：“老实说，我实在是没办法了。后来我想起来了他秘书提到的事——邮票及十二岁的儿子……我还想起来我们银行的国际部门在收集邮票——那里有来自五湖四海的信。

“第二天下午我给这个人打了电话，转告他我有邮票要给他儿子。我被笑脸相迎了吗？没错。他和我握手时的热情就像在竞选国会议员一般——有过之而无不及。他散发着微笑与友善。‘我的乔治会爱这张邮票的，’他一边翻阅着邮票一边说，‘还有这张！这真是太宝贵了。’

“我们用了半个小时的时间看邮票、看他儿子的照片，然后他用了超过一个小时的时间告诉了我所有我需要的信息——我连问都没问。他告诉了我他所知道的全部，还把他的下属叫来并打电话给几个同事进行询问。他给了我大量事实、数据、报告和信件。用媒介的说法就是，我得到了‘有料’的信息。”

下面是另外一个例子：

费城的小C．M．耐弗里多年来一直想卖石油给一家大型连锁机构，而那家公司一直从外地的商家进油，每次运油车都从耐弗里的公司门口路过。一天晚上，耐弗里先生在我的一个培训班中当着所有人面宣泄出对大型连锁店的愤怒，骂他们是国家的祸害。

然而他还是好奇为何自己没能把油卖给他们。

我建议他尝试另一种方式。简单地说，事情是这样子的。我们在培训班里办了一场辩论，内容是连锁店的兴起为国家带来的伤害是否多于利益。

在我的建议下，耐弗里加入了反方，要为连锁店做辩护。于是他直接找到了那位他一直鄙视的连锁店的总裁，对他说：“我不是来卖石油的。我想请你帮我一个忙。”他向对方解释了我们的辩论，“我来请求你的帮助，因为我觉得除了你没有第二个人能给我我所需要的信息了。我特别想赢这场辩论。我会深深地感激你给我的任何帮助的。”

之后的故事用耐弗里的原话描述是这样的：

“我只向他索要一分钟的时间。也是在这个前提下，他答应了我的请求。听完事情的缘由后，他示意我坐下，然后我们的谈话持续了一个小时四十七分钟。他还请了另外一位总裁进来，这个人曾写过关于连锁店的书。他还给全国连锁店协会写信，让他们寄给我一份关于这个话题已有的辩论记录。他觉得连锁店是真正服务于人类的产物，他为自己在上百个社区中的服务而自豪。他说话时两眼放光，而我必须承认，他让我大开眼界，知道了之前从未想过的事。他改变了我的整个态度。

“临走时，他把我送到门口，把手臂搭在我的肩上，祝我在辩论中取得好成绩，还让我告诉他辩论的结果。他对我说的最后一句话是：‘晚春时再来找我，那时我会下单买你们的石油。’

“对我来说，这简直是一个奇迹。这一次我连问都没问，他就主动提出购买我们的石油。在我真心关注他和他的问题的这两个小时里，我所取得的进展比试图让他对我的产品感兴趣的十年里还要多。”

耐弗里的事例表明，你并没有发现新大陆。在耶稣诞生的数百年前，一位罗马诗人就说过：“关心他人，才能得到他人的关心。”

你所表示出的关心必须是真诚的——就如人际关系中的其他准则一样。表示关心的一方不能是唯一的受益者；对方也应该从中受益。这是一件互利的事。

在纽约长岛参加培训班的马丁·金斯伯格讲起过一位护士对他的关心是如何彻底改变他的生活的：

“那天是感恩节，我十岁。我住在医院的福利病房，第二天要接受外科手术。我知道接下来的几个月里我都会在病房中度过，慢慢康复，但充满痛苦。我的父亲去世了，母亲和我住在一家小公寓里，靠福利救济。那天妈妈不能来看我。

“我慢慢被孤独、绝望和恐惧吞噬。我知道妈妈肯定独自在家为我担心，没人陪伴她，没人与她一同用餐，她也没有钱吃一顿感恩节大餐。

“我的眼泪涌上了眼眶，我把头埋在被子里默默流泪，默默但凄苦地流泪，整个身体都颤抖了起来。

“一位年轻的实习护士听到哭声走了过来，她把被子从我的脸上掀起，为我擦眼泪。她告诉我她也很寂寞，她在节日里要上班，不能和家人团聚。然后她问我是否愿意和她一起用餐并拿来两盘食物：切片的火鸡肉、土豆泥、红莓酱，还有当甜点的冰淇淋。她一直和我说话，试着抚慰我心中的恐惧。虽然她下午四点就该下班了，但她一直陪着我直到将近晚上十一点。她和我玩游戏、聊天，直到我睡着才离开。

“之后我又度过了一个又一个的感恩节，每次我都会想起十岁的那个感恩节以及那时失意、恐惧、孤独的感受，还有来自陌生人的温暖和温柔——她神奇般地使一切不那么难以承受了。”

如果你希望他人喜欢你，想拥有真正的友谊，想在帮助他人时自己也有所收获，请记住这条准则：

真诚地关心他人！

第九章　与人交往的最大秘密

天底下只有一种让别人做事的方法。你是否停下来想过这个问题？是的，只有一种。那就是让对方愿意做这件事。

记住，再没有其他的方式。

当然，你可以用枪口顶着对方的脑袋，让他给你手表。你也可以用威胁开除员工的方式使他为你的企业努力工作。你可以用打骂的方式让小孩做你想让他做的事。然而这些原始的方式都有极度不利的后果。

我能让你做任何事的唯一方式就是给你你想要的。

你想要什么？

西格蒙德·弗洛伊德说过，每个人做事只有两个动机：性冲动和渴望卓越。

美国影响最深远的哲学家之一约翰·杜威却有不同的观点。他说人性最根本的需求是“对重要感的追求”。请记住这几个字：“对重要感的追求”。这很重要。你在此书中会多次听到这些字。

你想要什么？好像不多，但你对少数几样东西的渴望是势不可挡的。大多数人渴望的东西包括：

1．健康长寿

2．食物

3．睡眠

4．金钱以及金钱可以买到的东西

5．永生

6．性满足

7．子孙的幸福

8．重要感

这几乎都能被满足，除了一个。但是还有一种渴求——几乎和对食物与睡眠的渴求一样深切与急迫——却很少被满足。那就是弗洛伊德所说的“渴望卓越”，即约翰·杜威所说的“对重要感的追求”。

林肯曾在一封信的开头写道：“每个人都喜欢被称赞。”威廉·詹姆士说过：“人性最基本的规律便是对称赞的渴求。”注意，他并没有说对称赞的需要或欲望，而是说对它的“渴求”。

这就是令人苦恼却又不懈追求的人性欲望，而有能力真正满足这种心之所向的少数人便是把他人掌握在股掌中了。但“即便是这些操纵者，在临死前也会有遗憾”。

“对重要感的追求”是人和动物的区别之一。比如说：当我还是密苏里农场里的小男孩时，我爸爸养殖着品种优良的杜洛克大红猪和纯种白面牛。我们还会到中西部的乡村展览和牲口秀上展示我们的猪和牛，并得了好几次第一名。我爸爸把他的所有蓝缎荣誉钉在一块白布上，亲朋好友来访时，他会拿出长长的白布给他们看。每次展示蓝缎时，他都拿着白布的一端，而我拿着另一端。

那些猪不在意它们赢得的荣誉，但是爸爸在意。这些奖章给了他重要感。

如果我们的祖先没有这种对重要感的热切渴望，人类文明便不会诞生。没有文明，我们和动物之间也就没多大差别了。

这种对重要感的渴望让狄更斯写下了不朽的篇章；这种渴望使克里斯多夫·雷恩爵士砌出了石头的交响曲；这种渴望令洛克菲勒积攒了他一辈子也花不完的千百万美金。而这种渴望也让你的城镇里最富裕的家庭建起了超出实际需要的大房子。

这种渴望支配着你——你想要穿最流行的衣服，开最新款的车，并不厌其烦地夸赞你那聪明的孩子。

这种渴望也引诱了很多少男少女加入帮派，从事犯罪活动。据纽约市前公安局局长所说，一般的年轻犯罪分子都有很强的自我意识，被关押后的第一个要求便是让那些不靠谱的小报把他们报道成大英雄。令人不悦的监禁生活对他们来讲并不要紧，只要他们能心满意足地看着自己的头像和体育明星、影视明星以及政治家出现在同一个版面上。

如果你能告诉我你是如何获取重要感的，我就能告诉你你是怎样的人。这决定了你的人格，是关于你的最重要的信息。比如，约翰·D．洛克菲勒获取重要感的方式是通过捐钱为中国北京建立一座现代医院，照料成千上万他不曾见到也不会见到的穷苦人。相反的，迪林杰通过做一名土匪、强盗和杀手而得到重要感。当联邦调查局特工追捕他时，他闯入明尼苏达的一个农家并宣布：“我是迪林杰！”他对于自己是国民头号公敌而感到骄傲。“我不会伤害你，不过我是迪林杰！”他这样说道。

没错，洛克菲勒和迪林杰的首要区别便是他们获取重要感的方式。

历史上名人努力获取重要感的闪光例子数不胜数。就连乔治·华盛顿都让别人称自己为“至高无上的美国总统”。哥伦布为自己争取了头衔：“海军上将、印度总督”；凯萨琳女皇拒绝拆阅任何没有注明“女王陛下”敬语的信件；而林肯夫人和格兰特夫人翻脸时像母老虎一样吼叫道：“没有我的邀请你怎敢坐在我的眼前！”

1928年，我们的百万富翁们资助了海军上将伯德的南极探险，而条件是要以他们的名字命名冰山。维克多·雨果渴望巴黎以自己的名字重新命名，以表达对他的敬意。就连莎士比亚——至高无上的代表，都希望为自己的家庭赢得一枚盾徽从而为自己的名字增辉。

有时人们还会用无能来获取同情和关注，从而得到重要感。比如说麦金莱夫人就是以此种方式获得重要感的。她强迫她的丈夫——一位美国总统——抛下国家大事，陪她在床上一躺就是几个小时，抱着她、哄她入睡。她拔牙时都需要丈夫陪伴左右从而获取重要感，当丈夫因赶赴与国务卿约翰·海伊的会议离开时，她便公然大吵大闹。

作家玛丽·罗伯特·莱因哈特曾经给我讲过一位聪明、强壮的年轻女人是如何为了获取重要感而失去行动能力的故事。莱因哈特夫人说：“有一天，这个女人被迫面对了一些事实，或许是她的年龄。她发现前方是漫长的孤独岁月，也对一切失去了期待。

“她躺到床上，卧床不起。而在之后的十年里，她的母亲要往返于三层楼间，端着盘子照顾她。然后有一天这位老母亲累倒了，很快便与世长辞。接下来的几周内，这个‘病人’越来越憔悴，直到有一天，她站起身来，穿上衣服，重新开始生活。”

一些权威人士说，如果一个人对重要感的渴望在残忍的现实中无法被满足，那么他有可能会疯掉，从而在疯狂的世界里找到满足。在美国，精神病患者比其他所有疾病患者的总和还要多。

精神病是什么导致的？

没有人能回答这么大的问题，但是我们知道有些疾病，例如梅毒，会毁坏脑细胞，导致精神病。实际上，一半的精神病是由物理伤害引起的，比如脑损伤、酒精中毒以及其他外伤。然而另一半精神病患者的脑细胞并没有生理病变——这才是更令人震惊的现象。检验时，他们的脑细胞经过高倍显微镜的观察，并没有显示出有何异常。

这些人又是怎么患上精神病的呢？

我向最著名的精神病院主治医师询问过这个问题。这位医生曾经在专业领域获得过最高荣誉和令人仰慕的殊荣，而他坦白地告诉我，他也不知道人们为何会疯掉。没人能准确地知道。但他也说到，很多人在疯癫的世界里找到了从前在现实世界中不曾拥有的重要感。然后他给我讲了下面的这个故事：

“我现在有一位患者，她的婚姻已被证明是个悲剧。她希望得到爱、性满足、小孩和社会名望，然而生活浇灭了她所有的希望。她的丈夫不爱她，甚至拒绝和她一起用餐，并强迫她把饭端到楼上他自己的屋子里。她没有孩子，没有社会地位。她疯了，而在她的幻想中，她和丈夫离婚了，重新使用婚前的名字。她现在认为自己嫁给了英国贵族，并坚持让别人叫她史密斯夫人。

“说到孩子，她现在每晚都认为自己刚生了一个孩子。每次我看望她时她都会对我说：‘医生，我昨晚刚生下一个婴儿。’”

生活曾经把她的梦想之船撞毁在现实的锋利礁石上，但在充满阳光和幻觉的疯癫之岛上，她所有的船都扬帆驶入港口——风儿在帆间歌唱。

听起来很可悲吗？哦，这我不知道。她的医生告诉我：“即使我伸出手就能治好她的病我也不会那样做。现在的她开心多了。”

既然人们如此渴望重要感，甚至愿意在精神病的世界里获取它，想象一下如果我们在正常的世界里给予他人真诚的感恩，那么又将发生怎样的奇迹呢？

美国第一个挣到超过一百万美金年薪的人是查尔斯·施瓦布（那时还没有施行个人所得税，人均一周五十美金已经算是不错的了）。1921年，他被安德鲁·卡耐基任命为新成立的美国钢铁公司的第一任总裁。后来，施瓦布离开了美国钢铁公司，接管了当时问题重重的伯利恒钢铁公司，并使它摇身成为美国最赚钱的公司之一。

为什么安德鲁·卡耐基会付给施瓦布每年一百万美元，或者说每天超过三千美元的薪水？这是为什么呢？因为施瓦布是天才吗？不是。因为他的钢铁业知识比别人过硬？也不是。查尔斯·施瓦布亲口对我说，他手下的很多人对钢铁业的了解比他多得多。

施瓦布说他能得到这样的薪水很大程度上是因为他懂得如何与人交往。我问他是如何做到的。下面是他表述的秘诀，这些话真应该被刻在不朽的铜牌上，挂在陆地上的每个人家、每间学校、每个店铺和每间办公室中。学生们与其花时间背拉丁文的动词形式转换或是巴西的年降雨量，不如熟记下面一段话。这些话会改变你我的生活，如果我们愿意付诸行动。

施瓦布说：“我认为我能激发人们的热情，这种能力是我最宝贵的财富。而激励他人做到最好的方式就是感谢与鼓励。

“没什么比上级的批评更能摧毁一个人的斗志了，我从不批评任何人，我相信给人树立工作动机的重要性。所以我愿意表扬，不愿批评。如果我喜欢一件事，那我会衷心地赞美，并毫不保留赞美之辞。”

这就是施瓦布的做法。而普通人是怎么做的呢？恰恰相反。如果他们不喜欢一件事，他们会痛骂下属；如果他们喜欢一件事，他们却闷不作声。就如一句老话所述：“坏事做一次，听一生；好事做两次，从未闻。”

施瓦布说：“在我与各式各样的人打交道、会见全世界最了不起的人后，还没有遇到一个在批评声中比在赞许声中更加卖力做事的人——不论他多伟大、多尊贵。”

他坦言，这就是安德鲁·卡耐基获得非凡成就的一大显著原因。无论在公开和私下场合，卡耐基都会赞美他的同事。

甚至在自己的墓碑上，卡耐基都不忘赞美同事。他为自己写的墓志铭是这样的：“躺在这里的是一个懂得如何与更聪明的人相处的人。”

真诚的感激也是老洛克菲勒成功与人交往的秘诀。举个例子来说吧，当他的一个合作伙伴爱德华·T．贝德福德轻信了一个南美坏人，使公司亏损了一百万时，洛克菲勒本可以批评他，但他知道贝德福德已经尽力了，且事态已经无法扭转。但是洛克菲勒找到了可以表扬的地方，他恭喜贝德福德挽救了60％的资金。洛克菲勒说：“这太棒了。我们上层管理者有时都做不到这么好。”

我的日记本中还有一个我知道是虚构的故事，但它反映了真理，所以让我把它讲出来吧。

这个荒唐的小故事是这样的：一个农妇在一天辛劳工作后，摆了一堆干草在男人们面前。当他们愤怒地问妇人是不是疯了的时候，她回答：“为什么？我怎么知道你们会注意到？我为你们这些人做了二十年的饭，也没人告诉我吃的不是草。”

几年前，有一项关于妻子离家出走的原因的调查。你认为她们这样做最主要的原因是什么？没错，是“不被感激”。我相信调查离家的男人也会显示同样的结果。我们往往觉得另一半的付出是理所当然的，以至于从未让对方知道我们的感激。

我们训练班上的一个人讲过他妻子提出的一个要求。他的妻子和在教堂结识的一组女友加入了一个自我提高的项目，她让丈夫帮助她列出六个需要改进的地方，以成为更完美的妻子。他对班上的人说：“我为这一要求感到吃惊。老实说，列出六个她能改进的地方很容易。天啊，她能列出一千条我需要改变的地方。但是我没有这样做。我对她说：‘让我仔细想想，明早给你答案。’

“第二天早晨，我很早起床并让花店寄来六朵玫瑰，还附上一段留言：我想不出你需要改进的六个地方。我就爱原本的你。

“猜猜那天晚上回家时谁在门口等我？没错，是我老婆！她几乎热泪盈眶。不用说，我很高兴没有按照她的指示提出改进意见。

“之后的那个周日当她在小组中公布了她的任务结果时，小组中的好几个女人过来跟我说：‘这是我听过的最体贴的事。’就是在那时我意识到了赞美的重要性。”

百老汇最耀眼的制作人弗洛伦茨·齐格菲尔德以具有“把美国女孩变得光彩夺目”的神奇能力而著称，他一次又一次地把毫不起眼的蓬头垢面的小丫头们转变为舞台上充满神秘感与诱惑的夺目风景。他深知赞美与自信的价值，他用他那绅士风度与纯粹的关怀使女孩们觉得自己很美。他的做法很实际，他把歌舞团女孩的薪水从每周30美金提高到最高175美金。他还很懂礼节，在富丽秀的首演之夜，他送了美国美人玫瑰给歌舞团的每个女孩。

有一次我无法抵抗潮流，也尝试斋戒，持续了六天六夜没吃饭。这并不难。到了第六天晚上，我的饥饿感还没有第二天晚上强烈。但你我都知道，如果你让家人或雇员六天不吃饭，那就像是犯罪一样；可是人们会六天、六周甚至六十年不给予他人衷心的赞美，而人们对赞美的渴求并不亚于对食物的渴求。

那个时代的当红演员，饰演了《重聚维也纳》中男主角的阿尔弗雷德·朗特，他说：“我最需要的莫过于自尊的滋养了。”

我们照顾着孩子、朋友和职员的身体，但对他们自尊的关怀又有多少？我们提供烤牛肉和土豆来为他们补充体力，却忘记了给予赞美的话语，而正是这些话语，会像晨星的音乐一样在他们的记忆中长久歌唱。

保罗·哈维在他的一栏广播节目《故事的结局》中说过，表达衷心的赞美能改变人的一生。他在广播中讲述了这样一件事，一年前底特律州的一名老师让史蒂夫·莫里斯帮她找教室里丢失的老鼠，而史蒂夫是个失明的孩子。你看，她欣赏自然赋予史蒂夫的独特能力。自然为了弥补史蒂夫失明的眼睛而使他的听觉变得格外发达，但这是第一次史蒂夫的超能听觉被赏识。多年后的史蒂夫说道，那个赏识之举是他全新生活的开始。从那时起，他不断开发自己的听觉天赋，后来成了70年代伟大的流行歌曲作者和演唱家之一，他的艺名是史提夫·汪达(1)。

我想，一些读者读到这里会不禁说道：“哦，去他的吧！谄媚！奉承！这些我都试过了。对聪明人来说根本不起作用。”

当然，对于有辨识能力的人来说，谄媚很难起作用。它肤浅、自私，也不诚恳。它不该奏效也通常不会奏效。没错，有些人对赞美是如此渴望，甚至愿意为得到赞美而做任何事，就像饥荒中的人会去吃草和鱼饵。

就连维多利亚女王都无法抵抗阿谀奉承。英国首相本杰明·迪斯雷利承认他曾大肆吹捧女王，用他自己的话说，就是“用铲子抹上去厚厚的一层恭维”。然而迪斯雷利是统治过大英帝国的首相里最有教养、最机敏、最灵活的人，他简直就是个政治天才。对他来说奏效的方式对你我来说不一定有用。从长远角度讲，谄媚带来的危害比益处多。谄媚是虚伪的，就像假钞一样，一旦使它流通，早晚会给你惹麻烦。

赞美与谄媚有什么不同呢？这很简单就能区分开来。一个是真诚的，一个是虚伪的。一个发自内心，一个出自牙缝。一个无私，一个自私。一个被所有人钦佩，一个被所有人鄙夷。

我最近在墨西哥城查普特佩克宫看到了墨西哥英雄阿尔瓦洛·奥博雷贡将军的半身像，雕像下刻有奥博雷贡将军的一句至理名言：“别畏惧攻击你的敌人，要畏惧奉承你的朋友。”

难道之前我不是在鼓吹奉承吗？不！不！不！赞美与奉承相差甚远！我讲的是一种新的生活方式。让我重复一遍——新的生活方式。

乔治五世国王在白金汉宫的墙上陈列了六条箴言，其中一条便是：“教给我不要给予和接受廉价的赞扬。”廉价的赞扬——这才是奉承的全部。我曾经读到过一条“奉承”的定义，值得复述：“奉承是准确地告诉对方他对自己的看法。”

拉尔夫·沃尔多·爱默生说：“不论运用何种语言，你说的话都能反映你是什么样的人。”

如果我们只渴求谄媚，每个人都能很快学会，那样的话我们就都成了人际关系的高手了。

当我们没有在思考具体问题时，95％的时候都是在想与自己有关的事。如果我们少想想自己，多想想对方，我们就不用进行廉价而荒谬的谄媚了。其实在你张口谄媚前对方就早已把你看穿了。

日常生活中，我们最缺乏的美德便是赞美。不知为何，当我们的子女考了好成绩回家时，我们忘了表扬他们；当他们第一次成功烤出一个蛋糕或是做出一个鸟屋时，我们忘了鼓励他们。对于孩子来说，没有什么比家长的关注和认同更能令他们欢呼雀跃的了。

下次当你在会所享受了一块菲力牛排后，请把对厨艺的赞美转达给厨师；当一个疲惫的销售员对你格外彬彬有礼时，也请做出相应的称赞。

每个官员、讲师和公共讲演者都明白，对观众掏心掏肺却没有得到一丝赞许的回应，这多么令人泄气。对于专业人士来讲已然如此，那么对办公室、商店和工厂里的工人以及我们的家人和朋友来讲则更是如此。在人际交往中，我们要永远记住，每个和我们打交道的都是人，都有对赞许的渴求。这是每个灵魂都欣然接受的通用货币。

试着在你的每日轨迹中洒满赞美的火花，你会惊讶地发现，你种下的友谊火种在你下一次路过时早已成为了玫瑰色的篝火。

康涅狄格州费尔菲尔德市的帕梅拉·邓纳姆每日工作中的一个任务就是监管一名工作做得很糟糕的清洁工。其他员工会嘲笑这个清洁工，并把垃圾撒在过道里，以表示对他工作的不满。他的情况太糟糕，以至于浪费了店里许多的工作时间。

帕梅拉试过多种方式来鼓励这名清洁工，但都以失败收场。她发现这个人有时会把一小部分工作做得非常好，于是她特意当众表扬了他。后来，他的整体工作越做越好，不久便能高效完成他所有的任务了。现在，他工作更加出色，人们也给予了他赞赏与认可。诚恳的称赞解决了批评和嘲笑所不能解决的问题。

伤害他人不但无法改变他，还永远不受欢迎。我把一句老话贴在了我的镜子上，每天都会不自觉地看到它：

这条路我只能走一次，如果我能为任何人做些有益的事，对任何人表示善意，那就让我立刻行动。不要等待也不要怠慢，因为这条路我只能走一次。

爱默生说过：“我遇到的每个人在某些方面都比我强，都是我的导师。”

如果对爱默生都是如此，那么对你和我来说，这话更是有千百倍的道理了。让我们少想想自己的成就和需求，试图多发现他人的优点。让我们忘记谄媚这件事，诚实、诚恳地给予赞美。“真心地称赞，不吝惜赞美之词”，人们便会珍视你说的话，不仅珍藏它们，并一辈子想着它——在你已然忘记的时候依然会重复着你说过的话。

请给予诚实、诚恳的赞美。

————————————————————

(1) 保罗·奥朗特，保罗·哈维的《故事的结局》（纽约：双日出版社，1977）。琳·哈维编辑并整理。Paulynne公司版权所有。

第十章　如何让人们立刻喜欢上你

我正在纽约三十三街和第八大道交口的邮局排队寄挂号信，我发现邮局员工看上去对工作有些不耐烦。称重、贴邮票、找钱、打印收据，他们年复一年、日复一日重复着同样的动作。但是我对自己说：“我要试着让这个员工喜欢我。显然，为了让他喜欢我，我得说些好听的话——当然是关于他的而不是关于自己的。”于是我问自己：“在他身上有什么我真正羡慕的东西呢？”这个问题有时很难回答，尤其是面对着陌生人的时候。但在当前的情形中，回答这个问题恰好很容易。我瞬间就发现了自己羡慕得不得了的东西。

所以当他在给我的信称重时，我热情地对他说：“我真希望我有你那么好的头发。”

他抬起头，显得有点吃惊，随即脸上浮现出微笑。他谦虚地说：“已经不如从前喽。”我向他保证道，即便或许不像以前那么油亮，也依然让人羡慕。他听完很高兴，我们接着进行了简短的对话，最后他对我说：“很多人都羡慕我的头发呢。”

我打赌那个人中午出去吃饭时肯定高兴得手舞足蹈。我保证他当晚回家会向他妻子说起这件事。我相信他一定会对着镜子里的自己说：“我的头发真是不错。”

有一次，我公开讲了这个故事，之后一个人问我：“你想从他那儿得到什么呢？”

我想从他那儿得到什么？！我想从他那儿得到什么！！！

如果我们自私到如此严重的地步，就连传递小小的开心、表达小小的欣赏时还必须得到回报，说明我们的灵魂还没有酸沙果大，那么我们将注定得到我们应得的失败。

哦！没错，我的确想从那个朋友那儿得到些什么。我想要一种无价的东西，而我得到了。我感觉到了为对方做点什么但不求回报的快感。这是一种事后依然久久在你记忆中流淌和歌唱的感受。

人类行为中有一个最重要的法则，如果我们遵从了这个法则便几乎永远不会陷入麻烦，而且能收获无数朋友和恒久的快乐，但一旦违背了这个法则便会遇到无尽的麻烦。这法则就是：永远要让对方感觉到他的重要。就如我们之前提到过的约翰·杜威的话：“重要感是人性最根本的需求。”还有威廉·詹姆士的话：“人性最基本的规律便是对称赞的渴求。”就如我之前所述，这种渴求是人类和动物之间的区别。这种渴求也是文明诞生的基石。

哲学家千百年来一直探索着人际关系的法则，而在一切推断中只有一个法则是最重要的。这并不是新的发现，有史以来就有了它。两千五百年前，琐罗亚斯德就对波斯的门徒传授过这个法则；两千四百年前，孔夫子就在中国讲授过这个法则；两千五百年前，老子在函谷关也讲过这个道理；在耶稣诞生的五百年前，佛祖就在恒河边布过此道；此前一千年，印度的圣书里也印着同样的道理；一千九百年前，耶稣在犹大石山里也总结出了这个法则。这个世上最重要的法则就是：希望如何被对待，就该如何待他人（己所不欲，勿施于人）。

你希望接触过的人能够肯定你，你希望你的价值能被认可，你想要在你的小世界中感觉自己很重要。你不想听廉价、虚伪的奉承，对真诚的赞赏如饥似渴。你希望朋友和同事能够“真诚地赞美，并不吝赞美之词。”——就如查尔斯·施瓦布所说的那样。我们每个人都想要这些。

所以，让我们遵从黄金法则：“希望如何被对待，就该如何待他人。”

怎么做？在什么时候做？在什么地方做？答案是：随时随地。

威斯康星州欧克莱尔市的大卫·G．史密斯曾在培训班里讲过他是如何处理一个微妙的情形的。那时他被要求负责一个公益音乐会的饮料安排。

“音乐会那晚，我赶到公园里，看到两位女士面色难看地站在饮料桌旁，原来她俩都认为自己是当晚负责饮料桌的人。我正在思考如何是好，这时赞助方的人过来递给我一个收款盒，并感谢我答应接管饮料事宜。他把罗丝和珍介绍给我为我当助手，然后就走开了。

“接下来又是一阵沉默。我意识到收钱盒是一种权力的象征（从某个角度来讲），就把它交给了罗丝，并告诉她我可能管不好钱，如果她能负责收钱我就放心了。然后我让珍教被派来帮忙的两个年轻学生如何操作饮料机，并让她负责所有饮料机相关的事宜。

“结果那个晚上大家过得非常愉快。罗丝高兴地数着钱，珍指导着两个少年操作饮料机，而我享受着音乐会。”

你不必等到当上法国大使或是社交委员会主席时才开始使用感激之词。你每天都可以施展它的魔力。

比如说，你在餐馆点了薯条，而服务员端来了土豆泥，让我们这样说：“不好意思给你添麻烦了，但是我们点的是薯条。”她很可能会回答：“一点都不麻烦”，然后会愉快地帮你换成薯条，因为我们对她表示了尊重。

类似于“不好意思麻烦你……”“你能帮我一个忙吗？”“可否请你……”“你是否介意”“谢谢”之类的简短客气语句能给单调乏味的生活带来一丝慰藉。当然，这也是良好家教的体现。

让我们再来看看另外一个例子。霍尔·凯恩的小说《基督徒》《法官》《马恩岛人》等都是20世纪初的畅销书，读过他的书的人不计其数。他是一个铁匠的儿子，总共只上过八年学。然而他去世时却是那个年代最富有的文学家。

他的故事是这样子的：霍尔·凯恩喜欢十四行诗和叙事诗，所以他嚼烂了但丁·加布里尔·罗赛蒂的诗歌。他甚至写过一篇赞美罗赛蒂艺术成就的散文并寄给了罗赛蒂本人。罗赛蒂很高兴，他可能心里暗想：“任何对我的能力有如此高评价的年轻人一定都是才华横溢的。”因此罗赛蒂邀请这位铁匠的儿子到伦敦给他当秘书。这是霍尔·卡恩人生中的转折点，因为通过这份工作，他遇到了诸多那个年代最优秀的文学艺术家。他从那些人的建议中得到启发，受到鼓励，终于开启了自己的写作生涯，他的大名也得以载入史册。

他在马恩岛的家——格里巴城堡也成了全世界游客向往的旅游胜地，还留下了价值几百万美金的房产。如果他没有写过那篇赞美名人的散文，他或许会在贫穷和默默无闻中死去。

这就是真诚赞美的惊人力量。

罗赛蒂认为自己很重要，这一点都不奇怪。几乎每个人都觉得自己非常重要，无可替代。

很多人的生活轨迹都可能会改变，前提是如果有人让他们感觉到自己的重要性。罗纳德·J．罗兰是我们加州培训班的一位讲师，他也是一名教艺术和手工的老师。他曾写信给我们讲过他的初级手工班里一名叫克里斯的学生的故事：

“克里斯非常安静，是一个没什么自信的害羞男孩，就是那种总是得不到应有关注的学生。我还教一个高级班，能为自己赢得那堂课一个席位的学生便拥有了荣誉和某种身份象征。

“那是某个周三，克里斯在他的课桌前用功地制作着工艺品。我真的觉得这孩子心里仿佛有一团隐形的火，因此我问克里斯是否愿意加入我的高级班。我真希望我能描绘出他听到这话时的表情，这个十四岁的腼腆男孩努力地克制住泪水。

“‘谁？我吗，罗兰先生？我够好吗？’

“‘是的，克里斯，你足够好。’

“那一刻我必须离开，因为我的眼泪就要涌出来了。那天克里斯走出课堂时仿佛长高了两英寸。他用明亮的蓝眼睛望着我，声音激动地说：‘罗兰先生，谢谢你。’

“克里斯让我学到了一堂终生难忘的课程——我们对重要感的深深渴望。为了时刻记得这一道理，我制作了一个牌子，上面写着‘你很重要’并把它挂在了教室最前方。我希望每个学生都能看到，也希望这能提醒我，每个学生都是同样重要。”

显而易见的真相就是：你遇到的每个人都认为自己在某个方面比你强，而走进他们心里的方法便是让他们意识到你真诚地承认他们的重要性。

别忘了爱默生的话：“我遇到的每个人在某些方面都比我强，都是我的导师。”

可悲的是，那些最不配拥有成就感的人却上演着喧闹、欺瞒的戏码，助长着令人作呕的自负。就如莎士比亚所说：“……人类，自负的人类，穿着那一丁点的权威，在天堂面前玩着荒诞的把戏，使天使落下眼泪。”

你知道我们培训班中的商务人士是如何对这些法则应用于现实生活并得到显著成效的吗？让我来告诉你吧。就举康涅狄格州的一名律师的例子吧（由于对亲戚的顾虑，他希望不公布自己的名字）。

加入课程不久后，R先生和妻子开车到长岛拜访妻子的亲戚。妻子中途离席去和年轻的亲戚攀谈，留下R先生和她的一位年长的姨妈在一起聊天。他想到自己不久将要在班里做关于感激的实际应用的演讲，便觉得或许能从和老姨妈的聊天中得到一些有用的内容。所以他环顾四周，想找找有什么可以真诚欣赏的东西。

“这房子是1890年盖起来的，对吧？”他问道。

“没错，”她回答，“就是1890年。”

“这让我想到了我出生的那个房子。”他说，“这房子真漂亮。建得又坚固又温馨。你知道的，现在的人建不出这样的房子了。”

“说得没错。”老阿姨表示赞同。“现在的年轻人不在乎房子好不好看。他们只想要一个小公寓，然后坐在车里四处游荡。”

“这是个梦想之家。”她的声音因充满温柔的回忆而微微颤抖，“这是用爱建起的房子。我丈夫和我在建它之前憧憬了好几年，我们没有建筑师，一切都是我们自己设计的。”

她领R先生参观了房子，而他对老阿姨在旅行时收集到并珍惜了一生的小物件表示衷心的欣赏——佩斯利披肩、一套古老的英国茶具、韦奇伍德瓷器、法国的床和椅子、意大利的画还有曾经挂在法国城堡里的丝绸帷幔。

向R先生展示过房子后，老姨妈带他去看了停车库。在石阶上停着一辆崭新的帕卡德。

她轻声说：“这是我先生去世前不久给我买的，他死后我就再也没有开过。你懂得欣赏美好的事物，我要把这辆车送给你。”

“哦，阿姨，这怎么行？”他说道，“这太贵重了。当然我很感激您的慷慨，但是我不能接受。我甚至连您的亲戚都不是。我已经有一辆新车了，我相信您有很多亲戚会想要这辆帕卡德的。”

“亲戚！”她大叫道，“是啊，我是有亲戚，他们都等着我死，然后就能把那辆车开走了。但是我不会让他们得到这辆车的。”

“如果您不想送给亲戚也可以卖给二手车商。”他告诉她。

“卖掉它！”她喊道，“你觉得我会卖掉它吗？你觉得我能忍受陌生人开着这辆车在街上穿梭吗？那可是我丈夫买给我的车！我想都没想过要卖掉它。我要把它送给你，你会欣赏美好的东西。”

R先生想尽办法拒绝，但无法不伤害她的感情地达到目标。

这位女士，孤单地和她的佩斯利披肩、法国古董以及她的回忆住在这间大房子里，渴望得到的只是一丝丝的重视。她也曾经年轻貌美、颇受欢迎。她曾经用爱建筑了温馨的房子，并从欧洲收集了各种物件来打扮房子。而现在，到了孤苦伶仃的年龄，她渴望那一丝来自他人的温暖和一点真诚的欣赏，但没有人能给她。当她得到了温暖和欣赏时就像在沙漠中找到了绿洲，她想不到什么能表达她的感激之情了，所以她把珍贵的帕卡德赠予了R先生。

让我们来看另一个例子。唐纳德·M．麦克马洪是路易斯瓦伦丁的主管，纽约莱伊市的苗圃和园林建筑师。他讲到了这样一件事：

“我参加‘如何赢得朋友、影响他人’的培训班后不久，开始为一位知名法官的庄园设计园艺。庄园主给我列出了几条关于在什么地方种大片杜鹃花的指示。

“我对他说：‘法官，您的爱好真不赖。我特别喜欢您那几只狗，我知道您每年都在麦迪逊广场公园那边赢很多的蓝绶带。’

“我流露出的仰慕带来了惊人的效果。

“‘没错。’法官回答，‘我是很喜欢养狗。你想不想看看我的养狗场？’

“他用了差不多一个小时给我展示他的狗和他得过的荣誉。他甚至还拿出了这些狗的血统记录，给我解释了优良血统是如何使他的狗拥有出色的外貌和智力的。

“最后，他转身问我：‘你有小孩吗？’

“‘有的。我有个儿子。’我回答道。

“‘那他想不想养只小狗？’法官问道。

“‘哦，他很想。他会高兴坏了的。’

“‘好吧，我送给他一只。’法官宣布。

“然后他开始给我讲解如何养狗。过了一会儿他停了下来，说他怕这样告诉我我会忘记的，他决定写下来。于是这位法官回到屋里，打出了小狗的血统和喂养说明，并送给我一只价值几百美金的小狗。他从他宝贵的时间里为我抽出了一个小时十五分钟，只因我对他的爱好和成就表示了真诚的仰慕。”

柯达的创始人乔治·伊斯曼发明了促使电影胶片诞生的幻灯片，不仅挣了上亿美金，自己也成为世上最出名的商人之一。然而即便有这诸多的成就，他依然和你我一样渴望被认可。

比如说，当他在罗切斯特创建了伊斯曼音乐学院并盖起了库伯恩音乐厅时，纽约高档座椅公司的总裁詹姆斯·亚当森希望为音乐厅提供座椅。于是亚当森先生致电建筑师，并预约时间与伊斯曼先生在罗切斯特会面。

亚当森抵达后，建筑师说：“我知道你很想拿到这笔订单，但是我现在就可以向你保证，如果你占用了伊斯曼先生超过五分钟的时间，就一丁点希望都没有了。他是个厉行纪律的大忙人。所以请你尽快说明意图，尽快离开。”

亚当森事先正是准备这样做的。

当他被带入房间时，他看到伊斯曼先生正埋在桌上的一堆文件中。这时伊斯曼先生抬头摘掉了眼镜，走向建筑师和亚当森先生，并说：“早上好，先生们。有什么我可以效劳的？”

建筑师介绍了双方，然后亚当森说：“伊斯曼先生，在等您的时候，我一直在欣赏您的办公室，我真想自己也能在这样的房间里办公。我从事室内装修行业，但这辈子从没见过这么漂亮的办公室。”

乔治·伊斯曼回答：“你提醒了我几乎已经忘掉的事。它真的很美，不是吗？刚建起来的时候，我自己也是特别享受在这里工作的。不过现在每天脑子里都有太多的事，有时一连几周都不会注意到这房间本身。”

亚当森走过去，摸着一块板子说：“这是英国橡木吧？和意大利橡木有些不同。”

“没错。”伊斯曼回答，“这是进口的英国橡木。这是一个木材行家朋友帮我挑选的。”

然后伊斯曼向他展示了整个房间，讲解着比例、颜色、雕刻和其他他参与设计并执行的方方面面。

在参观房间、赞美木工活时，伊斯曼在窗前停住了，他用他那谦虚、温和的讲话方式介绍了他出资赞助从而能帮助更多人的机构：罗切斯特大学、综合医院、顺势疗法医院、友好家园、儿童医院。亚当森对伊斯曼用财富缓解人类痛苦的人道主义举动表示了衷心的敬仰。然后，伊斯曼打开了玻璃柜的锁，拿出了他拥有的第一台相机——那是他从一个英国人那里买来的。

亚当森详细地了解了伊斯曼先生创业初期的艰辛处境，而伊斯曼先生的话语中透露出对儿时贫苦生活的切实感受，也讲了他在保险公司工作时，他的母亲是如何照看一家寄宿舍的。对贫穷的恐惧日夜萦绕着他，使他下定决心赚足够的钱，让母亲不必工作。当伊斯曼先生讲到他的经历和照相干版的实验时，亚当森又不停询问并倾听着，听得入了迷。伊斯曼讲了他是如何在办公室里没日没夜地工作，连续七十二小时只有在等待照片成像时才能和衣小睡一会儿的。

十点十五分时，亚当森被带入伊斯曼的办公室，虽然之前已经被提醒了不能占用伊斯曼先生超过五分钟的时间，然而一个小时过去了，两个小时也过去了，他们还在聊。

最后乔治·伊斯曼转向亚当森说：“上次我去日本时买了些椅子带回家，然后放在了阳台上，但是阳光把它们晒掉漆了，所以前几天我到城里买了些油漆，自己重漆了这些椅子。你想不想看看我的手艺？如果可以的话，到我家和我一起吃午饭，让我展示给你看。”

午饭后，伊斯曼先生向亚当森展示了他从日本买来的椅子。这些椅子不过几百美金，但亿万富翁乔治·伊斯曼却视之如珍宝，因为那是他自己刷的漆。

椅子的订单合同金额总共九万美金。你认为是谁得到了这个订单？亚当森还是他的竞争对手？答案不言而喻。

从那时起直到伊斯曼去世，亚当森和他都保持着亲密的朋友关系。

法国鲁昂的餐馆老板克劳德·马拉依运用了这个法则，并留下了餐馆一名重要的员工。这位女士为马拉依工作了五年，是马拉依和21位员工之间的纽带。接到她寄来的辞职挂号信时，马拉依不由得大吃一惊。

马拉依说：“我非常吃惊，更是失望，因为我一直以为我对她很好，满足了她的需求。作为朋友和老板，或许对于她的努力，我接受得过于理所当然了，抑或对她的要求也比对其他员工高。

“当然我不会在没有听到任何解释的情况下接受她的辞职。我把她拉到一边，说：‘波莱，你必须知道我无法接受你的辞职。你对我和公司来说太重要了，对于公司的成功来说，你和我都是一样重要的。’我在所有员工面前又重复了这话，并邀请她到我家来，在家人面前重申了我对她的信心。

“之后波莱撤回了辞职请求，如今我更加信任她了。我常常表示对她努力工作的感谢，并告诉她对我和我的餐馆来说，她是多么的重要。”

大英帝国最精明的统治者之一迪斯雷利说过：“和别人谈他们的事，他们能听上好几个钟头。”所以，请记住：

发自真心地，让对方感觉到自己的重要性。

第十一章　“做到便拥有世界；做不到则形单影只”

夏天里，我常常北上去缅因州钓鱼。我很喜欢草莓和奶油，但我发现鱼儿很奇怪，它们喜欢吃蚯蚓。所以我钓鱼时不会想自己喜欢吃什么，而会想鱼儿喜欢吃什么。我不会在鱼钩上挂草莓和奶油，而是把蚯蚓或蚱蜢送到鱼儿眼前，问它们：“不想吃点吗？”

如果你试图吸引其他人，为何不这样尝试呢？

第一次世界大战时期的英国首相劳合·乔治就是这样做的。有人问他，其他战争时期领袖——威尔逊、奥兰多和克莱蒙梭，都已被人遗忘，而他是怎么做到一直掌权的？他回答，如果只能归功于一点，那就是他懂得用合适的鱼饵去钓鱼的重要性。

为什么要讨论自己的需求呢？这听起来似乎很幼稚、荒唐。当然，你对自己的需求感兴趣，能永远感兴趣，但再没有其他人对你感兴趣了。其他人都像你一样，也只对自己的需求感兴趣。

所以，这世上能对他人产生影响的方式只有一种，那就是谈论对方的需求并尽可能去满足那个需求。

因此，日后当你想让他人做某事时请记住这点。例如，如果你不希望你的孩子抽烟，那么请不要只是说教，不要讲你想要什么，而要让他们明白，抽烟有可能摧毁他们加入篮球队或夺得百米跑冠军的梦想。

不论你面对的是孩子、小牛还是大猩猩，都应该记住这一点。举个例子，有一天，拉尔夫·沃尔多·爱默生和他儿子试图把一头牛赶回牛棚里，但他们犯了用个人需求方式思考的错误。爱默生在后面推，儿子在前面拉。然而小牛和他们做着同样的事——只考虑自己的需求，所以它绷紧四肢，拒绝离开牧草地。一个爱尔兰女佣看到了他们的窘迫情形。她虽然不会写文章、写书，但应付这种情况她还是更有办法的。她想到了小牛的需求，所以她把她那充满母性的手指放入了小牛的口中，一边让小牛吸吮着，一边慢慢把它带入牛棚。

你从出生以来所做的每件事都源于你自己的需求。那么为红十字会捐款时呢？是的，这也不例外。你捐款是因为你想要伸出援助之手，想做一件美好、无私、神圣的事。“这些事，你既是为我最不起眼的兄弟做了，便是为我做了。”(1)

若不是你想奉献的感觉强于想留住钱的感觉，便不会做出捐款之举。当然，捐款还有可能是因为不好意思不捐，或者有人要求你这样做。但有一件事是肯定的，你捐款是因为你有此需求。

哈里·A．奥沃思特利特在他那颇能给人启迪的《人类行为》一书中说：“行为源于最基本的需求……不论是对商界、学校还是政界的未来领袖来说，首要铭记于心的便是：使他人产生迫切的需求。能做到这点的人便拥有了整个世界，做不到的人便形单影只。”

出身贫寒的安德鲁·卡内基曾经做着一小时两分钱的工作，但后来他仅仅捐款就捐了3.65亿美金。他早早就懂得了影响他人的唯一方法便是基于对方需求的道理。虽然他只上过四年学，而他懂得如何与人相处。

比如，他的嫂子为她两个儿子操碎了心。他们都在耶鲁大学念书，忙得不可开交时总是不记得写信回家，也总是对母亲发疯般的来信置之不理。

后来卡内基说他有办法不要求他们回信就收到他们的回复，并愿打一百元的赌。有人愿意和他赌，于是他写了封很长的信给那两个孩子，说了很多杂七杂八的事，最后还随意补充了一句，他随信给每人寄去五美金。

不过，他“忘记”把钱放进去了。

回信很快收到了，他们感谢了“亲爱的安德鲁叔叔”，而接下来发生的事情你应该可以猜到了。

另一个例子是俄亥俄州克利夫兰的斯坦·诺瓦克，他是我们培训课里的一名学员。斯坦一天晚上下班回家看见他的小儿子提姆在客厅里乱踢乱叫。提姆第二天就要开始上幼儿园了，因此在表示强烈的抗议。换作平时，斯坦肯定会把儿子赶回自己的小屋，让他最好听话乖乖上幼儿园，即使他不愿意也得去。然而那天晚上斯坦知道这种做法无益于提姆以最佳心态开始幼儿园生活，于是他坐下来思考：“如果我是提姆，我要怎样才会为上幼儿园而感到兴奋？”他和妻子列出一系列提姆会喜欢的有趣的事，比如用手指画画、唱歌、结交新朋友，然后他们开始行动。“我们一同开始在餐桌上用手指画画——我的妻子莉尔、我的另一个儿子鲍勃还有我。很快提姆就开始从角落里偷看了，然后他也准备加入进来。‘哦，不行！你必须去幼儿园学习手指作画才能跟我们一起玩。’我对他说。于是我声情并茂地、尽可能用提姆听得懂的语言讲了那一系列幼儿园里能做的趣事。第二天早晨，我以为我是第一个起床的。谁知我下楼看到提姆在客厅的椅子上睡得正香。‘你在这儿干吗呢？’我问道。他说：‘我在等着去幼儿园。我不想迟到。’全家人对游戏的热情激起了提姆对幼儿园的渴望，而任何谈话或威胁都做不到这点。”

某一天你或许需要说服他人做某事。当你开口前请停下来先问一下自己：“我如何能让他想做此事？”

思考这个问题能避免我们一不小心掉入对自己的需求滔滔不绝，结果却适得其反的情形中。

有一段时间，我每个季度都会租下纽约某大酒店的大宴会厅二十个晚上，用来做一系列讲座。

在某一个季度的开始，我忽然被告知我要付之前三倍的租金。听到这消息时，我的门票都已经开卖了，各种活动信息也已经发布了。

当然，我不愿付多倍的钱，但跟酒店说我的需求又有什么用呢？他们只对自己的需求感兴趣。所以，几天后我去见了他们的经理。

我对他说：“我接到信后着实吃了一惊，但是我不怪你。如果我是你，估计也会做同样的事。你作为酒店经理就是要为酒店挣钱，如果你不这样做就会被开除。现在让我们先来列一下涨价带来的好处和坏处，如果列完你还是执意涨价的话，那请便。”

然后我拿出一张信纸，在中间划了一道竖线，一边写着“优势”，一边写着“劣势”。

在优势下面，我写了：“腾出宴会厅”。我继续说道：“这样你的宴会厅就可以继续出租给跳舞和开会的人们了，这是很大的优势，因为那样的场合比讲座能给你们带来更大的收益。如果这二十个晚上宴会厅都被占，你可能会与一些很赚钱的活动失之交臂。

“现在我们来想想不利的一面。首先，来自我的收益会降低而不是提高。说实话，你将彻底失去这笔收益因为我无法支付你索要的价钱，而且我将被迫更改演讲地址。

“还有另外一个不利因素。这些演讲会吸引大量有文化、高学历的人士来到你的酒店，而这对你们来讲是好的宣传，不是吗？实际上，即便你花五千美金在报纸上打广告也没法吸引这么多人来多看你们酒店一眼，而现在我把他们带上了门。这对于酒店来讲也是很重要的，不是吗？”

我边讲便把这两点写在了劣势一栏下，并把这张纸递给了经理。“我希望你能仔细思考优劣势，以及它们对你意味着什么，然后给我一个最终答复。”

第二天我收到了一封信，通知我租金只会涨50％而非300％。

别忘了，我没有说一丁点自己的需求就得到了这个优惠。从头到尾我都是只在说对方需要什么、怎么达成。

假设我做了最自然、最符合一般常理的事——怒气冲冲地闯入他的办公室，说：“你都知道我已经开始卖门票、做宣传了，现在跟我说房租涨三倍是什么意思？三倍！你疯了吗？太荒唐了！我不可能付给你！”

那样又会发生什么呢？我们会开始争论，争论会白热化，最后不用想都知道争论的结局是怎样的。即便我可以证明他错了，他为了面子也不会服输、不会让步。

下面是关于人际关系最好的建议。亨利·福特曾说过：“如果成功只有一个秘诀，那就是理解对方的观点、站在对方的角度看问题的能力。”

这话说得太好了，让我再重复一遍：“如果成功只有一个秘诀，那就是理解对方的观点，站在对方的角度看问题的能力。”

这一句话太简单、太明显了，每个人一眼就能看出这是真理，然而地球上的人在90％的情形中都会把它忘记。

如果你留心查看明天早晨收到的信，你会发现大多数人都违背了这条重要的常识。看看下面这个例子，这是一个分公司遍布全球的广告公司广播部负责人写的信。（在每段后的中括号里都写了我看后的反应。）

约翰·某某先生

某某镇

印第安纳

亲爱的某某先生：

××公司希望在广播界继续保持广告公司的领军地位。

［谁在乎你们公司希望如何？我在担心我自己的问题。银行要取消我的房屋抵押贷款；虫子毁了我的蜀葵；股市昨天跌了；我错过了早晨8：15的车；昨晚琼斯家的舞会没有邀请我；医生说我有高血压、神经炎和头皮屑。然后呢？我心事重重地来到公司，拆开信，就看到一个纽约的傲慢家伙哇啦哇啦地开始讲他的公司想要什么。呸！如果他能意识到自己的信带给别人怎样的印象，他就应该撤出广告界，去生产羊羔清洗液！］

本公司全国广告业的客户是广播网的保障。我们所打折出售的电台时间也使我们年复一年保持在业界的领先地位。

［你们又大、又富裕、又领先，是不是啊？那又如何？你就算是有通用汽车、通用电气、美国陆军总参谋部加起来那么大，我也丝毫不会关心。如果你有蜂鸟一半的智商也会意识到我只关心我自己有多重要，而不是你多重要。你对巨大成功的吹嘘只会使我觉得你们渺小、不重要。］

我们希望为广播电台信息做主，从而更好地服务于我们的客户。

［你们希望！你们希望……你们这些十足的混蛋。我对你们的希望和美国总统的希望都丝毫不感兴趣。让我最后再告诉你一遍：我只对我自己希望如何感兴趣，而你这封愚蠢的信里对此丝毫没有提及。］

因此，你们是否可以把××公司加入每周电台信息的优先列表中，即每个对智能化购买广播时间有用的细节里。

［“推荐列表。”真是厚颜无耻啊！你的夸夸其谈已然让我感觉微不足道，现在居然还要我把你加到我的“优先”列表上，而你连个请字都没说过。］

及时确认收到此信并告知你们的最新动态，将会使双方都能受益。

［白痴！你寄了一封丝毫不讲究的信，就像秋天的树叶一样随意，而你竟然有胆量让我在担心我的抵押贷款、蜀葵和血压时给你回信，并确认收到你的信，还要“及时”。什么叫“及时”？你难道不知道我和你一样忙吗？至少我是这样认为的。还有，在我们的沟通过程中，是谁给了你命令我的权利？……你说“将会使双方都能受益”。终于，你终于开始为我考虑了，但是你没有说清楚我会如何受益。］

你最真诚的，

约翰·某某某

广播部门经理

又及，随信附上从《某某镇日报》中复制的文章，你们会感兴趣的，或许可以在电台中播出。

［终于，在最后的“又及”中你提到了有可能帮助我解决问题的内容。为什么不在一开始就说呢？不过已经于事无补了。任何能说出这番胡话的广告人脑子都有问题。你不需要我们回信告诉你最新动态，你需要的是吞下一瓶碘酒治治甲状腺。］

如果身为广告人，一生致力于宣传并号称是影响力艺术的专家的人，写出的竟然是这样一封信，那么屠夫、烘焙师或是汽车修理工又会做出什么呢？

下面还有一封信，是一个大客运站负责人写给我们培训班中一位学员的，这位学员名叫爱德华·费米伦。对于这封信他会做何感想？读完我会告诉你。

泽瑞嘉公司

前街28号

纽约布鲁克林　邮编11201

请爱德华·费米伦先生阅读

先生，您好：

由于大量货物都在下午抵达我们的火车出站点收货站，我们的运营将会受阻。这种状况也会造成工作程序不畅、公司员工加班、卡车延误以及偶尔的货物运输延迟。11月10日，贵公司的510件货物于下午4：20抵达我们的收货站。

我们希望得到贵公司的支持，与我们一同解决因货物晚到而带来的不良影响。我们可否恳请贵公司在运输与11月10日等量的货物时能够让卡车提前到达收货站或使部分货物在早晨抵达？

对贵公司而言，这样做卡车便能更顺利地卸货，也能确保您的货物在当天运出。

您最真诚的，

J_____　B_____，负责人

泽瑞嘉公司的销售经理费米伦先生读完这封信后把它转寄给我，并附上了下面这段评论：

这封信起到了相反的作用。它一开始描述了收货站面对的困境，而我们总的来说是不感兴趣的。然后又请我们合作，根本不考虑可能给我们带来的不便。最后他们才说这样做给我们带来的好处是更快速地卸货和当天运出的保证。

换言之，我们最关心的事反而放在最后说，这封信总的来说令我们反感，不会有合作的欲望。

我们试着来重写一下这封信。记住，不要浪费任何笔墨讨论谈自己的问题。就如亨利·福特所说，让我们去“了解对方的观点，站在对方的角度看问题”。

下面是重写此信的一种方式。这或许不是最好的方式，但谁能说没有进步呢？

费米伦先生收

c/o泽瑞嘉公司

前街28号

纽约布鲁克林，邮编11201

亲爱的费米伦先生，

十四年来，贵公司一直是我们的重要客户。我们很感激您的一贯支持，愿竭力为您提供您所应得的快速、高效的服务。但遗憾的是，如果贵公司的卡车像11月10日那天一样在傍晚才送到大批货物，我们将无法保证货物的及时运输。为什么呢？因为很多客户都在傍晚送货，这就造成了阻塞。这意味着贵公司的卡车将不可避免地需要排队卸货，有时还会导致货物的延迟输出。

这很糟糕，但可以避免。如果贵公司尽可能在早上送货，卡车将能够随时卸货，货物也将在第一时间被处理。这样，我们的员工也能按时下班，就可以在晚餐时间享用贵公司生产的美味通心粉和面条了。

当然，不论您的货物何时运到，我们都会愉快、竭诚地为您提供快捷服务。

您很忙碌。请不必回信。

你最真诚的，

J_____　B_____，负责人

在纽约一家银行工作的芭芭拉·安德逊因为儿子的健康原因想搬到亚利桑那州的凤凰城居住。她用在培训班中学到的准则给凤凰城的十二家银行写了如下一封信：

亲爱的先生，

相信飞速发展的贵银行对我十年的银行工作经验会有兴趣。

在信孚银行工作的这段时间里，我熟识了银行每日运营的全部过程，包括维护储蓄客户关系、信托、贷款和行政管理，后来成了分行经理。

我将在5月份迁至凤凰城，请相信我会为贵银行带来发展与效益。4月3日那周我会在凤凰城，如果您能给我一个展示如何为贵银行达成目标的机会，我将感激不尽。

真诚的，

芭芭拉·L．·安德逊

你觉得芭芭拉会得到银行的回复吗？结果是这十二家银行中的十一家邀请她参加面试，她得选择最终接受哪家银行的录用邀请。为什么呢？安德逊夫人没有说自己想要什么，在信中写的是她能带给对方什么，把重点放在了对方的需求上，而非自己的。

今天，有无数薪水微薄的销售人员疲惫、气馁地捶着地。为什么？因为他们总是想着自己要什么，他们没有意识到你和我根本不想买东西。如果想买，我们自然会出门买。然而你和我都永远对解决自己的问题最感兴趣。所以，如果销售人员能够展示给我们他们的服务或产品能怎样解决我们的问题，那么连推销都是不必要的了，我们自然会买。此外，顾客喜欢感觉自己是在购买，而非被兜售。

然而很多销售人员一辈子都不懂从顾客的角度看问题。比如，我曾在森林山住了很多年，那是大纽约中部的一个私宅小社区。有一天，我在去车站的路上碰到一个房地产经纪人。他在森林山社区从事房屋买卖多年，很了解那里的情况，所以我匆忙地向他询问我那水泥墙房是金属板条还是空心砖建造的。他说他不知道，并告诉了我我本就知道的信息，他建议我打电话给森林山园协会询问。第二天早晨我收到了他的来信，但他提供了我所需的信息了吗？原本他花六十秒钟打个电话就可以找出问题的答案，然而他没有。他再次告诉我可以打电话询问，然后让我买他家的保险。

他根本不想帮助我。他只对帮助自己感兴趣。

亚拉巴马州伯明翰的J．霍华德·卢卡斯给我讲了同家公司的两个销售人员是如何处理类似的情形的：

“几年前，我只是一家小公司管理团队中的一员。我们公司的旁边是一家大保险公司的区域总部办公室。他们公司的保险代理人各自负责不同的区域，而且我们公司正好是这两名保险代理员负责的。在这里就称他们为卡尔和约翰吧。

“一个早晨，卡尔到我们的办公室来，不经意间提到了一种新的高管人寿保险，他认为我们可能会感兴趣。他说一旦他有更多信息就会告诉我们。

“也是在同一天，约翰在路上看到我们买咖啡回来，于是喊住了我们：‘嘿，卢克，等一等。我有好消息告诉你们。’他兴奋地跑过来说他们公司当天推出了一种新的高管人寿保险（就是卡尔提到的那个），他希望我们能成为最早的签约人。他还告诉我们几个重要的保险项目，最后说：‘这个保险政策刚刚推出，我会让总部的人明天过来跟你们解释细节，但现在，我们先把申请表填好吧，这样总部的人到了以后就可以开始处理了。’他的热情激起了我们对这份保险的渴望，即便我们还不清楚其中的细节。总部的人过来后肯定了约翰最初的理解，他不仅仅卖给了我们一人一份保险，还帮我们把保险项目加了倍。

“卡尔本可以卖给我们这份保险的，但他并没有努力使我们产生兴趣。”

这世界充斥着只顾自己的人，所以那些少数的无私服务于他人的人就获得了无可比拟的优势。知名律师、美国最了不起的商业领袖之一欧文·D．扬曾说过：“那些能站在他人的角度考虑问题、懂得他人思维模式的人永远不用为未来而担忧。”

如果从这本书里你只收获了一个理念——多去思考他人的观点和立场——你便已经为自己的职业生涯奠定了一块基石。

观察他人的观点、激发他人的需求并不是为了让对方做使你受益、使他自己遭殃的事，而是让双方都受益。在致费米伦的信中，收信和寄信人都能在建议的行为中受益。安德逊夫人的信也能使她本人和银行都受益——银行将得到一名得力员工，而安德逊夫人将得到一份合适的工作。在约翰卖保险给卢卡斯的例子中，双方也都得到了利益。

罗德岛沃里克的迈克尔·E．维登是另一个激发他人需求从而使双方受益的例子。迈克尔是壳牌石油公司的区域销售员，他想成为该区域的销售冠军，但有一个加油站在拖后腿。这是一个年老的人经营的加油站，他没有维护的欲望，于是这个加油站变得破旧不堪，也严重影响了业绩。

经理不愿听取迈克尔让他重修加油站的请求，不论是严声逼迫还是晓之以理动之以情都不起作用。迈克尔决定邀请这位经理参观他的管辖区里新开的一家加油站。

这位经理看后颇为震撼，当迈克尔再一次走访这个加油站时却发现加油站已被收拾一新，业绩也有显著的提高。这使迈克尔最终成了地区销售冠军。那些谈话都没用，最有效的方式是展示给那位经理看现代化加油站的样子激发出他维护加油站的需求。迈克尔达成了目标，双方都能受益。

大多数人在大学中读了维吉尔，学了微积分，却从未探索过大脑的运作方式。例如，我曾给刚加入开利公司的应届毕业生做过一堂关于演讲技巧的讲座。开利公司是一家庞大的空调制造商。公司的一位学员想说服其他人在闲暇时一起打篮球，于是说：“我要你们出来打球。我喜欢打篮球，但是之前每次我去篮球场时人数都不够。有一天晚上我们只有两三个人打球，我的眼睛都被打肿了。我希望你们明天晚上都能来，我想打篮球。”

他提及了你的需求吗？没有。你不想去没人去的球场打球，不是吗？是的。你不在乎他想干什么，你不想被打肿眼。

他是否可以给你展示去球场的好处？当然。打球不仅能增加活力、增强食欲，而且使大脑更清晰、使人更愉悦。毕竟篮球比赛是有趣的事。

让我们牢牢记住奥沃思特利特教授的金玉良言：首先，要“使他人产生迫切的需求。能做到这点的人便拥有了整个世界，做不到的人便形单影只”。

训练班上的一个学员很担心自己的小儿子，他体重偏轻还不好好吃饭。他们连骂带哄地对儿子说：“妈妈想让你吃这个吃那个。”“爸爸想让你茁壮成长。”

那个男孩在乎这些诉求吗？他的在乎程度与你到海滩后对某粒沙子的在乎程度是一样的。

任何有常识的人都不会期待小孩能理解年长三十岁的父亲所持有的观点，然而那位父亲却是如此期待的。这很荒谬。后来他终于看到了这点，对自己说：“孩子想要什么呢？我如何才能为在我们二人的需求中架起桥梁呢？”

那位父亲开始思考后就发现这是个简单的问题。他儿子喜欢在布鲁克林家门口的街道上骑小三轮车，然而这一条街上还住着个小霸王——一个大一点的孩子，小霸王会把儿子推下车，然后自己把车骑走。

小男孩自然大哭着跑向妈妈，而妈妈就会出门从小霸王那儿把车要回来，再把儿子放上去。这样的事几乎每天都会发生。

小男孩想要什么？不用请来福尔摩斯也能回答这个问题。他的自尊、他的愤怒、他想感觉到自己很重要——这些最强烈的情绪驱使着他，使他想要报仇、彻底击败那个小霸王。后来爸爸告诉他，如果他听妈妈的话好好吃饭，那么用不了多久他就能把小霸王打得满地找牙了。听了这话后，小男孩吃饭再也不吵不闹了。菠菜、酸菜、咸鱼他都乖乖地吃，只要能让他长强壮，能战胜一直羞辱他的小霸王。

这一个问题解决后，这对父母又试图解决另一个问题了：儿子还有尿床的坏习惯。

他和奶奶一起睡。每天早晨奶奶醒来后总会感觉床单湿乎乎的，然后说：“小宝贝儿，你看你又尿床了！”

而他会说：“不，我没有！是你尿的！”

打骂、羞辱、重申爸妈希望他如何如何都没用，这些都没能挽救床单被尿湿的命运。所以父母开始思考：“我们如何能让小孩自己不想尿床？”

他的需求是什么？首先，他想要穿爸爸穿的那种睡衣裤，而不是奶奶穿的那种睡袍。奶奶受够了他的尿床行为，如果他能改邪归正，当然很愿意为他买套睡衣。其次，他想要自己睡。当然这一条遭到了奶奶的反对。

妈妈带儿子来到了布鲁克林的一家百货商店里，她对售货员眨了眨眼，说：“这位小绅士想要买点东西。”

售货员表现得对孩子很重视，问道：“小朋友，你想看点什么呀？”

他挺直身体踮起脚尖让自己高了好几英寸，说：“我想要买一张自己睡觉的床。”

母亲对售货员展示的一张床很满意，于是对她眨眼示意。小男孩最终也被说服了。

第二天床就送到了家。那天晚上父亲回家时，儿子跑向门口喊道：“爸爸！爸爸！快上楼看我买的小床！”

爸爸看了一眼小床，然后遵循了施瓦布先生的教诲，“真诚地赞赏并毫不吝惜赞赏之词”。

“你不会把这张床也尿湿了吧？”爸爸问。

“哦！不会不会！我不会再尿床了！”小男孩遵守了承诺，因为这涉及他的荣誉。那可是他自己的床，他自己挑选的床。现在，他还穿上了男士睡衣裤。他想要表现得像个男子汉，而他也的确做到了。

另一位参加讲座的父亲T．T．达赤曼是一名电话工程师，他的苦恼是无法让女儿吃早餐。常用的责骂、请求、哄骗都不起作用。所以这对父母也问自己：“我们怎样做她才会自己想要吃早饭？”

小女孩喜欢模仿妈妈，她觉得这样做就像个大人了，于是一个早晨，他们把她放在椅子上，让她自己做早餐。就在爸爸转身走进厨房的一刻，正在搅麦片的小女孩说：“哦，爸爸，你看，今天早晨我在做麦片粥呢。”

不用任何哄骗，她就吃了双份的麦片，因为她感兴趣。她得到了重要感。她从做麦片粥这件事中找到了一种自我表达的途径。

威廉·温特曾说过：“自我表达是人性中关键的需求。”为什么我们不能在商务往来中运用这种心理呢？当我们想到了一个好主意时，与其让别人认为这是我们的主意，倒不如在他人心中播下火种，让他们自己燃起这个想法呢。他们会把它当成自己的主意；他们会更喜欢这个主意，并为之加倍付出。

请记住这一首要建议：“使他人产生迫切的需求。能做到这点的人便拥有了整个世界，做不到的人便形单影只。”

使他人产生迫切的需求。

————————————————————

(1) 译者注：出自《圣经》马太福音25:40。

第十二章　“如果你想采蜜，不要踢翻蜂巢”

1931年5月7日，纽约市最轰动的一起追捕行动进入了白热化阶段。经过了几周的搜查后，杀人犯“双枪”克劳利终于走投无路，这个烟酒不沾的持枪歹徒被围困在他女友的西区公寓中。

一百五十名警察和侦探包围了顶层他的藏身处，他们在房檐上钻孔，试图用烟雾弹把这个警察杀手呛出来，他们还在周围的高楼上架设了机关枪。整整一个多小时内，这个纽约高档住宅区里回荡的都是手枪和机关枪发射子弹的声音。克劳利躲在堆得密密实实的椅子后面不停向警察开枪。一万多名兴奋的群众在观战，这样的场景从未在纽约市的街道上发生过。

克劳利被捕后，E．P．莫鲁尼警长宣布这个双枪亡命徒是纽约有史以来最危险的罪犯之一。警长说：“他可以为任何不起眼的事而杀人。”

但“双枪”克劳利是怎么看自己的呢？从他的信中我们可以窥探一二，就在警察向公寓开枪时，他写下了一封“致有关人士”的信。他用伤口涌出的血在信纸上留下一道殷红的印记，他在信中写道：“在我的外表下藏着一颗疲倦却善良的心，它不会伤害任何人。”

之前不久，克劳利和他的女友在长岛的一条乡间小路上激情拥吻。这时一名警察忽然走过来说：“出示你的驾照。”

克劳利二话不说，掏出枪对着警察疯狂扫射。在警察倒下时，他跳下车，用警察的枪又往那已经倒下的身体中射入了一枚子弹。这就是那个自己宣称“我的外表下藏着一颗疲倦却善良的心，不会伤害任何人”的人。

克劳利被判了电椅处死。当他走进纽约新新监狱的处刑室后，他说了一句话。他是否说“这就是我杀人的下场”？不，他说的是：“这就是自我防卫的下场。”

故事的重点在于，“双枪”克劳利不认为自己有任何问题。

在罪犯中，这种态度罕见吗？如果你这么认为，请听听这个：

“我用我最好的年华给人们带去最多的快乐，帮助他们获得更美好的时光，而我却只落得辱骂和被追捕的下场。”

这是艾尔·卡彭的原话。没错，就是那个美国最十恶不赦的公敌，芝加哥最邪恶的黑帮头目。卡彭没有谴责自己，他甚至把自己看作公共施恩者——一个不被感激、不被理解的公众恩人。

达奇·舒尔茨在被纽瓦克黑帮枪杀前也是这样想的。他是纽约最臭名昭著的混混之一。他也曾在接受报社采访时称自己为社会行善。并且，确信事实就是如此。

我曾与纽约新新监狱的狱监路易斯·劳斯进行过为期数年的有趣对话，谈论的内容正是围绕着此话题。他说：“新新监狱里很少有罪犯觉得自己是坏人。他们和你我一样都是人，所以都会为自己开脱、会把事情解释得合理化。他们理直气壮地讲出当时为何要抢保险柜，手指为何会那么敏捷地扣动扳机。他们中大多数人会用谬误或没有逻辑性的理由为自己的反社会行为进行辩解，自己也相信了这些理由。结果就是，他们坚定地相信自己压根不该被捕入狱。”

假如像卡彭、“双枪”克劳利、舒尔茨和监狱高墙背后的罪犯这样的人都不懂得从自己身上找问题，那么你我认识的人呢？

创立了以自己名字命名的百货公司的约翰·沃纳梅克曾经坦言：“三十年前我就懂得了责骂他人这一举动的愚蠢。克服自身的局限性并不去抱怨上帝没有公平分配智商就已经很不易了。”

沃纳梅克很早就领悟到了这个道理，而我则继续在这个老套的世界里跌跌撞撞三十余年才察觉到，在99％的情况下，人们都不会从自身找问题，不论自己做了怎样荒唐的事。

批评是毫无意义的，因为它会开启对方的自我防卫心理，往往使人竭力为自己辩护。批评也是很危险的，因为它会伤害一个人宝贵的尊严和自我价值，也会引起愤恨的情绪。

全球著名心理学家B．F．斯金纳曾通过实验证明，因做出正确行为而得到奖励的动物比因做出错误行为而受罚的动物能更有效地学习。之后的研究更显示，这理论也适用于人类。人们不会因批评而做出长久的改变，还往往会心生怨恨。

另一位伟大心理学家汉斯·塞利曾说过：“我们对指责的恐惧就如对肯定的渴望一样强烈。”

批评所引发的怨恨会使员工、家人和朋友意志消沉，到头来却依然没能解决问题。

俄克拉荷马伊尼德市的乔治·B．约翰斯顿是一家工程公司的安全协调人员，他的责任之一便是要确保员工进入工地时戴好安全帽。他说，每当他看到不戴安全帽的工人时，都会用权威而专业的口吻重申法规并命令他们严格遵从。虽然工人会在他面前闷闷不乐地答应，可等他一转身工人就又把帽子摘了下来。

他决定尝试新的方法。当他再看到不戴安全帽的员工时，他会首先询问帽子是否不舒服或者不合适，然后再用令人愉悦的口吻提醒他们帽子是为保护员工不受伤害而设计的，并建议他们工作时要一直戴着安全帽。结果遵守规定的人一下子增加了很多，怨气和愤怒也消失不见了。

历史上还存在着不少这类毫无意义的批评的例子，例如总统西奥多·罗斯福和塔夫脱之间的争论。这场争论分裂了共和党，把伍德罗·威尔逊送进了白宫，在第一次世界大战中留下一条清晰的线并改变了历史的轨迹。1908年，当西奥多·罗斯福离开白宫时，他是支持新当选的总统塔夫脱的。后来罗斯福去非洲猎狮子，返回后他的情绪爆发了。他指责塔夫脱过于保守，试图确保第三次任期的提名，还组建了雄鹿党，差点就摧毁了共和党。在随后的选举中，威廉·霍华德·塔夫脱和共和党只拿下了两个州——佛蒙特州和犹他州。这是共和党世上最惨烈的一次失利。

西奥多·罗斯福谴责塔夫脱，可塔夫脱会自责吗？坦白地说，我不知道。我想表达的是，罗斯福的批评并没有令塔夫脱认识到自己有问题，而只是让塔夫脱竭力为自己辩护，含泪重申：“我不认为有其他的方式来行事。”

或者也可以拿茶壶顶石油丑闻作为例子。这件事在20年代早期引起了轩然大波，各大报纸争相报道。它震惊了全国，在人们的记忆里，美国公众生活中还没有发生过这样的事。事情是这样的：哈丁的内政部长阿尔伯特·B．福尔被授权负责麋鹿山和茶壶顶的政府石油储备，这些石油是为海军日后的需求而储备的。福尔部长实行了竞争性投标吗？没有。他把这项利润极高的工程直接交给了朋友爱德华·L．多希尼。而多希尼是怎么做的呢？他给了福尔部长十万美金，声称是贷款。福尔部长专横地命令美国海军赶走在麋鹿山开采石油的其他竞争商家。在枪口和刺刀的威逼下，这些油商离开了油田，走进了法庭，揭露了茶壶顶丑闻。这个丑闻带来了巨大的不利影响，它摧毁了哈丁政权，引起了全国的反感，也威胁到共和党的存亡，并使阿尔伯特·B．福尔锒铛入狱。

福尔受到强烈的指责——很少有公众人物经历过这种程度的指责，他悔过了吗？从来没有！几年后赫伯特·胡佛在一次公共演讲中暗示哈丁总统的死是由于心理焦虑，因为一个朋友背叛了他。当福尔夫人听到此话时从椅子上跳了起来，她哭着说：“什么？哈丁被福尔背叛了？没有！我丈夫从未背叛任何人。就算满屋黄金也不能诱惑我的丈夫做坏事。他才是那个被人出卖、被杀戮、被迫害的人。”

这就是人性最真实的写照了。犯错的人总是怪罪于其他人，唯独不怪自己。我们皆是如此。所以当你我明天想要指责他人时，要记住艾尔·卡彭、“双枪”克劳利和阿尔伯特·福尔的例子。我们要认识到，指责就像家养的鸽子，总是会飞回家的。要知道，我们要去纠正和谴责的人很可能会为自己辩护，然后反过来指责我们。或者会像塔夫脱将军那样说：“我不认为有其他的方式行事。”

1865年4月15日的早晨，在一个廉价住所一楼走廊尽头的狭小卧室中，亚伯拉罕·林肯奄奄一息地躺在床上。旅馆对面就是约翰·威尔克斯·布斯枪杀林肯的福特剧院，林肯修长的身体在软塌塌的过于短小的床上呈对角线伸展开来。床头挂着罗莎·帮贺的名画《马市》的廉价复制品，还有阴沉的煤油灯闪动着昏黄的光。

林肯躺在那里即将辞世时，陆军部长斯坦顿说：“那里躺着的是人类在世间所见过的最完美的统治者。”

林肯和人打交道的成功秘诀是什么？我用十年时间研究了林肯的一生，用了三年时间撰写又不断重写一本书——《林肯传》（Lincoln the Unknown）。对林肯的性格和家庭生活的研究，我相信没有人比我做得更详尽了。我特别钻研了林肯与人交往的方式。他是否曾经乐于指责？哦，是的。年轻时还住在印第安纳州鸽溪山谷的林肯不但指责他人，还以写信、作诗的方式嘲讽别人，而且还会把这些信件撒放在必定会被人看到的乡间小路上。其中的一封信引起了一个人燃烧一生的愤恨。

即便林肯在伊利诺伊州的斯普林菲尔德市当执业律师时，依然会在报纸上公然发表信件来攻击对手。但或许他应该有所节制。

1842年的秋天，他嘲讽了一个自负、好斗的政治家，此人名叫詹姆斯·席尔斯。林肯在斯普林菲尔德日报上发表了一封匿名讽刺信，引起了全城人哄笑。敏感而骄傲的席尔斯极度愤怒，他找出了文章的作者，跳上马背追踪到林肯的面前并向他提出决斗的挑战。林肯不愿动武，他反对决斗，但无法保全荣誉地避开决斗。林肯可以自己选择武器，因为他的手臂很长，他选了骑兵大刀，然后开始和西点军校的毕业生学习搏斗。到了指定的日期，他和席尔斯在密西西比河畔的沙堤上见面了，准备战个你死我活，但在最后一分钟里，他们的副手前来阻止了这场决斗。

这是林肯一生中最可怕而重要的一件私事，它给林肯上了一堂人际交往的课。之后他再没写过侮辱性信件，也再没有嘲讽过任何人。从那时起，他几乎再也没有因任何事而指责过任何人。

在南北战争时期，林肯一次又一次地更换波多马克的军队首领——麦克莱伦、蒲伯、伯恩赛德、胡克、米德，但他们每个人都犯了悲剧性的错误，使得林肯不停地在绝望中踱步。半个美国都在凶狠地谴责这些无能的将军，但林肯“对任何人都没有恶意，对所有人都宽容、和善”，他保持着平和。他最爱的一句名言是“不评判，则不被评判。”

当林肯夫人和其他人都在严声指责南方人时，林肯说：“别指责他们。他们只是做了我们在那种情况下也会做的事罢了。”

然而最有权指责的人莫过于林肯了。我们只需看一个例子：

在1863年7月的前三天，葛底茨堡之役开始了。7月4日的晚上，乌云卷着雨笼罩着大地，当李将军带着惨败的军队来到波多马克河时，他发现面前淌着一条宽广、无法跨越的大河，而身后是完胜的北方军。李将军掉进了陷阱里，无处可逃。林肯看到了这个天赐良机，只要俘获李将军的军队就能立刻结束战争。所以林肯带着厚望命令米德不要召集军事会议，直接围剿李军。林肯先是用电报发出了指令，而后又派遣了一名特殊信差告知米德立刻行动。

米德将军做了什么呢？他做了截然相反的事。他彻底违背了林肯的指示，召集了军事会议。他犹豫、拖延，在电报里做了各种解释，拒绝直截了当地攻击李军。最后河水退了，李军越过了波多马克河，成功地逃脱了。

林肯怒不可遏，他对儿子罗伯特大喊：“这是怎么回事？上天啊！这是怎么回事？他们就在我们的掌控之中，只需伸出手指胜利就是我们的了，然而，我怎么说怎么做都没法让军队动起来。在那种情形下，任何一个将军都能打败李军，如果我在那儿都能亲手灭了他。”

在苦楚的绝望中，林肯坐了下来，给米德写了下面这封信。要知道，在这个人生阶段里林肯用词是极端保守和有节制的，所以林肯这封1863年写的信已经堪称最严厉的谴责了。

我亲爱的将军，

我认为你不了解李军逃脱的严重后果。他本就在我们的掌控之中，结合我们之前的胜利来看，剿灭了他也就等于结束了战争。现如今，战争又要无止境地延续下去。如果上周一你不能稳稳拿下李军，那现在只带着2/3的军力，你又怎可能成功向大河以南征战？现如今期待你改变局面已不太现实，而我也不会再如此期待。你失去了天赐良机，而我因此无比悲痛。

你猜米德读完这封信是怎么做的？

事实上，米德从未收到过这封信，因为林肯并没有把信寄出去。林肯去世后，人们在他的文件堆中找到了这封信。

我猜想——这仅仅是猜想而已——林肯写完信后望向窗外，对自己说：“等等，或许我不能如此草率。我坐在白宫里发号施令总是容易的，但如果我在葛底茨堡前线，亲眼看到米德上周看到的尸山血海，听到受伤者、垂死者发出的嚎叫，或许我也会不那么急于进攻了。如果我像米德那样个性腼腆，或许会做出同样的反应。不论如何事已至此，寄出这封信我会感觉好些，但会使米德急于为自己辩解。他会指责我，会产生怨气。这会影响他作为将领今后的表现，或许还会使他被迫辞职。”

所以就如我之前所说的那样，林肯把信放在了一边。他已经通过惨痛的经历学到了：尖锐的指责到最后几乎总是无谓的。

西奥多·罗斯福说，当他面临复杂问题时总会靠在椅背上看着白宫办公桌上方悬挂的林肯的大幅画像，然后问自己：“如果林肯面临同样的情况，他会怎么做？他会怎么解决这个问题？”

下次当我们想要批评别人时，让我们掏出五美金钞票看看林肯的头像，然后问自己：“林肯会如何解决这个问题？”

马克·吐温偶尔会发火，写些令人大惊失色的信。比如有一次他写信给一个令他愤怒的人：“你需要的是一张埋葬许可证。你只需开口，我保证你拿到手。”还有一次他给一位编辑写了封信，针对的是校对者关于订正他的拼写和标点符号所做的尝试。他命令道：“从此以后不要改动我的原稿，让校对者的建议保留在他那腐蚀成一坨糨糊的大脑里。”

写完这些尖锐的信让马克·吐温感觉舒服多了，这是一种发泄，而且也没有带来不好的影响，因为马克的妻子悄悄把这些信从信箱中拿了出来，从未寄出过。

你认识那些自己希望改变、管制和改善的人吗？很好，这没有问题。我完全赞同。但是为何不从自己开始？从完全自私的角度来说，这样做比改善别人获益更多，而且也更安全。中国古语说得好：“各人自扫门前雪，莫管他人瓦上霜。”

我在年轻时，也就是试图让每个人对我印象深刻的那个阶段里，曾经给理查德·哈丁·戴维斯写过一封愚蠢的信。他是当时美国文坛闪耀的一位作家，而那时我正在写一篇关于作家的杂志文章，希望戴维斯告诉我他的工作方式。几周前我从别人那儿收到一封信，底部写着“口述未核对”。这给我留下了极深的印象。我想对方肯定特别有威望，工作又忙碌。我一点也不忙，但为了让理查德·哈丁·戴维斯对我印象深刻，我在给他的那封短信下也写上了“口述未核对”。

他不做其他回复，只是把信退给了我，在底部草草写着：“你的无礼只能被你自己的无礼超越了。”没错，我是鲁莽了，或许罪有应得。但作为一个人，我很愤恨。我的这种情绪如此之强，以至于十年后当我听到了他的死讯时，第一个想到的就是他给我带来的伤害。——我羞愧地承认这点。

如果你我想引起持续几十年甚至一生的痛苦，那么就尽情地给予发泄性批判吧。

与人相处时要记得，人类不是逻辑动物。我们面对的是情绪动物，他们长着偏见的刺，被骄傲和虚荣所驱使。

哈代是英国文学史上最好的小说家之一，刻薄的批评使敏感的托马斯·哈代永远放弃了继续写小说。批评还使英国诗人托马斯·查特顿结束了自己的生命。

年轻时的本杰明·富兰克林不谙世事，后来变得非常有外交手段。他非常善于与人交往，后来成了美国驻法大使。他成功的秘密是什么？他说“我不说别人的坏话，并且只说我所知道的他们的优点。”

任何愚蠢的人都知道怎样批评、指责和抱怨别人，而大多数愚蠢人也是这样做的。

然而理解和宽容却需要人格和自制力。

卡莱尔说：“对待小人物的方式体现了伟人的伟大。”

鲍勃·胡佛是一个知名的试飞员，常常进行空中飞行表演。有一次，他完成了圣地亚哥的飞行表演正向着洛杉矶的家中返回，据《飞行操作》杂志的描述，在三百尺的空中，飞机的两个引擎忽然都失灵了，他靠熟练的操作才得以安全着陆。虽然无人受伤，但飞机受到了严重损坏。

胡佛紧急降落后做的第一件事便是检查机油。就如他所怀疑的那样，这架二战螺旋桨式飞机被灌了喷气机式燃油，而非汽油。

回到机场后他提出要见这架飞机的机械师。机械师是一个年轻人，他为自己的错误深感痛苦。当胡佛走近时，这个年轻人的眼泪马上涌了出来。他刚刚导致一架昂贵的飞机报废，还差点连累三个人丧命。

你能想象到胡佛有多生气，也能猜想到这位骄傲、严谨的飞行员将如何大骂机械师的疏忽。然而胡佛没有骂他，甚至没有批评他。相反，他用他结实的手臂搭着对方的肩膀说：“我相信你以后再也不会犯这样的错误。为了证明这点，我想让你明天维护我的F-51。”

家长总是爱批评孩子。你可能以为我会建议“不要这样”，但我想表达的不是这个。我只想说：“在批评他们之前，请阅读美国报纸杂志中的一篇经典——《爸爸忘了》。”这篇文章最初被刊登在《人类之家》杂志上，我们得到了作者的授权，在此刊登经《读者文摘》浓缩后的版本。

《爸爸忘了》是那种在瞬间的诚恳感受的启发下而写成的小文章，颇能触动读者的心弦，因极受欢迎所以被重刊多年。如作家W．利文斯顿·拉内德所述，这篇文章被“千百本杂志、企业商报和全国报纸刊印，也曾被翻译成多种文字出版。我个人就曾授权上千人在学校、教堂和讲台上宣读这篇文章。它也曾上过电台的各种场合和节目。出乎意料的是，大学期刊和高中杂志也都用过这篇文章。有时一篇小文章能神奇地触动人心。这篇就做到了。”

爸爸忘了

W．利文斯顿·拉内德

儿子，听我说：当我说这些话时，你正酣然入梦，一只小手蜷在脸颊下，金黄色的鬈发黏在湿乎乎的额头上。我一个人悄悄地走进了你的房间。几分钟前，我坐在书房看报纸，一阵令人窒息的懊恼向我袭来。我愧疚地来到了你的床前。

儿子，我在想这些事：我曾对你发脾气。在你梳洗准备上学时，我因你只用毛巾乱抹了下脸应付了事而责骂你；我因你没有擦鞋而批评你；当你把自己的东西丢在地上时，我生气地大喊大叫。

早餐时我也挑你的错。你会把食物撒出来；你狼吞虎咽；你把胳膊肘搭在桌上；你面包上抹的黄油太厚了。在你准备去玩而我准备赶火车时，你转身对我挥挥手，叫道：“爸爸再见！”我皱皱眉头回答：“挺起你的肩膀！”

下午这一切又会重演一次。我在路上看见你跪在泥上玩玻璃球，袜子上还磨出了洞。我命令你走到我面前，把你赶回家，让你在朋友前丢脸了。袜子很贵，如果你要自己掏钱买就会懂得珍惜了！儿子，想象一下，这是从一个父亲口中说出的话！

你还记得吗？之后我在书房看报，你怯生生地走进来，带着种伤痛的眼神。我把报纸放下看到了你，对于你的打扰很不耐烦。你在门口踌躇。“什么事？”我厉声说。

你什么都没说，但猛地跑过来，搂着我的脖子亲了我一下，那时你的小手臂环抱得更紧了，充满了爱。这爱是上帝在你心中盛开的花朵，即便被忽视也不会凋零。然后你走了，嗒嗒地跑上楼。

儿子，后来报纸从我手中滑落，我心中升起了令人不悦的恐惧。习惯把我变成了什么样子了？我养成了那种爱挑毛病、爱谴责的习惯，只因你是男孩我就如此对待你。不是因为我不爱你，只是因为我对孩子的要求太高了。我是用我自己的标准来要求你。

然而你的性格中还有那么多的善良、优秀和真实。你那颗小小的心脏比笼罩着宽阔山脉的黎明还要大。你跑进来亲吻我、道晚安的自发冲动就证明了这点。儿子，今晚其他事都不再重要。我在黑暗中走到你的床边，惭愧地跪在这里！

这些都无法弥补。我知道在你醒时跟你说这些你是不会明白的，但明天起我会做一个真正的父亲！我要和你成为朋友，为你的痛苦而痛苦，为你的喜悦而喜悦。当不耐烦的想法出现时，我会忍住不说出来。我会一直严肃地对自己说：“他只是个孩子而已，一个小孩子。”

我之前一直把你当作成年男子一样对待，而现在当我看着你时，儿子，你疲惫的身体蜷缩在小床上，我才意识到你还是个婴孩。昨天你还在妈妈的怀里，小脑袋搭在她的肩上。我要求的太多了，太多了。

让我们都试图去理解而不是谴责他人，让我们试着了解人们做事的原因。这会比谴责更有收获、更有趣；它还能培养同情、宽容与善良的心。“包容一切就是了解一切。”

就如约翰逊博士所述：“先生，上帝本身并没有要评判人类——直到末日来临的一刻。”那么你和我又为何要评判呢？记住：

请不要批评、谴责或抱怨。

第十三章　如此树敌屡试不爽

西奥多·罗斯福出任总统时曾坦言，如果他能做到在75％的情况下是正确的，那么他就达到了自己的最高要求。

如果这位二十世纪最杰出的人物之一能得到的最高分只有75，那么，你和我能得到多少分呢？

如果你觉得自己能维持55％的正确率，那么你就可以去华尔街一天挣一百万了。如果你不能保证55％的正确率，那么为什么还能告诉别人他们是错的呢？

你可以通过一个眼神、一个语调或一个动作就能有效地告诉对方他错了。如果你告诉对方他是错的，你认为会得到对方的认同吗？永远不会。因为你已经直接对他人的智力、判断力、骄傲和自尊射上了一箭。这只会引起对方的反击，却永不可能改变对方的想法。你可以用柏拉图或康德般的缜密逻辑来攻击对方，但别期待对方能改变主意，因为你伤了他的感情。

永远不要以这样的话语开始对话：“我要证明给你看……”这真的很糟糕。这就相当于在说：“我比你聪明。我会为你指点一二从而让你改变主意。”

这其实是在挑战对方，会引起敌意，使听者在你开始说话前就想先和你打一仗。即便是在最具善意的情况下，你也很难改变他人的主意。那么为什么要把事情变得更难，为什么要为自己设下障碍呢？

如果你想证明什么，先不要让别人知道，而要做得巧妙、机智、不被察觉。亚历山大·蒲柏就曾简单扼要地阐述过这个观点：

人只在不知被教诲时接受教诲；

不懂的事要当被遗忘的事来传授。

三百多年前，伽利略曾说过：

你无法教会别人任何东西，只能帮助别人发掘他们已知的东西。

查斯特菲尔德勋爵这样告诉他的儿子：

试着做比别人聪明的人，但是不要告诉别人。

苏格拉底在希腊不停向他的追随者重复：

我只知道一件事，那就是我的无知。

我不认为自己比苏格拉底还聪明，所以我不再对别人说他们的错误，并且我也发现那样做是徒劳无益的。

如果别人说了你认为不正确的话——即便你确认是错的，也最好以这种方式开始你的话：“嗯，我的想法不太一样，但我也有可能是错的，这种事常常发生，如果我错了请纠正我。让我们来分析一下这个问题吧。”

类似于“但我也有可能想错了，这种事常常发生，如果我错了请纠正我。让我们来分析一下这个问题。”这种的语句是有魔力的，而且是正面的魔力。

没有任何人会反对“我或许不对，让我们分析一下问题”的建议。

培训班里的一位同学在和客户打交道的过程中运用了这种方法，他叫哈罗德·莱恩克，是蒙大拿州比林斯市道奇汽车的经销商。他说，在汽车行业的巨大压力下，往往面对顾客的投诉，他的态度都是强硬、冷漠的。这导致他大动肝火、失去生意，带来了总体的不愉快情绪。

他在班里说：“我意识到这样做对我并没有好处，所以尝试了新的方式。我会以这样的话开头：‘我总是为我们车行所犯的错误感到惭愧。这次没有让您满意，请告诉我您的问题。’

“这样说能使对方解除戒备心理，而当顾客的不满情绪宣泄完毕后，他们往往能更理智地解决问题。实际上，好几位客户感谢了我尝试理解的态度，其中两个人甚至还带了他们的朋友来买车。在如此激烈的竞争环境中，我们需要的就是这样的客户，而我相信尊重所有客户的意见并礼貌对待他们会帮助我们在竞争中胜出。”

承认自己可能出错永远不会给你带来麻烦。这能停止一切争论并激励对手也同样做到公平、坦然、大度；这也会使对方愿意承认：他也有可能是错的。

如果你确信对方是错的并且直言相告，那又会发生什么呢？让我来举个例子。S先生是纽约市一名年轻的律师，曾经在美国最高法院为一个很重要的案子进行辩护，案件涉及很大一笔钱和一个重要的法律问题。在辩护过程中，最高法院的一名法官提问他：“法定时效是六年，不是吗？”

S先生呆望着法官数秒，然后直截了当地回答：“法官大人，海事法中并没有法定时效一说。”

“法庭里顿时响起一片嘘声。”S先生在我的一堂培训课中讲到此事，“法庭内似乎静止了。我是正确的，法官是错的。我不喜欢让他意识到这点，但这又能使法官变得友好吗？没有。我依然觉得我方占据了一切法律优势，我也表现得比每一次都好，但是我还是没能说服法官。我直白地指出了如此知识渊博、德高望重的人的错误，这真是太鲁莽了。”

逻辑性强的人是少数的，我们大多数人都充满偏见，带着先入为主的观念，而嫉妒、怀疑、恐惧和自负会使人逐渐枯萎。然而大多数人不愿改变自己的想法，不论是有关个人发型、宗教观念、共产主义还是他们最爱的电影明星的想法。所以如果你总是对别人说起他们的错误，请在每天早晨吃早饭前读一遍下面这段话，它选自詹姆斯·哈维·鲁滨逊所著的引人深思的《思维的形成》一书。

我们可以不夹杂任何阻力和激烈情绪地改变自己的主意，然而当我们被告知自己错了的时候，我们便会排斥别人的指正，变得心硬起来。我们从不推敲信念的形成，然而每当有人要挑战这些信念时，都会激起我们捍卫信念的荒唐热情。很明显，重要的不是那些想法本身，而是我们那受到威胁的自尊……“我的”二字是人类生活中最重要的两个小小的字，而正确应对这二字便成了智慧的起源。不论是“我的”晚餐、“我的”狗、“我的”房子、“我的”爸爸、“我的”国家或是“我的”上帝，都是同样的重要。我们不但拒绝承认我们的表不准、车很破，还对火星运河、爱比克泰德的发音、水杨苷的药用价值、萨尔贡一世的生卒日期有着不可侵犯的信念。我们希望继续保持一直认为是正确的想法，而任何对我们认知的怀疑都会激起憎恶，促使我们去寻找一切继续坚守那些信念的理由。因此，很多我们所谓的“讲道理”都不过是为巩固固有信念而寻找的理由罢了。

著名心理学家卡尔·罗杰斯在《个人形成论》一书中说过：

我发现如果我允许自己理解他人，那将是极具价值的一件事。或许我的观点让你觉得很诧异。我们需要允许自己理解他人吗？我觉得十分需要。我们对大多数（别人口中的）言论的第一反应是评价或评判，而不是理解。当他人表达了感受、态度或信仰后，我们总是习惯于做出这样的第一反应：“说得没错”“这很愚蠢”“这不正常”“这没有道理”“这不对”“这不好”。我们很少允许自己准确了解这话在别人脑中是什么意思。(1)

有一次，我雇了一名室内装饰师为我的家换几个帘子。但是，收到账单时，我心中很不悦。

几天后，一个朋友来串门，看到了新帘子。我跟她说了价钱，她用胜利的口吻大呼：“什么？那太糟糕了！他肯定在你这儿狠狠捞了一笔。”

她说得对吗？没错，她说的是实情，但很少有人愿意听反映了自身判断的实情。所以，被人性驱使，我试着为自己辩护。我说，当然物美价廉是最好的，但是质量、艺术品位和低廉的价格无法共存云云。

第二天，又有一个朋友到家里来看到了帘子，她非常欣赏并表现出极高的热情，还说她多希望自己有钱为自己家也添置如此精致的物件。我的反应截然不同。我说：“事实上，我自己也买不起。我买贵了，现在很后悔。”

当我们犯错的时候，我们会向自己承认。如果处理得温和得当，我们也愿意向他人承认自己的错误，而且从这种坦诚和大度中找到自豪感。但如果有人想硬塞给我们这不受欢迎的事实，我们则不再愿意承认自己的问题。

美国南北战争期间，最著名的报纸编辑霍勒斯·格里利曾强烈反对林肯的政策。他认为自己可以通过一系列的争论、嘲笑与谩骂迫使林肯接受他的意见。他日复一日，年复一年地进行着这些尖酸刻薄的活动，甚至还在林肯总统被布斯刺杀前的晚上给他写过一封粗暴、刻薄、嘲讽、颇具人身攻击意味的信。

然而格里利种种刻薄的做法是否让林肯接纳了他的意见呢？完全没有。嘲讽与谩骂永远无法做到这点。

如果你想得到如何与人相处、管理自己、提高自己的好建议，请阅读本杰明·富兰克林的自传——这是最引人入胜的传记故事之一，也是美国文学中的经典著作。在书中，本·富兰克林告诉我们，他是如何征服好辩的坏习惯并把自己转变为美国史上最有能力、最文雅、最有外交手段的人。

当本·富兰克林还是一个浮躁的年轻人时，一天，一位年迈的智者把他拉到一旁，用几个尖锐的事实给了他当头一棒：

本，你实在让人无法忍受，你的意见中总是带有对其他想法的攻击。它们太具冒犯性以至于人们已经不拿你的话当回事了。你的朋友们觉得你不在时他们玩得更尽兴。你觉得自己知道得很多，根本听不进别人的意见。实际上，没人想要告诉你任何事，因为那样做会令人不悦也太麻烦了。因此你的知识将无法超越现有的水平，而现在知道的也有限。

富兰克林明智之处便是他谦虚地接受了这智慧性的批判。他的胸怀足够宽广，头脑也足够聪明，所以他意识到了其中的道理，感觉到自己正在走向失败和社交灾难的不归路。于是他悬崖勒马，改变了自己那傲慢、武断的处事方式。

富兰克林说：“我给自己制定了一条规矩：克制住对他人想法的直接否定以及对自己观念的肯定。我甚至禁止自己运用那些表示固定思维的词语，例如‘当然’‘毫无疑问’等。与其让他人改变，不如先改变自己，于是我采纳了新的表述方式：‘我的看法是’‘我理解的是’‘我猜这件事是这样的’或者‘目前来讲我认为’。当对方表述了我认为不正确的观念时，我克制住激烈反驳对方、即刻证明其理论荒谬的快感。在回复时我会首先承认在某些情况下对方的观点是正确的，但在当前的情形中，我有不同的看法。我很快便发现了这一变化带来的好处，我所参与的对话能够在更愉悦的氛围中进行了。我展现出的更谦虚的态度使人们更容易接受、更少反对我的观点了。如果我被证明是错误的，我的羞辱感减少了；而如果我是对的，人们也更容易放弃他们错误的观点，采纳正确的意见。

“而这种我一开始需要违背自然倾向、强迫自己接纳的方式最终已变得如此简单和习以为常。这五十年来，或许再也没有人从我口中听到过武断的表述。我觉得一切都归功于这个习惯（在此之上是我正直的人格），才能让我在提议建立新制度、改变旧制度时深得民心，在成为公共理事会成员后产生了重大影响。但我从不是一名好的演讲者。我不会雄辩，在选词时犹豫不决，语法上也不见得正确，然而我通常可以表达出自己的观点。”

北卡罗来纳州国王山的凯瑟琳·A．奥瑞德是纺织厂的工业工程主管，她在一堂课中讲起了她在上课前后处理敏感问题的不同方法：

“我的职责之一便是为生产者建立和维护奖励制度及标准，从而激励他们制造更多的纱线。当我们只生产两三种纺线的时候，原本的系统还不错，但最近我们拓展了进货渠道，提高了生产能力，已经可以同时制造十二种纺线了，这时的奖励制度已经无法公平地反映员工的工作量并给予他们增强生产力的动力了。我设计出一套新的按纺织类别进行奖励的系统，我带着这套系统走进会议室，立志要向管理层证明我的方法是对的。我详尽地解释了他们的方法为何不好，为何不公平，而我有一切问题的答案。可是，最后我败得一塌糊涂。我太急于维护自己的立场，以至于没有给他人留下坦诚并优雅地承认问题的机会。这注定死路一条。

“参加了几堂培训课后，我清楚地认识到了自己的问题。于是，我再次召集了一次会议，而这次我向他们询问了他们的看法及问题出在哪里。我们探讨了每个方面，我也征求了他们的改革意见。我在适当的时机里提出了几个低调的建议，引领他们主动走入了我的思维模式。所以，当我在会议末尾提出了那个具体方案后，大家兴高采烈地接纳了。

“我现在彻底懂得了，如果你直截了当地告诉别人他的错误，你不仅无法得到任何建设性结果，还会造成很大的伤害。你只是成功地剥夺了对方的尊严，使自己变成任何对话中不受欢迎的一方。”

让我们再看一个例子，请记住，我引用的这些例子都是具有代表性的。R．V．克劳来是纽约一家木材公司的销售人员，他承认自己多年来一直不留情面地指出冷漠的木材检查员的错误，也在争论中屡居上风。然而这并没有带来任何正面的结果。“这些木材检查员就像棒球裁判一样。”克劳来说，“他们一旦做出判决便永不再改变。”

克劳来先生意识到，他赢得了争论中的胜利，但公司损失了数万美金。所以他在上我的培训班时发誓要改变自己处理问题的方式，放弃争论。结果又如何？下面是他在班里讲的他的故事：

“一天早晨我办公室里的电话响起了。电话另一端是个怒气冲冲、忧心忡忡的人，他告诉我，我们运给他工厂的木材全都不符合要求。他的工厂已经停止卸货，并要求我们立刻想办法把所有货物拉走。卸下四分之一的木材后，他们的木材检查员汇报说这批木材低于标准55％，在这种情况下，他们当然拒绝签收这批木材。“我立刻开车驶向他的工厂，路上想着处理此事的最佳办法。以往遇到这种事，我会复述木材评级的规定，并用我曾从事木材检查的全部知识和经验来试图说服对方的检查者，让他相信我们的木材实际是符合等级规定的，而他则搞错了检查规则。然而，这一次我想试着用培训班中学到的法则来解决问题。

“我到达工厂后发觉采购员和木材检查者的脸色都很阴郁，为争吵做好了准备。我们一起走到卸货车那里，我让他们继续卸货，好让我观察一切程序。我让检查者挑出不合格的木材，并把合格的放到另一堆。

“观察了一会儿之后，我发现他的检查过于严格了，他根本理解错了标准规格。我们卸的是白松木，我知道这位检查者是实木专家但对白松木不甚了解，而我对白松木却很熟悉。我对对方的检查方式提出了质疑吗？没有。我继续观察，并逐步询问他为何认为某些木材是不合格的。我丝毫没有暗示他是错的，我一再重申我询问只因想知道今后如何提供更合意的木材。

“我非常友好的提问和合作的态度以及对他们检查结果的肯定缓解了我们之间的关系，也使对方的态度逐渐缓和。我无意间的一句评论引起了他对自己判断的怀疑——或许这不合格的一堆中有些其实是合格的，而他们所要求达到的标准实际是属于更昂贵的一个等级的。不过我很小心地不让他觉得这想法是我灌输给他的。

“慢慢地，他整个态度都改变了。最后他承认他对检查白松木并不在行，并开始边卸货边询问我的意见。我给他解释合格的标准并一再确认我们不会让他们接受任何他们不满意的木材。最后他终于承认了自己每一次往不合格堆放木材时都充满了愧疚，其实是他们的错误，他们订的木材并不是自己需要的等级。

“最后的结果是：我走后他们又重新检查了一遍所有木材并全部接收了，而我们收到了全款。

“仅仅在那一件事中，这个小小的方法和避免直接指出对方错误的决心，就为公司挽回了损失的大笔金额。何况，这种做法所维护的信誉则是金钱所无法衡量的。”

马丁·路德·金曾被问到，身为和平主义者的他为何会敬仰战无不胜的空军上将丹尼尔·詹姆斯，即当时美国最显赫的黑人军官。马丁·路德·金回答道：“我以他人的准则而不是我自己的准则看待他人。”

无独有偶，有一次，罗伯特·E．李将军在和南军总统杰弗逊·戴维斯谈话时，他用最华丽的词语赞美了他手下的一位军官。旁边一位军官惊呆了，“将军，”他说道，“你难道不知道那个被你如此夸赞的人就是不放过任何机会诽谤你的大仇人吗？”“我知道。”李将军说，“但是总统问的是我对他的看法，而不是他对我的看法。”

对了，我在此章中讲到的东西都不是什么新鲜内容。两千年前，耶稣就说过：“立刻赞同你的敌人。”

在耶稣诞生前的两千两百年，埃及的阿托伊法老就曾对他儿子提出这样一句明智的建议，今天的我们依然迫切需要着这句话。法老教诲到：“要懂得外交手段，这样才能保住你的立场。”

换言之，别与你的客户、配偶或敌人争执；别指出他们的错误；别激怒他们；要多运用外交手段。

尊重他人的观点。永远别说：“你错了。”

————————————————————

(1) 改编自卡尔·罗杰斯的《个人形成论》（波士顿：米夫林出版公司，1961），pp．18ff。

第十四章　一滴蜂蜜

你的脾气被引爆，你要给对方好好上一堂课，你会享受这种发泄的快感。然而对方呢？他也会享受这份快感吗？你那好战的口吻、敌视的态度会让对方更容易同意你的观点吗？

伍德罗·威尔逊曾说过：“如果你双拳紧握地走过来，我可以保证，我也会在第一时间握紧双拳。但如果你走过来说：‘让我们坐下来商量问题。如果我们的意见不一样，让我们找出不同的原因和问题之所在。’那么我们立刻就会发现，我们的观点并非大相径庭，相左的观点少，相同的观点多。如果我们有合作的耐心、诚意和愿望，那么我们就能达成合作。”

没有人比洛克菲勒更推崇这句话了。1915年，洛克菲勒是科罗拉多最受鄙夷的人。美国工业历史上最血腥的一次示威就发生在科罗拉多，并震惊了全州长达两年时间。愤怒、好斗的矿工要求从科罗拉多燃料与铁矿公司那里得到更高的薪水，而洛克菲勒正是这家公司的控股人。大量财产遭到破坏，军队也被动用来镇压示威，很多示威者被枪击，身体被子弹打得千疮百孔，现场血流成河，惨不忍睹。

在那样的时刻里，空气中弥漫着的都是仇恨。洛克菲勒希望能说服示威者，而他做到了。他是如何做到的呢？请听下面的故事。洛克菲勒在表示了几周的友好后向示威群众代表做了一场演说，整个演说可谓是精彩绝伦，更是带来了惊人的效果。它平息了几乎要吞噬洛克菲勒的仇恨浪潮，还为他带来了不少仰慕者。这场演说用友好的方式陈述了事实，让示威者返回了岗位并只字不提不提之前暴力争取的提薪一事。

下面是那场演说的开头部分，请注意它表现出的友好态度。别忘了，洛克菲勒面对的听众是几天前希望把他吊死在酸苹果树上的人，然而洛克菲勒的语气比面对一群医学传教士还要友好和优雅。他的演说里通篇都是类似这样的句子和词组：“来到这里是我的荣幸”“我拜访过你们的家，见过你们中很多人的妻子和儿女，所以我们今天是以朋友而不是陌生人的方式见面……”“相互友好的氛围”“我们的共同利益”“承蒙你们的邀请我才能站在这里”。

洛克菲勒是这样开始这段演说的：“今天是我生命中值得纪念的日子，我第一次有幸同时见到我们伟大公司的员工代表、高级职员和主管。我可以向你们保证，来到这里是我的荣幸，在我有生之年里都不会忘记今天。如果今天的会面是两周前举行的，那么对于台下大多数人来说我还是个陌生人，我也只能认出台下的几张面孔。然而上周我有幸参观了南部煤炭厂的所有宿舍，和当天在场的每个员工代表一对一地交谈。我拜访过你们的家，见过你们中很多人的妻子和儿女后，所以我们今天是以朋友而不是陌生人的方式见面，也是在这种相互友好的氛围中，我很高兴有机会来和你们探讨我们的共同利益。

“这是公司高级职员和主管的会议，我没有这个荣幸加入其中的任何一方，所以承蒙你们的邀请我才能站在这里。然而我又觉得和你们紧密相连，因为我代表着股东和董事会。”

这难道不是化敌为友的演讲艺术的最佳范例吗？

假设洛克菲勒用了另一种方法，假设他和矿工争执，抛出了毁灭性的真相，假设他用语气和语调影射了对方的谬误，假设他运用了全部逻辑规则证明了对方就是错的，那么接下来会发生什么呢？他会激起更多的愤怒、憎恨和反抗。

如果他人对你充满了不满和厌恶，那么，你即便是用尽逻辑推理的方式也无法令对方采纳你的观点。爱责骂的家长、爱控制的老板和丈夫、爱抱怨的妻子都应该意识到这一点，人们不愿改变自己的想法，你无法强迫或驱使他人同意我们的意见。然而如果我们足够温和与友好，他们便可能同样温和与友好地被引导着采纳我们的意见。

林肯在一百多年前说过类似的话：

“一滴蜂蜜比一加仑胆汁能吸引更多的苍蝇。”这句话古老而确切。所以如果你想让一个人拥护你的立场，请首先说服对方相信你是他真正的朋友。那便是一滴俘虏人心的蜂蜜，也是影响对方逻辑的捷径——不论你怎么认为。

商界管理者已经懂得，友好地对待抗议者会受益无穷。比如，怀特汽车公司工厂里的两千五百名员工因要求加薪并建立工会车间而进行大罢工，但当时的公司总裁罗伯特·F．布莱克没有发火，没有指责，没有像暴君一样放出威胁之词，他反而表扬了罢工者。他在克利夫兰的报纸中发表了一篇公告，表扬了他们的“和平罢工方式”。为了丰富罢工者的闲暇生活他还买了一堆棒球球棒和手套，邀请他们在空地上打球。有的人更喜欢打保龄球，他便为那些人租了保龄球场。

布莱克先生的友好举动奏效了，那是友好常能带来的作用，它赢得了更多的友好。于是罢工者借来了扫帚、铲子、垃圾推车，开始捡工厂周围的火柴、纸屑和烟头。想象一下！想象罢工者在争取更高工资和工会车间的同时打扫着工厂周围的卫生，这样的事在美国悠长而混乱的工人奋斗史中闻所未闻。那次罢工在一周内就协商解决了，没有造成反感或仇恨。

外表如上帝、讲话如耶和华的丹尼尔·韦伯斯特是最成功的出庭律师之一。他总是用最友好的语言引出他的论证，例如：“希望陪审团考虑”“这一点或许值得思考”“我相信你一定不会忽视如下事实”“带着对人性的认识，你能轻而易举地看到这些事实的重要性”。没有威吓，没有高压手段，没有强加于人的观点，韦伯斯特以他那温和、平静而友好的方式而名扬四海。

你或许不需要平息一场罢工或是在陪审团面前发言，但你有可能需要压低房屋租金。这种友好的方式能帮上忙吗？让我们看看下面的例子。

工程师O．L．斯特劳布想要得到房租折扣，而他知道房东是冷漠无情的，他该怎么办？斯特劳布先生在培训课的演讲中说道：“我写信通知他，我的租房合同到期后就不再续租了，而事实上我并不想搬家。如果房租能降低一些，我很愿意续租。这是看似渺茫的事，其他房客也试过，但都以失败告终。每个人都对我说，房东很难打交道。然而我对自己说：‘我正在上如何跟人打交道的培训班，所以我要在他身上做实验，看看是否有成效。’

“他和他的秘书收到我的信后过来见了我。我在门口和他们友好地打招呼，表现得充满善意和热情。我没有上来就抱怨房租上调的事，我只是夸他们的公寓多么舒适。相信我，我是“真诚地赞美并不吝惜赞美之词”的。我还赞美了他经营公寓的方式。我说我很想继续租下去，但是我付不起房租了。

“房东从来没有从房客那儿得到过如此高的肯定，他受宠若惊。“后来他开始跟我讲述他遇到的麻烦，抱怨其他房客。有一个房客给他写了十四封信，其中有些信还颇具侮辱性。还有一个房客威胁房东说如果不能保证他楼上的人不再打呼噜，他就要违约提前搬走。他说：‘遇到像你这样称心如意的房客是多么让人欣慰啊。’接着，不用我请求，他就主动提出要给我稍微降低房租。我希望他能降低更多，便表明了我可以接受的价格，而他欣然接受了。

“他离开时转身问我：‘我能为你做些什么装修方面的事吗？’

“如果我按其他房客的方式索要折扣，我相信我也会以失败告终。最后赢得胜利的只会是友好的、富有同情心和感恩之情的方式。”

宾夕法尼亚州匹兹堡的迪恩·伍德考克是当地电力公司某部门的主管。他负责安排他的员工维修电线杆顶部的某个设备。这个工作原先是其他部门负责的，前不久才转交给伍德考克的部门。虽然他的员工都接受过这项技能的培训，但这是第一次被要求实际操作。部门中的每个人都很好奇自己是否能完成以及该如何去完成这项工作。伍德考克、他手下的几位经理以及其他公共设施部门的成员都前来参观他们工作，很多汽车、卡车停放在那里，很多人站在电线杆下围观顶部的那两位孤独的工人工作。

伍德考克环视四周，发现有个人下车后掏出了相机，开始为这个场景拍照。公共设施公司的人极度重视公共关系，伍德考克忽然意识到这场景对于拍照者来说就像是一群人被指派做两人就能完成的任务，于是他朝那位拍照者走了过去。

“我看到你对我们的工作好像很感兴趣。”

“是的，我妈妈会更感兴趣。她买了你们公司的股票，这个场景会让她大跌眼镜的，她可能会发现她的投资不那么明智。我一直在告诉她，你们这样的公司有好多低效环节，这照片就是好的证明。或许报纸也会对这照片感兴趣的。”

“看起来似乎真的是这样，不是吗？如果站在你的位置，我也会这样想，但在这次这个特殊情况里……”迪恩·伍德考克解释，这是他带领的部门第一次执行这类任务，而公司上上下下的人都非常感兴趣。他向那个人解释说，一般情况下这就是两个人的工作。拍照者放下了相机，和伍德考克先生握手并感谢他花时间向他解释情况。

迪恩·伍德考克的友好方式避免了公司一场令人难为情的公关危机。

培训班里的另一名学生杰拉尔德·H．韦恩，他来自新罕布什尔的立托顿，也用友好的方式在一项损失索赔协议中达成了满意的和解。

“早春的时候地上的冰还未融化，又下了一场大雨。雨水通常会流到沟渠里，然而这次却找到了新的路径，直接淹没了一块建筑用地，而我刚在那里盖好房子。

“雨水没有流走而是积聚在了房子地基周围，并渗透了地下室的水泥层，导致水泥层破裂，淹没了地下室。这使得供热和供水设备全被摧毁，损失超过了两千美金，而我没有任何这类损失的保险。

“但是，不久我就得知这块地的主人没有在房子周围做好排水设施，也就是说这个问题本是可以避免的，于是我约好和他会面。在开车到他办公室的二十五分钟的路程中，我仔细地回想了这件事的始末，并牢牢记住培训班里讲过的法则，我觉得表现愤怒是无法达成任何有意义的结果的。我抵达后竭力保持着平静，一开始先和他聊了他最近的西印度群岛之旅。后来，当我觉得时机合适时，我提起了水灾的‘小损失’。他很快便同意尽到所有他该尽的责任，协同我解决这个问题。

“几天后他打来电话，说他会赔偿我的损失并且做好排水设施以避免类似的事再次发生。

“虽然这是对方的责任，但倘若我没有以友好的态度着手处理此事，那么要让对方负全责还是困难重重的。”

多年前，我还是一个小男孩，当我赤脚走在通往密苏里西北部一所学校的小树林中时，我读到了一则关于太阳和风的伊索寓言。太阳和风儿争执着谁更强大。风儿说：“我会证明我更强大。看到那边穿棉衣的老人了吗？我肯定能比你更快地剥去他的外套。”

于是太阳躲到云层中，风儿开始吹啊吹，几乎吹成了龙卷风，然而它吹得越凶猛，老人把外套抓得越紧。

最后风儿平息下来，放弃了。这时太阳从乌云背后出来了，和蔼地对着老人微笑。然后，老人擦去挂在眉毛上的汗珠，脱下了外套。太阳对风儿说，温和与友好永远比狂暴和蛮力要强大。

一滴蜂蜜比一加仑胆汁能吸引更多苍蝇，懂得这个道理的人日复一日地发挥着温和与友好的积极作用。马里兰州卢瑟威尔市的F．盖尔·康纳的事例就证明了这一点，这是他第三次把那辆刚买了四个月的车送进修理厂。他在班里说：“很明显，与服务部经理的谈话、理论或叫嚷都无法给我的问题带来一个满意的结局。

“我走进车行，要求见他们的老板怀特先生。等了一会儿后，我被带入了怀特的办公室。我介绍了自己，并告诉他我是在朋友的推荐下在车行买了车，因为朋友告诉我这里的价格非常有竞争力，服务也是一流的。他听我说这些时满意地笑了，然后我解释了在服务部门遇到的问题。我补充道：‘我觉得最好让您知道有可能破坏贵车行声誉的情况。’他感谢我让他注意到了这件事，并且向我保证我的问题一定会解决。他不但亲自参与了这次维修，还在维修期间把他的车暂时借给了我。”

伊索是克洛伊索斯宫殿里的奴隶，他在耶稣之前六百年开始讲述不朽的寓言故事。而他在两千六百年前的雅典所表述的真理在今天的波士顿和伯明翰照样适用。太阳比风儿更快地使你脱下外套；和善、友好和感恩的方式也比世上全部的咆哮和暴躁能更好地改变他人的观念。

记住林肯说过的话：“一滴蜂蜜比一加仑胆汁能吸引更多的苍蝇。”

从友好开始。

第十五章　苏格拉底的秘密

和别人对话时，不要一开始就讨论存在异议的事。要先从双方意见一致的事开始讨论，别忘了不停地强调你们的共同点。如果可以的话，要一直强调你们的最终目标是一样的，唯一的不同只是达成目标的方式。

让对方从一开始就对你说“没错”而不是“不对”。

哈里·奥沃思特利特教授说：“一个否定的回应是最难逾越的障碍。当你说了‘不’以后，你的自尊心会要求你始终保持一致。或许后来你会发现不该说‘不’，但是你会顾虑到宝贵的自尊心！说了一句话以后，你就会想要贯彻到底。因此，在肯定中开始是至关重要的。”(1)

游刃有余的交谈者从一开始就会得到好几个“是”的回应，这便把听者带入了一系列肯定式的心理过程中。这就像台球一样，当你把球推向一个方向时，若想使球旋转则要多发些力，若想使球往反方向反弹则需要大很多的力气。

这里的心理规律很显著。当对方认真地说“不”时，他说的远远不止这一个字。这时，他的腺体、神经和肌肉都进入了反对的状态。通常会有微小的，但有时也很明显的身体上的退缩或准备退缩的状态。简而言之，整个肌肉神经系统都进入了自我保护机制，拒绝接受任何事情。然而当人们说“是”时，这些退缩活动都不会出现，整个机制是积极向前的、接纳和开放的状态。因此，如果我们一开始得到的肯定回应越多，就越有可能成功推广我们的提议。

让人们给予肯定的回应其实只是一个很简单的技巧，然而人们却往往忽视了它！人们仿佛总是一开始就用与他人对抗的方式为自己寻找重要感。

如果学生、顾客、孩子、丈夫或妻子从一开始就说了“不”，那么我们便需要天使的智慧与耐心才能把这布满荆棘的反对意见转化成肯定。

纽约市格林威治储蓄银行的出纳詹姆斯·艾伯森正是运用了“让他人说是”这个方法挽回了差点流失的一位客户。

艾伯森先生说：“一个人来开户，我递给他一份常规的申请表。他欣然回答了几个问题，对表格上的其他问题却拒绝回答。

“在学习这堂人际关系课之前，我会这样告诉他，如果他拒绝向银行提供信息，我们一定会拒绝他的申请。我对自己以往的行为感到愧疚，能够给人下最终审判自然是有快感的事。我强调了我们的制度，而且银行也不能乱了规矩。但是那样的态度肯定不会让来存钱的客户觉得受欢迎、受重视。

“今天早晨我决定运用常识，一开始先不说银行的需要，而是要询问客户的需求。最重要的是，我希望从一开始就把他带入说‘是’的状态。所以我同意了他的做法，告诉他他拒绝提供的信息并不是必需的。”

“我又对他说：‘但是假设您去世时账户里还有钱，难道您不希望银行能依法帮您把它转到您所授权的最亲近的人那里吗？’

“‘当然希望啦。’他回答。

“我又继续问道：‘那么，难道您不愿意提供这个人的姓名，好让我们在意外情况发生时能顺利把钱转给此人吗？’

“他再次回答了：‘当然愿意呀。’

“这位年轻人的态度逐渐平和下来了，当他意识到银行要求填写的信息并非是出于银行的利益时，他的观点发生了变化。这位年轻人离开银行时，不但给了我他的全部信息，还在我的建议下开了一个信托账号，指定他的母亲为受益人，也填写了有关他母亲的一切资料。

“我发现如果一开始就引领他进入肯定的思维模式中，这样他便会忘了之前为何要坚持以及在坚持什么，并愉快地做了一切我建议他做的事。”

西屋电气公司的一名销售代表约瑟夫·埃里森给我们讲了这样一个故事：“公司很希望当地的一个商人能成为他们的顾客，但我的前辈们已经向他电话推销了十年，也未能卖出去任何东西。我接管这个领域后也定期打电话向他推销，在长达三年的时间里，也毫无结果。在这十三年的电话交谈和商品推销后，我们终于成功地卖了几个发动机给他。如果这些发动机能够正常运行的话，他将会订购几百台发动机，这是我的理解。

“我知道这几个发动机不会有问题，所以当我三周后向他致电时，我是兴高采烈的。

“总工程师平静地向我们宣布了一个令人震惊的消息：‘埃里森，我们不能买更多的发动机。’

“‘为什么？’我震惊地问，‘究竟为什么？’

“‘因为你们的发动机散热不好，我都无法把手放在发动机上。’

“我知道争执无济于事，我之前曾经有过太多惨痛的教训，所以我想起了‘让对方说是’的方式。

“‘史密斯先生，你看，’我说，‘我完全同意。如果那些发动机过热你的确不该买。你肯定见过比国家电器制造商协会标准热度要低的发动机，对不对？’

“他说是的。这是我得到的第一个‘是’。

“‘国家电器制造商协会要求设计合理的发动机热度只可比室内温度高72华氏度。是不是？’

“‘没错。’他回答，‘非常正确。但是你们的发动机超过了那个温度。’

“我没有和他争执，只是问他：‘工厂里面的温度是多少？’

“‘哦，’他说，‘大概75华氏度。’

“我回应道：‘那么如果室内75华氏度，再加72度，那就是147度。如果你把手放在147度的流水下会烫伤的吧？’

“他再次给出肯定的答复。

“于是我说：‘这样的话是不是本来也不该用手去碰发动机呢？’

“‘嗯，我猜你是对的。’他承认道。我们又聊了一会儿，后来他就让秘书订了价值三万五千美金的发动机，这相当于接下来一整个月的营业额。

“浪费了多年时间，损失了上万美金后，我才懂得了争执无用的道理。用他人的立场思考问题并能让对方说‘是的’‘是的’才是最有利也是最有趣的方式。”

赞助了我们加州奥克兰培训班的艾迪·斯诺给我们讲述了他是如何因为店主懂得让他说“是”而成了店里的一名忠诚顾客的。艾迪喜欢用弓箭打猎，并花了很多钱在当地一间店铺里购置设备。当他的哥哥来看他时，他想从这家店里租一把弓，但销售人员说他们不外租，所以艾迪给另一家店打电话讲述了事情的经过：

“一位非常和蔼可亲的人接了电话，他给我的回答和另一家店完全不同。他说他很抱歉，他们停止了租弓箭的业务，因为他们负担不起了。之后他问我以前是否租过，我说：‘是的，几年前租过。’他猜测我那时应该付了25—30美金租金，我再次说‘没错’。后来他问我，我是否是喜欢省钱的人，我自然给予了肯定的回答。对方继续说道他们有一套弓箭正在促销，包含了所有必需的设备，一共34.95美金，仅需比租器材多花4.95美金就能买下这一套器材。他最后解释道，这就是他们停止出租器材的原因。我认为他的话合理吗？我的肯定回答使我买下了那一套器材。我去取货时还顺便在那家店里买了其他几样东西，后来慢慢地成了他们的常客。”

自喻为“希腊的牛虻”的苏格拉底是世上最伟大的哲学家之一。他做了有史以来只有少数人做到的事：他大大地改变了别人的思维方式。在他辞世两千四百年后的今天，他被奉为影响辩证体系的最具智慧的辩者。

他到底用了怎样的方式呢？他告诉别人“你是错的”了吗？哦，不，苏格拉底不会做如此不精明的事。他的辩证方法被称作“苏格拉底法”，而这方法就是基于让对方说“是”。他向对方提出一系列使对方不得不说“是”的问题。他在一个又一个的问题上得到肯定的答复，最后得到一箩筐的“是”。他会继续提问下去，直到最后对手在不经意间发现自己居然拥护着几分钟前还尖锐反驳的结论。

今后当我们想告诉对方“你是错的”时，让我们记住苏格拉底的做法，提一些温和的问题，能得到对方肯定答复的问题。

中国有句谚语，蕴含着东方的古老智慧：“轻履者行远。”

中国人用了五千年的时间揣摩人性、学习智者的思想，终于获得了敏锐的洞察力：“轻履者行远。”

立刻获取对方的赞同。

————————————————————

(1) 哈里·A．奥沃思特利特，《人类行为》（纽约：诺顿出版社，1925）。

第十六章　如何与他人合作

你是否更相信自己发现的而不是别人灌输给你的思想呢？如果是这样，那么你把自己的观念强加于人岂不是很不理智？难道不该以提建议的方式引导对方想出你所赞同的结论吗？这样才更明智吧！

费城的阿道夫·塞尔兹是车行的销售经理，也是我的培训课里的学生。他发现自己面对的是一群垂头丧气、无组织无纪律的销售人员，迫切需要给他们注入一些热情。于是，他召集了一次销售会议，让员工说出他们对他的期待。员工一边说，他一边抄写在黑板上。然后他说：“我会达到你们所有的期待。现在请你们告诉我，我有权对你们做出什么样的期待。”员工们毫不犹豫地回答：忠实、诚实、积极主动、乐观、富有团队精神，而且每天八小时对工作的热情投入。会议在更高的士气和启示中结束了，会后有个员工竟自动要求一天工作十四个小时。塞尔兹告诉我，销售额一下子显著增长了很多倍。

塞尔兹说：“员工们和我做了一个交换。只要我尽职尽责，他们就下定决心对他们的任务负责。询问他们的需求和渴望正是他们所需的强心剂。”

没有人喜欢被推销或被指使。我们更愿认为自己是出于自愿而买某物、做某事的。我们喜欢被问到自己的需求和想法。

让我们再来看一看尤金·韦森的例子，他在领悟了这个真理之前曾白白损失了数千美金的佣金。韦森先生向设计和纺织品业工作室提供草图，连续三年的时间里，他每周都向纽约某知名设计师致电询问结果。韦森先生说：“他从未拒绝见我，但是也从未买过我们的图。他总是很认真地翻看我的样图，然后说：‘不行，韦森先生，看来今天我们没什么可以交易。’”

失败了一百五十次后，韦森觉得自己一定是禁锢了思维，于是决心每周用一个晚上的时间学习影响人类行为的方法，从而得到灵感并产生更多的热情。

他决定尝试一种新方式。他带着手中好几幅未完成的草图去到了买方的办公室。“如果可能的话我希望你能帮我个忙。”他说，“这里是几张没画完的图。你能否告诉我，换作是你，你要如何完成这些图才能使他们派上用场？”

买方默默地看着那些图，终于说了：“把它们在我这儿放几天吧，韦森。过几天来见我。”

三天后，韦森回去见他，听取了他的建议，然后他把图纸拿回了工作室，按买方的意愿完成了那些图。结果呢？设计草图全部被采用。

从那之后，买方又从韦森那里购买了很多图纸，这些图纸全都是按照买方的意见画的。韦森先生说：“我知道了为何之前几年都会失败。我一直渴望他买我希望他得到的东西，后来我彻底改变了方式，我让他买他想买的东西。这使对方觉得图纸是自己的设计，而这也的确是事实。我不需要向他推销什么，他自然就买了。”

让对方认为主意是自己出的，这种方式不仅在商界、政界行得通，在家中也同样奏效。俄克拉荷马州塔尔萨市的鲍尔·M．戴维斯就在培训班中讲过他是如何运用这个法则的：

“我和家人开始了一次非常有趣的观光旅行，我们玩得非常尽兴。我一直渴望参观葛底茨堡的战争遗址、费城的独立大厅还有我们的首都。福吉谷、詹姆斯敦和重建的威廉斯堡殖民村都是我观光清单上排名最高的几个景点。

“3月时，我的妻子南希提到，她计划我们夏天的旅行要去西部的几个州，参观新墨西哥、亚利桑那、加利福尼亚和内华达的景点。她已经期待去这些地方旅行很多年了。但是很明显，我们无法同时实现我们的梦想。

“我们的女儿安妮刚在中学里修过一堂美国历史课，她对改变我们国家的重要事件非常感兴趣。我问她如果在下次旅行中能去在课本上读到的那些地方，她是否愿意。她说她非常愿意。

“两天后的一个晚上，我们围坐在晚饭桌边。南希宣布如果我们同意的话，我们这次将去东部几个州旅行，这对安妮会很有意义，对一家人来说也是令人激动的旅行。我们都同意了。”

一个X光仪器工厂也运用了同样的策略，把仪器销售到布鲁克林最大的医院里。这家医院正在盖附楼，而这里将成为美国最先进的X光中心。L医生是X光部门的主管，被各种推销自家品牌的销售代表吵得喘不过气来。

其中一家公司最高明。他们更懂得人性，于是写了这样的一封信：

我们厂最近研制出了一系列全新的X光设备，我们刚收到第一批货，它们堪称完美。我们知道这是事实，并希望还能精益求精。所以如果您能抽出时间看看这些仪器并提出如何能使它们更好地为您效劳，我们将不胜感激。我们知道您的时间宝贵，所以很愿意派车在您方便的时间去接您。

培训班中的L医生讲起这段故事时说：“收到那封信我很惊讶，简直受宠若惊。在这之前还没有任何一个X光厂家向我征求意见，这使我感觉到自己的重要性。那一周我每天晚上都很忙，但是我取消了一个晚饭应酬去看了他们的机器，我越看越喜欢那些机器。

“没人试图卖给我什么，我离开时觉得这个购买决定完全是自发的。我是自己把那些高品质的产品推销给自己的。后来我订购并安装了他们的机器。”

拉尔夫·沃尔多·爱默生在《自助》一文中曾写道：“在每个天才之作中，我们都能发现被自己遗弃的想法，它们带着生疏的威严回到我们的世界里。”

伍德罗·威尔逊在任总统期间，爱德华·M．豪斯上校对国家乃至世界来说，地位举足轻重。威尔逊常与豪斯上校密谈，询问他的意见。他对豪斯上校的依赖比谁都多，甚至超过了对内阁的依赖。

豪斯上校运用了何种方式来影响总统呢？我们有幸得知了答案，因为豪斯上校曾亲自对阿瑟·D．豪登·史密斯讲述过这个答案。史密斯在《周六晚报》中引用了豪斯的话：

“豪斯说，‘我认识了总统以后，明白了最能说服他的办法便是在不经意间把想法灌入他的脑海里，他便会产生兴趣，并且自行思考这个问题。这种方法第一次奏效时纯属偶然。我一直到白宫拜访他，希望他能批准一项他并不支持的政策。几天后，在一次晚餐的饭桌上，我意外地听到他提出了这项政策，仿佛是他自己的主意一般。’”

豪斯是否打断了总统并说“这不是你的主意，是我的”？当然没有，豪斯不会做如此愚笨的事。他不在乎如何抢功，他只想看到结果，所以他就让威尔逊认为那是他自己的主意了。不仅如此，豪斯还让威尔逊因这些想法而得到了公信度。

让我们记住，我们接触的每个人都有和伍德罗·威尔逊一样的人性。所以让我们运用起豪斯上校的技巧吧。

加拿大美丽的新不伦瑞克省的一个人就在我身上运用了这个技巧，拿下了我的一笔生意。那时我正打算在新不伦瑞克钓鱼、划船。所以我向那里的旅游局写信索要一些信息。显然，我的名字被加进了通讯录中，因为我立刻就收到了无数信件、宣传册及印刷出来的各种营地和导游的介绍，这些文件弄得我眼花缭乱，我不知道如何选择。而有一个营地的主人做了聪明的事。他寄给了我几个曾住在他营地的纽约人的姓名和电话号码，让我自行探索。

我惊讶地发现，我认识名单中的一个人。于是我向他致电，问询了他的看法后，我把到达日期发给了那个营地。

其他人都试着向我推销，而这个人让我自己向自己做推销，这个机构赢了。

两千五百年前老子说过的一段话现如今依然能让这本书的读者受益无穷：

“江海所以能为百谷王者，以其善下之，故能为百谷王。是以欲上民，必以言下之；欲先民，必以身后之。是以圣人处上而民不重，处前而民不害……”

让对方觉得主意是自己的。

第十七章　人人都喜欢的诉求

我是在密苏里乡下杰西·詹姆斯村附近长大的。有一次，我拜访了密苏里科尔尼的詹姆斯农场——那时杰西·詹姆斯的儿子住在那里。

他的妻子给我讲了杰西在火车上偷盗后成立了钱库并让周围农民拿这些钱还房贷的故事。

杰西·詹姆斯或许认为自己本质上是理想主义者，就像几代之后的达奇·舒尔茨、“双枪”克劳利、艾尔·卡彭和很多其他犯罪集团的“教父”们一样。实际上，你遇到的所有人都把自己看得很崇高，希望自己有好的名声，大公无私。

J．皮尔庞特·摩根在分析这个问题的时候发现，人们做事时通常有两个理由：好听的理由和现实的理由。

当事人一定会想着现实理由，这是毋庸置疑的。然而我们其他人，作为一个本质上的理想主义者，都喜欢那些好听的理由。所以若想改变别人，请触动对方高尚的动机。

这在商业中是否太过不切实际？让我们用宾夕法尼亚州格兰诺登市法瑞尔·米切尔公司的哈密尔顿·J．法瑞尔的例子检验一下。法瑞尔先生有一个很讨厌的房客，威胁要搬走，而离合同截止日期还有四个月，可是这个人依然不顾合同条例通知房东他要立刻搬家。

“这些人整个冬天都住在我的房子里，在全年最贵的季节。”法瑞尔先生向我们讲道，“而我知道在秋天前很难把房子租出去，我想到本该进账的租金打了水漂。相信我，这样下去我会破产的。

“通常我会强烈谴责房客，让他好好读合同。我会指出如果他要搬家就要一次性付给我所有合同范围内的租金，而我会采取一切办法收回这些租金，我会这样做也能做得到。

“然而我不希望上演如此戏剧性的场景，我决定试试其他方法。所以我是这样开始跟他交谈的：‘先生，我听说了你的事，现在依然觉得不可思议。我出租房子那么多年了，看得多了便也会看人了。我一直觉得你是个说话算话的人。实际上我依然坚信这一点，所以我想赌一把。

“‘这是我的提议。请你再仔细考虑一下搬家这件事。如果下个月你告诉我你还想搬家，那么我答应你，我会接受你的搬家要求，然后承认自己看人的眼光有问题。然而我相信你是个说话算话的人，会履行我们之间的合同。说到底，文明还是野蛮，这都是自己的选择。’

“当第二个月来临时，这位先生来见我，亲自把租金拿给了我。他说他和他的妻子重新考虑了搬家的事，他们决定留下，遵守合同才是唯一体面的方式。”

当已故的罗德·诺斯克利夫生前在报纸上看到了自己的一张不愿公开的照片时，他给报社编辑写了一封信。他说“别登我不喜欢的照片”了吗？没有。他希望触动对方的高尚动机，他运用的是我们每个人对母亲的尊重和爱戴。他写道：“恳请您不要再刊登那张照片了，我妈妈很不喜欢它。”

当小约翰·D．洛克菲勒希望报纸停止刊登他孩子的照片时，他也试图触动对方的高尚动机。他并没有说：“我不希望你们刊登这些照片。”他触动的是我们每个人内心深处的渴求——避免对孩子造成伤害。他说：“你也懂的，朋友们，你们中有些人也有孩子，你知道小孩子得到太多公开关注不是一件好事。”

当《周六晚报》和《妇女家庭杂志》的拥有者赛勒斯·H．K．科蒂斯刚刚开始创业时，他还是缅因州的一个穷苦男孩，他没有像其他报社、杂志社一样拥有足够的钱支付给投稿者，他雇不起一流的作者为赚取利益而写作。所以他要触动作者的高尚动机。比如说，他竟然说服了《小妇人》的作者路易莎·梅·阿尔科特在职业巅峰期为他写文章，他并没说要给她寄一百美金的支票，而是说会寄支票给阿尔科特喜欢的慈善组织。

或许读到这里，怀疑论者会说：“哦，这一套只对诺斯克利夫、洛克菲勒或是多愁善感的小说家管用。我希望你能展示给我看，这对于欠我债需要我去收的那些顽劣家伙也适用。”

或许你是对的。没什么是万能药，不可能在每个情形中，对每种人都奏效。如果你对自己的处事方式满意，那为什么要变？如果不满意，为何不试试呢？

不论如何，我觉得你会喜欢下面这个故事。这是我以前的一个学生，詹姆斯·L．托马斯讲的：

某个汽车公司的六名客户拒绝付维修费，他们并不是拒付全部费用，而都是说其中的某一项款额不能付。他们每一个人都在维修单上签了名，所以公司确定款额没有错，而他们也是这样说的。这是他们犯的第一个错误。

信用部门用了下述方式试图讨回到期未付的款额。你猜猜他们会不会成功？

他们打电话直接说对方欠款，而他们打电话的目的就是来收款的。

他们直接说，公司绝对没有出错，在任何情形下征收这些款项都是合理的。这也就是说顾客绝对是错的，在任何情况下拒付款项都是不合理的。

他们说，公司不管怎样都比顾客对汽车的了解要全面，所以没有争论的必要。

结果，他们开始争论起来。

这里有任何安抚客户情绪并清账的方式吗？答案很明显。

在这个阶段里，信用部经理都快要和客户开战了，他用法律条文一条条向客户开火，还好这时总经理注意到此事。经理调查了这几个人，发现他们并没有赖账的名声，所以一定是公司出了问题，公司的收款方式出了问题。于是他打电话给詹姆斯·L．托马斯，让他去收这些糊涂账。

托马斯先生是这样做的：

“我拜访了每一位客户，试图通过确认正确的账单收回糊涂账。但是关于这点我只字未提。我解释说我来的目的是为了找出公司到底哪里出了错。

“我说得很明白，我会不带偏见地聆听顾客的说法。我告诉他们公司从未认定自己是无懈可击的。

“我告诉客户我只是对他的车感兴趣，而他对自己的车的了解才是无人可比的，他才是这件事上的权威。

“我让对方说话，而我带着他所期待的兴趣和同情心听着一切。

“最后，当客户的情绪稳定下来后，我用对方认为公平的方式与他对话，我试着触动他高尚的动机。我说：‘首先，我希望您知道我也觉得在这件事上公司一直处理不当。我们的一位代表使您反感和动怒，给您带来了不便。这真不应该发生。我非常抱歉，我代表公司向你道歉。我在这儿听您讲述时就觉得您是个讲理又耐心的人，而因为您讲理又耐心，我请求您为我做一件事，您比任何人都适合做这件事。这里是您的账单，我知道我来调整它是保险的，如果您是我们公司的总裁也会有同样的决定。但是我想让您亲自来决定付多少钱。您说了算。’

“顾客调整了账单吗？当然，他们调整得可尽兴了。这些账单从一百五十到四百美金不等。有客户做出了最利己的决定吗？是的，有一个人一分钱都不肯付。而其余五人则付了大部分金额。而更妙的是，接下来的两年里，这六个人都又从我们这儿买了新车！

“经验告诉我，”托马斯先生说，“当我们无法足够了解客户的背景时，最牢靠的方法便是设定他们是诚恳、诚实、真诚的人，一旦被说服，他们便会主动支付账单。换一种更清楚的说法，那就是：人们是诚实的，愿意履行责任，这方面的特例很少。而且我确信，面对一个有欺骗倾向的人时，如果你让对方感受到你认为他诚实、正直、公正，那么他就会做出相应的行为。”

触动对方的高尚动机。

第十八章　如何批评而不招致怨恨

一天中午，查尔斯·施瓦布在视察他的一个钢铁厂时发现有员工在吸烟。而在他们头上，就顶着“请勿吸烟”的标示。施瓦布是否走过去指着标示问他们“你认字吗”？哦，不。施瓦布不会这样做。他走过去，给每人递上一根雪茄，说：“伙计们，到外面去抽我会很感激的。”他们都知道自己违反了规定，他们知道施瓦布也知道这点，然而施瓦布不但没有责骂他们，还给了他们小礼物，这让他们感受到自己的重要性。因此，他们爱戴施瓦布。谁都爱这样的人，不是吗？

约翰·沃纳梅克也运用了同样的技巧。沃纳梅克曾每天都去他费城的店里走一圈。有一次，他看到一位顾客在柜台旁等了半天也没人招呼她。服务员呢？哦，他们正围成一圈在柜台另一边谈笑风生呢。沃纳梅克什么也没说，自己走进柜台帮助女人结了账，并把货物递给售货员进行包装。

选民常抱怨无法接近公职人员。公职人员的确都是大忙人，不过有时却是那些过度保护官员的助手的错误，他们不希望官员被过多访客所扰。迪士尼所在的佛罗里达奥兰多市的市长卡尔·朗弗德时常告诫属下要允许访客见他。他宣称自己执行的是“开门”政策，然而当社区市民打来电话时，他们却被秘书和其他行政人员拒之门外。

最后市长找到了方法，他把办公室的门卸了下来！他的助手终于懂了。在那个颇具象征性的没有门的日子之后，他才真正做到了公开执政。

措辞的改变便是能否改变对方观点且不冒犯、不引起愤恨的关键。

很多人在提出批评前都会先赞美，然后用“但是”一词转折。例如，想改变孩子学习时粗心的毛病时，我们会说：“约翰，我们很为你骄傲，但是如果你能在代数上更加努力，你会做得更好。”

在这个例子中，约翰在听到“但是”二字前都备受鼓舞。但听到这个词后，他会怀疑赞美的真诚度。对他来说，赞美或许只是虚伪的开头，目的是批判并影射他的失败。家长会失去信誉，也不太可能改变约翰的学习态度。

这是很容易改变的一件事。你只需把“但是”变成“还有”。例如，“约翰，你这学期成绩进步了，我们很为你骄傲。还有，如果下学期你能继续用功，你的代数一定会和其他科目一样好的。”

现在约翰可以接受赞美了，因为后面没有跟着影射失败的词语。我们间接地让他注意到可以进步的方面，他很有可能会试着不辜负我们的期待。

那些敏感的人有可能对直接批判产生怨恨，这个时候，间接地让对方注意到自己的问题对这些人来说尤其适用。罗德岛温索基特的马姬·雅各布在训练班中告诉了我们，她是如何说服邋遢的建筑工人在加盖房屋后清理现场的。

刚开始施工的几天里，雅各布女士每次下班回家都会发现院子里堆满了木材碎块。她不想惹恼工人，因为他们的手艺非常好，所以工人回家后，她和她的孩子们会把碎块都捡起来堆在一边。后来的一个早晨，她把工头拉到一边说：“昨天你们把前院收拾得特别干净整齐，不会让邻居不满。”从那以后，工人都会把碎木整齐地堆到一边，而且工头每天都会来询问雅各布女士对院子每晚的状况是否满意。

陆军预备队的成员和他们的教官间最大的矛盾之一便是理发。预备队成员认为自己是平民（多数情况下的确如此），不愿意把头发剪得太短。

预备队第542学校的军士长哈利·凯瑟尔在训练一组未任命的预备军时也遇到了这个问题。大家以为他会大声责骂并吓唬这些人，然而他选择了另一种方式，间接表述观点。

他说：“先生们，你们都是领导者。如果你们都能以身作则就会事半功倍。你们必须当属下的好榜样。你们知道军规对发型的要求是什么，尽管我的头发已经比你们有的人短了，但我今天要去理发。你对着镜子看看，如果觉得理了发才能起到更好的表率作用，我们会为你安排理发时间。”

结果可想而知。有些人的确照了镜子，当天下午就去理了个大兵头。第二天早晨，凯瑟尔军士长说他已经看到了一些成员展现出的领导气质。

1887年3月8日，德高望重的牧师亨利·沃德·比奇去世了。之后的那个周日，莱曼·艾伯特被邀请在比奇留下的空讲道台上讲话。他希望做到最好，所以一遍又一遍地写布道词并进行润色，像福楼拜一样认真。写完后他读给妻子听，就如大多数演讲稿一样，它很糟糕。如果他妻子略微缺乏深思熟虑便会说：“莱曼，这真是太糟糕了。这行不通的。大家都会睡着的。听上去你就像在读百科全书。布道那么多年了，你应该能说得更好啊。老天啊，你为什么不能说人话呢？为什么不自然一些？如果你真在众人面前读了这些那真是会给你自己蒙羞啊。”

这是她有可能说出的话。如果真的说了，你知道后果会是怎样的，她也知道。所以她只是轻描淡写了一句：这听上去像是一篇《北美评论》上的出色文章。换言之，她赞美了这篇文章，同时巧妙地暗示了它并不适合演讲。莱曼·艾伯特明白她的意思，把精心准备的稿子撕掉，后来进行了脱稿演讲。

纠正他人错误的有效方式是：

间接让对方意识到自己的问题。

第十九章　先承认你自己的错误

我的外甥女约瑟芬·卡耐基到纽约来当我的秘书。她19岁，三年前高中毕业。她对商务的了解少得可怜，但后来她成了我最得力的秘书，然而在一开始的时候，她……总之，进步空间还很大。

有一天我想批评她时，我忽然对自己说：“等一下，戴尔·卡耐基。你的年龄是她的两倍，商务经验是她的一万倍，你怎能期望她具有你的观点、你的判断力和你的动力呢（当然也都是很平庸的了）？再等等，戴尔，你十九岁时在做什么？你还记得那些愚蠢的错误和莽撞吗？还记得你做过这样和那样的蠢事吗？”

诚实、公平地思考过这些问题后，我认为十九岁的约瑟芬比十九岁时的我能力更强。而我羞愧地承认——这对于约瑟芬来讲并不算是什么褒奖。

所以从那以后，每当我想让约瑟芬意识到错误时都会这样开始对话：“约瑟芬，你犯了错，不过老天知道这比我犯过的错轻多了。没有人生来就有好的判断力。只有经验才能让你成长，而你已经比我在你这个年龄时做得好多了。我自己做过很多愚蠢的事，所以我没有批评你的意思。但是你难道不认为这件事应该这样去做吗？”

如果批评你的人首先谦虚地承认了自己的不完美，那么听他讲你的缺点时是否就没那么难以接受了？

加拿大马尼托巴布兰登的工程师E．G．迪利斯通对秘书很不满意，他口述的信打出来后每页都有两三个拼写错误。迪利斯通先生讲了他是这样处理这件事的：

“就像很多工程师一样，我们不以卓越的英文水准和精确的拼写著称，几年来我都在用带有字母检索的小本子记录容易拼错的词。很明显，直接指出问题无法让我的秘书更仔细地检查或更多地翻阅字典，我决定换一种方式。所以，当我再次接到错误百出的信时，我和秘书一同坐下，并跟她说：

“‘不知为何，这个字看起来不对。这是我一直拼错的一个词。因此我把它写在我的拼写小本子上（然后我翻到相应的一页）。你看，拼错的词就在这儿。我现在对拼写特别敏感，因为人们的确会通过信件来评判一个人，而拼写错误会使我们显得没有职业精神。’

“我不知道她是否学习了我的方式，但从那次谈话以后，她的拼写错误率大幅度地降低了。”

1909年，做事谨慎的伯恩哈德·冯·比洛亲王就认识到这样做的重要性，那时的冯·比洛是德意志帝国总理，那时的国王是威廉二世，就是那个自大、傲慢的最后的恺撒。他正在建立陆军和海军军队并对他们的实力夸下海口。

后来发生了一件令人震惊的事。皇帝说了一些话，一些令人难以置信的话，震惊了全国乃至全世界。雪上加霜的是，皇帝又当众做出了愚蠢而傲慢的宣告。他在访问英国时发表了这些言论，还授予了《每日电讯报》合法的权利来刊登这些话。例如他声称自己是全德国唯一一个对英国有友好感情的人；他正在组建一支海军来抵抗日本的威胁；是他单枪匹马地把英国从俄国和法国的屈辱中解救出来；也是他的方案才使英国的罗伯茨勋爵击败了南非布尔人；等等。

在几百年的和平时期里，从来没有一个欧洲君主说过这样惊人的话，这在整个大陆引起了轩然大波。英国被激怒了，德国政治家惊呆了。而在这一片惊愕中，皇帝也惊慌失措了，他让总理冯·比洛替自己承担责任。没错，他希望冯·比洛宣布这都是他的责任，是他教皇帝说的这些惊人的话。

“但是陛下，”冯·比洛说，“德国或英国没有人会相信我有影响陛下您这样发言的能力啊。”

这话刚说出口，冯·比洛就意识到自己犯了严重的错误，皇帝爆发了。

他大喊道：“你认为我就是个傻瓜，犯了你永远不可能犯下的鲁莽错误。”

冯·比洛知道他本该先赞美再批评的，但是事已至此，他只能做力所能及的补救。他在批评后进行了赞美，这创造了奇迹。

“我完全不是这个意思。”他充满敬意地回答，“陛下在很多方面都比我优秀很多，当然不止在军事方面，在自然科学中也是如此。陛下每次给我讲解气压表、无线电话或伦琴射线时，我都充满了敬仰之情。我很羞愧，我对于自然科学的一切一窍不通，也没有任何关于物理、化学的常识，连很简单的自然现象都不会解释。但是，作为弥补，我还是知道一些历史知识和政治，尤其是外交手段的。”

皇帝露出了笑容，冯·比洛赞美了他，冯·比洛抬高了他而贬低了自己，皇帝因此原谅了他之前所说的一切。他兴高采烈地大声说：“我不是早就说过，咱们俩真是互补啊！我们应该在一起永不分离！一定会的！”

他和冯·比洛握手，不是一下而是很多下。那天晚上，他兴致高涨，竟然握紧双拳说：“谁要是敢跟我说冯·比洛亲王的坏话，我就一拳打到他的鼻子上！”

冯·比洛及时挽救了自己，但是身为谨慎的外交家他也犯了错误：他应该一开始就讲自己的缺陷和威廉的优点，而不是影射皇帝是个需要保护的笨蛋。

如果几句对对方的赞美和对自己的贬低就能使如此自大并认为自己受到侮辱的恺撒转变成忠实朋友，那么，如果我们在日常生活中运用这样的方式又将带来多大的影响！使用正确，它会为人际关系带来真正的奇迹。

承认自己的错误，哪怕是还未改正的错误，都能说服对方改变自己的行为。最近，马里兰蒂莫尼姆的克莱伦斯·泽尔胡森证明了这一点。那时他发现十五岁的儿子开始抽烟。

“当然我不希望大卫抽烟。”泽尔胡森先生说，“但是我和他母亲都抽烟，我们一直都是坏榜样。我向大卫解释我是如何在他的年龄就开始抽烟，尼古丁是如何侵蚀了我，而事到如今我已经很难戒烟了。我提醒他，我的咳嗽是多么惹人厌，而且几年前他还曾让我戒烟。

“我没有劝他、逼迫他戒烟，或警告他吸烟的诸多危害。我只是指出了我是如何染上烟瘾的以及它对我的不良影响。

“他想了一阵子，决定大学之前都不再吸烟。几年过去了，大卫再也没有吸过烟，也不再想吸烟。

“那次谈话后，我自己也决定戒烟了。在家人的帮助下，我也做到了。”

一位好的领导者会遵循下面的准则：

批评他人前先谈论自己的错误。

第二十章　没人喜欢被指使

我曾有幸与美国资深传记作家艾达·塔贝尔一同进餐。当我告诉她我正在写这样一本书后，我们便开始讨论待人接物时最重要的一点。她告诉我，她在写欧文·D．扬的传记时曾经访问过一个与扬先生在同一个办公室共事三年的人。这个人说，他从来也没听过扬先生直接给任何人下命令。他总是提出建议，而非命令。例如，欧文·D．扬从来不会说：“做这件事”“做那件事”“别这样做”“别那样做”。他会说：“你或许可以考虑这样做”或者“你觉得这样可行吗”。当他口述完一封信后，总是会说：“你觉得可以吗？”在审读助手写的信时，他会说：“或许如果我们重新措辞会更好。”他总是给人做事的主动权，从不指使助手做这做那，他放手让他们自己做事并从错误中学习。

这样的方式会使他人更容易改正错误。这样的方式保护了他人的自尊，能使他人感觉到自己的重要性。这促进了合作，减少了反抗。

粗暴的命令所引发的怨恨是长久的，即便命令是为了改善明显糟糕的情况。宾夕法尼亚州怀俄明一所技校的老师丹·桑塔莱利在班里讲了他的一个学生违规停车挡住学校里一家店入口的事。一位讲师冲了进来，用傲慢的口吻问：“谁的车挡住了通道？”当那个学生回应后，那个老师大喊：“把车开走！现在！要不然我用链子把它缠上然后拖走！”

那个学生固然做错了，不能把车停在那里。但从此以后，不仅那个学生厌恶那位老师的举动，所有学生都开始在他的班上捣乱，令他头疼。

他还能采取什么其他的方式吗？如果他友好地问“哪位同学把车停在过道上了”，然后建议那位同学把车移走，让其他车可以出入，学生会很乐意移车的。那个同学和其他同学都不会生气，也不会厌恶那个老师。

问问题的方式不仅能使命令更易被接受，还往往能激发对方的创造力。人们在认为自己参与了决定时会更乐意接受命令。

当南非约翰内斯堡的精密部件小工厂总经理伊恩·麦当劳接到一笔庞大订单时，他很确定他们无法如期交货。工厂里的工作早已安排好，而这笔订单交货时间之紧迫使按时交货都成了几乎不可能的任务。

伊恩并没有催促员工加快速度赶订单。他召集了全厂会议，向大家解释了情况，告诉他们如果能按时交货对公司来说将具有多重大的意义。然后他开始问问题：

“我们能用什么办法来处理这个订单？”

“有没有人能想到任何不同的操作方式以保证我们能按时交货？”

“我们该怎样调整工作时间和任务分配？”

职员们想出了很多主意，执意让经理接这笔订单。他们用“我们能做到”的态度来迎接这个问题。于是他接受了订单，开始生产，并且如期交货。

高效领导者会：

提出问题而不是直接下命令。

Chapter 4　Remember That No One Ever Kicks a Dead Dog

An event occurred in 1929 that created a national sensation in educational circles. Learned men from all over America rushed to Chicago to witness the affair. A few years earlier, a young man by the name of Robert Hutchins had worked his way through Yale, acting as a waiter, a lumberjack, a tutor, and a clothes-line salesman. Now, only eight years later, he was being inaugurated as president of the fourth richest university in America, the University of Chicago. His age? Thirty. Incredible! The older educators shook their heads. Criticism came roaring down upon the“boy wonder”like a rockslide. He was this and he was that—too young, inexperienced— his educational ideas were cockeyed. Even the newspapers joined in the attack.

The day he was inaugurated, a friend said to the father of Robert Maynard Hutchins:“I was shocked this morning to read that newspaper editorial denouncing your son.”

“Yes,”the elder Hutchins replied,“it was severe, but remember that no one ever kicks a dead dog.”

Yes, and the more important a dog is, the more satisfaction people get in kicking him. The Prince of Wales who later became Edward VIII (now Duke of Windsor) had that forcibly brought home to him.

He was attending Dartmouth College in Devonshire at the time—a college that corresponds to the Naval Academy at Annapolis. The Prince was about fourteen. One day one of the naval officers found him crying, and asked him what was wrong. He refused to tell at first, but finally admitted the truth: he was being kicked by the naval cadets. The commodore of the college summoned the boys and explained to them that the Prince had not complained, but he wanted to find out why the Prince had been singled out for this rough treatment.

After much hemming and hawing and toe scraping, the cadets finally confessed that when they themselves became commanders and captains in the King's Navy, they wanted to be able to say that they had kicked the King!

So when you are kicked and criticised, remember that it is often done because it gives the kicker a feeling of importance. It often means that you are accomplishing something and are worthy of attention. Many people get a sense of savage satisfaction out of denouncing those who are better educated than they are or more successful. For example, while I was writing this chapter, I received a letter from a woman denouncing General William Booth, founder of the Salvation Army. I had given a laudatory broadcast about General Booth; so this woman wrote me, saying that General Booth had stolen eight million dollars of the money he had collected to help poor people. The charge, of course, was absurd. But this woman wasn't looking for truth. She was seeking the mean-spirited gratification that she got from tearing down someone far above her. I threw her bitter letter into the wastebasket, and thanked Almighty God that I wasn't married to her. Her letter didn't tell me anything at all about General Booth, but it did tell me a lot about her. Schopenhauer had said it years ago:“Vulgar people take huge delight in the faults and follies of great men.”

One hardly thinks of the president of Yale as a vulgar man; yet a former president of Yale, Timothy Dwight, apparently took huge delight in denouncing a man who was running for President of the United States. The president of Yale warned that if this man were elected President,“we may see our wives and daughters the victims of legal prostitution, soberly dishonoured, speciously polluted; the outcasts of delicacy and virtue, the loathing of God and man.”

Sounds almost like a denunciation of Hitler, doesn't it? But it wasn't. It was a denunciation of Thomas Jefferson. Which Thomas Jefferson? Surely not the immortal Thomas Jefferson, the author of the Declaration of Independence, the patron saint of democracy? Yes, verily, that was the man.

What American do you suppose was denounced as a“hypocrite”,“an impostor”, and as“little better than a murderer”? A newspaper cartoon depicted him on a guillotine, the big knife read to cut off his head. Crowds jeered at him and hissed him as he rode through the street. Who was he? George Washington.

But that occurred a long time ago. Maybe human nature has improved since then. Let's see. Let's take the case of Admiral Peary—the explorer who startled and thrilled the world by reaching the North Pole with dog sleds on April 6, 1909—a goal that brave men for centuries had suffered and died to attain. Peary himself almost died from cold and starvation; and eight of his toes were frozen so hard they had to be cut off. He was so overwhelmed with disasters that he feared he would go insane. His superior naval officers in Washington were burned up because Peary was getting so much publicity and acclaim. So they accused him of collecting money for scientific expeditions and then“lying around and loafing in the Arctic.”And they probably believed it, because it is almost impossible not to believe what you want to believe. Their determination to humiliate and block Peary was so violent that only a direct order from President McKinley enabled Peary to continued his career in the Arctic.

Would Peary have been denounced if he had had a desk job in the Navy Department in Washington. No. He wouldn't have been important enough then to have aroused jealousy.

General Grant had an even worse experience than Admiral Peary. In 1862, General Grant won the first great decisive victory that the North had enjoyed—a victory that was achieved in one afternoon, a victory that made Grant a national idol overnight—a victory that had tremendous repercussions even in far-off Europe—a victory that set church bells ringing and bonfires blazing from Maine to the banks of the Mississippi. Yet within six weeks after achieving that great victory, Grant—hero of the North—was arrested and his army was taken from him. He wept with humiliation and despair.

Why was General U.S. Grant arrested at the flood tide of his victory? Largely because he had aroused the jealousy and envy of his arrogant superiors.

If we are tempted to be worried about unjust criticism here is Rule:

REMEMBER THAT UNJUST CRITICISM IS OFTEN A DISGUISED COMPLIMENT. REMEMBER THAT NO ONE EVER KICKS A DEAD DOG.

Chapter 21　Let the Other Person Save Face

Years ago the General Electric Company was faced with the delicate task of removing Charles Steinmetz from the head of a department. Steinmetz, a genius of the first magnitude when it came to electricity, was a failure as the head of the calculating department. Yet the company didn't dare offend the man. He was indispensable— and highly sensitive. So they gave him a new title. They made him Consulting Engineer of the General Electric Company—a new title for work he was already doing—and let someone else head up the department.

Steinmetz was happy.

So were the officers of G. E. They had gently maneuvered their most temperamental star, and they had done it without a storm—by letting him save face.

Letting one save face! How important, how vitally important that is! And how few of us ever stop to think of it! We ride roughshod over the feelings of others, getting our own way, finding fault, issuing threats, criticizing a child or an employee in front of others, without even considering the hurt to the other person's pride. Whereas a few minutes' thought, a considerate word or two, a genuine understanding of the other person's attitude. would go so far toward alleviating the sting!

Let's remember that the next time we are faced with the distasteful necessity of discharging or reprimanding an employee.

“Firing employees is not much fun. Getting fired is even less fun.”(I'm quoting now from a letter written me by Marshall A. Granger, a certified public accountant. )“Our business is mostly seasonal. There-fore we have to let a lot of people go after the income tax rush is over.

“It's a byword in our profession that no one enjoys wielding the ax. Consequently, the custom has developed of getting it over as soon as possible, and usually in the following way:‘Sit down, Mr. Smith. The season's over, and we don't seem to see any more assignments for you. Of course, you understood you were only employed for the busy season anyhow, etc., etc.’

“The effect on these people is one of disappointment and a feeling of being‘let down’. Most of them are in the accounting field for life, and they retain no particular love for the firm that drops them so casually.

“I recently decided to let our seasonal personnel go with a little more tact and consideration. So I call each one in only after carefully thinking over his or her work during the winter. And I've said something like this:‘Mr. Smith, you've done a fine job (if he has).That time we sent you to Newark, you had a tough assignment. You were on the spot, but you came through with flying colors, and we want you to know the firm is proud of you. You've got the stuff—you're going a long way, wherever you're working. This firm believes in you, and is rooting for you, and we don't want you to forget it.’

“Effect? The people go away feeling a lot better about being fired. They don't feel‘let down’. They know if we had work for them, we'd keep them on. And when we need them again, they come to us with a keen personal affection.”

At one session of our course, two class members discussed the negative effects of faultfinding versus the positive effects of letting the other person save face.

Fred Clark of Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, told of an incident that occurred in his company:“At one of our production meetings, a vice president was asking very pointed questions of one of our production supervisors regarding a production process. His tone of voice was aggressive and aimed at pointing out faulty performance on the part of the supervisor. Not wanting to be embarrassed in front of his peers, the supervisor was evasive in his responses. This caused the vice president to lose his temper, berate the supervisor and accuse him of lying.

“Any working relationship that might have existed prior to this encounter was destroyed in a few brief moments. This supervisor, who was basically a good worker, was useless to our company from that time on. A few months later he left our firm and went to work for a competitor, where I understand he is doing a fine job.”

Another class member, Anna Mazzone, related how a similar incident had occurred at her job—but what a difference in approach and results! Ms. Mazzone, a marketing specialist for a food packer, was given her first major assignment—the test-marketing of a new product. She told the class:“When the results of the test came in, I was devastated. I had made a serious error in my planning, and the entire test had to be done all over again. To make this worse, I had no time to discuss it with my boss before the meeting in which I was to make my report on the project.

“When I was called on to give the report, I was shaking with fright. I had all I could do to keep from breaking down, but I resolved I would not cry and have all those men make remarks about women not being able to handle a management job because they are too emotional. I made my report briefly and stated that due to an error I would repeat the study before the next meeting. I sat down, expecting my boss to blow up.

“Instead, he thanked me for my work and remarked that it was not unusual for a person to make an error on a new project and that he had confidence that the repeat survey would be accurate and meaningful to the company. He assured me, in front of all my colleagues, that he had faith in me and knew I had done by best, and that my lack of experience, not my lack of ability, was the reason for the failure.

“I left that meeting with my head up in the air and with the determination that I would never let that boss of mine down again.”

Even if we are right and the other person is definitely wrong, we only destroy ego by causing someone to lose face. The legendary French aviation pioneer and author Antoine de Saint-Exupéry wrote:“I have no right to say or do anything that diminishes a man in his own eyes. What matters is not what I think of him, but what he thinks of himself. Hurting a man in his dignity is a crime.”

A real leader will always follow…

LET THE OTHER PERSON SAVE FACE.

译序

中世纪的欧洲，出了一部伟大的禽兽史诗，这就是《列那狐》（Reynard the Fox）。我读了这部书，觉得异常的可爱，故费了一二月的工夫把它介绍给读者。

关于《列那狐》，学者间的争论颇不少，第一是它的作者问题，第二是它的产生地的问题。关于它的作者，有的主张是由民间传说发展而成的，有的主张是“僧侣诗人”们的创作。关于它的产地，有的主张是德国，有的主张是法国。但不管那许多纷纭莫决的主张，我们现在却有了一种概念：这部《列那狐》原有一个民间传说的来源，这来源是在法国。然在十世纪与十一世纪时，经了“僧侣诗人”与法国“宫廷诗人”的润饰，加上了时代的色彩与讽刺的意味。当时宫廷诗人大约必以此诗与那些古代史诗、骑士传奇，同样地读诵于听者之前，以娱悦他们。到了十二世纪时，有了一种德文本，又有了拉丁文本，变异的同源作品有数种，后来又有了散文本。到了十八世纪之末，大诗人歌德又著了Rainecke Fuchs，在文辞方面，是加上了不少的美漆，然它的原来的朴质可爱的风趣，却丧失了一些。

《列那狐》最可爱最特异的一点，便是善于描写禽兽的行动及性格，使之如真的一般，还有它引进了许多古代的寓言，如熊被骗，被紧夹在树缝中；狐低头看马蹄，被马所踢等，而能够自由地运用，使之十分的生动，也是极可使我们赞美的。

在歌德所述的Rainecke Fuchs里，会附有大画家Kaulbach所绘插图三十余幅，极为有趣。评论者都谓这给本书以新的生命。现在把它们转插于本书中。

为取便于中国的儿童计，此书采用“重述”法，但所删节的地方并不多见。另一英译本，删节了三分之二，只叙到第十四节为止。原书的结局是列那狐终于得释，这个英译本，却不欲使狡者得志，竟把它的结果改作：列那被处死刑，大快人心了！编译儿童书而处处要顾全“道德”，是要失掉许多文学的趣味的。

译者

3

狼说完了话，小猎狗考托士（Courtoys）又立起来向国王控诉说，怎样的在寒冷的冬天，霜雪满地，他为严冬所苦，什么食物都没有了，只存一个布丁，而列那狐却把这个布丁从他那里偷走了。

他说了这些话，特保（Tybert）猫愤怒地跳到他们中间，说道：“国王，吾主。我在这里听见列那狐被人苛刻地控告，没有别人，只有他自己，才能洗清他。但考托士在这里控告的，却是许多年前的事——那个布丁是我的，而我却不控告，因为我在夜间从一个磨坊里把它得来。磨坊主人躲在那里睡着了。如果考托士有什么份，那也是由我那里得来的。”

于是潘莎海狸说道：“你想一想看，特保，列那被人控告是不应该的么？他简直是一个谋杀者，一个海盗，一个贼，他不爱任何一个人，就是这里我们的王，我们的主，他也不爱。他只要能取得一只肥鸡的腿，即便失去善德与名誉也愿意。我要告诉你，我昨天看见他对于克瓦Cuwart兔所做的事，克瓦现在是站在这里，受着国王的和平而安全的保护。列那答应克瓦说，他要教克瓦他的‘克里独’（Credo），使他成一个好牧师。他叫他去坐他的两腿之中，唱着而且高声叫道：‘克里独，克里独！’我刚由那里经过，听见这个歌声。后来我走近了，却看见这位列那先生已放下他方才的教读与教歌的事而又在演他的旧戏了。因为，他这时已把克瓦的咽喉捉住，如果我这时不来，他已把克瓦的生命取去了。你们在这里还可以看出克瓦兔的新创痕。我的主，我的王，如果你对于这事没有刑罚，让那个破坏你的和平者安安静静地走掉，你便要没有权力审判你的部下，即你的子孙们在许多年之后也要受骂的。”

“的确如此，潘莎。”依赛格林说道，“你说的不错。实行正义与公理，是正当的，如此，弱者才能生存于和平之中。”

11

狮王道：“现在，去吧，格令巴，好好地照顾你自己。列那是又凶险又狡猾，你必须留意他。”

格令巴说，他一定会自己留意的。

于是格令巴向马里卜台去了。当他到了那个地方时，他见列那狐在家里，他的妻爱美林夫人（Dame Ermelyn）同几个幼子躺在暗隅。

格令巴先对他的舅父舅母问过了好，然后对舅父列那说道：“舅舅，大家在控告你，你不到庭是有损无益的。现在最好同我一起到宫廷去，不能再迟延了。控告的事件很多，这一次是第三次的召唤了。我告诉你实话，如果你明天不去，便不会有什么好结果的。你将见三天之内，你的屋便要四面被围起来，拷问机、绞架都要立在屋前。我说实话，你那时将不能逃命，便连你的妻，你的子也将不能活了。国王说，他要将你全家都杀死。所以最好你还是和我同到宫廷去。你的聪明的狡辩会使你得机会打翻一切的控辞，使你的仇人们含羞而去。你已做过比这次更大的事许多回了。”

列那狐答道：“你说的不错。我想最好还是和你同去。如果我到国王那里当面和他相见，和他说话，也许他会怜悯我的。虽然我做了许多坏事，然而宫廷里不能没有我，那是国王很明白的。宫廷里最需要机警聪明的咨议，而我却是最好的咨议。不过，宫廷里恨我的太多，我心里总未免有些忧愁，因为人一多便会比一个人害我力量大。但我最好还是和你同去，甥儿，一人做事一人担，比之妻子一同受害总是好些。起来，我们走吧，我将忍受一切。”

列那对他的妻爱美林夫人说道：“我把孩子们托给你，你好好地看顾他们。我最小的孩子列金（Reynkin）尤须特别留心抚养。他十分的像我，我希望他能学我一样。如果上帝保佑我得逃命归来，我必定十分感谢你。”于是列那别了他的妻而去。

唉，上帝！爱美林是如何的忧苦呀！马里卜台的主人，粮食的供给者走了，家中将要绝食了。

15

依赛格林说道：“如果我们有一条坚固的绞绳，立刻可把他结果了。”

列那狐好久没有说话，这时对依赛格林说道：“请减短我的痛苦。特保有一条强固的绳子，这绳子是牧师家里的，曾捉住他过。他会爬树，爬得又快，让他把绳挂好了。我很忧愁，我活了这么长久，快一点，不要迟延了。白鲁因，你在前引路；依赛格林你紧紧地跟着仔细监督着，不要让我逃走了。”

白鲁因说道：“列那说的话，是最好的建议了。”

于是他们立刻动身走了。依赛格林立在这边，白鲁因立在那边，如此的，他们引导列那到绞架上去。特保在前跑，他去结绳。尊贵的国王与王后以及所有在宫廷上的，都跟在后面，去看列那的结局。列那很害怕，心里在想，怎样才能救他自己；怎样才能欺骗那三个最望他死的仇人而使他们受羞辱；怎样才能用谎话使国王帮助他反对他们。他想了许久，自己暗说道：“国王和许多禽兽都怒我，这是无怪其然的，我是应受的。然而，不管国王如何的有权力，他的左右如何的聪明，如果我一说话，我便要把自己升在如他们置我于绞架上的地位一样高了。”

那时，依赛格林说道：“白鲁因爵士，现在你想想因那列之故你的头全红了，我们这时应该报仇了。特保！快点爬上去，把绳子紧缚在树上，再打一个死结；白鲁因，紧紧地捉住他，不要让他逃走了。我要将梯子放好了，叫他走上去。”

白鲁因说道：“好的。我将好好地帮助他。”

列那狐说道：“现在我心里很恐惧，因为我看见死在我的眼前，我不能逃脱。我的主，国王，我亲爱的王后，还有站在这里的所有的大众，我在离开这个世界之前，我要求你们一件事，我要在你们大众之前，公开地忏悔我自己，把我的罪恶都说出来。我的死可以容易些，你们大众求上帝怜恤我的灵魂！”

19

于是这个虚伪的朝陵者从依赛格林那里取得了两只靴。你看他取下时是如何的痛苦呀！他不能动弹，足上血淋淋的。其次是他的夫人的份了，她躺在草地上，脸上悲愁着。她失去了她的两只后靴。

列那很高兴，讥嘲地对他的婶母说道：“好婶母，为我之故，你受了多少苦？我要穿了你的靴，你将是朝陵的伴侣了，我得赦罪，你也可以有福了。”

母狼气得一句话也说不出。她终于说道：“唉，列那，现在随你怎么说都可以，我祈求上帝复仇！”

依赛格林与他的伴侣白鲁因，一句话也不说，他们静默地躺着。他们很难过，因绳子捆得极紧，已受了伤。如果特保猫也在此地，他便也将受些苦了，亏得他机警，没有同来。

第二天，太阳升起时，列那把从依赛格林及他的妻那里取来的靴，用油抹了，穿在足上，用带缚住，走到国王及王后那里，以快乐的面目，对他们说道：“高贵的王与后，我要走了，我要求你们给我背囊及棒子。”

国王叫巴林（Bellyn）羊给列那背囊及棒子，这背囊便是以白鲁因熊的皮为囊面的。于是列那要动身了。他向国王望着，好像他不舍得离别；又似要哭出来的样子，好像他心中真的难过。他想，不要延搁太久了，还是快走的好，因他自知有罪。

国王道：“列那，我忧你如此匆忙。不再耽搁。”

“不，我主，是时候了，我求你让我动身，我必须走了。”

国王道：“上帝与你在一起！”他叫全宫的人都去送列那一程，只有狼与熊被紧缚在地上，不能走。列那心里暗笑，国王起初如此恨他，后来竟让他愚弄了。

列那道：“我主，我请求你不要再送了。你那里还有两个奸臣被缚在地上呢。如果他们逃了，为害不浅，我求上帝保佑你！”于是他以后足立起来，为一切大的小的禽兽祝福，他们也祝福他。他快活地向克瓦兔及巴林羊说道：“朋友们，我们现在就分离么？你们与上帝将伴我再走几程。你们身份既高，又和蔼可亲，走在一处是最好不过的。”他说了好些欺骗的话，一直把他们引到他的屋马里卜台那里。

21

狐说道：“巴林，你不记得昨天国王命令我离开此地之前要给他两封信么？好兄弟，我求你把这两封信带去，它们已经写好了。”

羊道：“我不知道这事。如果你的信写得好，还有装信的东西，我可以把它们带去。”

列那道：“你可以有东西装信。我要把我的背囊给你，把送给国王的信放在里面。你会得国王的感谢的。”

因此，巴林答应把这两封信带去。

列那回到屋内，把背囊取出，放进克瓦的头颅，然后把这背囊交给巴林，要使他受危险。他把背囊挂在巴林颈上，再三嘱咐道，如果他要得国王的欢心，千万不要偷看背囊中的东西。“如果你要使国王尊重你，喜爱你，你要说，这个是你自己代我写的，并说这信写得如何的好。然后你便可以得到国王的感谢了。”

巴林羊很高兴，他想国王会感谢他的，说道：“列那，我很知道你现在为我做的事。如果大家知道我能够写得很好的信，我在宫廷中便要大被称赞了，虽然我本是不会写信的。一人做的工作，常常有被别人得其名誉的，我现在也要得别人的工作之名誉了。现在，你有什么话说，列那？克瓦兔和我一同到宫廷中去么？”

狐道：“不，他立刻便要跟你来了。他现在还不能出来，因为正在和他婶母说话。你先走吧。我要对克瓦说秘密的事。”

巴林道：“再见，列那。”于是他向宫廷走去。他急急地跑，一直奔到宫中，看见国王和大臣们都在朝中。国王看见了熊皮做的背囊又被带回来，觉得奇怪。他问道：“说，巴林，——你从什么地方来？狐在哪里？他为什么不把背囊带去？”

巴林道：“我主，我将告诉你一切的事。我伴列那到他家里，他问我可否带两封信给我主。我说，为国王之故，便带七封信也高兴。于是他给我这个背囊，信就在囊中。这信是我写的，我还参加些意见在内。我想，你以前不会见过写得这样好的信。”

国王立刻命令他的秘书博卡（Bokart）读这封信，因为他懂得各种的文字。特保猫和博卡从巴林颈上把背囊取下。

秘书博卡解开背囊，把克瓦的头颅取出，说道：“这是什么信！我主，这是克瓦的头颅。”

国王道：“唉，我总是相信这狐！”大家可以知道国王和王后是如何的懊丧。国王生气得把头低下，想了许久，不禁大叫了一声，所有的禽兽闻这叫声都惊怕起来。

勋爵菲拉辟（Firapeel）豹和国王有些亲谊，这时他说道：“我的王，怎么叫得这样响！你忧苦得如同王后死了。不要自苦了，好好地想想吧。这是大羞耻。你不是这个地方的主人与王么？这里的人不是全在你之下么？”

国王道：“菲拉辟勋爵，我怎么能忍得下这口气呢？一个狡贼与骗子欺哄了我，竟使我对不住我的朋友白鲁因熊与依赛格林狼。我十分懊悔。我疏远了最好的大臣们，反去信任了一个狡狐，这真与我的威信有关。我的妻也不好，她那样的求我，我听了她的话，我现在懊悔太迟了。”

豹道：“我主，事情虽做错了。现在还可以补救。我们可以给还白鲁因以他的皮及依赛格林与他的妻的靴——因为有巴林羊在那里呢。他自己承认说，克瓦之死，他是参与的，所以他须偿命。我们全体都去捉列那，把他捉住了绞死，不必再审判。那不是什么都满足了么？”

25

高贵的国王听了大兔与乌鸦的控辞，十分生气，生气得眼睛如火般照耀，形状很可怕。他高声地吼叫起来，所有宫廷上的人都怕得发抖了。后来，他叫道：“我以皇冠立誓，不能忍受这个狡贼的戏弄！我的安全，我的命令都被破坏了，我为他所愚，我竟信了这个狡贼。他的虚伪的假话，哄骗了我。他告诉我他要到罗马，从那里过海到圣地去。我给他背囊及棒子，使他为一个朝陵者，我以为都是真的。唉！他真狡恶！但这都因我的妻，都是她劝我的。我竟听了妇人的话！我求，我命令，所有忠于我的，要与我为友的，不管他们在这里或不在这里，都要以其智或力帮助我复这个大仇。我们捉住了他，便不再会受骗受害了。”

依赛格林狼及白鲁因熊，听了国王的话，十分的希望能对列那狐复仇，但他们不敢说一句话。国王是这样的生气，没有一个人敢开口。

后来，王后说道：“一个贵人不要轻信，也不要太生气，须等明白了一切之后。他须倾听别一部分人的话。我初以为狐改好了，不再骗人了，所以我尽力地帮助他。但我以为不管他是好，是坏，你为保存威信，不应该太匆促地反对他。那是不公平的，因为他不能逃出你的手外。你可以囚他，杀他，他必须服从你的裁判。”

菲拉辟豹说道：“我主，我想我后的话是对的，你听她的话吧。如果列那是如大家所控的有罪的，你便按律治他。”

依赛格林狼道：“菲拉辟勋爵，我们的意见与你一样。不过列那现在如果在这里，即使他能把所有的罪都洗刷清，我也要取他的命；可惜他现在不在这里，我只好不说什么话。然而，在一切事之上的是，他曾告诉国王说有无数财宝埋在克里铿辟。这是一个空前的大谎，他因此害了我们，使我和熊受了大苦。我敢以性命为赌，他说的没有一个字是真实的。国王的使者已经通知他了，他要来，便可以到这里来了。”

国王道：“我们不再去叫他来了。我命令所有在我下面的，服从我的，在六日之后，预备开战，所有弓箭手、步兵、马兵，等等，带了弓箭枪炮，都到马里卜台，把它围困起来。我如是一个国王，我必毁灭了列那狐。你们大家的意见如何？你们愿意这样做吗？”

他们全都喊道：“我的主，你要如何，我们便全体跟你去！”

28

“无所不知，无所不能的上帝保佑我的主，与我的后，愿上帝使他知道谁是对的，谁是错的。因为世界上有许多人，他们的内心是与外表绝不相同的。我愿上帝能公开地显示出每个人的罪过，而他们所有的罪状都能写在他们的前额上。我现在控诉那些恶贼，他们使我受了许多苦。但我愿你们，我的王与后，不要相信他们那些假造的谎话，你们是聪明正直的，我知道你们不会相信他们的。所以，我的爱主，我求你以你的智力研究合理合法的事。所有言动，都使每个人不受冤枉。我不再求别的了。他是有罪的，是说谎的，让他去受罚。人们在我离开朝廷之前，将十分明白我是什么样的人。我不会说好听的假话，只能心里有什么嘴里便说什么。”所有在宫殿上的人都沉默着，他们都震骇于狐的话说得如此的刚强。

国王道：“哈，列那，你真会哄骗人！但你的巧辩却不能帮助你。我已熟想过，你所做的事，在今天必须受绞刑。我不同你辩驳；我将减短你的痛苦。你对待兔及乌鸦的样子，就是你所谓爱我们的榜样了。你的谎话万不能延长你死的时候。‘一只水瓶汲了许久的水了，最后，它要碎成片片的。’我想，你的水瓶，骗了我们许久的，现在也要碎了。”

列那听了这些话，十分恐惧。他后悔来这里。然而他想，无论如何，他必须把讼事洗刷清楚。

他道：“我的主，我的王，请你听完我的话。虽然我被判定了死刑，然你应该听我的话。我以前曾为你划了许多策，做了许多事，在别人躲避着的时候，我都在你身边。如果现在恶兽们以假事控告我，我又不能得你的宽恕，那么我还能不辩诉么？旧的好处，应该记住。我见这里有许多我的同宗和朋友，他们心里都很忧愁，你，我的主，却不公平地要杀我。如果你杀了我，那么，你便要失掉你国内的最忠诚的仆人了。你们想想看，我的主，如果我觉得有罪，或有对不起人处，我怎么肯在所有我的仇人中投到法律之前呢？不，我王，不！就是为了全世界的黄金也不！因为我是自由的，无罪的。谢谢上帝，我知道自己是一点罪也没有的，所以我敢在光明中到这里来回答一切人对于我的控诉。但当格令巴把这些消息告诉我时，我很难过，不知怎么办好。恰好我的叔父米尔丁（Mertyne）猴遇到了我。他见我愁眉不解，便道：‘好侄儿，我觉得你不大舒服。有什么事，应该叫朋友们晓得。一个好朋友是一个大臂助，他可以设法救助你。’我道：‘好叔叔，我现在有大苦难，这是我所不应受的。这事起于一个朋友，大兔。他昨天清早到我这里来，那时我正坐在门外。他告诉我，他要到宫廷里去，他向我问好，我也问他好。

“‘于是他对我说道：“好列那，我是又倦又饿了，你有什么吃的么？”

“‘我道：“是的，有的——你来吧。”

“‘于是我给他一对圆面包，还涂上牛油。那天是礼拜三，是我不吃肉的日子。他吃完了，我的最少的孩子洛赛尔要把剩下的拿去。你知道，小孩子总是贪嘴的。不料大兔咬了他一口，他出血了，晕倒在地。我的大孩子列那定见了，跃过来把大兔的头捉住，如果我不赶快去救他，他几乎要被杀死了。我帮助他走开了，还把孩子打了一顿，不料大兔却到国王那里，诉说我要谋害他。看，叔叔，这就是他们说我有罪的一件事。

“‘此事之后，柯班特乌鸦来了，他悲鸣着飞来。我问他什么事。他说道：“唉，我的妻死了！那边有一只死兔，浑身都生了虫，她吃得太多了，虫把她的喉管弄断了。”

“‘我问他这事究竟怎样发生的。他不再说一句话，又飞开去了。现在他却说我咬了她。杀了她。我怎样能走近她？因为她是飞的，我是在地上走的。好叔叔，我是这样的被冤枉！我真不快活！’

“猴对我说道：‘侄儿，你到宫殿上去，求国王的原谅。’

“‘不，叔叔，不能去，因为主教要责罚我。这事是由依赛格林狼起的。他要脱离了他的教会，恢复自由的生活。他向我诉说，他的生活十分拘束，长久的素食，又要读书唱诗，他简直不能再住在那里了，如果他再住下去，他真要死了。我听了他的话，很可怜他，于是我帮助他出来。我现在很后悔，因为他倒竭力要陷害我，真是以怨报德。叔叔，因此我已到了智穷力尽之境。因为我必须到罗马去求赦罪，我去了，我的妻子恐要受害无穷。那些恶兽妒忌我的，恐将尽力地害他们。我如能到宫廷去，辩护了一切，便可保护他们了，但我又不敢去。我没有求赦罪，上帝会责备我。’

“猴道：‘不，不要怕。我可以帮助你，我知道到罗马去的路。我会替你去的。我还要带些钱去。祈祷者有了钱便会办得更妥。侄儿，不要愁！我明天就去，一直到罗马。你呢，到宫廷里去，立刻去。你所有的罪，我都替你承担了下来。你到了宫中的时候，可遇见我的妻绿克娜（Rukenawe），她的两个姊妹，和我的三个孩子，还有许多亲友。我的妻很高兴帮助人。如果你的事不得直，立刻叫人到罗马告诉我，我有法子想。所以，侄儿，你为我向国王要求，他对你存公道。我知道他不会拒绝你的。’

“我主，当我听见这些话，我笑了。我十分高兴地到这里来，告诉你所有的事。如果有人在这里能以充分的证据控告我，那么，有法律在；如果他不能如此，那么，可以定好日子，定好地方，我们可以相见于决斗场上。谁能以腕力得胜，让他得胜去。这个权利尚在，我不能因我而破坏。法律与公义不会冤枉人的。”

所有的禽兽，无论穷的富的，都沉默着，听狐这一席好像理直气壮的话。拉卜里大兔和柯班特乌鸦是十二分的害怕起来，他们不敢说话，都迅速地离开了宫殿。当他们俩到了远处的平原才说道：“神助这个恶贼作恶！他能隐藏他的虚谎，说来好像真的，如福音书一样的真，这些事只有我们知道，我们怎么会有证人呢？我们最好是忍耐着走开了，不要和他决斗。他的凶残，就是我们有五个也不能保护自己而要被他一个个杀死。”

依赛格林狼和白鲁因熊见他们两个离了宫殿，心里很忧愁。

国王说道：“如果有人要控告的，他可以站出来，我要听他：昨天到这里来的那么多——现在列那在这里了，他们却到哪里去了呢？”

狐道：“我的主，有许多控诉的人，而他们见了他们的仇人却沉默了，不控诉了。现在看拉卜里大兔和柯班特乌鸦，他们于我不在这里时向你控告我，现在呢，我来了，他们却逃走了，不敢再说一句话。如果人要相信了谎言的恶贼，好人是要受许多害——至于我，却不要紧。然而，我主，如果他们有你的命令向我求恕，任他们如何害我，我都可以为你之故原恕了他们。我不恨也不控告我的仇人们。但我把一切事放在上帝手上，他会报酬他们的。”

国王道：“列那，我想，你说你很难过。你以为事情已了了么？不，我必须说我的受害，这已足使你以生命报酬之了——当我把你的所有罪过都赦了时，你答应渡海去朝陵，我所以给你背囊和靴子，然而你此后却做了一件凶暴可羞的大罪。你叫巴林羊把背囊装了克瓦的头颅送还了我。你做的这事是否是一个大罪？你怎么敢给我这样的一个羞辱？把仆人的头颅送给一个主人，这是不是恶作剧？你再不能说没有这事了，因为巴林羊已经把这事的本末都说出来了，他把这信带给我们时，已得了那样的报酬，你也将有同样的，不然，公道要没有了！”

这时列那惊吓住了，他不知说什么话。他已智穷力尽了，很可怜地四面望着，见他的许多亲友都不说一句话。他整个脸都变白了，但没有一个人肯用一手或一足帮助他。

国王说道：“你这恶贼！你这谎徒！为什么不说话了？你现在成了哑子了么？”

狐十分恐惧地站在那里，重重地叹着气，什么人都能听见。但是狼与熊很喜欢。

30

“两年以前，有一个人和一条蛇同到这个宫殿上来要求评判，你和你们的大臣们都狐疑不决。那蛇要穿过一座篱笆，但他被一个网捉住了，如没有人帮助他逃，他便要死在那里了。人走来了，蛇叫他，求人救他出网，救他一条命。人可怜他，说道：‘如果你答应不吃我，不害我，我可以救你出网。’蛇发了一个恶咒，说他决不会害他一丝一毫。于是人把网解了，放他出网。他们同走了好一会，蛇觉肚子饿了，他已好久没有吃东西了，他向人扑去，要吃了他。人恐慌地避开了，说道：‘你现在要杀我么？你忘了你曾立誓不伤害我么？’蛇答道：‘我可以告诉全世界，我这样做是对的。饥饿的需求，可以叫一个人不守他的誓言。’人道：‘如不能相饶，等我们遇到了别的人时，叫他裁判一下。’蛇答应了。他们向前走，遇到了乌鸦特赛林和他的孩子，他们听了人蛇的告诉。特赛林立刻判说，蛇可以吃了人。他和他的孩子都想乘此得一份吃吃。蛇对人道：‘现在怎样？你怎么想？我不是赢了么？’人道：‘一个强盗怎么能判断这事？他要得些利益。且只遇到他一个呢，至少必须两个或三个懂得法律正义的在一起评判才好。’蛇答应了，他们向前去，又遇到熊与狼，他们对他们告诉了这事。他们判决道，蛇可以吃了人。因为因饥饿而背誓是常有的事。人那时十分疑惧，蛇张开大嘴向着他，但人却很艰难地避开了。蛇道：‘这不够了么？已判决了两次。’人道：‘不，那是杀人贼强盗们下的判决。他们本是不守信誓的。但我要向我们的主，国王，那里去告诉，想你不至于反对。他下什么判语，我都听从，永不反对。’狼与熊都说可以，蛇也不反对。他们以为这事到了你那里，也将有与他们同样的判语。我想你能记得住。他们到宫殿上了。人战栗地告诉出他怎样救了蛇的命，蛇却要破誓吃他。蛇答道：‘我要吃他，因为救自己的命；为了救命，一个人可以不顾誓约。’我的主，那时你和你殿上大臣们都难判决。你见了他的愁苦，不欲他因行好事而被杀。在另一方面，又说因饥饿而欲救命，要求帮助。在殿上的人一个也不能说判语应该怎么下。我见他们站在这里，他们不知怎样解决这个事件。于是你叫了我的侄儿列那来，问他对这事的意见。那时，他在这殿上是比别人都亲信，你叫他下公平的判语。列那说道：‘我主，只听了他们的话不足为凭，因为口说常有假话。但如果我见了蛇与人未救他之前一样的受缚于网中，那么，我就可以下判语了。’于是你道：‘列那，你的话是对的。我们就照你的话办。’人和蛇都到原地方了。列那叫蛇照旧被缚在网中。你，我的主说道：‘列那，你现在怎么想？我们判决什么话？’于是列那说道：‘我的主，现在他们都照以前一样了。他们不胜不败。看，我主，我现在下判语了。如果人现在还信他以前的誓约，他可以把他放了去。但，如果他以为蛇可怕，怕他因饥饿要破约吃他，我便判道，人可以自由地走去，让蛇还留在那里，好像起首一样。我想这样是公正的判断。’唉，我主，这个判语你和你的大臣们都以为好，都赞美列那能使人自由离开了。如此，狐以智慧保住你的高贵的尊严与名望，如一个忠仆对他的主所做的。熊与狼能这样的给你挣光荣么？他们知道的是怎样吼叫偷盗，吃肥胖的肉，然后他们以正义与法律，判决那偷鸡窃雏的小贼的死刑，但是他们自己却偷着牛、马，他们无事地走去，还做着爵主。他们似乎比所罗门、亚里士多德还聪明，每个都很高傲，赞美着大事业与勇敢，但如果他们到那里办这件事，恐将第一个逃走了。唉，我主，他们和像他们一样的，都不聪明，只知毁坏城市、堡垒、土地及人民，他们都只求自己的利益。但列那和他的亲友却都想为他们的主争荣誉、争利益，聪明的参议在这里是比赞美与夸口更有益的。列那这样做，他却没有得到谢意。最后，人会明白谁是最好，做了最多的好事的。我主，你说他的亲友们都离去他，因他的奸诈而不与接近。我主，我可以设法使你知道列那的亲友们。有许多的他们，肯为列那之故给他以生命及财产，我自己就是一个。我是一个妇人。如果他需要，我将以我的生命及财产给他。我还有三个孩子，他们都勇敢强壮，我可以叫他们为他之故而冒险，我不欲见他灭亡。”

33

他又说道：“我的主，我求你留意。这个谎言贼有一次又曾不忠实地骗辱了我的妻。事情是如此：在一个冬天，他与我的妻同行过一片大水。他告诉我的妻说，他可以教她用尾巴来钓鱼，并说，她如把尾巴挂在水下多时，便可以有许多鱼附在尾巴上，这些鱼，他们四个都吃不了。这个傻子，我的妻，居然以为他说的是真话。她在泥泽中走着，到了水的深处，狐叫她把尾巴放下，鱼自然会来的。她把尾巴放下了许久，后来竟坚固地冻结在冰上了，她不能把它拔起，当他见了便跃在她身上。唉！我不忍说出这恶贼如何污辱她的情形，她不能抵抗他，她深陷在泥泽中。这事，他万不能否认，因为这是我亲眼见到的。当时，我正在河岸上走着，见他正伏在我妻的背上，她咆哮地叫着。唉，那时我心上是如何的痛苦呀！我已失了神智，高声大叫道：‘列那，你在那里做什么？’当他见我走得这样近，便跳了下来，走开去了。我悲愁地向她走去，在泥中水中走着，然后去打破了冰块，她受了许多苦才把尾巴从冰上拔出，且还留一段尾巴在冰上。但我们的苦还未受完呢。她咆哮得极响，震动了的乡村中的人都执着种种木棒武器出来了，他们怒声叫道：‘杀死！杀死！打死他们！’我生平没有这样的恐惧过，我们几乎失去了性命。我们竭力奔逃得浑身出汗。一个人用长枪刺伤了我们，他又强壮又跑得快。如果不是天色晚了，我们一定会被杀了。后来，我们跑到了丛林的地方，躲在林中，他们因为夜晚了，才不敢再追，各各回家了。我的主，这种的谋害，奸计，你必须为我们主持公道！”

列那答道：“如果这些话是真的，那么我的名誉太污下了。上帝禁止这事成为真的！我叫她到一个地方去捉鱼，这是真的，我指给她一条好路，叫她不要走入泥中。但她听见了有鱼时，便没命地跑，并不由正路走，却到了冰上，因此被冻住了。如果她不贪心，一定可以得了好些鱼，且不会受苦的。这是常有的事，一个人要得到一切，反而失去了一切。过度的贪心，绝没有好结果。当时，我见她被冰冻住了，便去帮助她出来，但枉自费尽了力，因为她身子太重，我不能拖得动。那时恰好依赛格林来了，他由上望下，眼睛花了，其实我决无别的举动。他叫着骂着我，我只好走开了，让他去骂。于是他自己去把他的妻救出，他们一跳一跳地去取暖去了。这就是一切经过的事，没有一句谎话。如果你还有什么疑惑，给我八日的期限，我可以给你许多充足的证据看。狼他自己是一个欺蔑妇人的、凶恶的坏汉子，却反说着我。现在试问他的妻，究竟他的话对不对。如果她说真话，一定会和我说的一样。”

于是狼的妻说道：“唉，恶列那，没有人敢和你接近——你的谎话说得太像了，但结果你将要受罚的！有一次，你使我入了一口井，几乎使我丧了命。井口上有两只篮子，挂在绳的两端，绳则挂在一个滑车上，如果一只篮下去了一只篮便升上来，你那时坐在一只篮上，落于井中，心里十分惊慌。我恰好走近了井边，闻见你的叹声，便问你为何到井里去。你说那里有许多好鱼吃，你的肚子都吃得饱胀了。我说道：‘告诉我怎么能下去。’于是你说道：‘婶母，你跳在挂在那里的篮中，便可以立刻到我这里来了。’我依你的话跳下篮子，我沉了下去，你却升上来了！我于是生气起来。你却说道：‘一个升起来，一个沉下去，那正是世界上的常道！’于是你跳出井口，自己走去了——我独自坐在井中，坐了一个整天，愁苦着，饥饿着，寒冷着，在我出井之前，还受了许多下的打。”

狐道：“婶母，你挨了打，却救了我，但我却给你一个好教训，下一次你万不能过于仓促地相信别人，不管他是朋友还是亲戚，因为每个人都是求他自己的利益的。如果有生命危险而不肯骗人以自救，那么，他一定是个傻子。”

34

母狼道：“我的主，你听听他的话！”狼道：“他还有许多次使我受了危害。他有一次向他的婶母，母猴，卖了我。我受了大惊惶，几乎全只耳朵都落在那里了。现在叫狐自己把这事告诉出来，看他如何说谎，我先说，他又要以巧辩来掩饰了。”

狐道：“好的，我说实话，一句也不多说。他到了林中，告诉我说他十分饥饿，我很可怜他。我说：‘我也觉得饿呢。’于是我们一同走了半天，得不到什么吃的东西。于是他呻吟着，说不能再走了。这时，我见一个大洞，在丛林的密处，我听见洞中有瑟瑟的声音，我不知有什么东西在洞中。于是我说道：‘到那里去看看，也许有什么可以吃的，我知道那里有东西。’他说道：‘非我先知道洞内有什么，即你给我二十镑，我也不爬进去，我想，洞内或有什么可怕的东西。我在那株树下等你，你先爬进去。但须立刻出来，告诉我洞中有什么。你比我机警，绝没有危险的。’看，我的主，这个恶汉，他使我先去挡危险，他自己又大又壮，却平安地在旁观着。我只得勇敢地走进去。洞内黑暗而阔大，我走了一段路，到了洞的那边，见在光明中一个大猴躺在那里，两只大眼睛如火焰似的。她的大嘴中长着长牙，足上手上都是尖爪。我没有见过这样可怕的兽。在她身边，躺着三个小猴，也和他们的母亲一个模样。当他们见了我时，都不动地望着我。我害怕起来，后悔不该进来，但我却想道：‘已经进来了，必须设法平安地出去。’我见她比依赛格林狼还大，她的孩子们比我还大。我只好低头下心地说好话，我说道：‘婶母，上帝给你好日子，你的好孩子们都好！他们真是美，真是可爱！每个都是王子一样。我一听见你生产了，所以立刻跑来看你。’她说道：‘列那，欢迎你来！你居然会找到这里来，谢谢你！你必须把你的聪明教给我孩子们一点，使他们知道应做的事。’呵，我听了她的话真是快活！这值得我开头叫她为婶母；实则我与她毫无亲戚关系，我的真婶母乃是前面站着的绿克娜夫人。当时，我说道：‘婶母，我极愿意把所知的都教给他们。’说完了话，我便动身要走。她说道：‘吃完了饭再走吧。’于是她站起来，领我到别一洞里，那里有许多的吃的东西。我吃饱了之后，她还把一块肉给我带回家去。我由原路出来，见依赛格林躺在那里呻吟。他说道：‘好侄儿，有吃的东西没有？我要饿死了！’于是我很可怜他，把带来的肉给他，因此救了他的命。那时他向我千恩万谢，谁知他现在倒反对我了呢？他很快地把肉吃下了，然后他问道：‘列那，你在洞里得到了什么？我现在比以前更饿得慌！我的齿现在格外尖利的要咬东西。’我道：‘叔叔，你进洞去，可以得到好多东西吃。洞里住的是我的婶母和她的孩子们。如果你能藏了真情，编了一片大谎，你便可以得到许多吃的。但你如果说了真心话，你将要受苦的。’我的主，我不是如此的警告过他么？谁知粗鲁的兽类，全不懂得机警。他一见了他们，便惊得叫起来道：‘唉，简直是从地狱出来的，真可怕！我怕得根根毛都耸竖起来了。’她说道：‘依赛格林先生，他们是我的孩子们。他们生得好丑，与你何关？刚才来的一位就比你好得多，聪明得多了。谁叫你来的？’他道：‘夫人，我要吃东西。’她道：‘这里没有东西。’他道：‘这里有不少。’于是他直向贮物的洞中走去。我的婶母便带了孩子们奔到他面前，用长爪把他抓得血从眼中流下。我听见他痛楚地咆哮着，又见他飞奔出洞。他浑身都是伤，一只耳朵几乎全失去了。他向我诉苦，我问他说了谎没有。他道：‘我照直地说。’我道：‘不，叔叔，你不应该这样说，你应该说她的孩子们如何的好看，如何的可爱。你照直说，挨打是活该。有的时候，你要晓得，谎话要比真话好。他们比我们聪明的比我们强壮的都是如此地做的。’现在我主请你问他，事情是不是如此。”

37

母猴对狐说道：“列那侄儿，你在决斗时必须留心，要冷静机警。你的叔叔，告诉过我一首祷词，在战前唱祷极有效力。他说，谁要虔诚地念着祷词，那日出战，必定不会为人所败。明早，我要为你祷念——那么，你一定可以胜了狼了。决斗总比绞死好。”

狐道：“我谢你，亲爱的婶母。这次决斗，我是对的——所以我希望能有公道的结局。”

这一夜，所有他的亲友都来陪伴他。

母猴绿克娜夫人常常为他的福利着想。她把他的毛发弄得光顺；她用橄榄油擦他的全身；如此，他的身体是又光又滑，狼不能握住了他，他的身体真是胖，直成了圆圆的。

她对他道：“好侄儿，你现在可以多喝些，决斗时格外有精神。时候到了时，你可以用你松散的尾巴打他，如果你能打到他的眼睛，他便看不清东西，更容易赢他了。但以后，你的尾巴须常夹在两腿间，使他不至捉住你；你的两只耳朵也须平贴在头上，使他不会握住；处处须自己留心。开头你逃避他的打击，叫他跳着跑着追你；你要跑到多灰土的地方用足把灰土拨飞起来，使它飞到他眼中，益发使他看不清东西。当他去擦眼时，你却窥便尽力打他；常常用你的尾巴打他的脸。引他追随你后面，要使他疲倦。他的足还创痛着，且他虽然强大有力，却丝毫没有心计。侄儿，我的话就是如此。技巧胜过强力。所以你自己留心，机警防护自己，你和我们便都可以得最后的荣誉了。如果你失败了，我真要忧愁不已！侄儿，现在你放宽了心去休息，我们会叫醒你的。”

狐道：“婶母，我现在快活了，上帝谢你！你如此看待我，我下次真不配再受你的了。”

于是他去躺在一株树下的绿草上睡了，一直睡到太阳升上来时才醒来。于是水獭来叫醒他，给他一只胖小鸭吃，说道：“好兄弟，我昨夜跳入水中许多次，才得到这只胖小鸭。这是从一个养鸭人那里捉来的，拿去吃了吧。”

列那道：“这真是好赐品。如果我拒绝了，我必是一个傻子了。我谢谢你。兄弟，你还记念住我。如果我活着，我将报答你。”

狐吃了鸭，没有汤也没有面包。这鸭很好吃，他还喝了四大口水。然后他到决斗场上去，所有爱他的，全都跟了他去。

40

狼揩擦他的眼，狐见了很高兴。狼擦眼时，狐却乘势挣扎，跳起身来。狼赶快地去捉他的足，在他未逃去之前，不管自己流着血，还把他紧捉住。狼恼怒极了，忘了一切的痛苦，把狐直压在身下。

于是狼对狐道：“现在你声明自己是失败了，不然，我一定要杀你了。你现在什么伎俩都无用了。你不能逃开我了。你以前污辱我，谋害我许多次，现在你还使我失了一只眼，且使我浑身都是伤。”

列那听了这话，他迟疑了许久，不知是承认失败好呢，还是被杀死好呢。他知道二者之中必须取一，但不久，他便决定要说的话，于是说了许多好话：“叔叔，我很快乐地把我的财宝都给你，我成了你的人。我要为你到圣陵去，代你祷告。我永久是你的奴隶，我的亲属们也都给你差遣。那时，你将成了主上之主。什么人还敢反抗你呢？此后，我无论捉到了鸡鸭或得到了鱼肉，一定先给你拣选，还要先给你的妻及你的孩子们。我永远给你差遣，你可以永不会再有危害了。你有力，我机智，我们二人在一处，一个出主意，一个去做，再不会有错失的事发生了，且我们的种族相近，不应互相仇视。如果我昨天能避开，我一定不会和你决斗的。但那是你先要决斗的，于是我不得不去做这件不欲做的事。且在这次决斗中，我对你很客气，我没有用全力对付你，因为侄儿应该让叔叔的。好叔叔，你看我总是避了你，且我可以重伤你而我不肯。你的眼坏了，唉！我心里很难过！好叔叔，我愿意我的眼瞎了，不是你的！然而你此后也可以有大利益，因为你以后睡时只要闭上一只，别的人却须闭上两只！我的妻子，我的同类，都要跪在国王之前，你之前，以及你的人之前，恳求你赦了你的侄列那的命。我也将声明以前种种的不对，以及种种说你的话都是谎话。我给你这种光荣是比之给国王的还大些，所以我求你以后可以快快活活了。我知道，你如果杀我，立刻可以杀。但你如果杀了我，你得到了什么？你此后必须远离开我的朋友和亲戚了。聪明的人，愤怒要有限量，做事不可过急，且会仔细打算以后的事。许多愚人常因做事过快而后悔，但那时已经太迟了。好叔叔，我知道你是聪明人，会打算的。荣誉、赞美、安息、平和，以及许多预备帮助你的朋友，是比之羞辱、损害、不安，以及许多以后欲乘机复仇的仇人们好的。并且，已经打胜了人，又去杀他，是没有什么名誉的。这是大耻辱，并不是因为我的性命——我死了，不值得什么。”

依赛格林道：“呵，贼，你还要以美言逃了我，以为我可以听你的话！虽然你答应把全世界的好黄金都给了我，我也不能放了你，你所说的全都是谎话。你想以此欺骗我么？我早已知道你了，我不是容易捉的鸟。我很知道无危险的好谷或罗网中的谷。唉！如果我这样让你逃去了，你将如何的讥笑我呀！你可以把这一套话说给不知道你的去听，但对我说，你的甘言巧语却失掉效力了，因为我太明白你的谎话了。你骗我的次数太多，我现在必要留心你了。你这狡贼，你说你这次决斗，宽赦我好几次！看着我！我的一只眼睛不是被你挖出来么？我的头上还被你伤了二十次。你简直紧紧地逼我，不让我呼吸一下。我如果赦了你，真要算是一个傻子了。你羞辱我及我挚爱的妻多少次，我一想起来，我的心便充满了恨怒，想要复仇。”

当依赛格林说话时，狐已在想自救之法。他暗中挣扎，脱出一只手来，把狼的睾丸紧紧地捏住。狼痛楚极了，大叫起来，狐乘势又脱出一只手来。

42

狐道：“我高贵亲爱的主，我十分满意。但当初我到你宫中来时，有许多恶人嫉妒我，我却永不曾害过他们。他们都帮了我的仇人反对我，都要除去了我以为快，因为他们想依赛格林在你那里比我的地位高得多。他们不知别的了。

“我的主，这正如我有一次在一个爵士地方所看见的一大群猎犬。他们聚在那里，等人来带东西给他们吃。后来，他们见一只猎犬由厨房中跑出来，衔着一块肥牛排，那是偷来的，他跑得极快，但厨子在他未逃远之前，把一大碗滚热的水，泼倒在他背上，使他的毛都落了。但他终于逃出，衔着偷到的东西。

“当他的朋友们及别的猎犬见了他衔了这块肥牛排出来，他们都对他说道：‘呵，厨子与你的交情真好，他给你这么好的一块牛排，上面有那么多的肉！’

“那只猎犬说道：‘你们不知道什么事。你们赞美我的前面，因为衔了肉。但你们没有见到我的背后。请留心，请看我的背上，然后你们就可以知道我是怎么取得这块肉的了。’

“当他们见了他背上被滚水烫脱的毛与烂肉，他们全都叫了起来，害怕那开水，他们不同他做朋友了。飞逃了开去，留他一个在那里。

“我的主，你看，这正是这一班恶贼的情形。当他们为爵主时，为所欲为，有力有威，抢夺百姓们的，吃食百姓们的，正如一群饥饿的猎犬一样，这正是他们衔了肥肉在口之时。没有人不赞颂他们，不恭敬他们。有的还助他们为暴，从中染指。唉，我的主！他们简直没有看见他们的背后，没有看见他们最后的结局。他们受了大羞大辱，由高跌到低，然后他们的暴行才为大家所知，没有人可怜他们，没有人理会他们。至于他们的朋友呢，就如那一班猎犬们，一见他受害了，便一个个地离开了，留下他一个在忧苦中。

“我的主，我求你记住我这个比喻。这些日子，这种恶人真多——他们所做的坏事，比之猎犬偷骨还甚些——他们压迫可怜的人民卖去他们的自由与特权，只为了一己的利益。愿上帝给他们以羞辱，且立刻把他们都除去了，不管他们是谁！

“谢谢上帝，我及我的亲属却都还光明，不做恶事。我亲爱的主，我全心全意爱你比一切爵主都甚，谁都不能离间我，我永远地听你的命令。”

CHAPTER III

WHEN these words were spoken, so stood there a little Hound and was named Courtoys, and complained to the King, how that in the cold winter in the hard frost he had been sore forwintered, in such wise as he had kept no more meat than a pudding, which pudding Reynart the Fox had taken away from him.

With this so came Tybert the Cat, with an irous(1) mood, and sprang in among them, and said:“My Lord the King, I here hear that Reynart is sore complained on, and here is none but that he has enough to do to clear himself. That Courtoys here complaines of, that is passed many years gone, howbeit, that I complain not; that pudding was mine, for I had won it by night in a mill. The miller lay and slept. If Courtoys had any part hereon, that came by me too.”

Tho spake Panther,“Think you, Tybert, that it were good that Reynart should not be complained on? He is a very murderer, a rover, and a thief, he loves no man so well, not our Lord the King here, but that he well would that he should lose good and worship, so that he might win as much as a leg of a fat hen. I shall tell you what I saw him do yesterday to Cuwart the Hare, that here stands in the King's peace and safeguard. He promised to Cuwart and said he would teach him his Credo, and make him a good chaplain. He made him go sit between his legs, and sang and cried loud,‘Credo, Credo!’My way lay thereby there that I heard this song. Tho went I near and found Master Reynart that had left that he first read and sang, and began to play his old play. For he had caught Cuwart by the throat, and had I not that time come he should have taken his life from him, like as you here may see on Cuwart the Hare the fresh wound yet. Forsooth, my Lord the King, if you suffer this unpunished, and let him go quit that has thus broken your peace, and will do no right after the sentence and judgment of your men, your children many years hereafter shall be misprised and blamed therefor.”

“Sikerly, Panther,”said Esegrim,“you say truth. It were good that right and justice were done, for them that would fain live in peace.”

————————————————————

(1) Irous, angry.

CHAPTER IV

THEN spake Grymbart the Dasse, and was Reynart's sister's son, with an angry mood.

“Sir Esegrim that is evil said. It is a common proverb an enemy's mouth says seldom well. What lie you and wite(1) you my Eme(2) Reynart? I would that you would adventure that who of you two had most trespassed to other should hang by the neck as a thief on a tree. But and if he were as well in this court and as well with the King as you be, it should not be thought in him that it were enough that you should come and ask him forgiveness; you have bitten and nipped my uncle with your fell and sharp teeth many more times than I can tell. Yet will I tell some points that I well know. Know not you how you misdealed on the plaice which he threw down from the car, when you followed after from afar, and you ate the good plaice alone, and gave him no more than the grate or bones which you might not eat yourself. In like wise did you to him also of the fat flitch of bacon which savoured so well that you alone ate it in your belly, and when my Eme asked his part tho answered you him again in scorn,‘Reynart, fair youngling, I shall gladly give you your part’—but my Eme got nor had nought, nor was not the better. Notwithstanding he had won the flitch of bacon with great dread, for the man came and threw him in a sack that he scarcely came out with his life. Such manner things has Reynart many times suffered through Esegrim. O you lordes, think you that this is good? Yet is there more. He complaines how that Reynart my Eme has much trespassed to him by cause of his wife. My Eme has lain by her, but that is well seven years before, ere he wedded her; and if Reynart for love and courtesy did with her his will, what was that? She was soon healed thereof. Hereof by right should be no complaint, were Esegrim wise. He should have believed that he does to himself no worship thus to slander his wife. She plaines not. Now makes Cuwart the Hare a complaint also. That thinks me a vyseuase.(3) If he read nor learned aright his lesson, should not Reynart his master beat him therefor? If the scholars were not beaten nor smitten and reprised(4) of their truantry, they should never learn. Now complaines Courtoys that he with pain had gotten a pudding in the winter, at such time as the cost(5) is evil to find. Thereof him had be better to have held his peace, for he had stolen it. Male quæsisti et male perdidisti. It is right that it be evil lost that is evil won. Who shall blame Reynart if he have taken from a thief stolen good. It is reason. Who that understands the law, and can discern the right, and that he be of high birth as my Eme Reynart is, knows well how he shall reserve stolen good. Yet all had he Courtoys hanged when he found him with the menour(6) he had not much misdone nor trespassed, save against the Crown, that he had done justice without leave. Wherefore for the honour of the King he did it not, all has he but little thanks. What scathed it him that he is thus complained on? My Eme is a gentle and true man. He may suffer no falsehood. He does nothing but by his priest's counsel. And I say you, since that my lord the King has do proclaim(7) his peace, he never thought to hurt any man; for he eats no more than once a day; he lives as a recluse; he chastises his body, and wears a shirt of hair; it is more than a year that he has eaten no flesh. As I yesterday heard say of them that came from him he has left and given over his Castle Maleperdays and has builded a cluse; therein dwells he and hunts no more nor desires no winning, but he lives by alms and takes nothing but such as men give him for charity, and does great penance for his sins, and he is waxen much pale and lean of praying and waking, for he would be fain with God.”

Thus as Grymbart his Eme stood and preached these words, so saw they coming down the hill to them Chanticleer the Cock and brought on a bier a dead hen of whom Reynart had bitten the head off, and that must be showed to the King for to have knowledge thereof.

————————————————————

(1) Wite, blame.

(2) Eme, uncle.

(3) Vyseuase, wish-wash.

(4) Reprised, reprehended.

(5) Cost, food (kost).

(6) With the menour, in the very act, i.e., with the thing stolen in his hands.

(7) Has do proclaim, has caused to be proclaimed.

CHAPTER V

CHANTICLEER came forth and smote piteously his hands and his feathers; and on each side of the bier went two sorrowful hens, that one was called Cantart and that other good hen Crayant, they were two the fairest hens that were between Holland and Arderne. These hens bare each of them a burning taper which was long and straight. These two hens were Coppen's sisters, and they cried so piteously“Alas and weleaway”for the death of their dear sister Coppen. Two young hens bare the bier, which cackled so heavily and wept so loud for the death of Coppen their mother, that it was very hard. Thus came they together before the King.

And Chanticleer tho said,“Merciful lord, my lord the King, please it you to hear our complaint and abhor the great scathe that Reynart has done to me and my children that here stand. It was so that in the beginning of April, when the weather is fair, as that I, as hardy and proud because of the great lineage that I am come of and also had, for I had eight fair sons and seven fair daughters which my wife had hatched, and they were all strong and fat, and went in a yard which was walled round about, in which was a shed wherein were six great dogs which had tore and plucked many a beast's skin in such wise as my children were not afraid. On whom Reynart the thief had great envy because they were so sure that he could none get of them; how well often has this fell thief gone round about this wall and has laid for us in such wise that the dogs have be set on him and have hunted him away; and once they leapt on him upon the bank, and that cost him somewhat for his theft, I saw that his skin smoked. Nevertheless he went his way. God amend it!

“Thus were we quit of Reynart a long while. At last came he in likeness of an hermit, and brought to me a letter for to read, sealed with the King's seal, in which stood written that the King had made peace over all in his realm, and that all manner beasts and fowls should do none harm nor scathe to any other. Yet said he to me more that he was a cloisterer or a closed recluse become, and that he would receive great penance for his sins. He showed me his slavyne and pylche(1) and an haired shirt thereunder, and then said he,‘sir Chanticleer after this time be no more afraid of me, nor take no heed, for I now will eat no more flesh. I am further so old that I would fain remember my soul. I will now go forth, for I have yet to say my sixth, none, and my evensong. To God I betake(2) you.’Tho went Reynart thence, saying his Credo, and laid him under an hawthorn. Then I was glad and merry, and also took none heed, and went to my children and clucked them together, and went without the wall for to walk; whereof is much harm come to us, for Reynart lay under a bush and came creeping between us and the gate, so that he caught one of my children and laid him in his male.(3) Whereof we have great harm, for since he has tasted of him there might never hunter nor hound save nor keep him from us. He has waited by night and day in such wise that he has stolen so many of my children that of fifteen I have but four, in such wise has this thief forslongen(4) them. And yet yesterday was Coppen my daughter, that here lies upon the bier, with the hounds rescued. This complain I to you, gracious King, have pity on my great and unreasonable damage and loss of my fair children!”

————————————————————

(1) Slavyne and pylche, old shoes (Dutch, sloffen) and skincoat.

(2) Betake, commend, entrust.

(3) Male, bag, wallet.

(4) Forslongen (verschlungen), swallowed.

CHAPTER VI

THEN spake the King:

“Sir Dasse, hear you this well of the recluse of your Eme? He has fasted and prayed, that if I live a year he shall abye(1) it. Now hark, Chanticleer, your plaint is enough. Your daughter that lies here dead, we will give to her the death's rite. We may keep her no longer, we will betake her to God. We will sing her vigil and bring her worshipfully on earth, and then we will speak with these lords and take counsel how we may do right and justice of this great murder, and bring this false thief to the law.”

Tho began they Placebo domino, with the verses that to longen,(2) which if I should say were me too long. When this vigil was done and the commendation, she was laid in the pit, and there upon her was laid a marble stone polished as clear as any glass, and thereon was hewn in great letters in this wise: COPPE CHANTEKLERS DOUGHTER, WHOM REYNART THE FOX HAS BYTEN, LYETH HIER VNDER BURYED, COMPLAYNE YOU HER FFOR, SHE IS SHAMEFULLY COME TO HER DETH.

After this, the King sent for his lords and the wisest of his council for to take advice how this great murder and trespass should be punished on Reynart the Fox. There was concluded and appointed for the best that Reynart should be sent for, and that he left not for any cause, but he came into the King's court for to hear what should be said to him; and that Bruin the Bear should do the message.

The King thought that all this was good and said to Bruin the Bear,“Sir Bruin, I will that you do this message; but see well to for yourself, for Reynart is a shrew, and fell,(3) and knows so many wiles that he shall lie and flatter, and shall think how he may beguile, deceive, and bring you to some mockery.”

Then said Bruin,“What, good lord, let it alone! Deceives me the Fox, so have I ill learned my casus. I think he shall come too late to mock me.”

Thus departed Bruin merrily from thence, but it is to dread that he came not so merrily again.

————————————————————

(1) Abye, pay for.

(2) To longen, belong thereto.

(3) Fell, cruel.

CHAPTER VII

NOW is Bruin gone on his way toward the Fox with a stout mood, which supposed well that the Fox should not have beguiled him. As he came in a dark wood in a forest whereas Reynart had a bypath when he was hunted, there beside was an high mountain and land, and there must Bruin in the middle goon over for to go to Maleperdays. For Reynart had many a dwelling-place, but the Castle of Maleperdays was the best and the fastest burgh that he had. There lay he in when he had need, and was in any dread or fear. Now when Bruin was come to Maleperdays, he found the gate fast shut. Tho went he before the gate, and sat upon his tail, and called,“Reynart, be you at home? I am Browning. The King has sent me for you that you should come to Court, for to plead your cause. He has sworn there by his God, come you not, or bring I you not with me, for to abide such right and sentence as shall be there given, it shall cost you your life. He will hang you or set you on the rack. Reynart, do by my counsel, and come to the Court.”

Reynart lay within the gate, as he oft was wont to do, for the warmth of the sun. When Reynart heard Bruin, tho went he inward into his hole. For Maleperdays was full of holes, here one hole and there another, and yonder another, narrow, crooked and long, with many ways to go out, which he opened and shut after that he had need. When he had any prey brought home, or that he wist that any sought him for his misdeeds and trespasses, then he ran and hid him from his enemies into his secret chambers, that they could not find him; by which he deceived many a beast that sought him. And tho thought Reynard in himself how he might best bring the Bear in charge and need, and that he abode in worship.

In this thought Reynart came out, and said,“Bruin, Eme, you be welcome! I heard you well before, but I was in my evensong, therefore have I the longer tarried a little. Dear Eme, he has done to you no good service, and I con him no thank,(1) that has sent you over this long hill; for I see that you be also weary, that the sweat runs down by your cheeks. It was no need I had nevertheless come to Court to-morrow: but I sorrow now the less, for your wise counsel shall well help me in the Court. And could the King find none less messenger but you for to send hither? That is great wonder. For next the King you be the most gentle, and richest of levies and of land. I would well that we were now at the Court, but I fear me that I shall not con well go thither, for I have eaten so much new meat that me thinks my belly will break or cleave asunder, and because the meat was new I ate the more.”

Tho spake the Bear,“Lief Neve,(2) what meat have you eaten that maked you so full?”

“Dear Eme, that I ate, what might it help you that if I told you? I ate but simple meat. A poor man is no lord, that may you know, Eme, by me. We poor folk must eat often such as we gladly would not eat if we had better. They were great honey combs; which I must needs eat for hunger. They have made my belly so great that I can nowhere endure.”

Bruin then spake anon,“Alas, Reynart, what say you! Set you so little by honey? Me ought to prize and love it above all meat. Lief Reynart, help me that I might get a deal of this honey, and as long as I live I shall be to you a true friend, and abide by you, as far as you help me that I may have a part of this honey.”

————————————————————

(1) Con him no thank. To can or con thank was an old phrase for acknowledgment of thanks due.

(2) Lief neve, dear nephew.

CHAPTER VIII

“BRUIN, Eme, I had supposed that you had japed(1) therewith.”

“So help me God, Reynart, nay. I should not gladly jape with you.”

Then spake the red Reynart,“Is it then earnest, that you love so well the honey? I shall do let you have so much that ten of you should not eat it at one meal, might I get therewith your friendship.”

“Not we ten, Reynart Neve!”said the Bear.“How should that be? Had I all the honey that is between this and Portugal I should well eat it alone.”

Reynart said,“What say you, Eme? Hereby dwells an husbandman named Lantfert, which has so much honey that you should not eat in seven years; which you shall have in your hold if you will be to me friendly and helping against my enemies in the King's Court.”

Then promised Bruin the Bear to him, that if he might have his belly full he would truly be to him before all other a faithful friend.

Hereof laughed Reynart the shrew,(2) and said,“If you would have seven hamper barrels full I shall well get them and help you to have them.”These words pleased the Bear so well, and made him so much to laugh that he could not well stand.

Tho thought Reynart,“This is good luck; I shall lead him thither that he shall laugh by measure.”

Reynart said then,“This matter may not be long tarried. I must pain myself for you. You shall well understand the very yonste(3) and good will that I bear to you ward. I know none in all my lineage that I now would labour for thus sore.”

That thanked him the Bear and thought he tarried long.“Now, Eme, let us go a good pace, and follow you me. I shall make you to have as much honey as you may bear.”The Fox meant, of good strokes; but the caitiff marked not what the Fox meant; and they went so long together, that they came unto Lantfert's yard. Tho was sir Bruin merry.

Now hark of Lantfert. Is it true that men say, so was Lantfert a strong carpenter of great timber, and had brought that other day before into his yard a great oak, which he had begun to cleave. And as men be woned(4) he had smitten two betels(5) therein one after that other, in such wise the oak was wide open. Whereof Reynart was glad, for he had found it right as he wished, and said to the Bear all laughing,“See now well sharply to! In this tree is so much honey that it is without measure. Assay if you can come therein, and eat but little, for though the honeycombs be sweet and good, yet beware that you eat not too many, but take of them by measure, that you catch no harm in your body; for, sweet Eme, I should be blamed if they did you any harm.”

“What, Reynart, cousin, sorrow you not for me! Ween you that I were a fool?”

“Measure is good in all meat,”Reynart said.“You say truth. Wherefore should I sorrow? Go to the end and creep therein.”

Bruin the Bear hasted sore toward the honey, and trode in with his two foremost feet, and put his head over his ears into the clift of the tree. And Reynart sprang lightly and brake out the betle of the tree. Tho helped the Bear neither flattering nor chiding; he was fast shut in the tree. Thus has the Neve, with deceit, brought his Eme in prison in the tree, in such wise as he could not get out with might nor with craft, head nor foot.

What profits Bruin the Bear that he strong and hardy is? That may not help him. He saw well that he was beguiled. He began to howl, and to bray, and crutched with the hinder feet, and made such a noise and rumour, that Lantfert came out hastily, and knew nothing what this might be, and brought in his hand a sharp hook. Bruin the Bear lay in the clift of the tree, in great fear and dread, and held fast his head, and nipped both his fore feet. He wrang, he wrestled, and cried, and all was for naught. He wist not how he might get out.

Reynart the Fox saw from far how that Lantfert the carpenter came, and tho spake Reynart to the Bear,“Is that honey good? How is it now? Eat not too much, it should do you harm; you should not then well con go to the Court. When Lantfert comes, if you have well eaten he shall give you better to drink, and then it shall not stick in your throat.”

After these words tho turned him Reynart toward his castle, and Lantfert came and found the Bear fast taken in the tree. Then ran he fast to his neighbours and said,“Come all in to my yard, there is a bear taken!”The word anon sprang over all in the thorp. There nor bleef(6) neither man nor wife, but all ran thither as fast as they could, every one with his weapon, some with a staff, some with a rake, some with a broom, some with a stake of the hedge, and some with a flail; and the priest of the church had the staff of the cross, and the clerk brought a vane. The priest's wife Julocke came with her distaff, —she sat tho and span, —there came old women that for age had not one tooth in their head.

Now was Bruin the Bear nigh much sorrow that he alone must stand against them all. When he heard all this great noise and cry he wrestled and plucked so hard and so sore that he got out his head. But he left behind all the skin and both his ears, in such wise that never man saw fouler nor loather beast, for the blood ran over his eyes. And or he could get out his feet he must lete(7) there his claws or nails and this rough hand. This market came to him evil, for he supposed never to have gone, his feet were so sore, and he might not see for the blood which ran so over his eyes.

Lantfert came to him with the priest, and forthwith all the parish, and began to smite and strike sore upon his head and visage. He received there many a sore stroke. Every man beware hereby: who has harm and scathe, every man will be thereat and put more to. That was well seen on the Bear, for they were all fierce and wroth on the Bear, great and small, yea Hughelyn with the crooked leg, and Ludolf with the broad long nose, they were both wroth. That one had a leaden malle, and that other a great leaden wapper, therewith they wappered and all forslingered(8) him, Sir Bertolt with the long fingers, Lantfert, and Ottram the long. This did to the Bear more harm than all the other, that one had a sharp hook and the other a crooked staff well leaded on the end for to play at the ball. Baetkyn and Aue, Abelquak, my dame Baue, and the priest with his staff, and dame Julocke his wife, these worked to the Bear so much harm that they would fain have brought him from his life to death, they smote and stack him all that they could.

Bruin the Bear sat and sighed and groaned, and must take such as was given to him. But Lantfert was the worthiest of birth of them all, and made most noise; for dame Pogge of Chafporte was his mother, and his father was Macob the stoppelmaker, a much stout man. There as he was alone Bruin received of them many a cast of stones. Before them all sprang first Lantfert's brother with a staff, and smote the Bear on the head that he nor heard nor saw; and therewith the Bear sprang up between the bush and the river among a heap of wives, that he threw a deal of them in the river, which was wide and deep.

There was the parson's wife one of them, wherefore he was full of sorrow when he saw his wife lie in the water. He lusted no longer to smite the Bear, but called,“Dame Julocke in the water! Now every man see to, All they that may help her! Be they men or women, I give to them all pardon of their penance, and release all their sins!”All they then left Bruin the Bear lie, and did that the priest bade.

When Bruin the Bear saw that they ran all from him, and ran to save the women, tho sprang he into the water and swam all that he could. Then made the priest a great shout and noise, and ran after the Bear with great anger, and said,“Come and turn again, thou false thief!”The Bear swam after the best of the stream and let them call and cry, for he was glad that he was so escaped from them. He cursed and banned the honey tree, and the Fox also that had so betrayed him that he had crept therein so deep that he lost both his hood and his ears. And so forth he drove in the stream well a two or three mile. Tho wax he so weary that he went to land for to sit and rest him, for he was heavy; he groaned and sighed, and the blood leapt over his eyes, he drew his breath like as one should have died.

Now hark how the Fox did. Ere he came from Lantfert's house he had stolen a fat hen and had laid her in his male, and ran hastily away by a byou path where he weened that no man should have come. He ran toward the river, that he sweat, he was so glad that he wist not what to do for joy, for he hoped that the Bear had been dead. He said,“I have now well sped, for he that should most have hindered me in the Court is now dead, and none shall wite(9) me thereof, may I not, then, by right be well glad?”With these words the Fox looked to the riverward, and espied where Bruin the Bear lay and rested him. Tho was the Fox sorrier and heavier than before was merry, and was as angry, and said in chiding to Lantfert,“Alas, Lantfert, lewd fool! God give him a shames death that has lost such good venison, which is good and fat, and has let him go which was taken to his hand! Many a man would gladly have eaten of him. He has lost a rich and fat Bear.”Thus all chiding he came to the river, where he found the Bear sore wounded, bled, and right sick, which he might thank none better thereof than Reynart, which he spake to the Bear in scorn:“Chiere priestre, Dieu vous garde! Will you see the red thief?”

Said the Bear to himself,“The ribald and the fell deer,(10) here I see him coming.”

Then said the Fox,“Have you aught forgotten at Lantfert's? Have you also paid him for the honeycombs that you stole from him? If you have not, it were a great shame, and not honest; I will rather be the messenger myself for to go and pay him. Was the honey not good? I know yet more of the same prize. Dear Eme, tell me ere I go hence into what order will you go that wear this new hood? Were you a monk or an abbot? He that shaved your crown has nipped off your ears, you have lost your top and don off your gloves, I think verily that you will go sing compline.”

All this heard Bruin the Bear, and waxed all angry, and sorry for he might not avenge him. He let the Fox say his will, and with great pain suffered it, and start again in the river, and swam down with the stream to that other side.

Now must he sorrow how that he should come to the Court, for he had lost his ears and the skin with the claws of his forefeet; for though a man should have slain him he could not go; and yet he must needs forth, but he wist not how.

Now hear how he did. He sat upon his hams and began to rustle over his tail; and when he was so weary, he wentled(11) and tumbled nigh half a mile; this did he with great pain so long till at last he came to the Court. And when he was seen so coming from far, some doubted what it might be that came so wenteling.

The King at last knew him, and was not well paid,(12) and said,“This is Bruin the Bear, my friend! Lord God, who has wounded him thus? He is passing red on his head: me thinks he is hurt unto the death. Where may he have been?”

————————————————————

(1) Japed, jested.

(2) Shrew, malicious deceiver.

(3) Yonste (gunst), favour.

(4) Woned, accustomed.

(5) Betels, heavy mallets used for beating in wedges.

(6) Bleef (blieb), remained.

(7) Lete, leave.

(8) Wappered and forslingered, beat at and overwhelmed with blows. The Low German slingen, to swallow, is to be distinguished from Low German, slingern, the word here.

(9) Wite, blame.

(10) Deer, wild beast.

(11) Wentled, twisted, wriggled round and round. There is a mollusc called for its spiral“wentle-trap”from G. wendel-treppe, a winding staircase.

(12) Paid, satisfied.

CHAPTER X

THEN the King said,“Sir Tybert, you shall now go to Reynart and say to him this second time, that he come to Court unto the plea for to answer; for though he be fell to other beasts, he trusts you well and shall do by your counsel. And tell him if he come not he shall have the third warning and be dayed, and if he then come not, we shall proceed by right against him and all his lineage without mercy.”

Tybert spake,“My lord the King, they that this counselled you were not my friends. What shall I do there? He will not, for me neither, come nor abide. I beseech you, dear King, send some other to him. I am little and feeble. Bruin the Bear, which was so great and strong, could not bring him. How should I then take it on hand?”

“Nay,”said the King,“Sir Tybert, you are wise and well learned. Though you be not great, there lies not on. Many do more with craft and cunning than with might and strength.”

Then said the Cat,“Since it must needs be done, I must then take it upon me. God give grace that I may well achieve it, for my heart is heavy, and evil willed thereto.”

Tybert made him soon ready toward Maleperdays. And he saw from far come flying one of Saint Martin's birds, tho cried he loud and said,“All hail, gentle bird, turn thy wings hitherward, and fly on my right side.”The bird flew forth upon a tree which stood on the left side of the Cat. Tho was Tybert woe; for he thought it was a shrewd token and a sign of harm. For if the bird had flown on his right side he had been merry and glad, but now he sorrowed that his journey should turn to unhappe. Nevertheless he did as many do, and gave to himself better hope than his heart said. He went and ran to Maleperdays ward, and there he found the Fox alone standing before his house.

Tybert said,“The rich God give you good even, Reynart. The King has menaced you for to take your life from you if you come not now with me to the court.”

The Fox tho spake and said,“Tybert, my dear cousin, you be right welcome. I would well truly that you had much good luck.”What hurted the Fox to speak fair. Though he said well, his heart thought it not, and that shall be seen ere they depart.

Reynart said,“Will we this night be together. I will make you good cheer, and to-morrow early in the dawning we will together go to the Court. Good Nephew, let us so do, I have none of my kin that I trust so much to as to you. Here was Bruin the Bear, —the traitor! He looked so shrewdly on me, and methought he was so strong, that I would not for a thousand mark have gone with him; but, cousin, I will to-morrow early go with you.”

Tybert said,“It is best that we now go, for the moon shines all so light as it were day; I never saw fairer weather.”

“Nay, dear cousin, such might meet us by day-time that would make us good cheer and by night peradventure might do us harm. It is suspicious to walk by night. Therefore abide this night here by me.”

Tybert said,“What should we eat if we abode here?”

Reynart said,“Here is but little to eat. You may well have an honeycomb, good and sweet. What say you, Tybert, will you any thereof?”

Tybert answered,“I set nought thereby. Have you nothing else? If you gave me a good fat mouse I should be better pleased.”

“A fat mouse!”said Reynart.“Dear cousin, what say you? Hereby dwells a priest and has a barn by his house; therein are so many mice that a man should not lead them away upon a wain. I have heard the priest many times complain that they did him much harm.”

“Oh, dear Reynart, lead me thither for all that I may do for you!”

“Yea, Tybert, say you me truth? Love you well mice?”

“If I love them well?”said the Cat.“I love mice better than anything that men give me. Know you not that mice savour better than, venison, yea, than flawnes(1) or pasties? Will you well do, so lead me thither where the mice are, and then shall you win my love, yea all had you slain my father, mother, and all my kin.”

Reynart said,“You mock and jape therewith.”

The Cat said,“So help me God, I do not!”

“Tybert,”said the Fox,“wist I that verily, I would yet this night make that you should be full of mice.”

“Reynart!”quoth he,“Full? That were many.”

“Tybert, you jape!”

“Reynart,”quoth he,“in truth I do not. If I had a fat mouse I would not give it for a golden noble.”

“Let us go, then, Tybert,”quoth the Fox,“I will bring you to the place ere I go from you.”

“Reynart,”quoth the Cat,“upon your safe-conduct, I would well go with you to Monpelier.”

“Let us then go,”said the Fox,“we tarry all too long.”

Thus went they forth, without letting(2) to the place whereas they would be, to the Priest's barn, which was fast walled about with a mud wall. And the night before the Fox had broken in, and had stolen from the Priest a good fat hen; and the Priest, all angry, had set a gryn(3) before the hole to avenge him; for he would fain have taken the Fox. This knew well the fell thief, the Fox, and said,“Sir Tybert, cousin, creep into this hole, and you shall not long tarry but that you shall catch mice by great heaps. Hark how they pipe! When you be full, come again; I will tarry here after you before this hole. We will to-morrow go together to the Court. Tybert, why tarry you thus long ? Come off, and so may we return soon to my wife which waiteth after us, and shall make us good cheer.”

Tybert said,“Reynart, cousin, is it then your counsel that I go into this hole? These Priests are so wily and shrewish I dread to take harm.”

“Oh ho, Tybert!”said the Fox,“I saw you never so sore afraid. What ails you?”

The Cat was ashamed, and sprang into the hole. And anon he was caught in the gryn by the neck, ere he wist. Thus deceived Reynart his guest and cousin.

As Tybert was ware of the gryn, he was afraid and sprang forth; the gryn went to. Then he began to wrawen, for he was almost strangled. He called, he cried, and made a shrewd noise.

Reynart stood before the hole and heard all, and was well paid, and said,“Tybert, love you well mice? Be they fat and good? Knew the Priest hereof, or Mertynet, they be so gentle that they would bring you sauce. Tybert, you sing and eat, is that the guise of the Court? Lord God, if Esegrim were there by you, in such rest as you now be, then should I be glad; for oft he has done me scathe and harm.”

Tybert could not go away, but he mawed and galped so loud, that Mertynet sprang up, and cried loud,“God be thanked, my gryn has taken the thief that has stolen our hens. Arise up, we will reward him!”

With these words arose the Priest in an evil time, and waked all them that were in the house, and cried with a loud voice,“The Fox is taken!”

There leapt and ran all that there was. The Priest himself ran, all mother naked. Mertynet was the first that came to Tybert. The Priest took to Locken his wife an offering candle, and bade her light it at the fire, and he smote Tybert with a great staff. There received Tybert many a great stroke over all his body. Mertynet was so angry that he smote the Cat an eyou out. The naked Priest lift up and should have given a great stroke to Tybert, but Tybert that saw that he must die sprang between the Priest's legs with his claws and with his teeth. That leap became ill to the Priest and to his great shame.

When Dame Julocke knew that, she sware by her father's soul, that she would it had cost her all the offering of a whole year, that the Priest had not had that harm, hurt, and shame, and that it had not happened; and said,“In the Devil's name was the gryn there set! See Mertynet, lief son, this is a great shame and to me a great hurt!”The Fox stood without, before the hole, and heard all these words, and laughed so sore that he vnnethe(4) could stand. Thus scorned and mocked the Fox the Priest's wife, Dame Julocke, that was full of sorrow. The Priest fell down aswoon. They took him up, and brought him again to bed. Tho went the Fox again in to his burgh ward and left Tibert the Cat in great dread and jeopardy, for the Fox wist none other but that the Cat was nigh dead. But when Tibert the Cat saw them all busy about the Priest, tho began he to bite and gnaw the gryn in the middle asunder; and sprang out of the hole, and went rolling and wentling towards the King's Court. Ere he came thither it was fair day, and the sun began to rise. And he came to the Court as a poor wight. He had caught harm at the Priest's house by the help and counsel of the Fox. His body was all tobeaten, and blind on the one eye. When the King wist this, that Tibert was thus arrayed, he was sore angry, and menaced Reynart the thief sore, and anon gathered his council to wit what they would advise him, how he might bring the Fox to the law, and how he should be fetched.

Tho spake Sir Grymbart, which was the Fox's sister son, and said,“You lords, though my Eme were twice so bad and shrewish, yet is there remedy enough. Let him be done to as to a free man. When he shall be judged he must be warned the third time for all; and if he come not then, he is then guilty in all the trespasses that have been laid against him and his, or complained on.”

“Grymbart, who would you that should go and dayou him to come? Who will adventure for him his ears, his eye, or his life; which is so fell a beast? I think there is none here so much a fool.”

Grymbart spake,“So help me God, I am so much a fool that I will do this message myself to Reynart, if you will command me.”

————————————————————

(1) Flawnes, custard tarts.

(2) Letting, hindrance.

(3) Gryn, snare or trap. A word used by Chaucer.

(4) Vnnethe, not easily.

CHAPTER XI

“NOW go forth, Grymbart, and see well before you. Reynart is so fell and false, and so subtle, that you need well to look about you and to beware of him.”

Grymbart said he should see well to.

Thus went Grymbart to Maleperdays ward, and when he came thither he found Reynart the Fox at home, and Dame Ermelyn his wife lay with her whelps in a dark corner.

Tho spake Grymbart and saluted his Eme and his Aunt, and said to Reynart,“Eme, beware that your absence hurt you not in such matters as be laid and complained on you; but if you think it good, it is high time that you come with me to the Court. The withholding you from it can do you no good. There is much thing complained over you, and this is the third warning; and I tell you for truth, if you abide to-morrow all day, there may no mercy help you. You shall see that within three days that your house shall be besieged all about, and there shall be made before it gallows and rack. I say you truly you shall not then escape, neither with wife nor with child, the King shall take all your lives from you. Therefore it is best that you go with me to the Court. Your subtle wise counsel shall peradventure avail you. There are greater adventures fallen, ere this; for it may hap you shall go quit of all the complaints that have been complained on you, and all your enemies shall abide in the shame. You have often done more and greater things than this.”

Reynart the Fox answered,“You say sooth. I think it is best that I go with you, for there lacks my counsel. Peradventure the King shall be merciful to me if I may come to speak with him, and see him under his eyes. Though I had done much more harm, the Court may not stand without me; that shall the King well understand. Though some be so fell to me ward, yet it goes not to the heart. All the council shall conclude much by me. Where great Courts have been gathered, of kings or of great lords, whereas needs subtle counsel, there must Reynart find the subtle means. They may well speak and say their advice, but tho my is best, and that goes before all other. In the Court are many that have sworn to do me the worst they can, and that causes me a part to be heavy in my heart, for many may do more than one alone that shall hurt me. Nevertheless, nephew, it is better I go with you to the Court and answer for myself, than to set me my wife and my children in adventure for to be lost. Arise up, let us go hence. He is over mighty for me. I must do as he will. I cannot better it; I shall take it patiently and suffer it.”

Reynart said to his wife Dame Ermelyn,“I betake you my children, that you see well to them and specially to Reynkin, my youngest son. He belikes me so well I hope he shall follow my steps. And there is Rossel a passing fair thief, I love them as well as any may love his children. If God give me grace that I may escape, I shall, when I come again, thank you with fair words.”Thus took Reynart leave of his wife.

Ah, gods! how sorrowful abode Ermelyn with her small whelps, for the victualler and he that sorrowed(1) for Maleperdays was gone his way, and the house not purveyed nor victualled.

————————————————————

(1) Sorrowed, took care (sorge).

CHAPTER XII

WHEN Reynart and Grymbart had gone a while together, tho said Reynart,“Dear Cousin, now am I in great fear, for I go in dread and jeopardy of my life. I have so much repentance for my sins that I will shrive me, dear Cousin, to you; here is none other priest to get. If I were shriven of my sins my soul should be the clearer.”

Grymbart answered,“Eme, will you shrive you, then must you promise first to leave your stealing and roving.”

Reynart said, that wist he well.“Now hark, dear Cousin, what I shall say. Confiteor tibi, pater, of all the misdeeds that I have done, and gladly will receive penance for them.”

Grymbart said,“What say you, will you shrive you? Then say it in English, that I may understand you.”

Reynart said,“I have trespassed against all the beasts that live; in especial against Bruin the Bear, my Eme, whom I made his crown all bloody; and taught Tybert the Cat to catch mice, for I made her leap in a grynne where she was all to-beaten; also I have trespassed greatly against Chanticleer with his children, for I have made him quit of a great deal of them. The King is not gone all quit, I have slandered him and the Queen many times, that they shall never be clear thereof. Yet have I beguiled Esegrim the Wolf, oftener than I can tell well. I called him Eme, but that was to deceive him; he is nothing of my kin. I made him a monk at Eelmare, where I myself also became one; and that was to his hurt and no profit. I made bind his feet to the bell rope, the ringing of the bell thought him so good that he would learn to ring; whereof he had shame, for he rang so sore that all the folk in the street were afraid thereof and marvelled what might be on the bell, and ran thither before he had come to axe the religion, wherefore he was beaten almost to the death. After this I taught him to catch fish, where he received many a stroke; also I led him to the richest priest's house that was in Vermedos, this priest had a spynde wherein hung many a good flitch of bacon wherein many a time I was wont to fill my belly; in this spynde I had made an hole in which I made Esegrim to creep. There found he tubs with beef and many good flitches of bacon, whereof he ate so much without measure that he might not come out at the hole where he went in; his belly was so great and full of the meat, and when he entered his belly was small; I went in to the village and made there a great shout and noise; yet hark what I did then, I ran to the priest where he sat at the table and ate, and had before him as fat capon as a man might find: that capon caught I, and ran my way therewith all that I might. The priest cried out, and said,‘Take and slay the Fox! I think that man never saw more wonder. The Fox comes in my house and takes my capon from my table: where saw ever man an hardier thief!’and as me thought he took his table knife and cast it at me, but he touched me not. I ran away, he shoved the table from him and followed me crying‘Kill and slay him!’I too go, and they after, and many moo came after, which all thought to hurt me.

“I ran so long that I came whereas Esegrim was, and there I let fall the capon, for it was too heavy for me, and against my will I left it there, and then I sprang through a hole whereas I would be. And as the priest took up the capon, he espied Esegrim and cried,‘Smite down here, friends, here is the thief, the Wolf! See well to, that he escape us not!’They ran all together with stocks and staves, and made a great noise, that all the neighbours camen out, and gave him many a shrewd stroke, and threw at him great stones, in such wise that he fell down as he had been dead. They slipped him and drew him over stones and over blocks without the village and threw him into a ditch, and there he lay all the night. I wot never how he came thence, since I have goten of him, for as much as I made him to fill his belly, that he sware he would be my help a whole year.

“Tho led I him to a place where I told him there were seven hens and a cock which sat on a perch and were much fat. And there stood a fall-door by, and we climbed thereup. I said to him if he would believe me, and that he would creep into the door, he should find many fat hens. Esegrim went all laughing to the doorward, and crept a little in, and tasted here and there, and at last he said to me,‘Reynart, you bord and jape with me, for what I seek I find not.’Then said I,‘Eme, if you will find, creep further in. He that will win, he must labour and adventure. They that were wont to sit there, I have them away.’Thus I made him to seek further in, and shoved him forth so far, that he fell down upon the floor, for the perch was narrow. And he fell so great a fall, that they sprang up all that slept, and they that next the fire cryden that the fall-door was open and something was fallen, and they wist not what it might be. They rose up and light a candle, and when they saw him, they smiten, beaten, and wounded him to the death. I have brought him thus in many a jeopardy, more than I can now reckon. I should find many more, if I me well bethought, which I shall tell you hereafter. Also I have bedriuen(1) with dame Ersewynde his wife. I would I had not done it. I am sorry for it. It is to her great shame, and that me repents.”

Grymbart said,“Eme, I understand you not.”

He said,“I have trespassed with his wife.”

“You shrive you, as though you held somewhat behind. I wot not what you mean, nor where you have learned this language.”

“Ach, Dear Neve, it were great shame if I should say it openly as it happened. I have lain by my aunt, I am your Eme, I should anger you if I spake villainy of women. Nephew, now have I told you all that I can think on. Set me penance, and assoil me, for I have great repentance.”

Grymbart was subtle and wise. He broke a rod off a tree and said,“Eme, now shall you smite yourself thrice with this rod on your body, and then lay it down upon the ground, and spring three times thereover, without bowing of your legs and without stumbling, and then shall you take it up and kiss it friendly in token of meekness and obedience of your penance that I gave you. Herewith be you quit of all sins that you have done to this day, for I forgive it you all.”

The Fox was glad.

Tho said Grymbart to his Eme,“Eme, see now further that you do good works: read your psalms, go to church, fast, and keep your holydays, and give your alms; and leave your sinful and ill life, your theft, and your treason, and so may you come to mercy.”

The Fox promised that he would so do, and then went they both together to the Court ward.

A little beside the way as they went stood a cloister of black nuns, where many geese, hens and capons went without the walls; and as they went talking the Fox brought Grymbart out of' the right way thither, and without the walls by the barn went the polaylle. The Fox espied them, and saw a fat young capon which went alone from his fellows, and leapt, and caught him that the feathers flew about his ears, but the capon escaped.

Grymbart said,“What, Eme, cursed man, what will you do! Will you for one of these pullets fall again in all your sins of which you have shriven you ? You ought sore repent you.”

Reynart answered,“Truly, cousin, I had all forgotten. Pray God that he forgive it me, for I will never do so more.”

Then turned they again over a little bridge, yet the Fox alway looked after the polaylle; he could not refrain himself; that which clevid by the bone might not out of the flesh: though he should be hanged he could not let the looking after the polaylle as far as he might see them.

Grymbart saw his manner, and said,“Foul false deceiver, how go your eyes so after the polaylle!”

The Fox said,“Cousin, you misdo to say to me any such words. You bring me out of my devotion and prayers. Let me say a pater noster for all the souls of polaylle and geese that I have betrayed, and oft with falsehood stolen from these holy nuns.”

Grymbart was not well apaid, but the Fox had ever his eyes toward the polaylle(2) till at last they came in the way again, and then turned they to the Courtward. How sore quaked tho Reynart when they approached the Court! For he wist well that he had for to answer to many a foul feat and theft that he had done.

————————————————————

(1) Bedriuen, had experience (Dutch, bedreven; German, betrieben).

(2) Polaylle, poultry.

CHAPTER XIII

AT the first when it was known in the Court that Reynart the Fox and Grymbart his cousin were come to the Court, there was none so poor nor so feeble of kin and friends but that he made him ready for to complain on Reynart the Fox.

Reynart looked as he had not been afraid, and held him better than he was, for he went forth proudly with his nephew through the highest street of the Court, right as he had been the King's son, and as he had not trespassed to any man the value of an hair: and went in the middle of the place standing before Noble the King and said—

“God give you great honour and worship. There was never King that ever had a truer servant than I have been to your good grace, and yet am. Nevertheless, dear lord, I know well that there are many in this Court that would destroy me if you would believe them; but nay, God thank you, it is not fitting to your crown to believe these false deceivers and liars lightly. To God mote it be complained how that these false liars and flatterers nowadays in the lord's Courts are most heard and believed, the shrews and false deceivers are borne up for to do to good men all the harm and scathe they may. Our Lord God shall once reward them their hire.”

The King said,“Peace, Reynart, false thief and traitor! How well can you bring forth fair tales! And all shall not help you a straw. Ween you with such flattering words to be my friend, you have so oft served me so as you now shall well know. The peace that I have commanded and sworn, that have you well holden, have you?”

Chanticleer could no longer be still, but cried,“Alas, what have I by this peace lost!”

“Be still, Chanticleer, hold your mouth. Let me answer this foul thief. Thou shrewd fell thief,”said the King,“thou sayest that thou lovest me well: that hast thou showed well on my messengers, these poor fellows, Tibert the Cat and Bruin the Bear, which yet are all bloody; which chide not nor say not much, but that shall this day cost thee thy life. In nomy Patris et Christi filii.”

Said the Fox,“Dear lord and mighty King, if Bruin's crown be bloody what is that to me? When he ate honey at Lantfert's house in the village and did him hurt and scathe, there was he beaten therefor; if he had willed, he is so strong of limbs, he might well have be avenged ere he sprang into the water. Tho came Tybert the Cat, whom I received friendly. If he went out without my counsel for to steal mice to a priest's house, and the priest did him harm, should I abyou that, then might I say I were not happy. Not so, my liege lord. You may do what you will, though my matter be clear and good; you may siede(1) me, or roast, hang, or make me blind. I may not escape you. We stand all under your correction. You be mighty and strong. I am feeble, and my help is but small. If you put me to the death it were a small vengeance.”

Whiles they thus spake, up sprang Bellyn the Ram and his ewe Dame Olewey, and said,“My lord the King, hear our complaint.”Bruin the Bear stood up with all his lineage and hisfellows. Tybert the Cat, Esegrim the Wolf, Cuwart the Hare, and Panther; the Boar, the Camel, and Brunel the Goose; the Kid and Goat; Boudewyn the Ass, Borre the Bull, Hamel the Ox, and the Weasel; Chanticleer the Cock, Pertelot with all their children, all these made great rumour and noise, and came forth openly before their lord the King, and made that the Fox was taken and arrested.

————————————————————

(1) Siede, seethe, boil.

CHAPTER XIV

HEREUPON was a Parliament; and they desired that Reynart should have been dead. And whatsomever they said against the Fox he answered to each to them. Never heard man of such beasts such plaints of wise counsel and subtle inventions. And on that other side, the Fox made his excuse so well and formably thereon, that they that heard it wondered thereof. They that heard and saw it may tell it forth for truth; I shall short the matter and tell you forth of the Fox. The King and the Council heard the witnesses of the complaints of Reynart's misdeeds. It went with them as it oft does, the feeblest has the worst. They gave sentence, and judged that the Fox should be dead and hanged by the neck. Tho list not he to play. All his flattering words and deceits could not help him. The judgment was given, and that must be done. Grymbart, his nephew, and many of his lineage might not find in their hearts to see him die, but took leave sorrowfully, and roomed(1) the court.

The King bethought him, and marked how many a youngling departed from thence all weeping, which were nigh of his kin, and said to himself,“Here behoves other counsel hereto; though Reynart be a shrew, there be many good of his lineage.”

Tybert the Cat said,“Sir Bruin and Sir Esegrim, how be you thus slow? It is almost even. Here are many bushes and hedges. If he escaped from us and were delivered out of this peril, he is so subtle, and so wily, and can so many deceits, that he should never be taken again. Shall we hang him? How stand you all thus? Ere the gallows can be made ready it shall be night.”

Esegrim bethought him tho, and said,“Hereby is a gibbet or gallows.”And with that word he sighed.

And the Cat espied that, and said,“Esegrim, you be afraid. Is it against your will? Think you not that he himself went and laboured that both your brethren were hanged? Were you good and wise, you should thank him, and you should not therewith so long tarry.”

————————————————————

(1) Roomed, vacated (räumen).

CHAPTER XV

1 ESEGRIM balked(1) and said,“You make much ado, Sir Tybert; had we an halter which were meet for his neck and strong enough, we should soon make an end.”

Reynart the Fox, which long had not spoken, said to Esegrim,“Short my pain. Tybert has a strong cord which caught him in the Priest's house. He can climb well, and is swift; let him bear up the line. Esegrim and Bruin, this becomes you well, that you thus do to your Nephew! I am sorry that I live thus long; haste you, you be set thereto; it is evil do that you tarry thus long. Go before, Bruin, and lead me; Esegrim, follow fast, and see well to, and be ware that Reynart go not away.”

Tho said Bruin,“It is the best counsel that I ever yet heard, that Reynart here says.”

Esegrim commanded anon and bade his kin and friends that they should see to Reynart that he escaped not, for he is so wily and false. They held him by the feet, by the beard; and so kept him that he escaped not from them.

The Fox heard all these words, which touched him nigh, yet spake he and said,“Oh, dear Eme, methinks you pain yourself sore for to do me hurt and scathe. If I durst, I would pay you of mercy, though my hurt and sorrow is pleasant to you. I wot well, if my Aunt, your wife, bethought her well of old ferners,(2) she would not suffer that I should have any harm; but now I am he that now you will do on me what it shall please you. You Bruin and Tybert, God give you shames death but you do to me your worst. I wot whereto I shall. I may die but once, I would that I were dead already. I saw my father die, he had soon done.”

Esegrim said,“Let us go, for you curse us because we lengthen the time. Evil might we fare if we abide any longer.”

He went forth with great envy on that one side, and Bruin stood on the other side, and so led they him forth to the gallows ward. Tybert ran with a good will before, and bare the cord; and his throat was yet sore of the grynne, and his croppe did him woe of the stroke that he was take in; that happened by the counsel of the Fox, and that thought he now to quit.

Tybert Esegrim and Bruin went hastily with Reynart to the place there as the felons are wont to be put to death. Noble the King and the Queen and all that were in the Court followed after, for to see the end of Reynart. The Fox was in great dread if him myshapped, and bethought him oft how he might save him from the death; and tho three that so sore desired his death, how he might deceive them and bring them to shame; and how he might bring the King with leasings for to hold with him against them. This was all that he studied, how he might put away his sorrow with wiles, and thought thus:“Though the King and many one be upon me angry, it is no wonder, for I have well deserved it; nevertheless, I hope for to be yet their best friend. And yet shall I never do them good. How strong that the King be, and how wise that his council be, if I may brook(3) my words I know so many an invention, I shall come to my above(4) as far as they would come to the gallows.”

Tho said Esegrim,“Sir Bruin, think now on your red crown which by Reynart's mean you caught; we have now the time that we may well reward him. Tybert, clime up hastily and bind the cord fast to the lynde, and make a riding knot or a strope, you be the lightest; you shall this day see your will of him. Bruin, see well to, that he escape not, and hold fast. I will help that the ladder be set up, that he may go upward thereon.”

Bruin said,“Do. I shall help him well.”

The Fox said,“Now may my heart be well heavy for great dread; for I see the death before my eyes, and I may not escape. My lord the King, and dear Queen, and forth all you that here stand, ere I depart from this world I pray you of a boon: that I may before you all make my confession openly, and tell my defaults all so clearly that my soul may not be acumbred, and also that no man hereafter bear no blame for my theft nor for my treason. My death shall be to me the easier, and pray you all to God that he have mercy on my soul.”

————————————————————

(1) Balked, brayed (Dutch, balken; vulg., bölken).

(2) Old ferners, auld lang syne.

(3) Brook, have use of (brauchen).

(4) Come to my above, rise in the world.

CHAPTER XVI

ALL they that stood there had pity when Reynart said tho words, and said it was but a little request if the King would grant it him, and they prayed the King to grant it him. The King gave him leave.

Reynart was well glad, and hoped that it might fall better, and said thus:

“Now help, Spiritus Domini, for I see here no man but I have trespassed unto. Nevertheless yet was I, unto the time that I was weaned from the teat, one of the best children that could anywhere be found. I went tho and played with the lambs, because I heard them gladly bleat. I was so long with them that at the last I bit one; there learned I first to lappen of the blood. It savoured well; me thought it right good. And after I began to taste of the flesh thereof, I was licorous; so that after that I went to the gate into the wood, there heard I the kids bleat and I slew of them two. I began to wax hardy after. I slew hens, polaylle and geese wherever I found them. Thus worden(1) my teeth all bloody. After this, I wex so fell and so wroth that whatsomever I found that I might over, I slew all. Thereafter came I by Esegrim, now in the winter, where he hid him under a tree, arid reckoned to me that he was my eme. When I heard him then reckon alliance, we became fellows, which I may well repent. We promised each to other to be true, and to use good fellowship, and began to wander together. He stole the great things and I the small, and all was common between us. Yet he made it so that he had the best deal;(2) I got not half my part. When that Esegrim got a calf a ram or a wether, then grimmed he, and was angry on me, and drove me from him, and held my part and his too, so good is he. Yet this was of the least. But when it so lucked that we took an ox or a cow, then came thereto his wife with seven children; so that unto me might vnnethe come one of the smallest ribs, and yet, had they eaten all the flesh thereof, therewithall must I be content; not for that I had so great need, for I have so great scatte(3) and good of silver and of gold, that seven wains should not can carry it away.”

When the King heard him speak of this great good and riches, he burned in the desire and covetyse thereof, and said,“Reynart, where is the riches become? tell me that.”

The Fox said,“My lord, I shall tell you. The riches was stolen. And had it not be stolen, it should have cost you your life and you should have been murdered, —which God forbid!—and should have been the greatest hurt in the world.”

When the Queen heard that, she was sore afraid and cried aloud,“Alas and weleaway! Reynart, what say you? I conjure you by the long way that your soul shall go, that you tell us openly the truth hereof, as much as you know of this great murder that should have be done on my lord, that we all may hear it!”

Now hearken how the Fox shall flatter the King and Queen, and shall win both their good will and loves, and shall hinder them that labour for his death. He shall unbind his pack and lie, and by flattery and fair words shall bring forth so his matters that it shall be supposed for truth.

In a sorrowful countenance spake the Fox to the Queen,“I am in such case now that I must needs die, and had you me not so sore conjured I will not jeopardise my soul, and if I so died I should go therefor in to the pain of hell. I will say nothing but that I will make it good, for piteously he should have been murdered of his own folk. Nevertheless they that were most principal in this feat were of my next kin, whom gladly I would not betray, if the sorrow were not of the hell.”

The King was heavy of heart, and said,“Reynart, sayest thou to me the truth?”

“Yes,”said the Fox.“See you not how it stands with me? Ween you that I shall damn my soul? What should it avail me if I now said otherwise than truth? My death is so nigh. There may neither prayer nor good help me.”Tho trembled the Fox, by dissembling, as he had been afraid.

The Queen had pity on him, and prayed the King to have mercy on him, in eschewing of more harm, and that he should do the people hold their peace, and give the Fox audience, and hear what he should say.

Tho commanded the King openly that each of them should be still, and suffer the Fox to say unberisped(4) what that he would.

Then said the Fox,“Be you now all still, since it is the King's will, and I shall tell you openly this treason. And therein will I spare no man that I know guilty.”

————————————————————

(1) Worden, became.

(2) Deal, share, division.

(3) Scatte, treasure, money;“shot”in the locker.

(4) Unberisped, untroubled, unexcited (Dutch, rispen).

CHAPTER XVII

NOW hearken how the Fox began. In the beginning he appealed Grymbart his dear Cousin, which ever had helped him in his need. He did so because his words should be the better believed; and that he further might the better lie on his enemies. Thus began he first and said:

“My lord, my father had found King Ermeryk's treasure dolven in a pit; and when he had this great good, he was so proud and orguillous that he had all other beasts in despite which before had been his fellows. He made Tybert the Cat to go into that wild land of Ardenne to Bruin the Bear for to do him homage, and bade him say, if he would be King that he should come in to Flanders. Bruin the Bear was glad hereof, for he had long desired it, and went forth in to Flanders; where my father received him right friendly. Anon he sent for the wise Grymbart, my nephew, and for Esegrim the Wolf, and for Tybert the Cat. Tho these five came between Gaunt and the thorp called Yfte, there they held their council an whole dark night long. What with the devil's help and craft, and for my father's riches, they concluded and swore there the King's death. Now hearken, and hear this wonder. The four swore upon Esegrim's crown that they should make Bruin a king and a lord, and bring him in the stool at Akon,(1) and set the crown on his head; and if there were any of the King's friends or lineage that would be contrary or against this, him should my father with his good and treasure fordrive, and take from him his might and power.

“It happed so that on a morrowtide early when Grymbart, my nephew, was of wine almost drunk, that he told it to Dame Sloepcade, his wife, in counsel, and bade her keep it secret. But she anon forgot it, and said it forth in confession to my wife upon an heath where they both went a pilgrimage, but she must first swear, by her truth and by the holy Three Kings of Cologne, that for love nor for hate she should never tell it forth, but keep it secret. But she held it not, and kept it no longer secret but till she came to me; and she then told to me all that she heard, but I must keep it in secret. And she told me so many tokens that I felt well it was truth; and for dread and fear my hair stood right up, and my heart became as heavy as lead and as cold as ice. I thought by this a likeness which here aforetime befell to the frosshis(2) which were free and complained that they had none lord nor were not bydwongen,(3) for a comynte(4) without a governor was not good, and they cried to God with a loud voice that he would ordain one that might rule them, this was all that they desired. God heard their request, for it was reasonable, and sent to them a Stork which ate and swallowed them in, as many as he could find; he was alway to them unmerciful. Tho complained they their hurt, but then it was too late; they that were before free and were afraid of nobody are now bound and must obey to strength their king: herefor, you rich and poor, I sorrowed, that it might happen us in likewise.

“Thus, my lord the King, I have had sorrow for you whereof you can me but little thank. I know Bruin the Bear for such a shrew and ravener, wherefore I thought if he were king we should be all destroyed and lost. I know our sovereign lord the King of so high birth, so mighty, so benign and merciful, that I thought truly it had been an evil change for to have a foul stinking thief and to refuse a noble mighty stately Lion; for the Bear has more mad folly in his unthrifty head, and all his ancestors, than any other has. Thus had I in my heart many a sorrow, and thought alway how I might break and foredo my father's false counsel, which of a churl and a traitor and worse than a thief would make a lord and a king. Alway I prayed God that he would keep our King in worship and good health, and grant him long life, but I thought well if my father held his treasure he should with his false fellows well find the way that the King should be deposed and set aside. I was sore bethought how I might best wit(5) where my father's good lay. I awaited at all times as nigh as I could, in woods, in bushes, in fields; where my father laid his eyes; were it by night or by day, cold or wet, I was alway by him to espy and know where his treasure was laid.

“On a time I lay down all plat on the ground and saw my father come running out of an hole. Now hark what I saw him do. When he came out of the hole, he looked fast about if anybody had seen him. And when he could nowhere none see, he stopped the hole with sand and made it even and plain like to the other ground by. He knew not that I saw it. And where his footspore stood, there stryked he with his tail, and made it smooth with his mouth, that no man should espy it. That learned I there of my false father, and many subtleties that I before knew nothing of. Then departed he thence and ran to the village ward for to do his things; and I forgot not, but sprang and leapt to the hole ward, and how well that he had supposed that he had made all fast I was not so much a fool but that I found the hole well, and scratched and scraped with my feet the sand out of the hole, and crept therein. There found I the most plenty of silver and of gold that ever I saw. Here is none so old that ever so much saw on one heap in all his life. Tho took I Ermelyne my wife to help, and we nor rested night nor day to bear and carry away, with great labour and pain, this rich treasure in to another place that lay for us better, under an hawe in a deep hole. In the mean while that my housewife and I thus laboured, my father was with them that would betray the King. Now may you hear what they did. Bruin the Bear and Esegrim the Wolf sent all the land about if any man would take wages that they should come to Bruin and he would pay them their souldyou or wages before. My father ran all over the land and bare the letters. He wist little that he was robbed of his treasure; yea though he might have wonnen all the world, he had not conne find a penny thereof.

“When my father had been over all in the land between the Elbe and the Somme, and had gotten many a soldier that should the next summer have come to help Bruin, tho came he again to the Bear and his fellows, and told them in how great a venture he had be before the boroughs in the land of Saxon, and how the hunters daily ridden and hunted with hounds after him in such wise that he uneasily escaped with his life. When he had told this to these four false traitors, then showed he them letters that pleased much. To Bruin therein were written twelve hundred of Esegrim's lineage by name, without the bears, the foxes, the cats, and the dassen, all these had sworn that with the first messenger that should come for them they should be ready, and come for to help the Bear if they had their wages a month before. This aspied I, I thank God. After these words my father went to the hole where his treasure had lain, and would look upon it. Tho began he a great sorrow; that he sought he found nothing. He found his hole broken, and his treasure borne away. There did he that I may well sorrow and bewail, for great anger and sorrow he went and hung himself. Thus abode the treason of Bruin by my subtilty after. Now see my infortune. These traitors Esegrim and Bruin are now most privy of counsel about the King, and sit by him on the high bench. And I, poor Reynart, have nor thanks nor reward. I have buried my own father, because the King should have his life. My lord,”said the Fox,“where are they that would so do, that is, to destroy them self for to keep you.”

The King and the Queen hoped to win the treasure and without council took to them Reynart and prayed him that he would do so well as to tell them where this treasure was.

Reynart said,“How should I tell the King, or them that would hang me for love of the traitors and murderers which by their flattery would fain bring me to death? Should I tell to them where my good is, then were I out of my wit.”

The Queen then spake,“Nay, Reynart, the King shall let you have your life, and shall altogether forgive you, and you shall be from henceforth wise and true to my lord.”

The Fox answered to the Queen,“Dear lady, if the King will believe me, and that he will pardon and forgive me all my old trespasses, there was never King so rich as I shall make him. For the treasure that I shall do him have is right costly and may not be numbered.”

The King said,“Ach Dame, will you believe the Fox? Save your reverence, he is born to rob, steal, and to lie. This cleaves to his bones, and can not be had out of the flesh.”

The Queen said,“Nay, my lord, you may now well believe him. Though he were before fell, he is now changed otherwise than he was. You have well heard that he has impeached his father and the Dasse his nephew, which he might well have laid on other beasts if he would have been false, fell, and a liar.”

The King said,“Dame, will you then have it so, and think you it best to be don, though I supposed it should hurt me I will take all these trespasses of Reynart upon me and believe his words. But I swear by my crown, if he ever hereafter misdo and trespass, that shall he dear abyou and all his lineage unto the ninth degree.”

The Fox looked on the King stoundmele,(6) and was glad in his heart, and said,“My lord, I were not wise if I should say things that were not true.”

The King took up a straw from the ground, and pardoned and forgave the Fox all the misdeeds and trespasses of his father and of him also. If the Fox was tho merry and glad, it was no wonder; for he was quit of his death and was all free and frank of all his enemies. The Fox said,“My Lord the king and noble Lady the Queen, God reward you this great worship that you do to me. I shall think and also thank you for it in such wise that you shall be the richest king of the world; for there is none living under the sun that I vouchsafe better my treasure on, than on you both.”

Then took the Fox up a straw and proffered it to the King, and said,“My most dear Lord, please it you to receive here the rich treasure which King Ermeryk had. For I give it unto you with a free will, and knowledge it openly.”

The King received the straw, and threw it merely from him with a joyous visage, and thanked much the Fox.

The Fox laughed in himself.

The King then hearkened after the counsel of the Fox. And all that there were were at his will.

“My Lord,”said he,“hearken and mark well my words. In the west side of Flanders there stands a wood and is named Hulsterlo, and a water that is called Krekenpyt lies thereby. This is so great a wilderness, that oft in a whole year man nor wife comes therein, save they that will, and they that will not eschew it. There lies this treasure hidden. Understand well that the place is called Krekenpyt, for I advise you, for the least hurt, that you and my Lady go both thither; for I know none so true that I durst on your behalf trust; wherefore go yourself. And when you come to Krekenpyt you shall find there two birch trees standing althernext(7) the pit. My Lord, to tho birch trees shall you go: there lies the treasure untherdolven.(8) There must you scrape and dig away a little the moss on the one side. There shall you find many a jewel of gold and silver, and there shall you find the crown which king Ermeryk wore in his days. That should Bruin the Bear have worn, if his will had gone forth. You shall see many a costly jewel, with rich stones set in gold work, which cost many a thousand mark. My Lord the King, when you now have all this good, how oft shall you say in your heart and think,‘Oh how true art thou, Reynart the Fox, that with thy subtle wit delvest and hidest this great treasure! God give thee good hap and welfare wherever thou be!’”

The King said,“Sir Reynart, you must come and help us to dig up this treasure. I know not the way. I should never conne find it. I have heard often named Paris, London, Aachen, and Cologne; as me thinks this treasure lies right as you mocked and japed, for you name Krekenpyt. That is a feigned name.”

These words were not good to the Fox, and he said with an angry mood, and dissembled and said,“Yea, my Lord the King, you be also nigh that as from Rome to Maye. Ween you that I will lead you to flume(9) Jordan. Nay, I shall bring you out of weening and show it you by good witness.”

He called loud,“Cuwart the Hare, come here before the King.”The beasts saw all thitherward and wondered what the King would.

The Fox said to the Hare,“Cuwart, are you acold; how tremble you and quake so? Be not afraid; and tell my Lord the King here the truth, and that I charge you, by the faith and truth that you owe him and to my Lady the Queen, of such thing as I shall demand of you.”

Cuwart said,“I shall say the truth, though I should lose my neck therefor. I shall not lie, you have charged me so sore, if I know it.”

“Then say, know you not where Krekenpyt stands? Is that in your mind?”

The Hare said,“I knew that well twelve year agone, where that stands. Why ask you that? It stands in a wood named Hulsterlo, upon a warande(10) in the wilderness. I have suffered there much sorrow for hunger and for cold, yea, more than I can tell. Pater Symonet the Friese was woned(11) to make there false money, wherewith he bare himself out and all his fellowship but that was before ere I had fellowship with Ryn the Hound, which made me escape many a danger; as he could well tell if he were here, and that I never in my days trespassed against the King otherwise than I ought to do with right.”

Reynart said to him,“Go again to yonder fellowship. Hear you, Cuwart? My Lord the King desires no more to know of you.”The Hare returned and went again to the place he came from.

The Fox said,“My Lord the King, is it true that I said?”

“Yea, Reynart,”said the King,“forgive it me; I did evil that I believed you not. Now, Reynart, friend, find the way that you go with us to the place and pit where the treasure lies.”

The Fox said,“It is a wonder thing. Ween you that I would not fain go with you; if it were so with me that I might go with you in such wise that it no shame were unto your lordship, I would go. But nay, it may not be. Hearken what I shall say, and must needs, though it be to me villainy and shame. When Esegrim the Wolf, in the devil's name, went into religion and became a monk shorn in the order, tho the provender of six monks was not sufficient to him, and had not enough to eat, he then plained and wailed so sore that I had pity on him, for he became slow and sick. And because he was of my kin, I gave him counsel to run away, and so he did. Wherefore I stand accursed, and am in the Pope's ban and sentence. I will to-morrow betimes, as the sun rises, take my way to Rome for to be assoiled(12) and take pardon. And from Rome I will over the sea into the Holy Land, and will never return again till I have done so much good that I may with worship go with you. It were great reproof to you, my Lord the King, in what land that I accompanied you that men should say you reysed(13) and accompanied yourself with a cursed and person agravate.”

The King said,“Since that you stand accursed in the censures of the Church, if I went with you men should arette villainy unto my crown. I shall then take Cuwart or some other to go with me to Krekenpyt; and I counsel you, Reynart, that you put you yourself out of this curse.”

“My Lord,”quoth the Fox,“therefore will I go to Rome as hastily as I may. I shall not rest by night nor day till I be assoiled.”

“Reynart,”said the King,“me thinks you are turned into a good way. God give you grace to accomplish well your desire.”

As soon as this speaking was done, Noble the King went and stood upon an high stage of stone and commanded silence to all the beasts, and that they should sit down in a ring round upon the grass, everiche in his place after his estate and birth. Reynart the Fox stood by the Queen, whom he ought well to love. Then said the King,“Hear you all that be poor and rich, young and old, that stands here. Reynart, one of the head officers of my house, had done so evil, which this day should have been hanged, has now in this Court done so much, that I and my wife the Queen have promised to him our grace and friendship. The Queen has prayed much for him, insomuch that I have made peace with him. And I give to him his life and member freely again, and I command you upon your life that you do worship to Reynart and his wife, and to his children, wheresomever you meet them by day or night. And I will also hear no more complaints of Reynart. If he has heretofore misdone and trespassed, he will no more misdo nor trespass, but now better him. He will to-morrow early go to the Pope for pardon and forgiveness of all his sins, and forth over the sea to the Holy Land, and he will not come again till he bring pardon of all his sins.”

This tale heard Tyselyn the Raven and leapt to Esegrim to Bruin and to Tybert, there as they were, and said,“You caitifs, how goes it now? You unhappy folk, what do you here? Reynart the Fox is now a squire and a courtier, and right great and mighty in the Court. The King has skylled him quite of all his brokes,(14) and forgiven him all his trespasses and misdeeds. And you be all betrayed and appeached.”

Esegrim said,“How may this be? I think Tyselyn that you lie.”

“I do not, certainly,”said the Raven.

Tho went the Wolf and the Bear to the King. Tybert the Cat was in great sorrow, and he was so sore afraid that for to have the Fox's friendship he would well forgive Reynart the loss of his one eyou that he lost in the priest's house, he was so woe he wist not what to do, he would well that he never had seen the Fox.

————————————————————

(1) Akon, Aachen, Aix-la-Chapelle.

(2) Frosshis, frogs.

(3) Bydwongen, held in restraint.

(4) Comynte, community.

(5) Wit, know.

(6) Stoundmele, for a space of time.

(7) Althernext, next of all.

(8) Untherdolven, dug under.

(9) Flume, river.

(10) Warande, warren, a place privileged by a franchise from the King for keeping or hunting certain animals, to the exclusion of all persons entering without permission.

(11) Woned, accustomed.

(12) Assoiled, absolved.

(13) Reysed, travelled (reisen).

(14) Skylled him quite of all his brokes, judged him acquitted of all his dealings.

CHAPTER XVIII

Esegrim came proudly over the field before the King, and he thanked the Queen, and spake with a fell mood ill words on the Fox, in suchwise that the King heard it and was wroth, and made the Wolf and the Bear anon to be arrested. You saw never wood(1) dogs do more harm than was done to them. They were both fast bounden, so sore that all that night they might not stir hand nor foot. They might scarcely roar nor move any joint. Now hear how the Fox forth did. He hated them. He laboured so to the Queen that he got leave for to have as much of the Bear's skin upon his rigge(2) as a foot long and a foot broad, for to make him thereof a scrip; then was the Fox ready if he had four strong shoon. Now hear how he did for to get these shoon. He said to the Queen,“Madam, I am your pilgrim. Here is my Eme, Sir Esegrim, that has four strong shoon which were good for me. If he would let me have two of them I would on the way busily think on your soul, for it is right that a pilgrim should always think and pray for them that do him good. Thus may you do your soul good if you will. And also if you might get of my aunt Dame Ersewynde also two of her shoon to give me, she may well do it, for she goes but little out, but abides alway at home.”

Then said the Queen,“Reynart, you behoves well such shoes; you may not be without them. They shall be good for you to keep your feet whole for to pass with them many a sharp mountain and stony rocks. You can find no better shoes for you than such as Esegrim and his wife have and wear. They be good and strong. Though it should touch their life, each of them shall give you two shoes for to accomplish with your high pilgrimage.”

————————————————————

(1) Wood, mad.

(2) Rigge, back.

CHAPTER XIX

THUS has this false pilgrim gotten from Esegrim two shoes from his feet, which were hauled off the claws to the sinews. You saw never fowl that men roasted lay so still as Esegrim did when his shoes were hauled off. He stirred not, and yet his feet bled. Then when Esegrim was unshod tho must Dame Ersewynde his wife lie down in the grass with an heavy cheer. And she lost there her hinder shoes.

Tho was the Fox glad, and said to his Aunt in scorn,“My dear Aunt, how much sorrow have you suffered for my sake, which me sore repents, save this, hereof I am glad for you be the liefest(1) of all my kin. Therefore I will gladly wear your shoes. You shall be partner of my pilgrimage and deal of the pardon that I shall with your shoes fetch over the sea.”

Dame Ersewynde was so woe that she uneasily might speak. Nevertheless this she said,“Ah, Reynart, that you now all thus have your will, I pray God to wreak(2) it!”

Esegrim and his fellow the Bear held their peace and were all still. They were evil at ease for they were bound and sore wounded. Had Tybert the Cat have been there, he should also somewhat have suffered, in such wise as he should not have escaped thence without hurt or shame.

The next day, when the sun arose, Reynart then did grease his shoes which he had of Esegrim and Ersewynde his wife, and did them on, and bound them to his feet, and went to the King and to the Queen and said to them with a glad cheer,“Noble Lord and Lady, God give you good morrow, and I desire of your grace that I may have male(3) and staff blessed as belongs to a pilgrim.”

Then the King anon sent for Bellyn the Ram, and when he came he said,“Sir Bellyn, you shall do mass before Reynart, for he shall go on pilgrimage; and give to him male and staff.”

The Ram answered again and said,“My Lord, I dare not do that, for he has said that he is in the Pope's curse.”

The King said what thereof master Gelys has said to us, if a man had don as many sins as all the world and he would tho sins forsake, shrive him and receive penance, and do by the priest's counsel, God will forgive them and be merciful unto him. Now will Reynart go over the sea into the Holy Land, and make him clear of all his sins.

Then answered Bellyn to the King,“I will not do little nor much herein but if you save me harmless in the spiritual court, before the bishop Prendelor and before his archdeacon Looswinde and before Sir Rapiamus his official.”

The King began to wax wroth, and said,“I shall not bid you so much in half a year! I had liever hang you than I should so much pray you for it!”

When the Ram saw that the King was angry, he was so sore afraid that he quoke for fear, and went to the altar and sang in his books and read such as him thought good over Reynart, which little set thereby save that he would have the worship thereof.

When Bellyn the Ram had all said his service devoutly, then he hung on the fox's neck a male covered with the skin of Bruin the Bear and a little psalter thereby. Tho was Reynart ready toward his journey. Tho looked he toward the King, as he had been sorrowful to depart; and feigned as he had wept, right as he had yamerde(4) in his heart; but if he had any sorrow it was because all the other that were there were not in the same plight as the Wolf and Bear were brought in by him. Nevertheless he stood and prayed them all to pray for him, like as he would pray for them. The Fox thought that he tarried long and would fain have departed, for he knew himself guilty.

The King said,“Reynart, I am sorry you be so hasty, and will no longer tarry.”

“Nay, my Lord, it is time, for we ought not spare to do well, I pray you to give me leave to depart: I must do my pilgrimage.”

The King said,“God be with you,”and commanded all them of the court to go and convey Reynart on his way, save the Wolf and the Bear which fast lay bounden. There was none that durst be sorry therefor, and if you had seen Reynart how personably he went with his male and psalter on his shoulder, and the shoes on his feet, you should have laughed. He went and showed him outward wisely, but he laughed in his heart that all they brought him forth which had a little before been with him so wroth. And also the King which so much hated him, he had made him such a fool that he brought him to his owne intent. He was a pilgrim of deuce ace.

“My Lord the King,”said the Fox,“I pray you to return again, I will not that you go any further with me. You might have harm thereby. You have there two murderers arrested. If they escape you, you might be hurt by them. I pray God keep you from misadventure!”With these words he stood up on his afterfeet, and prayed all the beasts, great and small, that would be partners of his pardon, that they should pray for him.

They said that they all would remember him.

Then departed he from the King so heavily that many of them ermed.(5)

Then said he to Cuwart the Hare and to Bellyn the Ram merrily,“Here, friends, shall we now depart? Yea, with a good will accompany me further. You two made me never angry. You be good for to walk with, courteous, friendly, and not complained on of any beast You be of good conditions and ghostly of your living; you live both as I did when I was a recluse. If you have leaves and grass you be pleased, you reck not of bread of flesh nor such manner meat.”

With such flattering words has Reynart these two flattered that they went with him till they came before his house Maleperdays.

————————————————————

(1) Liefest, best loved.

(2) Wreak, avenge.

(3) Male, bag, scrip.

(4) Yamerde, grief (jammer).

(5) Ermed, grieved.

CHAPTER XX

WHEN the Fox was come before the gate of his house, he said to Bellyn the Ram,“Cousin, you shall abide here without, I and Cuwart will go in, for I will pray Cuwart to help me to take my leave of Ermelyne my wife, and to comfort her and my children.”

Bellyn said,“I pray him to comfort them well.”

With such flattering words brought he the Hare into his hole in an evil hour. There found they Dame Ermelyne lying on the ground with her younglings, which had sorrowed much for dread of Reynart's death. But when she saw him come, she was glad. But when she saw his male and psalter, and espied his shoes, she marvelled and said,“Dear Reynart, how have you sped?”

He said“I was arrested in the court, but the King let me gon. I must go a pilgrimage. Bruin the Bear and Esegrim the Wolf they be pledge for me. I thank the King he has given to us Cuwart here, for to do with him what we will. The King said himself that Cuwart was the first that on us complained, and by the faith that I owe you I am right wroth on Cuwart.”

When Cuwart heard these words he was sore afraid. He would have fled but he might not, for the Fox stood between him and the gate, and he caught him by the neck. Tho cried the Hare,“Help, Bellyn, help! Where be you? This pilgrim slays me?”But that cry was soon done, for the Fox had anon bitten his throat a two.

Tho said he,“Let us go eat this good fat hare.”The young whelps came also. Thus held they a great feast, for Cuwart had a good fat body. Ermelyne ate the flesh and drank the blood; she thanked oft the King that he had made them so merry. The Fox said,“Eat as much as you may, he will pay for it if we will fetch it.”She said,“Reynart, I think you mock. Tell me the truth how you be departed thence.”

“Dame, I have so flattered the king and the queen that I suppose the friendship between us shall be right thin. When he shall know of this he shall be angry, and hastily seek me for to hang me by my neck. Therefore let us depart, and steal secretly away in some other forest where we may live without fear and dread, and there that we may live seven year and more an they find us not. There is plenty of good meat of partridges, woodcocks, and much other wild fowl, Dame, and if you will come with me thither there are sweet wells and fair and clear running brooks; Lord God, how sweet air is there. There may we be in peace and ease, and live in great wealth. For the King has let me gon because I told him that there was great treasure in Krekenpyt, but there shall he find nothing though he sought ever. This shall sore anger him when he knows that he is thus deceived. What! think you how many a great leasing must I lie ere I could escape from him. It was hard that I escaped out of prison; I was never in greater peril nor nearer my death. But how it ever go I shall by my will never more come in the King's danger. I have now gotten my thumb out of his mouth, that thank I my subtilty.”

Dame Ermelyne said,“Reynart, I counsel that we go not into another forest where we should be strange and elenge. We have here all that we desire. And you be here lord of our neighbours; wherefore shall we leave this place and adventure us in a worse? We may abide here sure enough. If the King would do us any harm or besiege us, here are so many by or side holes, in such wise as we shall escape from him; in abiding here we may not do amiss. We know all bypaths over all, and ere he take us with might he must have much help thereto. But that you have sworn that you shall go oversea and abide there, that is the thing that touches me most.”

“Nay, Dame, care not therefor. How more forsworn, how more forlorn. I went once with a good man that said to me that a bedwongen(1) oath, or oath sworn by force, was none oath. Though I went on this pilgrimage it should not avail me a cat's tail. I will abide here and follow your counsel. If the King hunt after me, I shall keep me as well as I may. If he be me too mighty, yet I hope with subtlety to beguile him. I shall unbind my sack. If he will seek harm he shall find harm.”

Now was Bellyn the Ram angry that Cuwart his fellow was so long in the hole, and called loud,“Come out, Cuwart, in the devil's name; how long shall Reynart keep you there? Haste you, and come! Let us go.”

When Reynart heard this, he went out and said softly to Bellyn the Ram,“Lief Bellyn, wherefore be you angry? Cuwart speaks with his dear Aunt. Methinks you ought not to be displeased therefor. He bade me say to you you might well go before, and he shall come after; he is lighter of foot than you. He must tarry awhile with his Aunt and her children, they weep and cry because I shall go from them.”

Bellyn said,“What did Cuwart? Methought he cried after help.”

The Fox answered,“What say you, Bellyn? Ween you that he should have any harm? Now hark what he then did. When we were come into my house, and Ermelyne my wife understood that I should go over sea, she fell down in a swoon; and when Cuwart saw that, he cried loud,‘Bellyn, come help my Aunt to bring her out of her swoon.’”

Then said the Ram,“In faith I understood that Cuwart had been in great danger.”

The Fox said,“Nay truly, or Cuwart should have any harm in my house I had liever that my wife and children should suffer much hurt.”

————————————————————

(1) Bedwongen, enforced.

CHAPTER XXI

THE Fox said,“Bellyn, remember you not that yesterday the King and his council commanded me that ere I should depart out of this land I should send to him two letters? Dear cousin, I pray you to bear them, they be ready written.”

The Ram said,“I wot never. If I wist that your inditing and writing were good, you might peradventure so much pray me that I would bear them, if I had anything to bear them in.”

Reynart said,“You shall not fail to have somewhat to bear them in. Rather than they should be unborne I shall rather give you my male that I bear; and put the King's letters therein, and hang them about your neck. You shall have of the King great thanks therefor, and be right welcome to him.”

Hereupon Bellyn promised him to bear these letters.

Tho returned Reynart into his house and took the male and put therein Cuwart's head, and brought it to Bellyn for to bring him in danger, and hang it on his neck, and charged him not to look in the male if he would have the King's friendship.“And if you will that the King take you into his grace and love you, say that you yourself have made the letter and indited it, and have given the counsel that it is so well made and written. You shall have great thanks therefor.”

Bellyn the Ram was glad hereof, and thought he should have great thanks, and said,“Reynart, I wot well that you now do for me. I shall be in the Court greatly praised when it is known that I can indite and make a letter, though I cannot make it. Often it happens that God suffers some to have worship and thank of the labours and cunning of other men, and so it shall befall me now. Now, what counsel you, Reynart? Shall Cuwart the Hare come with me to the Court?”

“Nay,”said the Fox,“he shall anon follow you. He may not yet come, for he must speak with his Aunt. Now go you forth before. I shall show to Cuwart secret things which are not yet known.”

Bellyn said,“Farewell, Reynart,”and went him forth to the Court. And he ran and hasted so fast, that he came before midday to the Court, and found the King in his palace with his Barons. The King marvelled when he saw him bring the male again which was made of the Bear's skin. The King said,“Say on, Bellyn, from whence come you? Where is the Fox? How is it that he has not the male with him?”

Bellyn said,“My Lord, I shall say you all that I know. I accompanied Reynart unto his house. And when he was ready, he asked me if I that would for your sake bear two letters to you. I said, for to do you pleasure and worship, I would gladly bear to you seven. Tho brought he to me this male wherein the letters be, which are indited by my cunning, and I gave counsel of the making of them. I think you saw never letters better nor craftlier made nor indited.”

The King commanded anon Bokart, his secretary, to read the letters, for he understood all manner languages. Tybert the Cat and he took the male off Bellyn's neck, and Bellyn has so far said and confessed that he therefore was dampned.(1)

The clerk Bokwart undid the male, and drew out Cuwart's head, and said,“Alas, what letters are these! Certainly, my Lord, this is Cuwart's head.”

“Alas,”said the King,“that ever I believed so the Fox!”There might men see great heaviness of the King and of the Queen. The King was so angry that he held long down his head, and at last, after many thoughts, he made a great cry, that all the beasts were afraid of the noise.

Tho spake Sir Firapeel the Leopard, which was sybbe(2) somewhat to the King, and said,“Sire King, how make you such a noise! You make sorrow enough though the Queen were dead. Let this sorrow go, and make good cheer. It is great shame. Be you not a Lord and King of this land? Is it not all under you, that here is?”

The King said,“Sir Firapeel, how should I suffer this? One false shrew and deceiver has betrayed me and brought me so far, that I have forwrought(3) and angered my friends the stout Bruin the Bear and Esegrim the Wolf, which sore me repents. And this goes against my worship, that I have done amiss against my best Barons, and that I trusted and believed so much the false Fox. And my wife is cause thereof. She prayed me so much that I heard her prayer, and that me repents, though it be too late.”

“What though, Sir King,”said the Leopard.“If there be any thing misdone it shall be amended. We shall give to Bruin the Bear to Esegrim the Wolf and to Ersewynde his wife for the piece of his skin and for their shoes, for to have good peace, Bellyn the Ram. For he has confessed himself that he gave counsel and consented to Cuward's death. It is reason that he abyou it. And we all shall go fetch Reynart, and we shall arrest him and hang him by the neck, without law or judgment. And there with all shall be content.”

————————————————————

(1) Dampned, condemned.

(2) Sybbe, related by blood.

(3) Forwrought, overwrought.

CHAPTER XXII

THE King said,“I will do it gladly.”

Firapeel the Leopard went tho to the prison and unbound them first, and then he said,“You, sirs, I bring to you a fast pardon and my lord's love and friendship. It repents him, and is sorry, that he ever has done spoken or trespassed against you, and therefore you shall have a good appointment. And also amends he shall give to you, Bellyn the Ram and all his lineage fro now further to doomsday, in such wise that wheresomever you find them, in field or in wood, that you may freely bite and eat them without any forfeit. And also the King grants to you that you may hunt and do the worst you can to Reynart and all his lineage without misdoing. This fair great privilege will the King grant to you ever to hold of him. And the King will that you swear to him never to misdo, but do him homage and fealty. I counsel you to do this, for you may do it honourably.”

Thus was the peace made by Firapeel the Leopard, friendly and well. And that cost Bellyn the Ram his tabart(1) and also his life, and the Wolf's lineage hold these privileges of the King. And in to this day they devour and eat Bellyn's lineage where that they may find them. This debate was begun in an evil time, for the peace could never sith(2) be made between them.

The King did forth with his Court and feast length twelve days longer for love of the Bear and the Wolf, so glad was he of the making of this peace.

————————————————————

(1) Tabart, coat. The sleeveless coat of a labourer.

(2) Sith, after.

CHAPTER XXIII

TO this great feast came all manner of beasts, for the King did do cry this feast over all in that land. There was the most joy and mirth that ever was seen among beasts. There was danced mannerly the hovedance,(1) with shalms, trumpets, and all manner of minstrelsy. The King did do ordain so much meat that everych found enough. And there was no beast in all his land so great nor so little but he was there, and there were many fowls and birds also, and all they that desired the King's friendship were there, saving Reynart the Fox, the red false pilgrim which lay in await to do harm and thought it was not good for him to be there. Meat and drink flowed there. There were plays and esbatemens. The feast was full of melody. One might have lust to see such a feast.

And right as the feast had dured eight days, about mid-day came in the Cony Lapreel before the King, where he sat on the table with the Queen, and said all heavily that all they heard him that were there,“My lord, have pity on my complaint, which is of great force and murder that Reynart the Fox would have done to me yester morrow as I came running by his borugh at Maleperdays. He stood before his door without, like a pilgrim. I supposed to have passed by him peaceably toward this feast, and when he saw me come he came against me saying his beads. I saluted him, but he spake not one word, but he raught out his right foot and dubbed me in the neck between my ears that I had weened I should have lost my head, but God be thanked I was so light that I sprang from him. With much pain came I off his claws. He grimmed as he had been angry by cause he held me no faster. Tho I escaped from him I lost my one ear, and I had four great holes in my head of his sharp nails that the blood sprang out and that I was nigh all aswoon, but for the great fear of my life I sprang and ran so fast from him that he could not overtake me. See, my Lord these great wounds that he has made to me with his sharp long nails. I pray you to have pity of me, and that you will punish this false traitor and murderer, or else shall there no man go and come over the heath in safety whiles he haunts his false and shrewd rule.”

————————————————————

(1) Hovedance, court (hof) dance.

CHAPTER XXIV

RIGHT as the Cony had made an end of his complaint, came in Corbant the Rook flowen in the place before the King and said,“Dear Lord, hear me. I bring you here a piteous complaint. I went to-day by the morrow(1) with Sharpebek my wife for to play upon the heath. And there lay Reynart the Fox down on the ground, like a dead caitiff. His eyes stared and his tongue hung long out of his mouth, like an hound had been dead. We tasted(2) and felt his belly but we found thereon no life. Tho went my wife and hearkened, and laid her ear before his mouth for to wit if he drew his breath, which misfell her evil: For the false fell Fox awaited well his time, and when he saw her so nigh him he caught her by the head and bit it off. The was I in great sorrow and cried loud,‘Alas! alas! what is there happened?’Then stood he hastily up and raught so covetously after me that for fear of death I trembled, and flew upon a tree thereby, and saw from far how the false caitiff ate and slonked(3) her in, so hungrily that he left neither flesh nor bone, no more but a few feathers. The small feathers he slang them in with the flesh; he was so hungry, he would well have eaten two. Tho went he his strete. Tho flew I down with great sorrow, and gathered up the feathers for to show them to you here. I would not be again in such peril and fear as I was there for a thousand mark of the finest gold that ever came of Araby. My Lord the King, see here this piteous work. These are the feathers of Sharpebek my wife! My Lord, if you will have worship you must do herefor justice, and avenge you in such wise as men may fear and hold of you, for if you suffer thus your safe conduct to be broken, you yourself shall not go peaceably in the highway. For the lords that do not justice, and suffer that the law be not executed upon the thieves, murderers, and them that misdo, they be partners before God of all their misdeeds and trespasses, and eueryche then will be a lord himself. Dear Lord see well to, for to keep yourself.”

————————————————————

(1) Morrow, morning.

(2) Tasted, touched.

(3) Slonked, swallowed (schlingen).

CHAPTER XXV

NOBLE the King was sore moved and angry when he had heard these complaints of the Cony and of the Rook. He was so frightful to look on that his eyes glimmered as fire; he brayed as loud as a bull, in such wise that all the Court quoke for fear; at the last he said, crying,“By my crown, and by the truth that I owe to my wife, I shall so awreak and avenge these trespasses that it shall be long spoken of after. That my safe conduct and my commandment is thus broken, I was over nice that I believed so lightly the false shrew. His false flattering speech deceived me. He told me he would go to Rome, and from thence over the sea to the Holy Land. I gave him male and psalter, and made of him a pilgrim, and meant all truth. Oh, what false touches can he! How can he stuff the sleeve with flocks! But this caused my wife. It was all by her counsel. I am not the first that have been deceived by women's counsel, by which many a great hurt has befallen. I pray and command all them that hold of me, and desire my friendship, be they here or wheresomever they be, that they with their counsel and deeds help me to avenge this over great trespass, that we and ours may abide in honour and worship and this false thief in shame. That he no more trespass against our safeguard, I will myself in my person help thereto all that I may.”

Esegrim the Wolf and Bruin the Bear heard well the King's words, and hoped well to be avenged on Reynart the Fox, but they durst not speak one word. The King was so sore moved that none durst well speak.

At last the Queen spake,“Sire, pour dieu no croyes myou toutes choses que on vous dye, et nor Iures pas legierment. A man of worship should not lightly believe, nor swear greatly, unto the time he knew the matter clearly; and also he ought by right hear that other party speak. There are many that complain on other and are in the default themself. Audi alteram partem: hear that other party. I have truly holden the Fox for good, and upon that that he meant no falsehood I helped him that I might. But howsomever it comes or goes, is he evil or good, me thinks for your worship that you should not proceed against him over hastily. That were not good nor honest, for he may not escape from you. You may prison him or flay him, he must obey your judgment.”

Then said Firapeel the Leopard,“My Lord, me thinks my Lady here has said to you truth and given you good counsel; do you well and follow her, and take advice of your wise council. And if he be founden guilty in the trespasses that now to you be showed, let him be sore punished according to his trespasses. And if he come not hither ere this feast be ended, and excuse him as he ought of right to do, then do as the council shall advise you. But and if he were twice as much false and ill as he is, I would not counsel that he should be done to more than right.”

Esegrim the Wolf said,“Sir Firapeel, all we agree to the same; as far as it pleases my lord the King, it cannot be better. But though Reynart were now here, and he cleared him of double so many plaints, yet should I bring forth against him that he had forfeited his life. But I will now be still and say not, because he is not present. And yet, above all this, he has told the King of certain treasure lying in Krekenpyt in Hulsterlo. There was never lied a greater leasing; therewith he has us all beguiled, and has sore hindered me and the Bear. I dare lay my life thereon that he said not thereof a true word. Now robbs he and steals upon the heath all that goes forth by his house. Nevertheless, Sir Firapeel, what that pleases the King and you that must well be done. But and if he would have come hither he might have been here, for he had knowledge by the King's messenger.”

The King said,“We will none otherwise send for him, but I command all them that owe me service and will my honour and worship that they make them ready to the war at the end of six days, all them that are archers and have bows, guns, bombards, horsemen and footmen, that all these be ready to besiege Maleperdays. I shall destroy Reynart the Fox if I be a king. You lords and sirs, what say you hereto? Will you do this with a good will?”

And they said and cried all,“Yea we, Lord, when that you will, we shall all go with you!”

CHAPTER XXVI

ALL these words heard Grymbart the Dasse, which was his brother son. He was sorry and angry. If it might have profited he ran then the highway to Maleperdays ward. He spared neither bush nor hawe, but he hasted so sore that he sweat. He sorrowed in himself for Reynart his rede Eme, and as he went he said to himself,“Alas, in what danger be you come in! Where shall you become! Shall I see you brought from life to death, or else exiled out of the land! Truly I may be well sorrowful, for you be head of all our lineage; you be wise of council, you be ready to help your friends when they have need, you can so well show your reasons that where you speak you win all.”

With such manner wailing and piteous words came Grymbart to Maleperdays, and found Reynart his Eme there standing, which had gotten two pigeons as they came first out of their nest to assay if they could fly, and because the feathers on their wings were too short they fell down to the ground; and as Reynart was gone out to seek his meat he espied them and caught them, and was come home with them.

And when he saw Grymbart coming, he tarried and said,“Welcome, my best beloved Nephew that I know in all my kindred. You have run fast, you are all besweat; have you any new tidings?”

“Alas,”said he,“lief Eme, it stands evil with you. You have lost both life and good. The King has sworn that he shall give you a shameful death. He has commanded all his folk within six days for to be here. Archers, footmen, horsemen, and people in wains! And he has guns, bombards, tents, and pavilions. And also he has do laden torches. See before you, for you have need. Esegrim and Bruin are better now with the King than I am with you. All that they will is done. Esegrim has don him to understand that you be a thief and a murderer; he has great envy to you. Lapreel the Cony, and Corbant the Rook have made a great complaint also. I sorrow much for your life, that for dread I am all sick.”

“Puf!”said the Fox.“Dear Nephew, is there nothing else? Be you so sore afraid hereof ? Make good cheer hardily. Though the King himself and all that are in the Court has sworn my death, yet shall I be exalted above them all. They may all fast jangle, clatter, and give counsel, but the Court may not prosper without me and my wiles and subtlety.”

CHAPTER XXVI

“DEAR Nephew, let all these things pass, and come here in and see what I shall give you; a good pair of fat pigeons. I love no meat better. They are good to digest. They may almost be swolowen in all whole; the bones are half blood; I eat them with that other. I feel myself other while encumbered in my stomach, therefore eat I gladly light meat. My wife Ermelyne shall receive us friendly, but tell her nothing of this thing for she should take it over heavily. She is tender of heart; she might for fear fall in some sickness; a little thing goes sore to her heart. And to-morrow early I will go with you to the Court, and if I may come to speech and may be heard, I shall so answer that I shall touch some nigh ynowh. Nephew, will not you stand by me as a friend ought to do to another?”

“Yes truly, dear Eme,”said Grymbart,“and all my good is at your commandment.”

“God thank you, Nephew,”said the Fox.“That is well said: If I may live, I shall quite it you.”

“Eme,”said Grymbart,“you may well come before all the lords and excuse you. There shall none arrest you nor hold as long as you be in your words. The Queen and the Leopard have gotten that.”

Then said the Fox,“Therefor I am glad; then I care not for the best of them an hair; I shall well save myself.”

They spoke no more hereof, but went forth into the burrow, and found Ermelyne there sitting by her younglings, which arose up anon and received them friendly. Grymbart saluted his aunt and the children with friendly words. The two pigeons were made ready for their supper, which Reynart had taken. Each of them took his part, as far as it would stretch; if each of them had had one more there should but little have left over. The Fox said,“Lief Nephew, how like you my children Rossel and Reynerdine? They shall do worship to all our lineage. They begin already to do well. That one catches well a chicken, and that other a pullet. They conne well also duck in the water after lapwings and ducks. I would oft send them for provender, but I will first teach them how they shall keep them from the grynnes, from the hunters, and from the hounds. If they were so far come that they were wise, I durst well trust to them that they should well victual us in many good divers meats that we now lack. And they like and follow me well, for they play all grimming, and where they hate they look friendly and merrily; for thereby they bring them under their feet, and bite the throat asunder. This is the nature of the Fox. They be swift in their taking, which pleases me well.”

“Eme,”said Grymbart,“you may be glad that you have such wise children. And I am glad of them also because they be of my kin.”

“Grymbart,”said the Fox,“you have sweat and be weary. It were high tide that you were at your rest.”

“Eme, if it pleases you, it thinks me good.”Tho lay they down on a litter made of straw. The Fox his wife and his children went all to sleep, but the Fox was all heavy and lay, sighed, and sorrowed(1) how he might best excuse himself.

On the morrow early he roomed(2) his castle and went with Grymbart. But he took leave first of Dame Ermelyne his wife and of his children, and said,“Think not long. I must go to the Court with Grymbart, my cousin. If I tarry somewhat, be not afraid; and if you hear any ill tidings, take it alway for the best. And see well to yourself and keep our castle well. I shall do yonder the best I can, after that I see how it goes.”

“Alas, Reynart,”said she,“how have you now thus taken upon you for to go to the Court again? The last time that you were there, you were in great jeopardy of your life. And you said you would never come there more.”

“Dame,”said the Fox,“the adventure of the world is wonderly; it goes otherwhile by weening. Many one weens to have a thing which he must forego. I must needs now go thither. Be content. It is all without dread. I hope to come at altherlengest within five days again.”

Herewith he departed; and went with Grymbart to the Court ward. And when they were upon the heath, then said Reynart,“Nephew, since I was last shriven I have done many shrewd turns. I would you would hear me now of all that I have trespassed in: I made the Bear to have a great wound for the male which was cut out of his skin; and also I made the Wolf and his wife to lose their shoon; I peased(3) the King with great leasings, and bare him on hand that the Wolf and the Bear would have betrayed him and would have slain him, so I made the King right wroth with them where they deserved it not; also I told to the King that there was great treasure in Hulsterlo of which he was never the better nor richer, for I lied all that I said; I led Bellyn the Ram and Cuwart the Hare with me, and slew Cuwart and sent to the King by Bellyn Cuwart's head in scorn; and I dowed(4) the Cony between the ears that almost I benamme(5) his life from him, for he escaped against my will, he was to me overswift; the Rook may well complain for I swallowed in Dame Sharpebek his wife. And also I have forgotten one thing, the last time that I was shriven to you, which I have since bethought me; and it was of great deceit that I did; which I now will tell you. I came with the Wolf walking between Houthulst and Elverdynge. There saw we go a red mare, and she had a black colt or a foal of four months old which was good and fat. Esegrim was almost storven for hunger, and prayed me go to the Mare and wit of her if she would sell her foal.

“I ran fast to the Mare and asked that of her. She said she would sell it for money.

“I demanded of her, how she would sell it.

“She said,‘It is written on my hinder foot. If you can read and be a clerk you may come see and read it.’

“Tho wist I well where she would be, and I said,‘Nay, for sooth, I cannot read. And also I desire not to buy your child. Esegrim has sent me hither, and would fain know the price thereof.’

“The Mare said,‘Let him come then himself, and I shall let him have knowledge.’

“I said,‘I shall;’and hastily went to Esegrim, and said,‘Eme will you eat your bellyful of this colt, so go fast to the Mare for she tarries after you. She has do write the price of her colt under her foot. She would that I should have read it, but I can not one letter, which me sore repents for I went never to school. Eme will you buy that colt? Can you read, so may you buy it.’

“‘Oh, Nephew, that can I well. What should me let? I can well French, Latin, English, and Dutch. I have gone to school at Oxenford, I have also with old and ancient doctors been in the audience and heard pleas, and also have given sentence, I am licensed in both laws; what manner writing that any man can devise I can read it as perfectly as my name: I will go to her, and shall anon understand the price,’and he bade me to tarry for him, and he ran to the Mare, and asked her how she would sell her foal or keep it. She said,‘The sum of the money stands written after on my foot.’He said,‘Let me read it.’She said,‘Do,’and lifte up her foot, which was new shod with iron and six strong nails; and she smote him, without missing, on his head, that he fell down as he had been dead. A man should well have ridden a mile ere he arose. The Mare trotted away with her colt, and she left Esegrim lying shrewdly hurt and wounded. He lay and bled, and howled as an hound. I went tho to him and said,‘Sir Esegrim, dear Eme, how is it now with you? Have you eaten yenowh of the colt? Is your belly full? Why give you me no part? I did your errand. Have slept you your dinner? I pray you tell me, what was written under the mare's foot? What was it, prose or rhyme, metre or verse? I would fain know it. I think it was cantum, for I heard you sing, me thought, from fear; for you were so wise that no man could read it better than you.’

“‘Alas, Reynart, alas!’said the Wolf,‘I pray you to leave your mocking. I am so foul arrayed and sore hurt than an heart of stone might have pity on me. The Mare with her long leg had an iron foot, I weened the nails thereof had been letters, and she hit me at the first stroke six great wounds in my head that almost it is cloven. Such manner letters shall I never more desire to read.’‘Dear Eme, is that truth that you tell me? I have great mervaylle. I held you for one of the wisest clerks that now live. Now I hear well it is true that I long since have read and heard, that the best clerks are not the wisest men. The lay people otherwhile wax wise. The cause that these clerks are not the wisest is that they study so much in the cunning and science that they therein doole.’Thus brought I Esegrim in this great laste and harm, that he vnneth byhelde his life.

“Lief Nephew now have I told you all my sins that I remember. Whatsoever fallen at the Court—I wote never how it shall stand with me there—I am not now so sore afraid, for I am clear from sin. I will gladly come to mercy and receive penance by your counsel.”

Grymbart said,“The trespasses are great. Nevertheless who that is dead must abide dead, and therefore I will forgive it you altogether, with the fear that you shall suffer therefor ere you shall conne excuse you of the death, and hereupon I will assoil you. But the most hinder that you shall have shall be, that you sent Cuwart's head to the Court, and that you blinded the King with sutthe(6) lies. Eme, that was right evil done.”

The Fox said,“What, lief nephew! Who that will go through the world this to hear and that to see and that other to tell, truly it may not clearly be done. How should any man handle honey but if he licked his fingers? I am often rored and pricked in my conscience as to love God above all thing and my even Crysten as myself, as is to God well acceptable and according to his law. But how ween you that reason within forth fights against the outward will, then stand I all still in myself, that me thinks I have lost all my wits, and wote not what me ails, I am then in such a thought I have now all left my sins, and hate all thing that is not good, and climb in high contemplation abone his commandments. But this special grace have I when I am alone; but in a short while after, when the world comes in me, then find I in my way so many stones, and the foot spores(7) that these loose prelates and rich priests go in, that I am anon taken again. Then comes the world and will have this; and the flesh will live pleasantly; which lay before me so many things that I then lose all my good thoughts and purpose. I hear there sing, pipe, laugh, play, and all mirth, and I hear that these prelates and rich curates preach and say all otherwise than they think and do. There learn I to lie, the leasings are most used in the lord's courts; certainly lords, ladies, priests, and clerks, maken most leasings. Men dare not tell to the lords now the truth. There is default. I must flatter and lie also or else I should be shut without the door. I have often heard men say truth and rightfully, and have their reason made with a leasing like to their purpose, who brought it in and went through because their matter should seem the fairer. The leasing often comes unavised, and falls in the matter unwittingly, and so, when she is well clad, it goes forth through with that other.

“Dear Nephew thus must men now lie here and there, say sooth, flatter and menace, pray and curse, and seek every man upon his feeblest and weakest. Who otherwise will now haunt and use the world than devise a leasing in the fairest wise, and that bewimple with kerchiefs about in such wise that men take it for a truth, he is not run away from his master. Can he that subtilty in such wise that he stammer not in his words, and may then be heard, Nephew, this man may do wonder. He may wear scarlet and grise.(8) He wins in the spiritual law and temporal also, and wheresomever he has to do. Now are there many false shrews that have great envy that they have so great fardel,(9) and ween that they can also well lie; and take on them to lie and to tell it forth. He would fain eat of the fat morsels. But he is not believed nor heard. And many are there that be so plump and foolish that when they ween best to pronounce and show their matter and conclude, they fall beside and out thereof, and cannot then help themself, and leave their matter without tail or head; and he is acompted for a fool; and many mock them therewith. But who can give to his leasing a conclusion, and pronounce it without tatelying, like as it were written before him, and that he can so blind the people that his leasing shall better be believed than the truth: that is the man. What cunning is it to say the truth that is good to do? How laugh these false subtle shrews that give counsel, to make these leasings and set them forth, and maken unright go above right, and maken bills and set in things that never were thought nor said, and teach men see through their fingers; and all for to win money and let their tongues to hire for to maintain and strengthen their leasings. Alas, Nephew, this is an evil cunning, of which life-scathe and hurt may come thereof. I say not but that otherwhile men must jape, bourd,(10) and lie in small things; for whoso says alway truth, he may not now go nowhere through the world. There are many that play Placebo. Whoso alway says truth, shall find many lettings in his way. Men may well lie when it is need, and after amend it by counsel. For all trespasses there is mercy. There is no man so wise, but he dooleth(11) other while.”

Grymbart said,“Well, dear Eme, what thing shall you let? You know all thing at the narrowest. You should bring me hastily in doting; your reasons passen my understanding. What need have you to shrive you? You should yourself by right be the priest, and let me and other sheep come to you for to be shriven. You know the state of the world in such wise as no man may halt before you.”

With such manner talking they came walking in to the Court. The Fox sorrowed somewhat in his heart, nevertheless he bare it out and striked forth through all the folk till he came into the place where the King himself was. And Grymbart was alway by the Fox and said,“Eme, be not afraid, and make good cheer! Who that is hardy, the adventure helps him.(12) Often one day is better than sometime a whole year.”

The Fox said,“Nephew, you say truth. God thank you, you comfort me well.”

And forth he went, and looked grimly here and there, as who says,“What will you? here come I.”He saw there many of his kin standing which yonned(13) him but little good, as the Otter, Beaver, and other to the number of ten whom I shall name afterward. And some were there that loved him.

The Fox came in and fell down on his knees before the King, and began his words and said:—

————————————————————

(1) Sorrowed, took careful thought.

(2) Roomed, vacated.

(3) Peased, pacified, appeased.

(4) Dowed, struck.

(5) Benamme, took away.

(6) Sutthe, flattering.

(7) Spores, tracks.

(8) Grise, fur.

(9) Fardel, burden.

(10) Bourd, jest.

(11) Dooleth, errs (Dutch, doolen).

(12) Fortune favours the bold.

(13) Yonned, conceded. First English unnan, to grant.

CHAPTER XXVIII

“GOD from whom nothing may be hid, and above all thing is mighty, save my Lord the King and my Lady the Queen and give him grace to know who has right and who has wrong. For there live many in the world that seem otherwise outward than they be within, I would that God showed openly every man's misdeeds, and all their trespasses stooden written in their foreheads, and it cost me more than I now say; and that you, my Lord the King, knew as much as I do how I dispose me both early and late in your service. And therefore am I complained on of the evil shrews, and with leasings am put out of your grace and conceit, and would charge me with great offences, without deserving, against all right. Wherefore I cry out harowe on them that so falsely have belied me, and brought me in such trouble. Howbeit, I hope and know you both my Lord and my Lady for so wise and discreet, that you be not led nor believe such leasings nor false tales out of the right way, for you have not be woned so to do. Therefore, dear Lord, I beseech you to consider by your wisdom all things by right and law. Is it in deed or in speech, do every man right. I desire no better. He that is guilty and found faulty, let him be punished. Men shall well know ere I depart out of this Court who that I am. I cannot flatter, I will always show openly my head.”How the King answered upon Reynart's excuse. All they that were in the palace weren all still and wondered that the Fox spake so stoutly.

The King said,“Ha, Reynart, how well can you your fallacy and salutation doon! But your fair words may not help you. I think well that you shall, this day, for your works be hanged by your neck. I will not much chide with you, but I shall short your pain. That you love us well, that have you well showed on the Cony and on Corbant the Rook. Your falseness and your false inventions shall without long tarrying make you to die. A pot may go so long to water, that at the last it comes tobroken home. I think your pot, that so oft has deceived us, shall now hastily be broken.”

Reynart was in great fear of these words. He would well he had been at Cologne when he came thither. Then thought he I must here through, how that I do.

“My Lord the King,”said he,“it were well reason that you heard my words all out. Though I were dampned to the death, yet ought you to hear my words out. I have yet heretofore time given to you many a good counsel and profitable, and in need alway have biden by you where other beasts have wyked(1) and gone their way. If now the evil beasts with false matters have before you with wrong belied me, and I might not come to my excuse, ought I not then to plain? I have before this seen that I should be heard before another; yet might these things well change and come in their old state. Old good deeds ought to be remembered. I see here many of my lineage and friends standing, that seem they set now little by me, which nevertheless should sore dere(2) in their hearts, that you, my Lord the King, should destroy me wrongfully. If you so did, you should destroy the truest servant that you have in all your lands. What ween you, Sir King, had I known myself guilty in any feat or broke,(3) that I would have come hither to the law among all my enemies? Nay, sire, nay. Not for all the world of red gold. For I was free and at large. What need had I to do that? But, God be thanked, I know myself clear of all misdeeds, that I dare welcome openly in the light and to answer to all the complaints that any man can say on me. But when Grymbart brought me first these tidings, tho was I not well pleased but half from myself, that I leapt here and there as an unwise man, and had I not been in the censures of the Church I had without tarrying have come, but I went dolynge(4) on the heath, and wist not what to do for sorrow. And then it happened that Mertyne, my Eme, the Ape, met with me, which is wiser in clergy than some priest. He has been advocate for the Bishop of Cameryk nine year during. He saw me in this great sorrow and heaviness, and said to me,‘Dear Cousin, me thinks you are not well with yourself, what ails you? Who has displeased you? Thing that touches charge ought to be given in knowledge to friends. A true friend is a great help; he finds oft better counsel than he that the charge rests on, for whosomever is charged with matters is so heavy and acombred with them that oft he can not begin to find the remedy, for such be so woe like as they had lost their inwytte.’(5) I said‘Dear Eme, you say truth, for in likewise is fallen to me. I am brought into a great heaviness, undeserved and not guilty, by one to whom I have alway been an hearty and great friend; that is the Cony which came to me yesterday in the morning whereas I sat before my house and said matins.’

“He told me he would go to the Court, and saluted me friendly, and I him again.

“Tho said he to me,‘Good Reynart, I am an hungred and weary. Have you any meat?’

“I said,‘Yea, ynowh; come near.’

“Tho gave I him a couple of manchets(6) with sweet butter. It was upon a Wednesday, on which day I am not wont to eat any flesh, and also I fasted because of this feast of Whitsuntide which approached. For who that will taste of the overest wisehede, and live ghostly in keeping the commandments of our Lord, he must fast and make him ready against the high feasts. Et vos estote parati. Dear Eme, I gave him fair white bread with sweet butter, wherewith a man might well be eased that were much hungry. And when he had eaten his bellyful, tho came Rossel, my youngest son, and would have taken away that was left. For young children would alway fain eten. And with that he tasted for to have taken somewhat, the Cony smote Rossel before his mouth that his teeth bled, and he fell down half aswoon. When Reynardyn, my eldest son, saw that, he sprang to the Cony and caught him by the head, and should have slain him had I not rescued him. I helped him, that he went from him, and beat my child sore therefor.

“Lapreel the Cony ran to my Lord the King and said I would have murdered him. See, Eme, thus come I in the words and I am laid in the blame. And yet he complaines, and I plain not.

“After this came Corban the Rook fleeing with a sorrowful noise. I asked what him ailed.

“And he said,‘Alas my wife is dead. Yonder lies a dead hare full of moths and worms, and there she ate so much thereof that the worms have bitten atwo her throat.’

“I asked him how comes that by. He would not speak a word more, but flew his way, and let me stand.

“Now says he that I have bitten and slain her. How should I come so nigh her? For she flees and I go afoot. Behold, dear Eme, thus I am born on hand. I may say well that I am unhappy. But peradventure it is for my old sins. It were good for me if I could patiently suffer it.

“The Ape said to me,‘Nephew, you shall go to the Court before the lords, and excuse you.’

“‘Alas, Eme, that may not be, for the Archdeacon has put me in the Pope's curse because I counselled Esegrim the Wolf for to leave his religion at Elmare and forsake his habit. He complained to me that he lived so straitly, as in long fasting, and many things reading and singing, that he could not endure it; if he should long abide there, he should die. I had pity of his complaining, and I holpe him as a true friend, that he came out. Which now me sore repents, for he laboures all that he can against me to the King for to do me be hanged. Thus does he evil for good. See, Eme, thus am I at the end of all my wits and of counsel. For I must go to Rome for an absolution, and then shall my wife and children suffer much harm and blame. For these evil beasts that hate me shall do to them all the hurt they may, and fordrive them where they can. And I would well defend them if I were free of the curse, for then I would go to the Court and excuse me, where now I dare not. I should do great sin if I came among the good people, I am afraid God should plague me.’

“‘Nay, cousin, be not afraid. Ere I should suffer you in this sorrow, I know the way to Rome well. I understand me on this work. I am called there Mertyne the bishop's clerk, and am well beknown there. I shall do cite the Archdeacon and take a plea against him, and shall bring with me for you an absolution against his will, for I know there all that is for to be done or left. There dwells Simon, my Eme, which is great and mighty there. Who that may give aught, he helps him anon. There is Prentout, Wayte, Scathe, and other of my friends and allies. Also I shall take some money with me if I need any. The prayer is with gifts hardy;(7) with money alway the right goes forth. A true friend shall for his friend adventure both life and good, and so shall I for you in your right. Cousin, make good cheer! I shall not rest after to-morrow till I come to Rome, and I shall solicit your matters. And go you to the Court as soon as you may. All your misdeeds and the sins that have brought you in the great sentence and curse, I make you quit of them and take them in myself. When you come to the Court you shall find there Rukenawe my wife, her two sisters, and my three children, and many more of our lineage. Dear cousin, speak to them hardily. My wife is sondrely(8) wise, and will gladly do somewhat for her friends. Who that has need of help shall find in her great friendship. One shall alway seek on his friends, though he has angered them, for blood must creep where it cannot go. And if so be that you be so overcharged that you may have no right, then send to me by night and day to the Court of Rome, and let me have knowledge thereof, and all tho that are in the land, is it King or Queen, wife or man, I shall bring them all in the Pope's Curse and send there an interdict that no man shall read nor singen nor christen children, nor bury the dead, nor receive sacrament, till that you shall have good right. Cousin, this shall I well get, for the Pope is so sore old that he is but little set by, and the cardinal of Pure Gold has all the might of the Court. He is young and great of friends, he has a concubine whom he much loves, and what she desires that gets she anon. See, Cousin, she is my niece, and I am great and may do much with her, in such wise what I desire I fail not of it but am alway furthered therein. Wherefore, Cousin, bid my Lord the King that he do you right I wote well he will not warn(9) you, for the right is heavy enough to every man.’

“My Lord the King, when I heard this I laughed, and with great gladness came hither, and have told you all truth. If there be any in this Court that can lay on me any other matter with good witness, and prove it, as ought to be to a noble man, let me then make amends according to the law; and if you will not leave off hereby, then set me day and field, and I shall make good on him all so ferre as he be of as good birth as I am and to me like, and who that can with fighting get the worship of the field, let him have it. This right has standen yet hitherto, and I will not it should be broken by me. The law and right does no man wrong.”

All the beasts both poor and rich were all still when the Fox spake so stoutly. The Cony Lapreel and the Rook were so sore afraid that they durst not speak, but piked and striked them out of the Court both two, and when they were a room far in the plain they said,“God grant that this fell murderer may fare evil. He can bewrap and cover his falsehood, that his words seem as true as the gospel. Hereof knows no man than we: how should we bring witness. It is better that we wyke(10) and depart, than we should hold a field and fight with him; he is so shrewd, yea though there of us were five we could not defend us, but that he should slay us all.”

Esegrim the Wolf and Bruin the Bear were woe in themself when they saw these two room the court.

The King said,“If any man will complain, let him come forth, and we shall hear him: yesterday camen here so many, where are they now Reynart is here?”

The Fox said,“My Lord, there are many that complain that and if they saw their adversary they would be still and make no plaint; witness now of Lapreel the Cony and Corbant the Rook, which have complained on me to you in my absence, but now that I am come in your presence they flee away, and dare not abide by their words. If men should believe false shrews it should do much harm and hurt to the good men, as for me it skills not. Nevertheless, my lord, if they had by your commandment asked of me forgiveness, how be it they have greatly trespassed, yet I had for your sake pardoned and forgive them; for I will not be out of charity, nor hate nor complain on my enemies. But I set all thing in God's hand, he shall work and avenge it as it pleases him.”

The King said,“Reynart, me thinks you be grieved as you say. Are you withinforth as you seem outward? Nay, it is not so clear nor so open, nowhere nigh, as you here have showed. I must say what my grief is, which touches your worship and life, that is to wit that you have done a foul and shameful trespass when I had pardoned you all your offences and trespasses, and you promised to go over the sea on pilgrimage, and gave to you male and staff. And after this you sent me by Bellyn the Ram the male again and therein Cuwart's Head. How might you do a more reprovable trespass? How were you so hardy to dare to me do such a shame? Is it not evil done to send to a lord his servant's head? You cannot say nay hereagainst, for Bellyn the Ram, which was our chaplain, told us all the matter how it happed? Such reward as he had when he brought us the message, the same shall you have, or right shall fail.”

Tho was Reynart so sore afraid that he wist not what to say. He was at his wit's end, and looked about him piteously, and saw many of his kin and allies that heard all this, but nought they said. He was all pale in his visage, but no man proffered him hand nor foot to help him.

The King said,“Thou subtle fellow and false shrew, why speakest thou not? Now dumb?”

The Fox stood in great dread, and sighed sore that all heard him. But the Wolf and the Bear were glad thereof.

————————————————————

(1) Wyked, flinched (Dutch, wyken; German, weichen).

(2) Dere, take hurt.

(3) Broke, usage.

(4) Dolynge, grieving.

(5) Inwytte, inner consciousness.

(6) Manchets, small loaves of white bread.

(7) Hardy, bold.

(8) Sondrely, peculiarly.

(9) Warn, refuse.

(10) Wyke, flinch, yield.

CHAPTER XXIX

DAME Rukenawe the She Ape, Reynart's Aunt, was not well pleased. She was great with the Queen and well beloved. It happened well for the Fox that she was there, for she understood all wisdom, and she durst well speak, where as it to do was. Wherever she came everich was glad of her.

She said,“My Lord the King, you ought not to be angry when you sit in judgment, for that becomes not your nobleness. A man that sits in judgment ought to put from him all wrath and anger. A lord ought to have discretion that should sit in justice. I know better the points of the law than some that wear furred gowns, for I have learned many of them and was made cunning in the law. I had in the Pope's palace of Woerden a good bed of hay, where other beasts lay on the hard ground, and also when I had there to do I was suffered to speak, and was heard before another because I knew so well the law. Seneca writes that a lord shall overall do right and law, he shall charge none to whom he has given his safeguard to above the right and law; the law ought not to halt for no man. And every man that stands here would well bethink him what he has done and bedriven(1) in his days, he should the better have patience and pity on Reynart. Let every man know him self, that is my counsel. There is none that stands so surely but otherwhile he falls or slides. Who that never misdid nor sinned is holy and good, and has no need to amend him. When a man does amiss and then by counsel amendeth it, that is humanly and so ought he to do; but alway to misdo and trespass and not to amend him, that is evil and a devily life. Mark then what is written in the gospel, Estote misericordes, be you merciful; yet stands there more, Nolite judicare et non judicabimini, deem you no man and you shall not be deemed. There stands also how the pharisees brought a woman taken in adultery and would have stoned her to death. They asked Our Lord what he said thereto; he said,‘Who of you all is without sin let him cast the first stone.’Tho abode no man but left her there standing. Me thinks it is so here. There be many that see a straw in another's eyou that can not see a balke in his own. There be many that deem other, and himself is worst of all. Though one fall oft, and at last arises up and comes to mercy, he is not thereof damned. God receives all them that desire his mercy. Let no man condemn another though they wist that he had done amiss; yet let them see their own defaults, and then may they themself correct first, and then Reynart my Cousin should not fare the worse. For his father and his grandfather have alway been in more love and reputation in this Court than Esegrim the Wolf or Bruin the Bear with all their friends and lineage. It has been heretofore an unlike comparison, the wisdom of Reynart my Cousin, and the honour and worship of him, that he has done, and the counsel of them; for they know not how the world goes. Me thinks this Court is all turned upside down. These false shrews, flatterers, and deceivers, arise and wax great by the lordes, and are enhanced up; and the good, true, and wise are put down, for they have been wont to counsel truly and for the honour of the King. I can not see how this may stand long.”

Then said the King,“Dame, if he had done to you such trespass as he has done to other it should repent you. Is it wonder that I hate him? He breaks away my safeguard. Have you not heard the complaints that here have been showed of him, of murder, of theft, and of treason? Have you such trust in him? Think you that he is thus good and clear? then set him up on the altar, and worship and pray to him as to a saint. But there is none in all the world that can say any good of him; you may say much for him, but in the end you shall find him all nought. He has neither kin nor one friend that will enterprise to help him. He has so deserved. I have great marvel of you. I heard never of none that has fellowshipped with him that ever thanked him or said any good of him, save you now, but alway he has striked them with his tail.”

Then the She Ape answered and said,“My lord, I love him and have him in great charity. And also I know a good deed that he once in your presence did, whereof you could him great thank. Though now it be thus turned, yet shall the heaviest weigh most. A man shall love his friend by measure, and not his enemy hate overmuch. Steadfastness and constancy is fitting and behoves to the lords, how soever the world turns. Me ought not to praise too much the day, till even be come. Good counsel is good for him that will do thereafter.”

————————————————————

(1) Bedriven, experienced (Dutch, bedreven).

CHAPTER XXX

“NOW two year past came a Man and a Serpent here into this Court for to have judgment, which was to you and yours right doubtful. The Serpent stood in an hedge whereas he supposed to have gone through, but he was caught in a snare by the neck that he might not escape without help, but should have lost his life there. The Man came forth by, and the Serpent called to him and cried, and prayed the Man that he would help him out of the snare, or else he must there die. The Man had pity of him, and said,‘If thou promise to me that thou wilt not envenom me, nor do me none harm nor hurt, I shall help thee out of this peril.’The Serpent was ready, and swore a great oath that he now nor never should do him harm nor hurt. Then he unloosed him and delivered him out of the snare. And they went forth together a good while that the Serpent had great hunger, for he had not eaten a great while before, and sterte to the Man and would have slain him. The Man sterte away and was afraid, and said,‘Wilt thou now slay me? hast thou forgotten the oath that thou madest to me that thou shouldest not misdo nor hurt me?’The Serpent answered,‘I may do it good before all the world that I do. The need of hunger may cause a man to break his oath.’The Man said,‘If it may be not better, give me so long respite till we meet and find that may judge the matter by right.’The Serpent granted thereto. Thus they went together so long that they found Tyseln the Raven and Slyndpere his son; there rehearsed they their reasons. Tyseln the Raven judged anon that he should eat the Man. He would fain have eaten his part, and his son also. The Serpent said to the Man,‘How is it now? What think you? Have I not won?’The Man said,‘How should a robber judge this? He should have avail thereby. And also he is alone: there must be two or three at least together, and that they understand the right and law, and that done let the sentence gon; I am nevertheless ill on enough.’They agreed and went forth both together so long that they found the Bear and the Wolf, to whom they told their matter. And they anon judged that the Serpent should slay the Man. For the need of hunger breaks oath alway. The Man then was in great doubt and fear, and the Serpent came and cast his venom at him; but the Man leapt away from him with great pain, and said,‘You do great wrong that you thus lie in await to slay me. You have no right thereto.’The Serpent said,‘Is it not enough yet? It has been twice judged.’‘Yea,’said the Man,‘that is of them that are wont to murder and rob. All that ever they swear and promise they hold not. But I appeal this matter into the Court before our Lord the King, and that thou mayst not forsake.(1) And what judgment that shall be given there, shall I obey and suffer, and never do the contrary.’The Bear and the Wolf said that it should be so, and that the Serpent desired no better. They supposed if it should come before you it should go there as they would. I think you be well remembered hereof. Tho came they all to the Court before you; and the Wolf's two children came with their father, which were called Empty Belly and Never Full, because they would eat of the Man; for they howled for great hunger. Wherefore you commanded them to avoid your Court. The Man stood in great dread, and called upon your good grace, and told how the Serpent would have taken his life from him, to whom he had saved his life, and that, above his oath and promise, he would have devoured him. The Serpent answered,‘I have not trespassed, and that I report me wholly unto the King. For I did it to save my life, for need of life one may break his oath and promise.’My Lord that time were you and all your Council herewith accombred. For your noble grace saw the great sorrow of the Man, and you would not that a man should for his gentleness and kindness be judged to death. And on that other, since hunger, and need to save the life, seeks narrowly to be holpen, here was none in all the Court that could nor knew the right hereof. There were some that would fain the Man had be holpen. I see them here standing. I wot well they said that they could not end this matter. Then commanded you that Reynart, my nephew, should come and say his advice in this matter. That time was he above all other believed and heard in this Court, and you bade him give sentence according to the best right and we all shall follow him, for he knew the ground of the law. Reynart said,‘My Lord, it is not possible to give a true sentence after their words, for in hearsaying are oft leasings. But and if I might see the Serpent in the same peril and need that he was in when the Man loosed him and unbound, then wist I well what I should say. And who that would do otherwise he should misdo against right.’Then said, you, my Lord,‘Reynart, that is well said. We all accord hereto; for no man can say better.’Then went the Man and the Serpent into the place whereas he found the Serpent. Reynart bade that the Serpent should be set in the snare in likewise as he was. And it was done. Then said you, my Lord,‘Reynart, how thinks you now? What judgment shall we give?’Then said Reynart the Fox,‘My Lord, now are they both like as they were before. They have neither won nor lost. See, my Lord, how I judge for a right, also ferre as it shall please your noble grace. If the Man will now loose and unbind the Serpent, upon the promise and oath that he before made to him, he may well do it. But if he think that he for anything should be encumbered or hindered by the Serpent, or for need of hunger would break his oath and promise, then judge I that the Man may go freely where he will, and let the Serpent abide still bounden, like as he might have done at the beginning: for he would have broken his oath and promise, whereas he holp him out of such fearful peril. Thus thinks me a rightful judgment that the Man shall have his free choice like as he before had.’Lo my Lord this judgment thought you good, and all your council which at that time were by you; and followed the same, and praised Reynart's wisdom, that he had made the Man quit and free. Thus the Fox wisely kept your noble honour and worship, as a true servant is bound to do to his Lord. Where has the Bear or the Wolf done ever to you so much worship? They conne well huylen and blasen, steal and rob, and eat fat morsels and fill their bellies, and then judge they for right and law that small thieves that steal hens and chickens should be hanged, but they themself that steal kine, oxen, and horses, they shall go quit and be lords. And same as though they were wiser than Solomon, Avicene, or Aristoteles; and each will be holden high proud, and praised of great deeds and hardy; but and they come where as it is to do, they are the first that flee. Then must the simple go forth before, and they keep the reward behind. Och, my Lord, these and other like to them be not wise, but they destroy town, castle, land, and people. They reck not whose house burns, so that they may warm them by the coals. They seek all their own avail and singular profit. But Reynart the Fox and all his friends and lineage sorowen(2) and think to prefer the honour, worship, fordeel,(3) and profit of their lord, and for wise counsel which oft more profits here than pride and boast. This does Reynart, though he have no thank. At long it shall be well known who is best and does most profit. My Lord, you say that his kin and lineage draw all afterward from him, and stand not by him for his falsehood and deceivable and subtle touches. I would another had said that; there should then such wrake be taken thereof that him might growl that ever he saw him. But, my Lord, we will forbear you; you may save your pleasure; and also I say it not by you. Were there any that would bedrive anything against you, with words or with werkes, him that would we so do to, that men should say we had been there. There as fighting is, we are not wont to be afraid. My Lord, by your leave, I may well give you knowledge of Reynart's friends and kin. There are many of them that for his sake and love will adventure life and good. I know myself for one. I am a wife. I should, if he had need, set my life and good for him. Also I have three full waxen children which are hardy and strong, whom I would all together adventure for his love, rather than I should see him destroyed; yet had I liever die than I saw them miscarry before my eyes, so well love I them.”

————————————————————

(1) Forsake, deny.

(2) Sorowen, take care.

(3) Fordeel, advantage (Dutch, Voordeel; German, Vortheil).

CHAPTER XXXI

DAME Rukenawe called them forth and said,“Welcome, my dear children: to me forth, and stand by Reynart, your dear nephew.”Then said she,“Come forth all you that be of my kin and Reynart's, and let us pray the King that he will do to Reynart right of the land.”

Tho came forth many a beast anon, as the Squirrel, the Muskrat, the Fitchews, the Marten, the Beaver with his wife Ordegale, the Genete,(1) the Otter, the Boussyng, and the Ferret, these two eat as fain polaylle as does Reynart. The Otter and Pantecroet his wife, whom I had almost forgotten, yet were they before, with the Beaver, enemies to the Fox, but they durst not gainsay Dame Rukenawe, for they were afraid of her. She was also the wisest of all his kin of counsel and was most doubted.(2) There came also more than twenty other, because of her, for to stand by Reynart. There came also Dame Atrote with her two sisters, Weasel and Hermelin, the Ass, the Badger, the Water-rat, and many more to the number of forty, which all camen and stoden by Reynart the Fox.

“My Lord the King,”said Rukenawe,“come and see here if Reynart have any friends. Here may you see we are your true subjects, which for you would adventure both life and good if you had need. Though you be hardy, mighty, and strong, our well-willed friendship cannot hurt you. Let Reynart the Fox well bethink him upon these matters that you have laid against him, and if he cannot excuse them, then do him right. We desire no better. And this by right ought to no man be warned.”(3)

The Queen then spake,“This said I to him yesterday. But he was so fierce and angry that he would not hear it.”

The Leopard said also,“Sire, you may judge no further than your men give their verdict; for if you would go forth by will and might, that were not worshipful for your estate. Hear always both parties, and then by the best and wisest counsel give judgment discreetly according to the best right.”

The King said,“This is all true, but I was so sore moved when I was informed of Cuwart's death and saw his head, that I was hot and hasty. I shall hear the Fox Can he answer and excuse him of that is laid against him, I shall gladly let him go quit; and also at request of his good friends and kin.”

Reynart was glad of these words, and thought, God thank my Aunt, she has the rys do blosme again.(4) She has well holpen me forth now. I have now a good foot to dance on. I shall now look out of my eyes, and, bring forth the fairest leasing that ever man heard, and bring myself out of this danger.

————————————————————

(1) The genete is related to the civet cat.

(2) Doubted, feared.

(3) Warned, refused.

(4) She has made the twig blossom again.

CHAPTER XXXII

THEN spake Reynart the Fox and said,“Alas, what say you! is Cuwart dead? And where is Bellyn the Ram? What brought he to you when he came again? For I delivered to him three jewels; I would fain know where they are become. That one of them should he have given to you, my Lord the King, and the other-two to my Lady the Queen.”

The King said,“Bellyn brought us nought else but Cuwart's head, like as I said you before; whereof I took on him wrake. I made him to lose his life, for the foul caitiff said to me that he himself was of the counsel of the letters making that were in the male.”

“Alas, my lord, is this very truth? Woe to me caitiff that ever I was born! Since that these good jewels be thus lost, my heart will break for sorrow. I am sorry that I now live! What shall my wife say when she hears hereof? She shall go out of her wit for sorrow. I shall never, all so long as I live, have her friendship. She shall make much sorrow when she hears thereof.”

The She Ape said,“Reynart, dear Nephew, what profits that you make all this sorrow? Let it pass, and tell us what these jewels were. Peradventure we shall find counsel to have them again. If they be above earth Master Akeryn shall labour for them in his books, and also we shall curse for them in all the churches, unto the time that we have knowledge where they been. They may not be lost.”

“Nay, Aunt, think not that, for they that have them will not lightly depart from them. There was never King that ever gave so rich jewels as these be. Nevertheless you have somewhat with your words eased my heart and made it lighter than it was. Alas, lo, here you may see how he or they to whom a man trusts most is often by him or them deceived. Though I should go all the world through, and my life in adventure set therefor, I shall wit where these jewels are become.”With a dismalled and sorrowful speech, said the Fox:“Hearken you all my kin and friends, I shall name to you these jewels what they were, and then may you say that I have a great loss. That one of them was a ring of fine gold, and within the ring next the finger were written letters enamelled with sable and azure, and there were three Hebrew names therein. I could not myself read nor spell them, for I understand not that language; but Master Abrion of Trier he is a wise man, he understands well all manner of languages and the virtue of all manner herbs, and there is no beast so fierce nor strong but he can dompte him, for if he see him once he shall do as he will, and yet he believes not on God. He is a Jew, the wisest in conning, and specially he knows the virtue of stones. I showed him once this ring. He said that they were tho three names that Seth brought out of Paradise when he brought to his father Adam the Oyle of Mercy, and whosomever bears on him these three names he shall never be hurt by thunder nor lightning, nor no witchcraft shall have power over him, nor be tempted to do sin. And also he shall never take harm by cold though he lay three winters long nights in the field, though it snowed, stormed, or frore, never so sore, so great might have these words, witness of Master Abrion. Without forth on the ring stood a stone of three manner colours; the one part was like red crystal, and shone like as fire had been therein, in such wise that if one would go by night him behoved none other light, for the shining of the stone made and gave as great a light as it had been midday; that other part of the stone was white and clear as it had been burnished, who so had in his eyes any smart or soreness, or in his body any swelling, or headache, or any sickness, withoutforth if he striked this stone on the place where the grief is he shall anon be whole; or if any man be sick in his body of venom, or ill meat in his stomach, of colic, strangulation, stone, fistel, or cancer, or any other sickness, save only the very death, let him lay this stone in a little water and let him drink it, and he shall forthwith be whole and all quit of his sickness. Alas,”said the Fox,“we have good cause to be sorry to lose such a jewel! Furthermore the third colour was green like glass, but there were some sprinkles therein like purple; the master told for truth, that who that bare this stone upon him should never be hurt of his enemy, and was no man, were he never so strong and hardy, that might misdo him; and wherever that he fought he should have victory, were it by night or by day, also ferre as he beheld it fasting; and also thereto, wheresomever he went and in what fellowship, he should be beloved, though he had hated him before, if he had the ring upon him they should forget their anger as soon as they saw him. Also though he were all naked in a field again an hundred armed men, he should be well hearted and escape from them with worship; but he must be a noble gentleman and have no churl's conditions, for then the stone had no might. And because this stone was so precious and good, I thought in myself that I was not able nor worthy to bear it, and therefore I sent it to my dear Lord the King, for I know him for the most noble that now lives, and also all our welfare and worship lies on him, and for he should be kept from all dread, need, and ungheluck.(1)

“I found this ring in my father's treasure, and in the same place I took a glass or a mirror and a comb which my wife would algates have. A man might wonder that saw these jewels. I sent these to my Lady the Queen, for I have founden her good and gracious to me. This Comb might not be too much praised. It was made of the bone of a clean noble beast named Panthera, which feeds him between the great Inde and Earthly Paradise. He is so lusty fair and of colour, that there is no colour under the heaven but some likeness is in him; thereto he smells so sweet, that the savour of him boteth(2) all sickness; and for his beauty and sweet smelling all other beasts follow him, for by his sweet savour they are healed of all sickness. This Panthera has a fair bone, broad and thin; when so is that this beast is slain all the sweet odour rested in the bone, which cannot be broken, nor shall never rot, nor be destroyed by fire, by water, nor by smiting, it is so hardy, tight and fast, and yet it is light of weight. The sweet odour of it has great might; that who that smells it sette nought by none other lust in the world, and is eased and quit of all manner diseases and infirmities, and also he is jocund and glad in his heart. This Comb is polished as it were fine silver, and the teeth of it be small and strait, and between the greater teeth and the smaller is a large field and space where is carven many an image subtilly made and enamelled about with fine gold; the field is checked with sable and silver, enamelled with cybore(3) and azure, and therein is the history how Venus, Juno, and Pallas strove for the apple of gold which each of them would have had, which controversy was set upon Paris that he should give it to the fairest of them three. Paris was that time an herdman, and kept his father's beasts and sheep without Troy. When he had received the apple, Juno promised to him if he would judge that she might have the apple, he should have the most riches of the world. Pallas said if she might have the apple she would give him wisdom and strength, and make him so great a lord that he should overcome all his enemies and whom he would. Venus said,‘What needest thou riches or strength, art not thou Priamus' son, and Hector is thy brother, which have all Asia under their power? Art not thou one of the possessors of great Troy? If thou wilt give to me the apple, I shall give thee the richest treasure of the world, and that shall be the fairest woman that ever had life on earth, nor never shall none be born fairer than she. Then shalt thou be richer than rich, and shalt climb above all other, for that is the treasure that no man can prize enough; for honest fair and good women can put away many a sorrow from the heart, they be shamefast and wise, and bring a man in very joy and bliss.’Paris heard this Venus, which presented him this great joy and fair lady, and prayed her to name this fair lady that was so fair, and where she was. Venus said,‘It is Helen, King Menelaus' wife of Greece, there lives not a nobler, richer, gentler, nor wiser wife in all the world.’Then Paris gave to her the apple, and said that she was fairest. How that he got afterward Helen by the help of Venus, and how he brought her in to Troy and wedded her, the great love and jolly life that they had together, was all carven in the field, everything by himself, and the story written.

“Now you shall hear of the Mirror. The glass that stood thereon was of such virtue that men might see therein all that was done within a mile, of men of beasts and of all thing that me would(4) desire to wit and know. And what man looked in the glass, had he only disease of pricking or motes, smart, or pearls in his eyes, he should be anon healed of it, such great virtue had the glass. Is it then wonder if I be moved and angry for to lose such manner jewels? The tree in which this glass stood was light and fast and was named Cetyne.(5) It should endure ever ere it would rot, or worms should hurt it, and therefore King Solomon ceiled his temple with the same wood withinforth. Men praised it dearer than fine gold; it is like to tree of hebenus, of which wood King Crompart made his horse of tree for love of King Morcadigas' daughter that was so fair, whom he had weened for to have won. That horse was so made within, that whosoever rode on it, if he would, he should be within less than one hour an hundred miles thence; and that was well proved, for Cleomedes the king's son would not believe that that horse of tree had such might and virtue. He was young, lusty, and hardy, and desired to do great deeds of praise for to be renowned in this world, and leapt on this horse of tree. Crompart turned a pin that stood on his breast, and anon the horse lift him up and went out of the hall by the window, and ere one might say his pater noster he was gone more than ten mile away. Cleomedes was sore afraid, and supposed never to have turned again, as the history(6) thereof tells more plainly. But how great dread he had, and how far that he rode upon that horse made of the tree of hebenus ere he could know the art and craft how he should turn him; and how joyful he was when he knew it; and how men sorrowed for him; and how he knew all this, and the joy thereof when he came again, all this I pass over for losing of time; but the most part of all came to by the virtue of the wood, of which wood the tree that the glass stood in was made. And that was, without forth of the glass, half a foot broad, wherein stood some strange histories, which were of gold, of sable, of silver, of yellow, azure, and cynope, these six colours were therein wrought in such wise as it behoved; and under every history the words were graven and enamelled, that every man might understand what each history was. After my judgment there was never mirror so costly, so lustly, nor so pleasant. In the beginning stood there an Horse, made fat, strong, and sore envious upon an Hart which ran in the field so far and swiftly that the Horse was angry that he ran so far before him and could not overtake him. He thought he should catch him and subdue him, though he should suffer much pain therefor. The Horse spake tho to a Herdman in this wise,‘If thou couldst taken an Hart that I well can show thee, thou shouldst have great profit thereof; thou shouldst sell dear his horns, his skin, and his flesh.’The Herdman said,‘How may I come by him?’The Horse said,‘Sit upon me, and I shall bear thee, and we shall hunt him till he be take.’The Herdman sprang and sat upon the Horse, and saw the Hart; and he rode after; but the Hart was light of foot and swift, and outran the Horse far. They hunted so far after him that the Horse was weary, and said to the Herdman that sat on him,‘Now sit off, I will rest me, I am all weary, and give me leave to go from thee.’The Herdman said,‘I have arrested thee; thou mayst not escape from me; I have a bridle on thy head and spurs on my heels; thou shalt never have thank hereof; I shall bedwynge and subdue thee, hadst thou sworn the contrary.’See how the Horse brought himself in thraldom and was taken in his own net. How may one better be taken than by his own proper envy suffer himself to be taken and ridden. There are many that labour to hurt other, and they themselven are hurt and rewarded with the same. There was also made an Ass and an Hound which dwelled both with a rich man. The man loved his Hound well, for he played oft with him as folk do with Hounds. The Hound leapt up and played with his tail, and licked his master about the mouth. This saw Howdwin the Ass, and had great spite thereof in his heart, and said to himself,‘How may this be? and what may my lord see on his foul Hound, whom I never see does good nor profit save springs on him and kisses him? But me, whom men putten to labour, to bear and draw and do more in a week than he with his fifteen should do in a whole year, —and yet sits he nevertheless by him at the table and there eats bones, flesh, and fat trenchours, —and I have nothing but thistles and nettles, and lie on nights on the hard earth, and suffer many a scorn. I will no longer suffer this. I will think how I may get my lord's love and friendship, like as the Hound does.’Therewith came the lord, and the Ass lift up his tail and sprang with his fore feet on the lord's shoulders and blared, grinned, and sang, and with his feet made two great boles about his ears, and put forth his mouth and would have kissed the lord's mouth as he had seen the Hound done. Tho cried the lord, sore afraid,‘Help! help! this Ass will slay me!’Then came his servants with staves and smiten and beat the Ass so sore that he had weened he should have lost his life. Tho returned he to his stable and ate thistle and nettles and was an Ass as he before was. In likewise whoso have enough and spite of another's welfare, and were served in likewise, it should be well behoveful. Therefore it is concluded that the Ass shall eat thistles and nettles and bear the sack. Though men would do him worship he cannot understand it, but must use old lewd manners. Whereas asses getten lordships, there men see seldom good rule. For they take heed of nothing but on their singular profit; yet are they take up and risen great, the more pity is. Hearken further how my father and Tybert the Cat went together, and had sworn by their truth that for love nor hate they should not depart. And what they got they should depart to each the half. Then on a time they saw hunters coming over the field with many hounds. They leapt and ran fast from themward all that they might, as they that were afraid of their life.‘Tybert,’said the Fox,‘Whither shall we now best flee? the hunters have espied us. Know you any help?’My father trusted on the promise that each made to other, and that he would for no need depart from him.‘Tybert,’said he,‘I have a sackful of wiles if we have need; as far as we abide together we need not to doubt hunters nor hounds.’Tybert began to sigh and was sore afraid, and said,‘Reynart, what availlen many words? I know but one wile, and thither must I too.’And tho clamb he up on a high tree into the top under the leaves, whereas hunter nor hound might do him none harm, and left my father alone in jeopardy of his life, for the hunters set on him the hounds all that they could. Men blew the horns, and cried, and hallooed,‘The Fox! Slee and take!’When Tybert the Cat saw that, he mocked and scorned my father and said,‘What, Reynart, cousin, unbind now your sack where all the wiles are in! It is now time. You be so wise called; help yourself, for you have need.’This much must my father hear of him to whom he had most his trust on, and was almost taken, and nigh his death. And he ran and fled with great fear of his life, and let his male slide off because he would be the lighter. Yet all that could not help him, for the hounds were too swift and should have bitten him; but he had one adventure that thereby he found an old hole, wherein he crept, and escaped thus the hunters and hounds. Thus held this false deceiver Tybert his sykernes that he had promised. Alas, how many are there now a days that keep not their promise, and set not thereby though they break it! And though I hate Tybert herefor, is it wonder? But I do not. Sikerly, I love my soul too well thereto. Nevertheless, if I saw him in adventure and misfall in his body or in his goods, I think it should not much go to my heart, so that another did it. Nevertheless, I shall neither hate him nor have envy at him. I shall, for God's love, forgive him. Yet is it not so clear out of my heart but a little ill-will to himward abides therein as this comes to my remembrance; and the cause is that the sensuality of my flesh fights against reason. Ther stood also in that Mirror, of the Wolf, how he found once upon a heath a dead horse flayen, but all the flesh was eaten. Then went he and bote great morsels of the bones, that for hunger he took three or four at once and swallowed them in, for he was so greedy that one of the bones stack thwart in his mouth. Whereof he had great pain, and was of great fear of his life. He sought all about for wise masters and surgeons, and promised great gifts for to be healed of his disease. At last, when he could nowhere find remedy, he came to the Crane with his long neck and bill, and prayed him to help him, and he would love and reward him so well that he should ever be the better. The Crane hearked after this great reward, and put his head into his throat, and brought out the bone with his bill. The Wolf start aside with the plucking, and cried out,‘Alas, thou doest me harm! but I forgive it thee. Do no more so, I would not suffer it of another.’The Crane said,‘Sir Esegrim, go and be merry, for you be all whole. Now give to me that you promised.’The Wolf said,‘Will you hear what he says? I am he that has suffered and have cause to plain, and he will have good of me! He thanketh not me of the kindness that I did to him. He put his head in my mouth, and I suffered him to draw it out whole without hurting; and he did to me also harm. And if any here should have a reward, it should be I, by right.’

“Thus the unkind men nowadays reward them that do them good. When the false and subtle arise and become great, then goes worship and profit all to nought. There are many, of right that ought reward and do good to such as have helpen them in their need, that now find causes and say they be hurt, and would have amends where they ought to reward and make amends themself. Therefore it is said, and truth it is, who that will chide or chastise see that he be clear himself. All this and much more than I now can well remember was made and wrought in this glass. The master that ordained it was a cunning man and a profound clerk in many sciences. And because these jewels were over good and precious for me to keep and have, therefore I sent them to my dear Lord the King and to the Queen in present. Where are they now that give to their lords such presents. The sorrow that my two children made when I sent away the glass was great; for they were wont to look therein and see themself how their clothing and array became them on their bodies. Oh, alas! I knew not that Cuwart the Hare was so nigh his death when I delivered him the male with these jewels. I wist not to whom I might better have taken them, though it should have cost me my life, than him and Bellyn the Ram. They were two of my best friends. Out, alas! I cry upon the murderer. I shall know who it was, though I should run through all the world to seek him, for murder abides not hid, it shall come out. Peradventure he is in this company that knows where Cuwart is become, though he tells it not; for many false shrews walk with good men, from whom no man can keep him, they known their craft so well and can well cover their falseness. But the most wonder that I have is that my Lord the King here sayeth so felly, that my father nor I did him never good. That thinks me marvel, of a king. But there come so many things before him that he forgets that one with that other, and so fares by me. Dear Lord, remember not you when my Lord your father lived, and you an youngling of two year were, that my father came from school from Monpellier whereas he had five year studied in recipes of medicines. He knew all the tokens of the urine as well as his hand, and also all the herbs, and nature of them which were viscous or laxative. He was a singular master in that science. He might well wear cloth of silk and a gilt girdle. When he came to Court he found the King in a great sickness, whereof he was sorry in his heart, for he loved him above all other lords. The King would not forego him, for when he came all other had leave to walk where they would; he trusted none so much as him. He said,‘Reynart, I am sick, and feel me the longer the worse.’My father said,‘My dear Lord, here is an urinal: make your water therein, and as soon as I may see it I shall tell what sickness it is and also how you shall be holpen.’The King did as he counselled him, for he trusted no man better that lived. Though so were that my father did not as he should have done to you, but that was by counsel of evil and foul beasts —I had wonder thereof—but it was a raising against his death. He said,‘My Lord, if you will be whole you must eat the liver of a wolf of seven year old, that may you not leave or else you shall die; for your urine shows it plainly.’

“The Wolf stood thereby and said nought.

“But the King said to him,‘Sir Esegrim, now, you hear well that I must have your liver if I will be whole.’

“Tho answered the Wolf and said,‘Nay my lord not so, I wot well I am not yet five year old. I have heard my mother say so.’

“My father said,‘What skills these words? Let him be opened, and I shall know by the liver if it be good for you or not.’

“And therewith the Wolf was taken to kitchen, and his liver taken out, which the King ate and was anon all whole of all his sickness. Then thanketh he my father much, and commanded all his household upon their lives that after that time they should call him Master Reynart.

“He abode still by the King, and was believed of all things, and must always go by his side; and the King gave to him a garland of roses which he must always wear on his head. But now this is all turned. All the old good things that he did be forgotten, and these covetous and ravenous shrews are taken up and set on the high bench, and are heard and made great, and the wise folk are put aback, by which these lords oft lack, and cause them to be in much trouble and sorrow. For when a covetous man of low birth is made a lord, and is much great, and above his neighbours has power and might, then he knows not himself, nor whence he is come, and has no pity on no man's hurt, nor hears no man's request, but if he may have great gifts. All his intent and desire is to gather good, and to be greater. Oh, how many covetous men are now in lords' courts! They flatter and smeke,(7) and please the prince, for their singular avail, but and the prince had need of them or their good, they should rather suffer him to die, or fare right hard, ere they would give or lend him. They be like the Wolf that had liefer the King had died than he would give him his liver. Yet had I liefer ere that the King or the Queen should fare amiss, that twenty such wolves should lose their lives; it were also the least loss. My lord, all this befell in your youth, that my father did thus. I think you have forgotten it.

“And also I have my self done you reverence, worship, and courtesy. Unroused be it, though you now thank me but little, but peradventure you remembered not that I shall now say, —not to any forwitting of you, for you be worthy all worship and reverence that any man can do; that have you of Almighty God by inheritance of your noble progenitors, wherefore I your humble subject and servant am bounden to do to you all the service that I can or may. I came on a time walking with the Wolf Esegrim, and we had gotten under us both a Swine. And for his loud crying we bit him to death; and, sire, you came from far out of a grove against us. You saluted us friendly, and said we were welcome, and that you and my Lady the Queen, which came after you, had great hunger and had nothing for to eat, and prayed us for to give you part of our winning. Esegrim spake so soft that a man uneasily might hear him, but I spake out and said,‘yea, my lord, with a good will. Though it were more, we will well that you have part.’And then the Wolf departed as he was wont to do; departed, and took that one half for himself, and he gave you a quarter for you and for the Queen. That other quarter he ate and bit as hastily as he might, because he would eat it alone. And he gave to me but half the lungs, that I pray God that evil might he fare.

“Thus showed he his conditions and nature. Ere men should have sungen a Credo, you, my lord, had eaten your part, and yet would you fain have had more, for you were not full. And because he gave you no more, nor proffered you, you lift up your right foot and smote him between the ears that you tore his skin over his eyes, and tho he might no longer abide, but he bled, howled, and ran away, and left his part there lying. Tho said you to him,‘Haste you again hither, and bring to us more. And here after see better to how you deal and part.’Then said I,‘My lord, if it please you I will go with him, I wot well what you said.’I went with him. He bled and groaned, as sore as he was, all softly; he durst not cry loud. We went so far that we brought a calf. And when you saw us come therewith you laughed, for you were well pleased, you said to me that I was swift in hunting:‘I see well that you can find well when you take it upon you. You be good to send forth in a need. The calf is good and fat, hereof shall you be the dealer.’I said,‘My lord, with a good will. The one half, my lord, shall be for you. And that other half for my lady the Queen. The moghettis, liver, lungs, and the inward, shall be for your children. The head shall Esegrim the Wolf have, and I will have the feet.’Tho said you,‘Reynart, who has taught you to depart so courteously?’‘My lord,’said I,‘that has done this priest that sits here with the bloody crown. He lost his skin with the uncourteous departing of the swine, and for his courtesy and ravin he has hurt and shame.’

“Alas there be many wolves now a days that, without right and reason, destroy and eat them that they may have the overhand of. They spare neither flesh nor blood, friend nor enemy. What they can get that take they. O, woe be to that land and to towns where as the wolves have the overhand!

“My lord, this and many other good thing have I done for you, that I could well tell if it were not too long, of which now you remember little by the words I hear of you. If you would all thing oversee well, you would not say as you do. I have seen the day that there should no great matter be concluded in this Court without my advice. Albeit that this adventure is now fallen, it might happen yet that my words shall be heard and also believed as well as another's, as far as right will, for I desire none other. For if there be any can say and make good by sufficient witnesses that I have trespassed, I will abide all the right and law that may come thereof; and if any say on me anything of which he can bring no witnesses, let me then be ruled after the law and custom of this court.”

The King said,“Reynart, you say reasonably. I know not of Cuwart's death more than that Bellyn the Ram brought his head hither in the male. Thereof I let you go quit, for I have no witness thereof.”

“My dear lord,”said Reynart,“God thank you. Sykerly you do well. For his death makes me so sorrowful that methinks my heart will break in two. Oh, when they departed from me, my heart was so heavy that I should have swooned. I wot well it was a token of the loss that tho was so nigh coming to me.”

All the most part of them that were there and heard the Fox's words of the jewels, and how he made his countenance and stretched him, had verily supposed that it had not be feigned but that it had be true. They were sorry of his loss and misadventure, and also of his sorrow. The King and the Queen had both pity of him, and bade him to make not too much sorrow, but that he should endeavour him to seek them. For he had so much praised them that they had great will and desire to have them. And because he had made them to understand that he had sent these jewels to them, though they never had them yet they thanked him, and prayed him to help that they might have them.

The Fox understood their meaning well, he thought toward them but little good for all that. He said,“God thank you, my lord and my lady, that you so friendly comfort me in my sorrow. I shall not rest night nor day, nor all they that will do anything for me, but run, and pray, threaten, and ask all the four corners of the world, though I should ever seek, till that I know where they are become. And I pray you, my Lord the King, that if they were in such place as I could not get them by prayer, by might, nor by request, that you would assist me and abide by me; for it touches yourself, and the good is yours; and also it is your part to do justice on theft and murder, which both are in this case.”

“Reynart,”said the King,“that shall I not leave, when you know where they are. My help shall be alway ready for you.”

“Oh, dear lord, this is too much presented to me. If I had power and might I should deserve against you.”

Now has the Fox his matter fast and fair, for he has the King in his hand as he would. Him thought that he was in better case than it was like to have be; he has made so many leasings that he may go freely where he will, without complaining of any of them all, save of Esegrim, which was to himward angry and displeased, and said,“O noble King, are you so much childish that you believe this false and subtle shrew, and suffer yourself with false lies thus to be deceived? Of faith it should be long or I should believe him, he is in murder and treason all bewrapped, and he mocks you before your visage. I shall tell him another tale. I am glad that I see now him here. All his leasings shall not avail him ere he depart from me.”

————————————————————

(1) Ungheluck, misfortune (unglüek).

(2) Boteth, is boot for, remedies.

(3) Cybore,“cyboire”was the decorated case that contained the consecrated elements of the host. From Greek κιβώριoν.

(4) Me would, one would.“Man”and“me”were our Teutonic forms for the French“on.”

(5) Shittim wood.

(6) The romance of Clyomon and Clamydes.

(7)  Smeke, flatter (schmeicheln).

CHAPTER XXXIII

“MY lord, I pray you to take heed. This false thief betrayed my wife once foul and dishonestly. It was so that in a winter's day they went together through a great water, and he bare my wife an honde that he would teach her take fish with her tail, and that she should let it hang in the water a good while and there should so much fish cleave on it that four of them should not conne eat it. The fool, my wife, supposed he had said truth. And she went in the mire ere she came into the water, and when she was in the deepest of the water he bade her hold her tail till that the fish were come. She held her tail so long that it was frozen hard in the ice and could not pluck it out. And when he saw that, he sprang up after on her body. She could not defend herself, the silly beast, she stood so deep in the mire. Hereof he cannot say nay, for I found him with the deed. Alas, what pain suffered I tho at my heart! I had almost for sorrow lost my five wits, and cried as loud as I might, and when he saw me so nigh he went his way. I went to her in a great heaviness, and went deep in that mire and that water ere I could break the ice, and much pain suffered she ere she could have out her tail, and yet left a gobbet of her tail behind her. And we were like both thereby to have lost our lives, for she yelped and cried so loud for the smart that she had ere she came out, that the men of the village came out, with staves and bills, with flail and pickforks, and the wives with their distaffs, and cried despitously,‘Slay! slay! and smite down right!’I was never in my life so afraid, for uneasily we escape. We ran so fast that we sweat. There was a villain that stake on us with a pike which hurted us sore; he was strong and swift a foot. Had it not be night, certainly we had been slain. The foul old queans would fain have beaten us. They said that we had bitten their sheep. They cursed us with many a curse. Tho came we in a field full of broom and brambles, there hid we us from the villains, and they durst not follow us further by night, but returned home again. See my lord this foul matter. You ought to do justice thereon sharply.”

Reynart answered and said,“If this were true, it should go too nigh my honour and worship. God forbid that it should be found true! It is well true that I taught her how she should in a place catch fish, and showed her a good way for to go over into the water without going into the mire. But she ran so desirously when she heard me name the fish, that she neither way nor path held, but went into the ice wherein she was forfrorn. And that was because she abode too long. She had fish enough, if she could have be pleased with measure. It falls oft, who that would have all loses all. Over covetous was never good. For the beast cannot be satisfied, and when I saw her in the ice so fast I went to have holpen her, and to have brought her out, but it was all pain lost, for she was too heavy for me. Tho came Esegrim, and saw how I did all my best, and he, as a foul churl, foul and rybadously slanders me with her, as these foul unthrifts are wont to do. But, my dear Lord, it was none otherwise. He belies me falsely. Peradventure his eyes dazzled as he looked from above down. He cried and cursed me, and swore many an oath I should dear abyou it. When I heard him so curse and threaten I went my way, and let him curse and threaten till he was weary. And tho went he and help his wife out, and then he leapt and ran, and she also, for to get them an heat and to warm them, or else they should have died for cold. And whatsomever I have said, afore or after, that is clearly all truth. I would not for a thousand mark of fine gold lie to you one leasing. It were not fitting for me. Whatsomever fall of me, I shall say the truth, like as my elders have always done since the time that we first understood reason. And if you be in doubt of anything that I have said otherwise than truth, give me respite of eight days, that I may have counsel, and I shall bring such information with good true and sufficient record that you shall all your life during trust and believe me, and so shall all your council also. What have I to do with the Wolf? It is before clearly enough showed that he is a foul villainous caitiff, and an unclean beast, when he dealed and departed the swine. So it is now known to you all by his own words, that he is a defamer of women as much as in him is, you may well mark euerychone. Now ask you his wife if it be so as he says. If she will say the truth I wot well she shall say as I do.”

Tho spake Ersewynde the Wolf's wife,“Ach, fell Reynart, no man can keep himself from thee, —thou canst so well utter thy words and thy falseness and reason set forth. But it shall be evil rewarded in the end. How broughtest thou me once into the well, where the two buckets hung by one cord running through one pulley, which went one up and another down, thou sattest in that one bucket beneath in the pit in great dread. I came thither and heard thee sigh and make sorrow, and asked thee how thou camest there. Thou saidst that thou hadst there so many good fishes eaten out of the water that thy belly would burst. I said,‘Tell me how I shall come to thee.’Then saidst thou,‘Aunt, spring into that bucket that hangs there, and you shall come anon to me.’I did so; and I went downward, and you came upward. Tho was I all angry. Thou saidst,‘Thus fares the world, that one goes up and another goes down.’Tho sprang you forth and went your way, and I abode there alone, sitting an whole day sore and hungered and a cold; and thereto had I many a stroke ere I could get thence.”

“Auntie,”said the Fox,“though the strokes did you harm, I had liever you had them than I, for you may better bear them; for one of us must needs have had them. I taught you good, will you understand it and think on it, that you another time take better heed and believe no man over hastily, is he friend or cousin, for every man seeks his own profit. They be now fools that do not so, and specially when they be in jeopardy of their lives.”

CHAPTER XXXIV

“MY Lord,”said Dame Ersewynde,“I pray you hear how he can blow with all winds, and how fair brings he his matters forth.”

“Thus has he brought me many time in scathe and hurt,”said the Wolf.“He has once betrayed me to the She Ape, my aunt, where I was in great dread and fear, for I left there almost my one ear. If the Fox will tell it, how it befel, I will give him the fordele thereof, for I cannot tell it so well but he shall beryspe me.”

“Well,”said the Fox,“I shall tell it without stammering. I shall say the truth. I pray you hearken me. He came into the wood and complained to me that he had great hunger; for I saw him never so full but he would alway have had fain more. I have wonder where the meat becomes that he destroys. I see now on his countenance that he begins to grymme for hunger. When I heard him so complain, I had pity of him. And I said, I was also hungry. Then went we half a day together and found nothing. Tho whined he and cried, and said he might go no further. Then espied I a great hole, standing in the middis(1) under an hawe which was thick of brambles, and I heard a rushing therein, I wist not what it was. Then said I,‘Go therein and look if there be anything there for us; I wot well there is somewhat.’Tho said he,‘Cousin, I would not creep into that hole for twenty pound, but(2) I wist(3) first what is therein. Methinks that there is some perilous thing. But I shall abide here under this tree, if you will go therein before. But come anon again, and let me wete(4) what thing is therein. You can many a subtlety, and can well help yourself, and much better than I.’See my Lord the King, thus he made me, poor wight, to go before into the danger, and he, which is great, long, and strong, abode without and rested him in peace. Await if I did not for him, there. I would not suffer the dread and fear that I there suffered, for all the good in earth, but if I wist how to escape. I went hardily in. I found the way dark, long, and broad. Ere I right in the hole came, so espied I a great light which came in from that one side. There lay in a great Ape with two great wide eyes, and they glimmed as a fire; and she had a great mouth with long teeth, and sharp nails on her feet and on her hands; I weened it had be a mermouse, a baubyn, or a mercatte, for I saw never fouler beast. And by her lay three of her children, which were right foul, for they were right like the mother. When they saw me come, they gapeden wide on me and were all still. I was afraid and would well I had been thence; but I thought, I am therein, I must there through, and come out as well as I may. As I saw her, me thought she seemed more(5) than Esegrim the Wolf, and her children were more than I. I saw never a fouler meyne.(6) They lay on foul hay which was all bepissed. They were beslabbed and beclagged to their ears too in her own dung. It stank that I was almost smothered thereof. I durst not say but good, and then I said,‘Aunt, God give you good day, and all my cousins, your fair children, they be of their age the fairest that ever I saw. O, Lord God, how well please they me! how lovely! how fair be they! Each of them for their beauty might be a great king's son! Of right we ought to thank you, that you thus increase our lineage. Dear Aunt, when I heard say that you were delivered and laid down I could no longer abide, but must come and friendly visit you. I am sorry that I had not erst known it.’‘Reynart, cousin,’said she,‘you be welcome. For that you have found me, and thus come see me, I thank you. Dear cousin, you be right true, and named right wise in all lands, and also that you gladly further and bring your lineage in great worship. You must teach my children with yours some wisdom, that they may know what they shall do and leave. I have thought on you, for gladly you go and fellowship with the good.’Oh how well was I pleased when I heard these words. This deserved I at the beginning when I called her aunt; howbeit that she was nothing sybbe to me; for my right Aunt is Dame Rukenawe that yonder stands, which is wont to bring forth wise children. I said,‘Aunt, my life and my good is at your commandment, and what I may do for you by night and by day. I will gladly teach them all that I can.’I would fain have be thence for the stench of them; and also I had pity of the great hunger that Esegrim had. I said,‘Aunt, I shall commit you and your fair children to God and take my leave. My wife shall think long after me.’‘Dear cousin,’said she,‘you shall not depart till you have eaten; for if you did I would say you were not kind.’Tho stood she up and brought me in another hole, whereas was much meat of harts and hinds, roes, pheasants, partridges, and much other venison, that I wondered from whence all this meat might come. And when I had eaten my bellyful, she gave me a great piece of an hind for to eat with my wife and with my household when I come home. I was ashamed to take it, but I might none otherwise do. I thanked her and took my leave. She bade me I should come soon again. I said I would, and so departed thence merrily that I so well had sped. I hasted me out, and when I came, saw Esegrim which lay groaning. And I asked him how he fared. He said,‘Nephew, all evil, for it is wonder that I live. Bring you any meat to eat? I die for hunger.’Tho had I compassion of him and gave him that I had, and saved him there his life; whereof then he thanked me greatly, howbeit that he now owes me evil will. He had eaten this up anon, tho said he,‘Reynart, dear cousin, what found you in that hole? I am more hungry now than I was before. My teeth are now sharped to eat.’I said then,‘Eme, haste you then lightly into that hole. You shall find there enough. There lies my Aunt with her children; if you will spare the truth, and lie great leasings, you shall have there all your desire. But and you say truth, you shall take harm.’My Lord, was not this enough said and warned, who so would understand it, that all that he found, he should say the contrary. But rude and plump beasts cannot understand wisdom; therefore hate they all subtle inventions, for they cannot conceive them. Yet nevertheless, he said he would go in, and lie so many leasings, ere he should mishap, that all men should have wonder of it; and so went forth into that foul stinking hole, and found the marmosette. She was like the devil's daughter, and on her hung much filth clottered in gobbets. Tho cried he,‘Alas, me growls of these foul nickers! Come they out of hell? Men may make devils afraid of them. Go and drown them, that evil might they fear! I saw never fouler worms, they make all my hair to stand right up.’‘Sir Esegrim,’said she,‘what may I do thereto? They are my children, and I must be their mother. What lies that in your way, whether they be foul or fair? They have you nothing cost. Here has been one to-day before you which was to them nigh of kin, and was your better and wiser; and he said that they were fair. Who has sent you hither with these tidings?’‘Dame, will you wit, I will eat of your meat. It is better bestowed on me than on these foul wights.’She said,‘Here is no meat.’He said,‘Here is enough.’And therewith he stert with his head toward the meat, and would have gone into the hole where the meat was. But my aunt stert up with her children, and run to him with their sharp long nails so sore that the blood ran over his eyes. I heard him cry sore and howl, but I know of no defence that he made but that he ran fast out of the hole. And he was there scratched and beaten, and many an hole had they made in his coat and skin. His visage was all on a blood and almost he had lost his one ear. He groaned and complained to me sore: then asked I him if he had well lied. He said,‘I said like as I saw and found, and that was a foul beast with many foul wights.’‘Nay, Eme,’said I,‘you should have said Fair niece how fare you and your fair children which are my wellbeloved cousins?’The Wolf said,‘I had liefer that they were hanged ere I that said.’‘Yea, Eme, therefore must you receive such manner payment. It is better otherwhile to lie than to say truth. They that are better wiser and stronger than we be have done so before us.’See, my Lord the King, thus got he his red coif. Now stands he all so simply as he knew no harm. I pray you ask you him if it was not thus. He was not far off, if I wot it well.”

————————————————————

(1) Middis, midst.

(2) But, except.

(3) Wist, knew.

(4) Wete, know.

(5) More, bigger.

(6) Meyne, household.

CHAPTER XXXV

THE Wolf said,“I may well forbear your mocks and your scorns and also your fell venomous words, strong thief that you are. You said that I was almost dead for hunger, when you help me in my need. That is falsely lied, for it was but a bone that you gave to me, you had eaten away all the flesh that was thereon. And you mock me and say that I am hungry, here where I stand. That touches my worship too nigh, —what many a spity word have you brought forth with false leasings!—and that I have conspired the King's death, from the treasure that you have said to him is in Hulsterlo, —and you have also my wife shamed and slandered that she shall never recover it, and I should ever be disworshipped thereby if I avenged it not. I have forborne you long, but now you shall not escape me. I can not make hereof great proof, but I say here before my lord and before all them that are here that thou art a false traitor and a murderer, and that I shall prove and make good on thy body within lists in the field, and that body against body, and then shall our strife have an end. And thereto I cast to thee my glove, and take thou it up I shall have right of thee or die therefor.”

Reynart the Fox thought, How come I on this campaign? we are not both like. I shall not well conne stand against this strong thief. All my proof is now come to an end.

CHAPTER XXXVI

YET thought the Fox I have good advantage: the claws of his forefeet are off, and his feet are yet sore thereof, when for my sake he was unshoed. He shall be somewhat the weaker.

Then said the Fox,“Who that says that I am a traitor or a murderer, I say he lies falsely; and that art thou specially Esegrim. Thou bringest me there as I would be. This have I oft desired. Lo here is my pledge that all thy words are false, and that I shall defend me and make good that thou liest.”

The King received the pledges, and admitted the battle, and asked borowes(1) of them both that on the morn they should come and perform their battle, and do as they ought to do. Then the Bear and the Cat were borowes for the Wolf; and for the Fox were borowes Grymbart the Dasse and Byteluys.

————————————————————

(1) Borowes, sureties.

CHAPTER XXXVII

THE She Ape said to the Fox,“Reynart Nephew, see that you take heed in your battle. Be cold and wise. Your Eme taught me once a prayer that is of much virtue to him that shall fight; and a great master and a wise clerk, and was abbot of Boudelo, that taught him, he said, who that said devoutly this prayer fasting shall not that day be overcome in battle nor in fighting. Therefore, dear Nephew, be not afraid, I shall read it over you to-morrow, then may you be sure enough of the Wolf. It is better to fight than to have the neck asunder.”

“I thank you, dear aunt,”said the Fox.“The quarrel that I have is rightful, therefore I hope I shall speed well, and that shall greatly be my help.”

All his lineage abode by him all the night and holp him to drive away the time.

Dame Rukenawe the She Ape, his aunt, thought alway on his profit and fordele. And she did all his hair from the head to the tail be shorn off smooth; and she anointed all his body with oil of olive; and then was his body also glat(1) and slipper that the Wolf should have none hold on him. And he was round and fat also on his body.

And she said to him,“Dear cousin, you must now drink much that to-morrow you may the better make your urine; but you shall hold it in till you come to the field. And when need is and time, so shall you piss full your rough tail and smite the Wolf therewith in his beard. And if you might hit him therewith in his eyes, then shall you byneme him(2) his sight. That should much hinder him. But else, hold alway your tail fast between your legs that he catch you not thereby; and hold down your ears lying plat after your head that he hold you not thereby; and see wisely to yourself. And at beginning flee from his strokes, and let him spring and run after you, and run before where as most dust is, and stir it with your feet that it may flee in his eyes, and that shall much hinder his sight. And while he rubs his eyes, take your advantage and smite and bite him there as you may most hurt him, and alway to hit him with your tail full of piss in his visage, and that shall make him so woe that he shall not wit where he is. And let him run after you for to make him weary. Yet his feet are sore of that you made him to lose his shoes, and though he be great he has no heart. Nephew, certainly this is my counsel. The connyng goes before strength; therefore see for yourself, and set yourself wisely at defence, that you and we all may have worship thereof. I would be sorry if you mishapped. I shall teach you the words that your Eme Martin taught me, that you may overcome your enemy, as I hope you shall do without doubt.”Therewith she laid her hand upon his head, and said these words:“Blaerde Shay Alphenio Kasbue Gorfons Alsbuifrio. Nephew, now be you sure from all mischief and dread. And I counsel you that you rest you a little, for it is by the day you shall be the better disposed; we shall awake you in all in time.”

“Aunt,”said the Fox,“I am now glad. God thank you, you have done to me such good I can never deserve it fully again. Methinks there may nothing hurt me since that you have said these holy words over me.”

Tho went he and laid him down under a tree in the grass, and slept till the sun was risen. Tho came the Otter and waked him, and bade him arise, and gave him a good young duck and said,“Dear cousin, I have this night made many a leap in the water ere I could get this young fat duck. I have taken it from a fowler. Take and eat it.”

Reynart said,“This is good handsel. If I refused I were a fool. I thank you, cousin, that you remember me. If I live I shall reward you.”

The Fox ate the duck without sauce or bread. It savoured him well, and went well in. And he drank thereto four great draughts of water. Then went he to the battle ward, and all they that loved him went with him.

————————————————————

(1) Glat, smooth.

(2) Byneme him, take away from him.

CHAPTER XXXVIII

WHEN the King saw Reynart thus shorn and oiled he said to him,“Ey, Fox, how well can you see for yourself!”

He wondered thereof; he was foul to look on.

But the Fox said not one word, but kneeled down low to the earth unto the King and to the Queen, and striked him forth into the field.

The Wolf was there ready and spake many a proud word. The rulers and keepers of the field were the Leopard and the Losse.(1) They brought forth the book on which sware the Wolf that the Fox was a traitor and a murderer, and none might be falser than he was, and that he would prove on his body and make it good. Reynart the Fox sware that he lied as a false knave and a cursed thief, and that he would do good on his body.

When this was done, the governors of the field bade them do their devoir. Then roomed they all the field, save Dame Rukenawe the She Ape, she abode by the Fox and bade him remember well the words that she had said to him. She said,“See well to. When you were seven years old you were wise enough to go by night without lantern or moonshine where you wist to win any good. You are named among the people wise and subtle. Pain yourself to work so that you win the prize, then may you have ever honour and worship, and all we that are your friends.”

He answered,“My dearest aunt, I know it well. I shall do my best, and think on your counsel. I hope so to do that all my lineage shall have worship thereby, and my enemies shame and confusion.”

She said,“God grant it you.”

————————————————————

(1) Losse, lynx (Dutch, los).

CHAPTER XXXIX

THEREWITH she went out of the field and let them two go together. The Wolf trode forth to the Fox in great wrath, and opened his forefeet, and supposed to have taken the Fox in them. But the Fox sprang from him lightly, for he was lighter to foot than he. The Wolf sprang after, and hunted the Fox sore. Their friends stood without the lists and looked upon them. The Wolf strode wider than Reynart did, and oft overtook him, and lift up his foot and weened to have smitten him. But the Fox saw to, and smote him with his rough tail, which he had all bepissed, in his visage. Tho weened the Wolf to have been plat blind; the piss started in his eyes. Then must he rest, for to make clean his eyes. Reynart thought on his fordele, and stood above the wind scraping and casting with his feet the dust, that it flew the Wolf's eyesful. The Wolf was sore blinded therewith, in such wise that he must leave the running after him, for the sand and piss cleaved under his eyes, that it smarted so sore that he must rub and wash it away.

Tho came Reynart in a great anger and bote(1) him three great wounds on his head with his teeth, and said,“What is that, Sir Wolf! Has one there bitten you? How is it with you? I will all otherwise on you yet. Abide. I shall bring you some new thing. You have stolen many a lamb, and destroyed many a simple beast, and now falsely have appealed me and brought me in this trouble. All this shall I now avenge on thee. I am chosen to reward thee for thine old sins, for God will no longer suffer thee in thy great raven and shrewdness. I shall now assoil thee, and that shall be good for thy soul. Take patiently this penance, for thou shalt live no longer. The hell shall be thy purgatory. Thy life is now in my mercy, but and if thou wilt kneel down and ask me forgiveness, and knowledge thee to be overcome, yet though thou be evil, yet I will spare thee. For my conscience counsels me I should not gladly slay no man.”

Esegrim weened with these mocking and spiteous words to have gone out of his wits; and that dered(2) him so much that he wist not what to say, buff nor haft, he was so angry in his heart. The wounds that Reynart had given him bled and smarted sore, and he thought how he might best avenge it. With great anger he lift up his foot and smote the Fox on the head so great a stroke that he fell to the ground. Tho stert the Wolf to, and weened to have taken him. But the Fox was light and wily, and rose lightly up, and met with him fiercely. And there began a fell battle which dured long. The Wolf had great spite on the Fox, as well it seemed. He sprang after him ten times each after other, and would fain have had him fast. But his skin was so slipper and fat of the oil, that alway he escaped from him. O, so subtle and snelle(3) was the Fox, that many times when the Wolf weened well to make sure of him, he stert then between his legs and under his belly, and then turned he again and gave the Wolf a stroke with his tail in his eyes, that Esegrim weened he should have lost his sight, and this did he often times. And alway when he had so smitten him, then would he go above the wind and raise the dust, that it made his eyes full of stuffs. Esegrim was woebegone, and thought he was at an afterdele;(4) yet was his strength and might much more than the Fox's. Reynart had many a sore stroke of him when he raught(5) him. They gave each other many a stroke and many a bite when they saw their advantage, and each of them did his best to destroy that other. I would I might see such a battle. That one was wily, and that other was strong. That one fought with strength, and that other with subtlety.

The Wolf was angry that the Fox endured so long against him. If his foremost feet had been whole, the Fox had not endured so long; but the sores were so open that he might not well run. And the Fox might better off and on than he, and also he swang his tail oft under his eyes, and made him that him thought that his eyes should go out. At last he said to himself, I will make an end of this battle. How long shall this caitiff dure thus against me? I am so great, I should, if I lay upon him, press him to death. It is to me a great shame that I spare him so long. Men shall mock and point me with fingers to my shame and rebuke, for I am yet on the worst side. I am sore wounded; I bleed sore; and he drowns me with his piss and casts so much dust and sand in my eyes that hastily I shall not conne see, if I suffer him any longer. I will set it in adventure and seen what shall come thereof.

With that he smote with his foot Reynart on the head that he fell down to the ground, and ere he could arise he caught him in his feet and lay upon him as he would have pressed him to death. Tho began the Fox to be afraid, and so were all his friends when they saw him lie under. And on that other side all Esegrim's friends were joyful and glad. The Fox defended him fast with his claws as he lay upward with his feet, and gave many a clope.(6) The Wolf durst not with his feet do him much harm, but with his teeth snatched at him as he would have bitten him. When the Fox saw that he should be bitten and was in great dread, he smote the Wolf in the head with his foremost claws and tare the skin off between his brows and his ears, and that one of his eyes hung out; which did him much pain. He howled, he wept, he cried loud, and made a piteous noise, for the blood ran down as it had been a stream.

————————————————————

(1) Bote, bit.

(2) Dered, injured.

(3) Snelle, quick.

(4) At an afterdele, about to pass away. Dutch, dalen, is to sink, as the sun when it is setting, begint to dalen.

(5) Raught, reached him.

(6) Clope, blow (Dutch, klop).

CHAPTER XL

THE Wolf wiped his eyes, the Fox was glad when he saw that. He wrestled so sore, that he sprang on his feet while he rubbed his eyes. The Wolf was not well pleased therewithal, and smote after him ere he escaped, and caught him in his arms, and held him fast, notwithstanding that he bled. Reynard was woe then. There wrestled they long and sore. The Wolf waxed so angry that he forgot all his smarts and pain, and threw the Fox all plat under him, which came him evil to pass, for his one hand, by which he defended him stert in the falling into Esegrim's throat, and then was he afraid to lose his hand.

The Wolf said tho to the Fox,“Now choose, whether you will yield you as overcome or else I shall certainly slay you. Thy scattering of the dust, thy piss, thy mocking, nor thy defence, nor all thy false wiles, may not now help thee. Thou mayest not escape me. Thou hast heretofore done me so much harm and shame, and now I have lost my one eyou and thereto sore wounded.”

When Reynart heard that it stood so rowme(1) that he should choose to knowledge him overcome and yield him or else to take the death, he thought the choice was worth ten mark, and that he must say that one or that other. He had anon concluded what he would say, and began to say to him with fair words in this wise:

“Dear Eme, I will gladly become your man with all my good. And I will go for you to the holy grave, and shall get pardon and winning for your cloister of all the churches that are in the holy land, which shall much profit to your soul and your elders' souls also. I think there was never such a proffer proffered to any king. And I shall serve you like as I should serve our holy father the Pope. I shall hold of you all that I have, and ever been your servant, and forth I shall make that all my lineage shall do in like wise. Then shall you be a lord above all lords. Who should then dare do anything against you? And furthermore whatsomever I take of polaille, geese, partridge, or plover, fish or flesh, or whatsomever it be, thereof shall you first have the choice, and your wife and your children, ere any come in my body. Thereto I will alway abide by you, that where you be there shall no hurt nor scathe come to you. You be strong, and I am wily: let us abide together that, one with the counsel and that other with the deed, then may there nothing misfall to usward. And we are so nigh of kin each to other that of right should be no anger between us. I would not have foughten against you if I might have escaped. But you appealed me first unto fight, tho must I do that I not do would gladly. And in this battle I have been curtoys to you, I have not showed the utterest of my might on you like as I would have done if you had been a stranger to me; for the Nephew ought to spare the Eme, it is good reason and it ought so to be. Dear Eme, so have I now do, and that may you mark well when I ran before you, my heart would not consent thereto. For I might have hurt you much more than I did, but I thought it never; for I have not hurt you, nor done you so much harm that may hinder you, save only that mishap that is fallen on your eye. Ach! therefore I am sorry, and suffer much sorrow in my heart. I would well, dear Eme, that it had not happed you, but that it had fallen on me, so that you therewith had been pleased; howbeit that you shall have thereby a great advantage. For when you hereafter sleep you need not to shut but one window where another must shut two. My wife and my children and my lineage shall fall down to your feet, before the King and before all them that you will, desire and pray you humbly that you will suffer Reynart, your nephew, live; and also I shall knowledge oft to have trespassed against you, and what leasings I have lied upon you. How might any lord have more honour than I proffer you. I would for no good do this to another. Therefore I pray you to be pleased herewithall. I wote well, if you would, you might have slew me; but and you so done had, what had you won? So must you ever after this time keep you from my friends and lineage. Therefore he is wise that can in his anger measure himself, and not be over hasty, and to see well what may fall or happe afterward to him. What man that in his anger can well advise him, certainly he is wise. Men find many fools that in heat hasten them so much that after they repent them and then it is too late. But, dear Eme, I think you be too wise so to do. It is better to have praise, honour, rest, and peace, and many friends that be ready to help him, than to have shame, hurt, unrest, and also many enemies lying in a wait to do him harm. Also it is little worship to him that has overcome a man then to slay him. It is great shame, not for my life, though I were dead that were a little hurt.”

Esegrim the Wolf said,“Ay, thief, how fain wouldest thou be loosed and discharged from me, that hear I well by thy words. Were thou now from me on thy free feet thou wouldst not set by me an egg shell. Though thou promisedst to me all the world of fine red gold, I would not let thee escape. I set little by thee and all thy friends and lineage. All that thou hast here said is but leasings and feigned falseness. Weenest thou thus to deceive me? it is long since that I knew thee. I am no bird to be locked, nor take by chaff. I know well enough good corn. O, how wouldest thou mock me if I let thee thus escape. Thou mightest well have said this to one that knew thee not, but to me thou losest thy flattering and sweet fluting, for I understand too well thy subtle lying tales. Thou hast so oft deceived me that me behoves now to take good heed of thee. Thou false stinking knave, thou sayest that thou hast spared me in this battle. Look hitherward to me. Is not my one eyou out? And thereto hast thou wounded me in twenty places in my head. Thou wouldest not suffer me so long to rest as to take once my breath. I were over much a fool if I should now spare thee or be merciful to thee. So many a confusion and shame as thou hast done to me; and that also that touches me most of all, that thou hast disworshipped me and sklaundred Ersewynde my wife, whom I love as well as myself, and falsely deceivedst her, which shall never out of my heart: for as oft as it comes to my mind all my anger and hate that I have to thee renews.”

In the meanwhile that Esegrim was thus speaking, the Fox bethought him how he might help himself, and stuck his other hand after between his legs, and grepe the Wolf fast. And he wrong him so sore that for woe and pain he must cry loud and howl. Then the Fox drew his other hand out of his mouth. The Wolf had so much pain and anguish of the sore wringing, that he spit blood.

————————————————————

(1) Rowme, ruefully (Dutch, rouw, sorrow).

CHAPTER XLI

THIS pain did him more sorrow and woe than his eyou did that so sore bled, and also it made him to overthrow all in a swoon. Then Reynart the Fox leapt upon him with all his might, and caught him by the legs, and drew him forth through the field that they all might see it, and he stack and smote him sore. Then were Esegrim's friends all full of sorrow, and went all weeping unto their Lord the King, and prayed him that he would do cease the battle, and take it up into his hand.

The King granted it. And then went the keepers of the field the Leopard and the Lossem and said to the Fox and to the Wolf,“Our Lord the King will speak with you, and will that this battle be ended. He will take it into his hand. He desires that you will give your strife unto him, for if any of you here were slain it should be great shame on both sides. For you have as much worship of this field as you may have.”

And they said to the Fox,“All the beasts give to you the prize that have seen this battle.”

The Fox said,“Thereof I thank them, and what that shall please my lord to command that shall not I gainsay. I desire no better but to have won the field. Let my friends come hither to me. I will take advice of them what I shall do.”

They said,“That they thought it good; and also it was reason in weighty matters a man should take advice of his friends.”

Then came Dame Slopecade and Grymbart the Dasse her husband, Dame Rukenawe with her two sisters, Byteluys and Fulrompe her two sons and Hatenit her daughter, the Flyndermows(1) and the Weasel. And there came more than twenty which would not have come if the Fox had lost the field. So who that winns and comes to hys aboue, he gets great loos and worship: and who that is overthrown and has the worse, to him will no man gladly come. There came also to the Fox the Beaver, the Otter and both their wives Panthecrote and Ordegale. And the Ostrole, the Marten, the Fitchews, the Ferret, the Mouse, and the Squirrel, and many more than I can name. And all because he had won the field. Yea some came that before had complained on him, and were now of his next kin, and they showed him right friendly cheer and countenance. Thus fares the world now. Who that is rich and high on the wheel, he has many kinsmen and friends that shall help to bear out his wealth but who that is needy and in pain or in poverty finds but few friends and kinsmen; for every man almost eschews his company and way.

There was then great feast. They blew up trumpets and piped with shalmoyses.

They said all,“Dear Nephew, blessed be God that you have sped well. We were in great dread and fear when we saw you lie under.”

Reynart the Fox thanked all them friendly, and received them with great joy and gladness. Then he asked of them what they counselled him. If he should give the field unto the King or no?

Dame Slopecade said,“Yea hardily cousin. You may with worship well set it in to his hands, and trust him well enough.”

Tho went they all with the keepers of the field unto the King. And Reynart the Fox went before them all, with trumpets and pipes and much other minstrelsy. The Fox kneeled down before the King.

The King bade him stand up, and said to him,“Reynart you be now joyful. You have kept your day worshipfully. I discharge you, and let you go freely quit where it pleases you. And the debate between you, I hold it on me, and shall discuss it by reason and by counsel of noble men, and will ordain thereof that ought be done by reason, at such time as Esegrim shall be whole. And then I shall send for you to come to me, and then by God's grace I shall give out the sentence and judgment.”

————————————————————

(1) Flyndermows, bat.

CHAPTER XLII

“MY worthy and dear Lord the King,”said the Fox,“I am well agreed and paid therewith. But when I came first into your Court there were many that were fell and envious to me, which never had hurt nor cause of scathe by me. But they thought that they might best over me, and all they crieden with my enemies against me and would fain have destroyed me, because they thought that the Wolf was better withholden and greater with you than I was, which am your humble subject. They knew none other thing, why nor wherefore. They thought not as the wise be wont to do, that is what the end may happen.

“My lord these are like a great heap of hounds which I once saw stand at a lord's place upon a dunghill, whereas they awaited that men should bring them meat. Then saw they an hound come out of the kitchen and had taken there a fair rib of beef ere it was given him. And he ran fast away withal; but the cook had espied or(1) he went away, and took a great bowl full of scalding water and cast it on his hips behind; whereof he thanked nothing the cook, for the hair behind was scalded off and his skin seemed as it had be through sodden. Nevertheless he escaped away and kept that he had won.

“And when his fellows the other hounds saw him come with this fair rib, they called him all and said to him,‘Oh how good a friend is the cook to thee, which has given to thee so good a bone, whereon is so much flesh.’

“The hound said,‘You know nothing thereof. You praise me like as you see me before with the bone. But you have not seen me behind. Take heed, and behold me afterward on my buttocks, and then you shall know how I deserved it.’

“And when they had seen him behind on his hips how that his skin and his flesh was all raw and through sodden, tho growled they all and were afraid of that syedyng water; and would not of his fellowship, but fled and ran away from him, and let him there alone.

“See, my Lord, this right have these false beasts. When they be made lords, and may get their desire, and when they be mighty and doubted,(2) then have been they extortioners and scatte and pylle the people and eaten them like as they were forhungred hounds. These are they that bear the bone in their mouth. No man dare have to do with them, but preyse all that they bedrive.(3) No man dare say otherwise but such as shall please them, because they would not be shorn. And some help them forth in their unrighteous deeds because they would not have part, and lick their fingers, and strengthe them in their evil life and works. O, dear Lord, how little seen they that do thus after behind them, what the end shall be at last. They fall from high to low in great shame and sorrow, and then their works come to knowledge and be open in such wise that no man has pity nor compassion on them in their mischief and trouble, and every man curse them and say evil by them to their shame and villainy. Many of such have been blamed and shorn full nigh, that they had no worship nor profit but lose their hair as the hound did, that is their friends which have help them to cover their misdeeds and extortions like as the hair covers the skin. And when they have sorrow and shame for their old trespasses, then each body plucks his hand from him, and flee, like as the hounds did from him that was scalded with the syedyng water, and let him these extortions in their sorrow and need.

“My dear Lord King, I beseech you to remember this example of me; it shall not be against your worship nor wisdom. What ween you how many are there such false extortioners now in these days, —yea much worse than an hound that bears such a bone in his mouth—in towns, in great lords' courts, which with great facing and bracing oppress the poor people with great wrong, and sell their freedom and privileges, and bear them on hand of things that they never knew nor thought, and all for to get good for their singular profit. God give them all shame, and soon destroy them, whosomever they be that so do!

“But God be thanked,”said the Fox,“there may no man indite me, nor lineage, nor kin, of such works, but that we shall acquit us, and come in the light. I am not afraid of any that can say on me any thing that I have done otherwise than a true man ought to do. Alway the Fox shall abide the Fox, though all his enemies had sworn the contrary. My dear Lord the King, I love you with my heart above all lords, and never for no man would I turn from you, but abide by you to the utterest. How well it has been otherwise informed your highness, I have nevertheless alway do the best, and forth so will do, all my life that I can or may.”

————————————————————

(1) Or, ere.

(2) Doubted, feared.

(3) Bedrive, experience.

CHAPTER XLIII

THE King said,“Reynart, you be one of them that owes me homage; which I will that you alway so do. And also I will that, early and late, you be of my council and one of my justices. See well to that you not misdo nor trespass no more. I set you again in all your might and power, like as you were before, and see that you further all matters to the best right. For when you set your wit and counsel to virtue and goodness, then may not our Court be without your advice and counsel, for here is none that is like to you in sharp and high counsel, nor subtler in finding a remedy for a mischief. And think you on the example that you yourself have told, and that you haunt righteousness and be to me true. I will from henceforth work and do by your advice and counsel. He lives not that if he misdid you, but I should sharply avenge and wreke it on him. You shall overall speak and say my words, and in all my land shall you be, above all other, sovereign and my bayle.(1) That office I give you. You may well occupy it with worship.”

All Reynart's friends and lineage thanketh the King highly.

The King said,“I would do more for your sake than you ween. I pray you all that you remember him that he be true.”

Dame Rukenawe then said,“Yes sykerly, my Lord, that shall he ever be, and think you not the contrary. For if he were otherwise, he were not of our kin nor lineage, and I would ever missake him, and would ever hinder him to my power.”

Reynart the Fox thanked the King with fair courteous words, and said,“Dear Lord, I am not worthy to have the worship that you do to me. I shall think thereon and be true to you all so long as I live, and shall give you as wholesome counsel as shall be expedient to your good grace.”

Herewith he departed with his friends from the King.

Now hark how Esegrim the Wolf did. Bruin the Bear, Tybert the Cat, and Ersewynde and her children with their lineage drewen the Wolf out of the field, and laid him upon a litter of hay, and covered him warm, and looked to his wounds which were well twenty-five. And there came wise masters and surgeons which bound them and wash them. He was so sick and feeble that he had lost his feeling, but they rubbed and wryued(2) him under his temples and eyes, that he sprang out of his swound, and cried so loud that all they were afraid. They had weened that he had been wood.(3) But the masters gave him a drink that comforted his heart and made him to sleep. They comforted his wife, and told to her that there was no death-wound nor peril of his life. Then the Court brake up; and the Beasts departed and went to their places and homes that they came from.

————————————————————

(1) Bayle, bailiff, deputy, one, who keeps in custody.

(2) Wryued, rubbed (Dutch, wryven, to rub).

(3) Wood, mad.

CHAPTER XLIV

REYNART the Fox took his leave honestly of the King and of the Queen. And they bade him he should not tarry long, but shortly return to them again. He answered and said,“Dear King and Queen, alway at your commandment I shall be ready, if you need anything, which God forbid. I would alway be ready with my body and my good to help you, and also all my friends and lineage in likewise shall obey your commandment and desire. You have highly deserved it, God quite it you, and give you grace long to live. And I desire your license and leave to go home to my wife and children. And if your good grace will anything, let me have knowledge of it, and you shall find me alway ready.”

Thus departed the Fox with fair words from the King.

Reynart's friends and lineage to the number of forty have taken also their leave of the King, and went all together with the Fox, which was right glad that he had so well sped and that he stood so well in the King's grace. He thought that he had no shame, but that he was so great with the King that he might help and further his friends, and hinder his enemies, and also to do what he would without he should be blamed; if he would be wise.

The Fox and his friends went so long together that they camen to his burgh to Malperdays, there they all took leave of each other with fair and courteous words. Reynart did to them great reverence, and thanked them all friendly of their good faith and also worship that they had done and showed to him. And proffered to each of them his service, if they had need, with body and goods. And herewith they departed, and each of them went to their own houses.

The Fox went to Dame Ermelyne his wife, which welcomed him friendly. He told to her and to his children all the wonder that to him was befallen in the Court, and forgot not a word, but told to them every deal how he had escaped. Then were they glad that their father was so enhanced and great with the King. And the Fox lived further with his wife and his children in great joy and gladness.

译者序

霍桑（Nathaniel Hawthorne，1804—1864）是美国19世纪中期浪漫主义文学最重要的作家。他的创作开始于短篇小说，先后出版了短篇小说集《重讲一遍的故事》（Twice-told Tales，1837）和《古屋青苔》（Mosses from an Old Manse，1846）。1850年出版长篇小说《红字》（The Scarlet Letter），奠定了他的文学地位，继后又出版了《带七个尖顶的阁楼》（The House of the Seven Gables，1851）、《福谷传奇》（The Blithedale Romance，1852）、《玉石雕像》（The Marble Faun，1860）等长篇小说。他还有多种散文、随笔和短篇小说于身后出版问世。

霍桑出生于美国马萨诸塞州塞勒姆，自幼丧父，随寡母在塞勒姆镇的外公家生活，而当地是历史上加尔文教派狂热迫害异端的著名“驱巫案”发生的地方。他深受清教徒意识的影响，从原罪思想出发，以抽象和严酷的“善恶”观念看待事物，认为社会弊病和道德堕落的根源在于人性中一种固有的“恶”。另一方面，他又生活在美国超验主义思潮兴起的时代，超验主义崇尚人文精神，提倡个性解放，强调个人的价值，开启了被称为“美国的文艺复兴”的新时期。霍桑受到这一场重要的思想运动的影响，一度参加过由超验主义者创办的乌托邦式公社布鲁克农场，与超验主义领袖人物爱默生和梭罗也保持着密切的关系。

这看似矛盾的两种影响，在霍桑的世界观里是融合统一的。他抨击宗教狂热和偏执教派的反人道、非人性以及对人的天性的压抑、对精神的摧残；同时，他对资本主义早期发展的社会问题和人性异化深感忧虑，基于宗教“原罪”观念，致力于在人心中挖掘与暴露隐秘的“恶”，希望能引导人们以善行来洗刷罪恶，净化心灵，进而纯洁人心、改进社会。霍桑对人性的罪恶、堕落与病态的揭示，应该说是具有积极意义的。

霍桑的思想观念，使得他的作品呈现出独特的艺术风格。他的作品多采用寓意和象征手法来揭示人性的阴暗与邪恶倾向，以怪诞情节、异域风情、超现实环境来营造一种神秘氛围，并长于刻画人的隐秘思想活动和情感激烈冲突，被称作“黑色浪漫主义”和“心理罗曼史”。

本书所选作品，从各个侧面展示了霍桑创作的思想内涵和艺术特色。其中有几篇突出显示了他的“原罪”观念和对人心中隐秘罪恶的揭示，如《牧师的黑面纱》写一位深受教民敬重的牧师突然在面部罩上一层黑面纱，终生不再摘下。大家凛然生畏，猜想黑面纱背后隐藏着某种秘密或罪恶，而牧师在临终时却说：“我环顾四周，看啊！你们的每一张脸上都有一块黑面纱！”。《小伙子古德曼·布朗》的主人公古德曼·布朗秘密接受魔鬼的邀请，骗过妻子去密林中赴约，结果他发现几乎所有的人，包括“庄重、可敬的虔诚人士以及教会长者、贞洁贵妇和纯洁少女”，甚至自己的妻子，都和自己一样来践魔鬼之约，原来人人的灵魂中都隐藏着秘密的“罪恶”。《能预言的画像》里的那位画家认为：真正的艺术家“必须深入到表象之下去探看……要看到人的心灵深处”，他的画笔能描绘“用魔法在心灵洞穴中唤醒的那种不变的表情”，竟然显示了一对情侣的内心隐秘，也预示了他们可怕的命运。

另几篇小说旨在揭示人类由于内在罪孽而产生的违反自然、有悖伦理和背离道德的欲望和行为。《海德格医生的实验》中的医生以似乎超越造化的神奇实验，给几个追求返老还童、渴望享乐生活的老人制造了一场可笑的幻景，给他们以“教训”。《埃莉诺小姐的斗篷》中的埃莉诺小姐被称为“傲慢者中的最傲慢者”“践踏人类同情心的人”，仅仅因为她对他人尊严的轻蔑与践踏，酿成了可怕的瘟疫。《罗杰·麦尔文的葬礼》里的主人公背弃了神圣的誓言，最后竟以爱子的死亡作为补赎。

霍桑的作品常表现科技发展对人性和社会所产生的破坏作用，《胎记》和《拉帕西尼的女儿》是这方面的代表作。《胎记》中的艾尔默是一位年轻有为的科学家，坚信科学的力量高于一切，执拗地要配制出一种神奇的药剂以去除美丽妻子面部的红色胎记，使之臻于完美，结果害死了妻子。《拉帕西尼的女儿》里那个精神近乎变态的医学家，其科学的探求变异为狂热的野心，不仅培育出各种含毒的艳丽花草，还用自己的女儿做毒物实验，使女儿“成为自己对科学的疯狂热情的牺牲品”，最终葬送了女儿的爱情和生命。霍桑认为，一切野心勃勃、违背伦理、对抗自然规律的科学研究都将酿成悲剧。

霍桑对科学技术的看法，其实也与“原罪”观念有关——在他看来，人类“征服自然”的野心也属于基督教的七罪之列，即人类僭越自然、妄图主宰宇宙的“骄傲”和源于人类压榨自然以求福祉的功利“贪欲”，这与西方自卢梭以来的浪漫主义思潮一脉相承，对我们思考人类与自然的关系颇有启发。事实上霍桑并不简单地、绝对地否定科学技术的发展。以本书收入的《美的艺术家》为例：一个堪称“艺术家”的年轻钟表匠造出了神奇的能飞翔的机械蝴蝶，但因为是出于对美和爱的追求，霍桑并未对他的技艺有丝毫苛责，却抨击了毁灭他的世俗的实用主义和功利主义。《雪人》更是别具一格，描述一对天真无邪的小姐弟堆成的小雪人竟然获得了生命，成了孩子们的玩伴，倒像一篇优美纯净的童话，一首对自然的神奇性的讴歌。但小雪人最终却毁于父亲那被物质化的愚钝头脑，让人读后心情沉重而悲凉。

海德格医生的实验

那个极其古怪的人，年迈的海德格医生，一次邀请四位可敬的朋友到他书房里聚会。客人中有三位是长着白胡须的绅士——梅德本先生、基利格鲁上校和盖斯科因先生，还有一位芳华消萎的女士，叫作威彻利寡妇。他们是一帮阴郁的老家伙，一辈子命运不济，而他们最大的不幸还在于不久就要进入坟墓了。梅德本先生在壮年时代曾是个发达的商人，可是因为一次疯狂的投机生意而丧失了全部财产，现在只不过比乞丐略胜一筹而已。基利格鲁上校在堕落生活的追求中荒废了大好年华，也耗竭了他的健康和体质，从而染上了一大堆疾病，譬如痛风症和其他种种折磨身心的病痛。盖斯科因先生是个身败名裂的政客，恶名昭著，或者至少说至今一直是恶名昭著，直到时间将他埋葬，从而使如今这一代人已不知道他，才得以湮没无闻而不致遗臭万年。至于威彻利寡妇呢，据说当年是个大美人，不过因为某些飞短流长的诽言谤语使得城里的士绅名流都对她侧目而视，许久以来便不得不销声匿迹了。还有一件事值得一提，那三位老绅士——梅德本先生、基利格鲁上校和盖斯科因先生——都是威彻利寡妇早年的情人，有一次为了她争风吃醋，几乎要割断彼此的脖子。在我继续往下说之前先透露一点情况，海德格医生和他的四位客人有时会被人们看作有点儿精神失常——上年纪的人当受到眼前的烦恼或者悲惨的回忆骚扰的时候，这种情况确实是常常发生的。

“我亲爱的老朋友们，”海德格医生一面招呼他们就座，一面说，“我在书房里常做一些小小的实验自娱，现在我希望你们来帮助我做这么一次实验。”

假如种种传言确切无误，那么海德格医生的书房一定是个非常怪异的地方。它是一间光线阴暗的老式房间，蜘蛛网在四处结着彩饰，布满了年代久远的尘埃。周围矗立着一些橡木书橱，下层的架子里塞满了一排排巨大的对开本书和黑体字印刷的四开本书，上层架子里则装着羊皮纸封面的十二开本的小书。正中的那个书橱上面，放着一尊希波克拉底(1)的青铜半身雕像，根据权威消息，海德格医生治病时每逢遇到疑难病症便要同这尊雕像磋商。在书房那个最幽暗的角落里，立着一个又高又窄的橡木柜，柜门微微开着一条缝，隐隐约约可以看见里面有一副骷髅。在两个书橱中间挂着一面镜子，高高的布满灰尘的镜面嵌在暗淡无光的镀金镜框里。关于这面镜子有许多稀奇的故事，其中一个故事说，凡是这位医生的死去的病人，其亡灵全都住在这面镜子里，每当医生照镜子的时候，他们就会面对面地凝视着他。书房的对面悬挂着一位年轻女人的全身肖像，身上锦缎刺绣的华服已经凋败褪色，花容玉貌也同服饰一样暗淡无光。大约五十年前，就在海德格医生即将同这位年轻女子结婚之际，她因为偶感不适而吞服了她的恋人所配的一副药剂，便在新婚之夜香消玉殒了。我们还没有说到书房里最奇怪的一件东西，那是一部笨重的对开本大书，用黑皮革封面装订，夹着硕大的银扣。书脊上一个字也没有，谁也说不出它的标题。不过众所周知那是一本魔法书。有一次，一个女仆把它搬起来，只不过想扫一扫灰尘，橱柜里的那副骷髅却发出了咯咯的响声，画里的年轻女子伸出一只脚来走下地板，几张吓人的鬼脸也从镜子里往外窥探，同时，那尊希波克拉底铜像也怒冲冲地皱起了眉头，喝道：“不准动！”

海德格医生的书房就是这个模样。在我们的故事发生的那个夏季的午后，房间的中央放着一张像乌檀木一样漆黑的小圆桌，桌子上放着一只形状美丽、工艺考究的雕花玻璃瓶。阳光从窗外照射进来，透过两块已经褪色的厚重的锦缎窗帘，直接映照在玻璃瓶上，所以玻璃瓶上反射出一片柔和的灿烂光彩，投射到围坐在桌子四周的五个老人那灰白色的面孔上。桌子上还摆放着四个盛香槟酒的玻璃杯子。

“我亲爱的老朋友们，”海德格医生又说了一遍，“我可以仰仗你们的帮助，来进行这次极为奇异的实验吗？”

海德格医生本是一位非常奇特的老绅士，他的怪癖已成为千百个奇异故事的核心。其中一些传说之所以会得以流传，说来惭愧，多半是因为我这个人生性爱讲实话；倘若现在这个故事中任何一段文字会使读者惊诧莫名而心旌动摇，我自当毫无怨尤地承担胡编乱造的罪名。

医生的四位客人听见他讲到准备做实验，都预料那不会是多么奇妙的事，只不过是在一个抽气筒里杀死一只小老鼠，用显微镜查看一片蜘蛛网，或者其他诸如此类的小把戏而已，那是他常常用来折腾亲密朋友们的玩意儿。可是海德格医生并没有等他们回答，便蹒跚着走到书房那头，随后便抱着人们公认为魔法书的那本硕大的黑皮封面的对开本厚书回来了。他解开银扣，把大书打开，从印满黑体字的书页之间拿出了一朵玫瑰花，或者说它曾经是一朵玫瑰花，因为现在它那青翠的嫩叶和绯红的花瓣已经变成了褐色，这朵年代久远的花捏在医生手里似乎随时都会碎成齑粉似的。

“这朵玫瑰花，”海德格医生长叹一声说，“就是这朵凋谢的、快要粉碎的玫瑰花，五十五年前还在盛开怒放哩。这是西尔维娅·华德送给我的，那边就挂着她的画像；我本来准备在婚礼上佩戴它的。五十五年来，它一直被夹在这本旧书的书页之间珍藏着。现在，你们认为这朵半世纪前的玫瑰花可能重现芳菲吗？”

“无稽之谈！”威彻利寡妇说，怒冲冲地把头一甩，“你倒不如问一个老太婆满是皱纹的脸能不能再现青春哩。”

“那就瞧着吧！”海德格医生答道。

他打开瓶口，把那朵枯萎的玫瑰花扔进瓶中的水里。一开始，这朵花轻轻地浮在水面上，看上去一点也没有吸收水的湿气。可是没过多久，便可以看出开始发生一种奇妙的变化。那些压扁了和干枯了的花瓣微微颤动，色泽渐渐加深为绯红，仿佛那花朵正从死一般的沉睡中苏醒过来；纤弱的茎干和缀着叶片的细枝变得青翠了；半个世纪前的一朵玫瑰花看上去是那样鲜嫩，就好像当初西尔维娅刚刚赠送给她爱人时一样。它还说不上是盛开怒放；因为还有些娇嫩的红叶轻轻地蜷曲在它那湿润的花心周围，而花心里还有两三点露珠在闪闪发光。

“这确实是一手挺妙的把戏，”医生的朋友们说，他们满不在乎，因为大家曾经在魔术师的演出中看到过更精彩的奇迹，“请你说说，这是怎么弄出来的呀？”

“你们从来没有听说过‘青春之泉’吗？”海德格医生问道，“西班牙探险家朋斯·德·勒昂在两三个世纪之前就在寻找它了。”

“可是朋斯·德·勒昂到底找到它没有呢？”威彻利寡妇问道。

“没有，”海德格医生回答，“因为他根本没有往正确的地方寻找。如果我所听说的情况是正确的，这口著名的‘青春之泉’应该位于佛罗里达半岛的南部，距马卡科湖不远。它的源头被覆盖在几株巨大的木兰树下，那些木兰树尽管生长了许多世纪，但因为获得了奇妙的泉水的滋养，一直长得像紫罗兰一般娇艳。我的一位朋友知道我对这类事物素来好奇，便给我送来了你们所看到的瓶子里的东西。”

“嗯哼！”基利格鲁上校说，他对医生所说的故事连一个字也不相信。“那么这种液体对于人的身体可能产生什么效果呢？”

“这你自己去判断好了，我亲爱的上校。”海德格医生回答，“在座诸位，我的尊敬的老朋友，欢迎你们尽量饮用这种妙不可言的液体，重放你们的青春之花吧。至于我本人，既然在渐入老境的过程中备尝了许多苦恼，倒也不急于再返老还童了。所以恳请各位允许，让我仅限于旁观这次实验的进程好了。”

海德格医生一面说着，一面将“青春之泉”的水液倾注到四只香槟酒杯里面。这液体里显然饱含着起泡的气体，因为有许多小泡沫从杯底不断地升起，到了水面便爆裂成银色的雾气。因为这液体散发着令人愉悦的芬芳，几个老人也就毫不怀疑它具有使人兴奋和舒畅的性质；尽管他们对于其返老还童的功能持绝对怀疑的态度，却也愿意立即将它一口吞下。可是海德格医生要求他们稍等片刻。

“在你们饮用之前，我尊敬的老朋友们，”他说，“最好运用一生所获的经验来作为指导，先拟定几条一般的规则作为人生的指南，以便再次经历青春时期的种种危险。请想一想，假如你们享有了这种特别的好处，却又不能在美德和智慧方面成为当代青年人的楷模，那将是何等的罪孽和耻辱！”

医生的四位可敬的朋友并不回答他，只发出一阵微弱的震颤的笑声；既然大家已经懂得在错误之后悔恨必将接踵而至，可医生却认为他们竟然会再入歧途，这种想法也真是太可笑了。

“那么，喝吧！”医生说，一面躬身作礼，“我很高兴能选择到这么合适的人来做我的实验对象。”

他们用麻痹的手把酒杯举到嘴唇边。假如这种液体真的具有海德格医生所认定的功效，那么世界上再也找不出比这四位更迫切需要它的人了。他们看上去似乎从来不懂得青春和享乐到底为何物，只像是造化在老年昏聩时产下的子孙，生来便是些灰白、老朽、枯槁和悲惨的动物，现在佝偻着身子围坐在医生的桌子边，即使眼前有了返老还童的希望，灵魂或肉体里也无法激起足够的活力。他们把那液体一饮而尽，再把杯子放回到桌子上。

确实，这几个人的面容几乎立即就有所改观，就好像饮下了一杯浓郁美酒似的，他们的脸上顿时闪耀着欢乐阳光的灿烂光辉。他们的脸颊上洋溢着健康的色彩，取代了原来那种使他们貌如死尸的灰白色泽。他们互相凝视着，相信真的有某种魔力开始抹平“时间老人”长期以来一直在他们的额头上深深镌刻的那些悲惨的皱纹。威彻利寡妇整理起她的帽子来，因为她几乎觉得自己又重新是个年轻女人了。

“再给我们一些这种神奇的水！”他们急切地叫喊着，“我们已经年轻一些了——不过还仍然太老！快点——再给一些！”

“耐心些，耐心些！”海德格医生说，他坐在那儿，以哲学家的冷静态度观察着这次实验，“你们花了很长的时间才慢慢变老的。现在半个钟头就变得年轻了，实在应该感到满意啦！不过，这水倒是可以任你们饮用。”

他再次向他们的杯子里斟满青春之水，而瓶子里留下的仍有许多，足以让整个城市一半的老人返回到他们孙子的年龄。当泡沫还在杯缘闪耀之时，医生的四位客人便从桌子上抢过玻璃杯，一口吞尽了杯中之物。这难道是幻觉吗？甚至在那口水正流下他们喉咙的时刻，他们全身的器官似乎就即刻发生了变化。他们的眼睛变得清晰而明亮了；他们那银白的发丝渐渐加深了色泽；坐在桌子旁边的，竟是三位中年绅士和一位刚刚越过风华盛年的妇人。

“我亲爱的寡妇，你真迷人！”基利格鲁上校大叫道；他目不转睛地紧盯着她的脸，而在她的脸上岁月的黑影正在迅速消失，犹如黑夜在绯红的黎明中消失一样。

美丽的寡妇从来就明白，基利格鲁上校的奉承总是不能当成真话的；因此她猛地跳起来，跑到镜子跟前，心里仍然惧怕自己所面对的会是一张老太婆的丑陋面容。与此同时，那三位绅士的行为也足以证明“青春之泉”的神水的确具有某种令人陶醉的性质，除非他们那种精神亢奋是由于猛然解除了年龄的重担，因而变得飘飘然了。盖斯科因先生的心思不断地考虑着政治问题，不过这些问题到底是关系到现在、过去或者将来，就不是轻易能确定的了，因为那些见解和词句在这五十年来都是同样的流行。他时而放开喉咙滔滔不绝地吼叫着关于爱国主义、民族光荣和人民权利的口号；时而躲躲闪闪、含含糊糊地悄声细语，咕哝着提出这种那种危险，态度谨慎得几乎连他自己的良知也无法捉摸其中的奥秘；时而他又用抑扬顿挫的腔调和毕恭毕敬的语气说着话，仿佛某位君主正在倾听他精雕细琢的词句。基利格鲁上校一直在反复高唱一支欢乐的饮酒歌，还敲击着玻璃杯来给自己伴奏，同时用眼光上下扫视着威彻利寡妇那丰满的体态。梅德本先生坐在桌子另一边，正专心致志一元一分地计算着钱，想用这笔钱来开办一种新奇的买卖，准备驾驭一队鲸鱼到北极去搬运冰山，再到东印度去做卖冰的生意。

至于威彻利寡妇，她正站在镜子前面对着自己的影像屈膝行礼，痴笑不已，她还朝它打招呼，仿佛那个影子是她在世上最亲爱的朋友似的。她探头把自己的脸凑近镜子，想看清长久存在于自己记忆中的那些皱纹和鱼尾纹是否真正消失了。她仔细查看头发里的那些银丝是否已经完全转黑，以便能将那顶肃然可敬的帽子安全地扔到一边去。她终于轻盈地转过身子，踏着舞步向桌子走去。

“我亲爱的老医生，”她高喊道，“请再给我一杯！”

“当然可以，我亲爱的女士，当然可以！”医生殷勤地回答说，“瞧！我已经把杯子斟满了。”

事实上，四只玻璃杯都满满地斟上了这种神奇的水，水面上沸腾的泡沫散发而成的纤细雾沫就仿佛是金刚钻在闪烁光辉。这时正接近日落时分，书房比刚才更幽暗了；但是玻璃瓶里放射出一种柔和的、月光似的华彩，映照在四位客人和医生身上。医生坐在一把高靠背的、雕镂精美的橡木扶手椅上，显示出一种年高德劭的尊严，颇有“时间老人”的气派，而“时间老人”的权威除了这几位幸运者外是从来不曾受到过非议的。甚至当他们一口气喝下第三杯“青春之泉”的时候，医生那神秘莫测的面容也几乎使他们深感敬畏。

可是紧接着，青春生命的活力猛然喷涌，贯通了他们周身的经脉。现在他们已经回到了幸福的青春盛年。而老年，连同它那一连串悲惨的忧虑、痛苦和疾病，回忆起来只不过像一场噩梦的骚扰而已，他们如今从梦中快乐地醒过来了。他们的心灵本已过早地失去了鲜亮的光彩，而一旦心灵变得灰暗无光，世上一切接续变幻的景象就只不过像挂满褪色图画的画廊而已；可是如今心灵之光又重新恢复了魅力，照耀着他们未来的人生。他们觉得自己就像刚刚创造成的宇宙中刚刚创造出来的生灵。

“我们年轻了！我们年轻了！”他们欣喜若狂地高喊道。

青春，也像极端衰老一样，把中年的一切显著特征抹消，将它们同化吸收。他们现在变成一群快活的年轻人了。由于这种年龄所特有的纵情欢闹的劲儿，他们几乎变得疯狂起来。他们的欢乐情绪非常奇怪地化为一种冲动，要对虚弱和衰老加以嘲弄，而他们自己刚才还是这样的牺牲品呢。他们对自己款式老旧的衣着高声嘲笑——年轻小伙子竟然穿着下摆阔大的外套和翻着褶边的马甲，妙龄女郎居然戴着老式便帽，穿着老式长袍。他们当中的一个人学着患痛风病的老祖父的样子，跛着脚在地上一瘸一拐地走路；另一个把一副眼镜架在鼻子上，假装仔细阅读那本魔术书里的黑体字；第三个则坐在扶手椅上，极力模仿海德格医生那尊严可敬的风度。接着大家一齐欢乐地大声吼叫，在屋子里四处蹦跳。威彻利寡妇——假使这么娇艳的大姑娘可以叫作寡妇的话——跑到医生的椅子跟前，玫瑰般红润的脸上带着调皮的快活神情。

“医生，亲爱的老头儿，”她叫道，“起来同我跳舞吧！”

接着，三个小伙子发出了比刚才更响亮的大笑声，他们想象着那可怜的老医生跳起舞来会是一副多么古怪的模样。

“请原谅，”医生静静地回答说，“我既衰老又有风湿症，而且我跳舞的时代也早已过去了。不过这三位快活的年轻绅士中的任何一位都乐意有你这么美丽的舞伴呢。”

“同我跳吧，克拉拉！”基利格鲁上校嚷着。

“不，不，我要做她的舞伴！”盖斯科因先生大叫道。

“她答应嫁给我的，在五十年前！”梅德本先生高喊着。

他们围在她身边。一个人激情澎湃地抓住她的双手，另一个用双臂抱住她的腰，第三个则把一只手插进寡妇帽子下面一簇簇光亮的鬈发里。她满面羞红，喘着气，挣扎着，责骂着，大笑着，温暖的呼吸依次吹拂着三个人的面颊；她竭力要挣脱出来，却仍然停留在三个人的拥抱之中。再也找不到一幅比这更生动的图画，来表现年轻人为获取令人神魂颠倒的美女而争风吃醋的情景了！然而因为房间里光线幽暗，也因为他们仍然身穿古旧的服装，据说产生了一种奇异的幻象，当时那面高高的镜子里映照出来的，却是三个衰老、阴郁、枯槁的老头子，正在荒唐地向一个皮包骨头的丑陋的鸡皮老妇争宠哩。

不过他们的确变年轻了：他们燃烧的情欲证明了这一点。妙龄寡妇半推半就地卖弄风情，把三个情敌的欲火煽动得近乎疯狂，他们开始恶狠狠地怒目相向。大家一面仍然牢牢抓紧这个美丽的俘获物，同时凶猛地扼住彼此的咽喉。他们从屋子的这头厮打到那头，桌子被掀翻了，玻璃瓶也被撞到地下摔成了上千的碎片。宝贵的“青春之泉”在地板上像一条发光的小溪淌流着，弄湿了一只蝴蝶的翅膀；这只蝴蝶在夏季将尽的时候已经衰老，正栖息在那里奄奄待毙。突然，这只虫子在屋子里翩翩飞舞起来，然后停落在海德格医生白发如雪的头顶上。

“好啦，好啦，先生们！——好啦，威彻利太太！”医生高声说，“我真得抗议你们这样胡闹了。”

他们站住不动，突然战抖起来；仿佛白发的“时间老人”正把他们从阳光灿烂的青春召回，再把他们放逐到岁月的寒冷而黑暗的幽谷中去。他们望着海德格医生，老医生仍然坐在他那张雕花的扶手椅上，手里拿着那朵半个世纪以前的玫瑰花，这是他从粉碎的玻璃瓶中抢救出来的。他做了个手势，四个胡闹的人便回到了自己的座位上；他们倒也乐意这样做，因为剧烈的活动已经让他们精疲力竭了，尽管他们是年轻人。

“我可怜的西尔维娅的玫瑰花啊！”海德格医生突发感叹，把那朵花举在日落时分云彩映照出的余晖中，“它似乎又在枯萎了。”

确实如此。就在那四个人凝视着它的时候，那朵花不断地萎缩着，直到它变得像海德格医生将它投入玻璃瓶时那样干枯和脆弱。医生抖掉了仍然附着在花瓣上的几滴水珠。

“我爱它现在的样子，正如爱它露珠盈盈时的鲜嫩。”他说道，一面把那朵枯槁的玫瑰贴在他枯槁的嘴唇上。就在他说话的时候，那只蝴蝶也从医生雪白的头顶上振翅飞下，跌回到地面。

他的客人们再次战抖起来。一股奇异的寒气——是在身体里还是在灵魂里，他们自己也说不清——渐渐渗透到了全身。他们互相凝视着，只觉得时间每过一刹那就从身上带走了一丝魔力，只剩下一道愈来愈深的从来没有人堕入过的幽谷。这是一种幻觉吗？难道一生的变幻就被挤压进这么一个短暂的时空中，他们现在又成了四个老人，坐在老朋友海德格医生的身边吗？

“我们又变老了吗，就这么快？”他们悲惨地哭喊道。

事实上他们已经老了。“青春之泉”只有短暂的功效，还比不上酒的作用持久。它所产生的振奋狂喜，也像泡沫一样化为乌有了。是啊！他们又变老了。寡妇突然打了一个寒战，这显示她依然是个老妇人，她用一双皮包骨头的手紧紧地掩住面孔，心里唯愿棺材盖把它盖住，因为这张脸再也不能变得美丽了。

“是啊，朋友们，你们又变老了，”海德格医生说。“看哪！青春之水全都抛洒在了地上！哦——我倒并不为它惋惜；因为纵然这泉水就在我的门前喷涌，我也不会俯身下去沾湿我的嘴唇——不，即使它的美妙幻景能够延续多年而不是转瞬即逝，我也不干。这就是你们给我的教训！”

可是医生的四位朋友自己却没有接受这个教训。他们立即决定到佛罗里达去做朝圣旅行，要早、午、晚三次狂饮“青春之泉”。

————————————————————

(1) 希波克拉底（Hippocrates，公元前460—前370）：古希腊医生，被视为医药之父。

胎记

上一世纪后期，有一位科学家，一位精通自然哲学各门学问的著名人士。在我们的故事开始之前不久，他体验到一种比任何化学亲和力更有吸引力的精神亲和力，便把自己的实验室交给一个助手去照料，将他英俊面庞上的炉灰烟尘彻底清除，将手指上的酸液污斑刷洗干净，然后打动了一个美丽女郎的芳心，使她成了自己的妻子。在那个时代，对电和大自然其他类似奥秘的新近发现，似乎开辟了进入奇迹境界的众多途径，因此对于科学的热爱竟然能与对女性的热恋在深度和精力专注程度上一竞高低，也就算不得什么特别的事情了。高超的智力、想象力、精神，甚至心灵，都能在各种科学追求中寻找到与之相宜的养料；正如当时一些科学的热忱倡导者所深信的，这些追求会在强大的智慧阶梯上步步攀登，直到自然哲学家最后把握到宇宙创造力的秘密，或许还能进而为自己开创一片崭新的天地呢。我们不知道这位艾尔默是否对人类最终控制大自然抱有这种高度的信心。不过，他的确毫无保留地献身于科学研究，任何别的激情与之相比都有所逊色，绝不能使他放弃对科学的追求。他对年轻娇妻的爱也许可以说是强于他对科学的爱；但是这种爱也只有与他对科学的爱互相交织，并让科学的力量与他自己的力量相结合，才会如此强烈。

两者的这种结合自然就发生了，并且导致了真正惊人的后果和深刻感人的教训。有一天，就在他们婚后不久，艾尔默坐在那儿凝视着妻子，表情中显示出越来越强烈的烦恼，最后终于说话了。

“乔治亚娜，”他说，“你从来没想过脸上的那块胎记也许可以弄掉吗？”

“不，真的没想过。”她说，微微一笑；可是她察觉到丈夫态度的严肃，霎时脸色通红。“说实话，别人常常说它妩媚动人，我也就当真以为是这样了。”

“啊，要是长在另一个人脸上也许是的，”丈夫答道，“但长在你的脸上绝非如此。不，最亲爱的乔治亚娜，大自然之手把你造得几乎十全十美，所以这一点微乎其微的瑕疵——我也拿不准该叫它瑕疵还是美丽——却令我震惊，因为它是人世缺憾的明显标记。”

“令你震惊，我的丈夫！”乔治亚娜叫道，她受到了很深的伤害，一时气愤得满面通红，接着眼泪便夺眶而出。“那你为什么从我母亲身边把我娶来？你当然不能爱一个令你震惊的人！”

要解释这场谈话，必须提到乔治亚娜左边脸颊中央有一个特殊的印记，仿佛与她面部的肌肤组织深深地渗合在一起。当她的肤色处于平常状态时——一种虽然娇嫩但很健康的肤色——这个印记便带着较深的红晕，在周围的玫瑰红中显露出不规则的形状。当她脸红的时候，这个印记便会渐渐变得更加模糊，最后消失在满面焕发光彩的一片红潮之中。可是，只要她情绪发生变化而脸色转为苍白，那个印记又会再次显现，犹如白雪之中呈现出一点深红，有时候真让艾尔默觉得它清晰得近乎可怕。它的形状很像人的一只手，虽说只有最矮小的侏儒的手那样大。乔治亚娜的倾慕者常常说，在她出生时一定有位仙女把纤手按在了这个婴儿的脸上，留下这个印记来显示她具有神奇的禀赋，足以让所有男子一见倾心。许多渴慕若狂的年轻人甚至愿意拿生命来冒险，只要能得到亲吻这神秘手印的特权。不过无须讳言的是，人们因为气质各不相同，对仙女留下的这个手印也会有不同的印象。某些吹毛求疵的人——只不过无一例外都与她同一性别——宁愿称这个印记为血手，硬说它大大毁损了乔治亚娜美貌的魅力，使她的面目丑得可怕。当然，最纯净的大理石有时也会含有细小的蓝色瑕疵，只需一小点就足以将出自鲍尔斯(1)之手的夏娃雕像变成怪物，这样说也有道理。至于男性观察者们，如果说这个胎记没有增强他们的恋慕，却也宁愿它消失才觉得满意，以便让世界拥有一个毫无瑕疵的合乎理想美的活标本。艾尔默在婚前很少或者说根本没有想过这件事，婚后才发现自己的心愿正是如此。

倘若她没有这么美丽——倘若妒忌之神能找到任何其他嘲弄目标——他也许会因这个手印似的美妙胎记而爱意倍增；它时而朦胧显现，时而消失无影，时而又悄然复归，总伴随着内心深处的情感波动而忽明忽暗、若隐若现。可是既然她除此之外处处都那么完美无缺，随着他们共同生活的时日增进，艾尔默便越来越觉得这个缺点难以容忍。这是人类的一种致命缺陷，大自然总是要以这种或那种方式给它的创造物留下不可磨灭的印记，或者暗示一切事物无不短暂而有限，或者意味着它们的完美还必须经过千辛万苦才能达成。这个深红的手形胎记代表着一只无可逃脱的命运之手，死亡用这只手紧紧抓住最崇高最纯洁的尘世造物，将他们贬到最卑贱的甚至是畜生的地位，让人类有形的躯体也像畜生一样归于尘土。正是按照这种思考方式，艾尔默认定这个胎记乃是妻子无法逃避罪孽、痛苦、腐朽和死亡的象征，他那阴暗的想象力不久就把这个胎记视为不祥之物，这给他带来了越来越多的烦恼和恐惧，压倒了乔治亚娜心灵与容貌的美给他带来的欢乐。

在一切他们应该感到最愉快的时刻，他总会一成不变地回到这个灾难般的话题上来；他并非故意如此，不，他本意想要回避但又身不由己。这件事初看起来微不足道，但它总是同无数联想和各种感觉联系起来，结果变成了一切问题的中心。在曙光朦胧中，艾尔默睁开眼就看见妻子的脸，立即就辨认出那个不完美的标记；在黄昏的炉火旁，当他们并坐在一起时，他的目光会偷偷溜到她的脸颊上，借助柴火摇曳的光线看到那只鬼魅之手忽隐忽现，在他乐于赞赏的地方写下死亡的命数。乔治亚娜不久就形成了一种反应，每逢他凝视自己就不免浑身战栗。只要他在脸上挂着那种惯常的怪异表情对她瞟上一眼，她那玫瑰般红润的脸颊就会变得像死一样苍白。这时那只深红色的手印就会强烈地显现出来，犹如在雪白的大理石上刻出的一块红宝石浮雕。

一个深夜，当光线逐渐暗淡，几乎照不清这位可怜的妻子脸颊上的斑记时，她本人第一次主动提起了这个话题。

“你还记得吗，亲爱的艾尔默？”她说道，勉强露出一丝微笑，“你还记得昨天晚上你梦见了这只可憎的手吗？”

“不！什么也记不得了！”艾尔默答道，他大吃一惊，不过接着就用干涩而冷静的口气补上一句，以便掩饰自己内心深处的真实感情，“也许梦见了吧，因为我在入睡之前心里一直想着它。”

“那你真的梦见它啦？”乔治亚娜匆匆地问，因为她害怕夺眶而出的眼泪会打断她想说的话，“一个可怕的梦！我不相信你会忘记。你难道会忘记这句话吗？——‘它现在在她心里，我们必须把它弄出来！’想一想，我的丈夫，无论如何我都要请你把那个梦回忆出来。”

当包容一切的睡神不能将麾下的幽灵禁锢在她混沌的权力领域内，而听其摆脱羁绊冲脱出来，使实际生活受到那些应当属于意识深处的秘密的恐吓时，心灵便处于一种悲惨的境地。艾尔默现在想起了自己的梦。他梦见自己同仆人阿米那达勃一道，试图用手术除掉那个胎记；可是手术刀切得越深，那个手印也就陷得越深，到后来那只小手竟紧紧抓住了乔治亚娜的心脏。然而她丈夫却执意非把它切下来或者拧下来不可。

当整个梦境完全在记忆中浮现之后，艾尔默怀着愧疚的心情坐在妻子面前。事实真相常常偷偷地潜入被睡眠包裹着的心灵，然后对我们清醒时无意识中自我欺骗的种种行为作无情的揭露。直到现在他才意识到，有一个念头在暴戾地主宰着自己的心灵，而为了求得安宁，他内心的欲望又会发展到怎样的程度。

“艾尔默，”乔治亚娜严肃地接着说下去，“我不知道为了除掉这个不祥的胎记，我们两人可能付出多大代价。说不定去掉它会留下无可救治的残疾，或许这个印记就像生命本身一样的深哩。再说——我们是否知道即使不惜任何代价，到底有没有可能解开这只在我出生之前就已紧紧抓住了我的小手呢？”

“最亲爱的乔治亚娜，对这个问题我已经考虑很久了，”艾尔默急匆匆地打断她的话，“我深信去掉它是完全可行的。”

“就算是只有丝毫的可能性，”乔治亚娜接着说，“也让我们试一试，不管冒多大的风险。我对危险毫不在乎；至于说到生命，既然这个可恨的印记使我成了你恐惧和厌恶的对象——这生命也就成了我乐于扔掉的沉重负担。要么去掉这只可怕的手，要么就夺去我这悲惨的生命！你精通深奥的科学，世人有目共睹。你创造过许多伟大的奇迹。难道你连这么一个小而又小的、我用两个小手指尖都能盖住的斑点都除不掉吗？为了你自己的安宁，也为了拯救你可怜的妻子不至于发疯，这难道是你办不到的吗？”

“最高贵、最亲爱、最温柔的妻子，”艾尔默欣喜若狂，“不要怀疑我的能力。我对这件事已经作过深入的思考——这种思考给我带来的启发几乎能使我造出一个没有你那么完美的人来了。乔治亚娜，你使我比过去更深入地潜入了科学的核心。我觉得自己完全能够把这一侧可爱的脸颊变得与另一侧同样的完美无缺。那时候，最亲爱的，当我纠正了大自然在它最美丽的创造物上留下的瑕疵，我将怎样因成功而欣喜若狂！就连皮格马利翁(2)的少女雕像获得生命的时候，他心中的狂喜也不能和我相比。”

“那就这样决定了，”乔治亚娜露出了一丝微笑，“艾尔默，不要怜惜我，即使你最后发现这个胎记藏进了我的心里。”

她丈夫温柔地吻了吻她的脸颊——她的右脸颊——而不是长着绯红手印的那一边。

第二天，艾尔默向妻子说明自己已经有了一个计划，打算借此机会进行专注思考和持续观察，而这些都是拟议中的手术所必需的；同时乔治亚娜也可以得到彻底休息，这对于手术的成功至为关键。他们要远离尘嚣，退隐到艾尔默做实验室的那个宽阔的房间里去。在这里，他曾度过艰苦劳作的青年时代，在大自然的基本力量方面获得了若干重要发现，赢得了整个欧洲学术界的钦佩。这位脸色苍白的自然哲学家曾静坐在这个实验室里，探索过最高的云区和最深的矿层的秘密；他曾就火山爆发和不断冒火的原因寻找到自己满意的答案；他曾解释喷泉之谜，说明为什么它们从黑暗的地心喷涌而出时有的明澈纯净，有的富于医疗的功效；也是在这里，他曾在早期研究过人类身体的奥妙，试图探测自然之母如何吸取大地与天空以及精神世界的所有精华，创造和养育她的杰作——人类。不过，后面这种研究艾尔默早就弃置一旁了，他虽不情愿却不得不承认一条真理——所有探索者迟早都会在这儿碰钉子——那就是我们伟大的创造之母虽然为让我们快乐，在光天化日之下明明白白地工作着，可是她却小心地严守着自己的秘密，尽管装得公开坦白，却让我们除看到成果之外一无所知。确实，她允许我们损坏，却很少允许我们修补，就像一位心怀戒备的专利占有者，绝不允许我们去进行创造。然而，现在艾尔默又重新进行这些几乎已被遗忘了的研究；当然，他并未执着于当初所抱的希望或者愿望，只是因为这些研究涉及许多生理学方面的真理，而且是治疗乔治亚娜预定方案上必须解决的难题。

当他带着妻子跨过实验室的门槛时，乔治亚娜浑身发冷并且战抖起来。艾尔默兴致很高地望着她，想要让她放心，却吃惊地发现她雪白的脸颊上那个胎记发出灼热的红光，禁不住痉挛似的一阵战栗。他妻子竟然昏了过去。

“阿米那达勃！阿米那达勃！”艾尔默高声大叫，一面用力跺着脚。

从屋子里间立刻跑出一个人来，他个子矮小但身躯庞大，乱蓬蓬的头发吊在脸上，而那张脸则被炉烟熏得狰狞可怖。这个人在艾尔默的全部科学研究生涯中一直充当他的助手，而且对于这项工作十分称职，因为他具有机械式的迅速反应与动作，也具有处理主人实验中一切具体细节的技能，虽然他对于任何一项原理一窍不通。他那强大的力量，蓬乱的头发，满面的烟尘，以及笼罩全身的难以形容的纯朴粗陋，仿佛代表了人类肉体的本性；而艾尔默的颀长身材、苍白而带智慧色彩的面容，则恰好象征着人类的精神素质。

“快打开闺房的门，阿米那达勃，”艾尔默说，“再点燃一支香锭。”

“是的，主人。”阿米那达勃答道，并关注地看了看毫无生气的乔治亚娜；接着他又喃喃自语地说，“假如她是我妻子，我可绝不愿去掉那个胎记。”

当乔治亚娜醒过来的时候，她觉得自己正嗅着一种渗透心脾的芬芳，那香气温和的功效把她从死一般的昏晕中唤醒过来。周围的一切似乎都被施予了魔法。艾尔默已经把这些烟熏火燎、肮脏不堪、昏暗阴郁的房间——他在青春盛年曾在这里进行过艰深研究——改变成一间精美的套房，给一位可爱的女人做幽深的闺房倒颇为合适。墙上悬挂着的华丽帷幔使人既感豪华又觉高雅，其他任何装饰都不可能达到这种效果；那些帷幔从天花板直垂到地板上，层层富丽而厚重的褶皱将所有的尖角与直线都隐藏起来，仿佛要把这个小天地与无限的空间隔离开来。在乔治亚娜看来，这也许是一座仙境楼阁呢。艾尔默把阳光遮挡在外面，害怕它会影响自己的化学实验，却用能够散发香气的灯来取代，它们所燃烧起的五彩的光焰，全都融进一片柔和的紫色光辉中。艾尔默这时跪在妻子身旁，关切地注视着她，但并不惊慌；因为他对自己的科学十分自信，觉得他能在她周围划上一道魔圈，使任何妖孽都难以侵入。

“我在什么地方啊？哦，我想起来了。”乔治亚娜虚弱地说，同时把手放在那块可怕的胎记上，不让丈夫看见。

“别害怕，亲爱的！”他高声说，“别躲避我！相信我，乔治亚娜，我甚至为这个唯一的缺憾感到高兴，因为把它去掉将会带给我巨大的快乐。”

“啊，饶了我吧！”他的妻子哀伤地回答，“请别再去看它了。我永远也忘不了你那痉挛似的战栗。”

为了安抚乔治亚娜，似乎也可以说是为了让她卸掉现实的重负，艾尔默现在开始施行一些从科学的深奥学问中学来的轻松有趣的秘密。许多飘忽的形体、无形的意念和虚幻的美景翩然而至，在她面前舞蹈，把它们转瞬即逝的舞步映照在一道道光柱之上。尽管她对产生这些光学现象的方法也有某些模糊的认识，但这种幻觉却如此近乎完美，足以使她相信自己的丈夫真的拥有控制精神世界的力量。接着，当她觉得自己希望从这幽居独处的地方看看外界的景象时，她这个念头仿佛立即就获得了应答，外界事物随即依次在一块屏幕上飞掠而过。实际生活中的种种景象和人物都栩栩如生地呈现在眼前，但又具有那种令人心醉神迷却又难以形容的差异，正是这种差异使得一幅画、一个形象或者一片阴影比原物更能吸引人。当她厌腻了这种景象之后，艾尔默又要她看一看一只盛着泥土的桶。她照着做了，起初并无兴趣，可是很快就吃惊地发现有一棵植物的幼芽破土而出，接着就长出了纤细的茎干；叶片渐渐地舒展开来；在叶丛中竟然有一朵娇美可爱的花。

“它是一朵魔花！”乔治亚娜叫道，“我可不敢碰它。”

“别怕，把它摘下来吧，”艾尔默回答——“摘下来，抓紧时间嗅它那短暂的香气。这朵花转瞬间就会枯萎，除了褐色的种子荚壳之外什么也不会留下；不过从这粒种子里将会繁殖出一种与它同样短命的花卉。”

可是，乔治亚娜刚一触摸到那朵花，整株植物顿时枯萎，叶子变得焦黑，就像被火烤过似的。

“里面含的刺激剂太强了。”艾尔默若有所思地说。

为了补偿这次失败的实验，他又建议用自己发明的一种科学方法来给她描绘一幅肖像。那是通过光线照射在一块光滑的金属片上来产生的。乔治亚娜同意了，可是她一旦看到结果就惊吓不已：肖像上面容模糊一团，简直看不清是什么，而本该是脸颊的地方却显现出一只小手的形状。艾尔默一把抢过金属片，把它扔进了一个装着腐蚀性酸液的罐子里。

不过他很快就忘记了这些使他丢脸的失败。他有时中断他的研究与化学实验，满面通红、精疲力竭地回到她身边来，但似乎一回到她跟前就立即精神振奋起来，热情洋溢地谈论着自己技艺的种种渊源。他谈起炼金术士王朝的漫长历史，他们耗费了许多世代的光阴，为的是要寻找到一种万能溶剂，它可以从一切低劣微贱的东西中提取出黄金。看来艾尔默深信不疑，根据显而易见的科学逻辑，要发现这种长期寻找的媒质是完全可能的。“不过，”他又补充道，“一个研究如此精深而获得这种能力的科学家，他也会达到极高的智慧，不屑于降格来做这种事了。”他对长生不老药的见解也同样很独特。他明白表示自己完全可以随意调配出一种药剂，能将人的寿命延长许多年，或许能够无限延长。只不过这会造成自然界的不调和，从而招致世人，主要是那些服用长寿药剂的人们的诅咒。

“艾尔默，你说这些是当真的吗？”乔治亚娜又惊又怕地看着丈夫，“有这种本领真是太可怕了，就是梦到自己有这种本领都会害怕的。”

“哦，别怕，亲爱的，”她丈夫说，“我不会对我们自己的生命施行这些乱七八糟的花样来害你或者害自己的。我只不过是要你想一想，去除这只小手印的技艺与此相比是多么微不足道。”

一提到胎记，乔治亚娜顿时就和平时一样畏缩起来，就像有一块烧红的烙铁触到了她的脸颊上。

艾尔默又回头去专心致力于他的工作。她能听见他从远处烧着炉子的房间里传来的说话声，他对阿米那达勃发指示，阿米那达勃用他那粗涩刺耳而又古怪的声音在回答，听起来不像人在说话，倒像一只野兽在哼叫或咆哮。艾尔默离开几个小时之后又回来了，提议说她应当去看看他那个装着化学制品和世间自然珍宝的橱柜。在那些化学制品中，他拿出了一个小药瓶给她看，他说瓶中装着一种柔和而极有威力的香精，能够让整个国度中吹拂的微风都蕴含香味。这个小瓶子里装的东西真具有不可估量的价值；他一边这样说一边朝空中洒出了几滴香精，房间里即刻就充满了强烈而令人振奋的愉悦香味。

“这又是什么呢？”乔治亚娜指着一个盛着金色液体的小水晶球说，“它看上去是那么美，我能够猜想到里面装的是长生不老药。”

“从某种意义上说是这样，”艾尔默回答道，“或者不如说它是一种不朽灵药。它是这个世界上所能配制出来的最宝贵的毒药。我可以用它任意限定你所指定的任何人的寿命。它的剂量可以决定那个人是将生命绵延许多年，还是在瞬息之间就丢命。坐在警卫森严的王座上的国王们没有一个能保住自己的性命，只要我在自己的私室里认定为了千万人的幸福有理由剥夺他的生命。”

“你为什么要保存着这么可怕的药剂呢？”乔治亚娜惊恐地问道。

“别怀疑我，亲爱的，”她的丈夫笑着说，“它的益处比坏处可大得多。看着！这里还有一种强效化妆剂。在一瓶水里滴上几滴，就能把雀斑像洗手一样洗得干干净净。如果加强剂量就会把脸上的血色洗掉，让脸色像玫瑰般红润的美女变成苍白的幽灵。”

“你就是想用这种药剂来洗我的脸吧？”乔治亚娜焦急地问。

“哦，不，”丈夫急忙回答，“这只能作用于表面。你需要的是一种效力更加深入的药。”

艾尔默在同乔治亚娜谈话的时候，总是要仔细询问她的感觉，了解她被幽闭在这些房间里是否乐意，室内的气温是否适宜。这些问题显示出一种特殊的意味，以致乔治亚娜开始猜想自己业已受到了某种自然物质的影响，要不是把它同芬芳的香气一道吸了进去，就是把它同食物一道吃了下去。她还想象——不过也许只是幻想——自己体内有什么在躁动，有一种奇怪的、不可名状的感觉正偷偷传遍全身经脉，然后半带痛楚半带愉悦地在心窝战栗。任何时候只要她鼓起勇气照照镜子，就会看见自己的脸色像白玫瑰般苍白，那绯红的胎记仍然赫然印在脸颊上。现在即使是艾尔默也赶不上她自己对这个胎记的憎恶了。

在丈夫必须致力于化合与分析实验的时候，乔治亚娜为了消磨掉乏味的时光，便翻阅起他那间科学图书室里的书籍来。从许多幽昧难解的古书中，她读到一些充满传奇故事和诗歌的篇章。它们是中世纪自然哲学家的著作，这些人当中有艾伯塔斯·马格努斯(3)、科尼利乌斯·阿格里帕(4)、帕拉塞尔苏斯(5)，以及那位创造出会预言的青铜头像的著名修道士(6)。所有这些古代的自然科学家都站在自己时代的前列，却又充满了那些时代的某些轻信，所以人们相信——或者他们自己也认为——他们从对大自然的探索中获得了超越自然的力量，并从物理学中取得了对精神世界的支配权。王家学会的那些早期学报也同样离奇古怪、异想天开。学会会员们几乎丝毫不了解自然可能性的极限，只是不停地记录着种种奇迹，或者提出制造奇迹的方法。

对于乔治亚娜来说，最引发兴趣的是她丈夫亲笔写成的一卷对开本的大书，里面记载着他在科学研究生涯中的每一项实验，包括其原定目标、进展过程中所采用的种种方法、最终的成功或失败，以及导致成功或失败的详情细节。事实上，对于他那满怀热忱、雄心勃勃和富于幻想而又勇于实践、勤奋钻研的一生，这本书既是历史记录，也是一种象征。他处理起物质细节来如此专注，犹如除此之外别的什么都不存在，但他又将物质全部予以精神化，并凭借自己对无限的热切追求而避免陷入纯粹的物质主义。在他手中，实实在在的一块泥土也具备了某种灵魂。乔治亚娜一边读着，一边对艾尔默油然而生敬意，对他也比过去爱得更深，但对他的判断力却不再像以前那样绝对信赖了。尽管他取得了那么多成就，她却不能不看到他最辉煌的成就与他的理想目标相比几乎只能算作失败。如果与他不可企及的那些无价珍宝相比，他现在握在手中的最灿烂的钻石只能算是些最普通的卵石，而且他自己也是这样认为的。这部书里写满了为作者本人赢得盛誉的许多成就，然而又是一卷出自凡夫俗子之手的阴郁的记录。它记录下了人的悲哀自白和无穷尽的例证，证明人这种混合物其精神总是为肉体所拖累，并只能借助物质来发挥机能，也说明崇高的天性发现自身悲惨地受制于肉体时如何遭受绝望的袭击。也许任何领域中的每一个天才，都能从艾尔默的日记中看出自身经历的生动体现。

这些思绪深深地感动了乔治亚娜，她把脸伏在翻开的书页上，禁不住泪水涌流。就在这时候她被丈夫撞见了。

“读巫士的书是很危险的啊。”他笑着说，尽管表情有些不安和生气，“乔治亚娜，这本书里有些地方连我自己看上一眼都很难保持理智。小心别让它让你受害。”

“它使我比过去更加崇拜你了。”她说。

“啊，等到这次成功后再说吧，”他回答道，“到那时如果你乐意再来崇拜我吧。我也不会认为自己受之有愧了。好啦，我找你为的是要享受一下你的歌声。亲爱的，给我唱支歌吧。”

于是她便以自己行云流水般的歌声慰解了他精神上的饥渴。然后他便带着孩子般的无限欢悦离开了，他还向她保证说幽居生活很快就会结束，成功是有绝对把握的。他刚刚离开，乔治亚娜便感到有种无法抗拒的力量驱使自己跟着他。她忘了告诉艾尔默，过去两三个钟头里她身上出现了一种令她担忧的症状。它就是产生在那块致命胎记里的某种感觉，不是疼痛，而是引起了整个身体的焦躁不安。她急匆匆地跟在丈夫后面，第一次闯进了那间实验室。进入她眼帘的第一件东西就是那个熔炉，通红火热，光焰熊熊，从炉顶堆积的大量烟尘看来它已经不停地燃烧了许多年头。一套蒸馏器械正在全速运转。房间里到处是蒸馏器、试管、量筒、坩埚和其他种种用于化学研究的器具。一台电动机械已经准备停当正马上要投入使用。整个气氛显得极其压抑，空中弥漫着由实验产生的各种刺鼻的气味。整个房间十分简陋朴素，墙壁光秃秃的，地下铺着砖块，在习惯于自己闺房的华丽雅致的乔治亚娜看来，一切都显得异常陌生。但吸引了她的主要注意力，简直是全部注意力的，却是艾尔默的模样。

他脸色像死人似的苍白，神情急切而专注，全身紧俯在熔炉上方，仿佛熔炉里蒸馏出来的液体到底是永恒幸福之药还是永恒苦难之药，就全依赖于他的全神贯注。这与他为了鼓励乔治亚娜而表现出的那种乐观自信的神态是多么的不同啊！

“现在要当心，阿米那达勃；当心点，你这人形的机械！当心点，你这凡俗之徒！”艾尔默这样咕咕哝哝着，与其说是在训诫助手，倒不如说是在自言自语。“现在，只要有一念之差，就全都完了。”

“嗬！嗬！”阿米那达勃含糊地咕噜着，“瞧，主人！瞧！”

艾尔默急忙抬起头来，看到了乔治亚娜，他脸色先是变红，接着又变得比原来更加苍白。他冲到乔治亚娜身边，那样紧地一把抓住她的胳膊，甚至在她的胳膊上留下了自己的指印。

“你为什么到这里来？难道你不相信你的丈夫吗？”他情绪暴躁地叫道，“你想让那块该死的胎记毁灭我苦心经营的事情吗？药剂还没制成哩。走吧，好奇的女人！走！”

“不，艾尔默，”乔治亚娜的语气中显示出她所固有的坚定性格，“你并没有权力来抱怨我。你不相信自己的妻子，你一直掩藏着自己在这场实验中的焦虑心情。你不要认为我那么不中用，我的丈夫。把我们所冒的风险告诉我吧，不要担心我会畏缩；因为我在这件事里所担的风险要比你轻多了。”

“不，不，乔治亚娜！”艾尔默不耐烦地说，“不能这样。”

“我会顺从的，”她平静地回答道，“而且，艾尔默，无论你给我的是什么药剂，我都会一口吞下；根据同样的道理，就算是你亲手递给我一杯毒药我也会服下去的。”

“我心地高尚的妻子，”艾尔默被深深感动了，“直到现在我才知道你的天性是多么高贵和深沉。我再不会有任何事情瞒着你了。你要知道，这只绯红的手印尽管显得很表浅，实际上却以一种我从来未能想象到的力量牢牢楔入了你的机体中。我已经试用过种种无所不能的强效药剂，就只差改变你的生理组织了。现在只有一种办法还没有尝试过。要是这也不行，我们就全完了。”

“你为什么一直犹豫着不把这事告诉我？”她问道。

“因为，乔治亚娜，”艾尔默用低沉的声音说，“这样做有危险。”

“危险？危险只有一个——那就是让这个可怕的印记继续留在我的脸颊上！”乔治亚娜高声叫道，“去掉它，去掉它，不管要多大的代价，要不然我们都会被弄疯的！”

“上天知道，你说得真是太对了，”艾尔默哀伤地说，“现在，最亲爱的，回你的闺房去吧。再过片刻时间，一切都将接受检验了。”

他陪她回到房里，然后带着庄严而温柔的神情离开了她，这种神情远比他的言辞更能表明现在他们所面临的风险有多大。在他走后，乔治亚娜陷入了凝神沉思之中。她仔细思量着艾尔默的性格，做出了比以往任何时候都更全面公正的判断。她想到他那高贵的爱情，心里不禁无比欢悦却又阵阵战栗——他的爱是那么纯洁和崇高，绝不能接受哪怕半点的不完美，也不愿可怜地满足于任何不符合理想境界的凡俗平庸。她觉得这种感情远比那种低劣的爱情更加珍贵，远远胜过因为爱她的缘故而不得不忍受她的缺憾，远远胜过因为将完美理想降低到现实水准从而终生怀着背弃神圣爱情的负罪感。于是她以整个心灵虔诚祈祷，但愿自己能满足他那最崇高最深沉的观念，哪怕只有短短一瞬也好。她也十分清楚，不可能比短短一瞬更加长久，因为他的精神永远在奋进，永远在攀登，每一瞬都在要求着某种超越前一瞬的东西。

丈夫的脚步声把她惊醒了。他端着一只水晶高脚杯，里面盛的液体像水一样透明无色，但那莹莹光辉足以证明它真是一种长生之药。艾尔默脸色苍白；不过那似乎是心智高度亢奋和精神紧张的结果，而并非是害怕或怀疑的征象。

“这种药剂调制得可谓尽善尽美。”他说，以此来回答乔治亚娜询问的眼神，“它万无一失，除非我所有的科学知识都欺骗了我。”

“要不是为了你，亲爱的艾尔默，”他妻子说，“我宁愿以抛弃生命本身的方式来除掉这块凡人的胎记，而不愿用任何别的方式。对于达到像我现在这种精神境界的人来说，生命不过是一笔可悲的财富罢了。假如我更软弱一些和盲目一些，生活也许会是快乐的。假如我更坚强一些，生活也许还能怀抱着希望去加以忍受。可是，既然我发现自己是这样的人，我想我就是一切人当中最适合去死的人！”

“你最适合生活在天堂里而无须品尝死亡的滋味！”她丈夫回答道，“不过我们为什么要谈到死呢？这服药剂不可能失败。看看它对这株植物的作用吧。”

窗台上放着一盆患黄斑病的天竺葵，所有的叶片上都布满了黄色的斑点。艾尔默朝天竺葵下面的泥土里倒了很少一点药水。不一会儿，天竺葵的根部获得了药水的滋润，难看的黄斑渐渐消融进一片生机勃勃的翠绿之中。

“完全用不着什么来证明，”乔治亚娜平静地说，“把杯子给我吧，我很高兴把一切都交付于你的一句话。”

“那么，喝吧，崇高的女人！”艾尔默满怀炽热的赞赏高声说，“你的心灵纯洁无瑕，你敏感的肉体很快也将变得完美无缺了。”

她大口地喝下药水，然后把杯子交还到他手里。“真舒服，”她平静地笑了笑，“我觉得它好像是来自天堂的甘泉水，因为它里面蕴含着我所不了解的温和的芳香和甘美的滋味。它平息了许多日子以来一直煎熬着我的狂热的焦渴。现在，最亲爱的，让我睡去吧。我的肉体感觉正在把我的灵魂包裹起来，就像日落时分玫瑰花心周围的叶片一样。”

她说到最后几个字的时候已显示出些微的勉强，仿佛要发出那含糊拖沓的几个音节已经超出了她的控制力。话刚从唇间吐出，她便沉沉睡去了。艾尔默坐在她旁边，以那样急切的感情注视着她的面容，就好像他整个生命的价值都维系在即将显示的实验结果之上。然而与这种情绪交织在一起的，还有一位科学家富于哲理性的探究态度。哪怕是最细微的症状也逃不过他的目光。她脸颊上泛起的红潮，呼吸中的一次轻微失调，眼睑的一次微小颤动，几乎难以觉察的一阵全身战栗——随着时间一刻刻推移而出现的所有这些细节，他都记录在那册对开本的大书里。这本书前面的每一页中都留下了他紧张思考的印记，但漫长岁月中的所有思索都凝聚在这最后一页之中。

他一边忙着记录，同时也没有忘记随时观察那个不幸的手形胎记，每次都禁不住要打个寒战。然而有一次，由于某种奇怪的莫名冲动，他用嘴唇去吻它；而在吻它的时候，他的精神又感觉到畏缩。乔治亚娜在沉睡中不安地动了动，同时咕哝了一声，仿佛在表示抗议。艾尔默接着继续进行观察。他看出了效果。那只绯红的手印原来在乔治亚娜大理石般苍白的脸上是极其显著的，现在却变得轮廓模糊起来。她的脸色仍然和原来一样的苍白，可是那个胎记却随着她的每一次呼吸而变得不像原来那样清晰了。胎记的存在曾令人畏惧，而它的消失则更是令人恐惧。看一看虹霓的色彩是怎样在天空中消失的，你就会明白那个神秘的表记是怎样消退的了。

“天哪！它差不多消失了！”艾尔默自言自语道，狂喜之情难以自抑，“现在我几乎看不见它了。成功了！成功了！现在它只像最淡的玫瑰红。她的脸颊只要微微泛红就能掩盖住它。可是她却这么苍白！”

他拉开窗帘，让白日的自然光照进房间里，照在她的脸颊上。就在这时候，他听见了一阵粗野的、嘶哑的嬉笑声，他早已熟知那是他的仆人阿米那达勃表示欢乐的方式。

“啊，你这泥土胚子！啊，你这肉体凡胎！”艾尔默高喊道，疯狂似的大笑起来，“你给我干得挺好！物质与精神——尘世与天堂——这一次两方面都算尽职尽责！笑吧！你这感官动物！你赢得了笑的权利！”

这一阵大喊大叫惊醒了沉睡中的乔治亚娜。她慢慢睁开双眼，凝视着丈夫特地为此而准备的镜子。她发现那只曾经以灾难般的艳红灿然闪耀、几乎骇跑了他们全部幸福的绯红手印如今几乎无法察觉了，这时嘴角掠过了一丝淡淡的微笑。可是接着她又用蕴含忧愁和焦急的目光寻找着艾尔默的面孔，而艾尔默完全不能理解她何以会显示出这种神情。

“我可怜的艾尔默！”她喃喃地说。

“可怜？不，我是最富有、最快乐、最有福的！”他高喊道，“我举世无双的新娘啊，成功啦！你是完美无缺的！”

“我可怜的艾尔默，”她带着无比的柔情又重复了一遍，“你的志向远大，你的行为崇高。你因为怀有如此高尚纯洁的感情而弃绝了尘世所能给予你的最好的东西，请你别为此而懊悔。艾尔默，最亲爱的艾尔默，我快死了！”

唉！情况的确是这样！那只致命的手印紧握住生命的秘密，它乃是将天使般的精神与凡人的躯体融合为一体的纽带。随着那块胎记的最后一丝绯红色彩——那是人类缺陷的唯一标志——从她脸上渐渐消失，这位如今完美无瑕的女性便向空中呼出了最后一丝气息，而她的灵魂在丈夫身旁流连片刻之后，也就冉冉飞向了天国。接着，又听见了那阵嘶哑的嬉笑声！尘世凡俗的死亡命数，总是这样扬扬得意地战胜永恒不朽的精神，而精神则在这片半开发状态的朦胧领域中渴求着更高的完美。不过，假如艾尔默达到了更深刻的智慧境界，他倒也不必这样抛掷掉自己的幸福，因为人生幸福本可以将他那同属凡人机体的尘世生命与神圣超凡的素质相融合。他无法承受人世短暂的事物；他未能将目光投向时间阴影的范围之外，而且因为总是活在永恒之中，他也未能在当前生活中找到完美的未来。

————————————————————

(1) 鲍尔斯（Hiram Powers，1805—1873）：美国出生的意大利著名雕刻家，《希腊奴隶》为其代表作。

(2) 皮格马利翁（Pygmalion）：古希腊神话中的塞浦路斯国王，传说他所雕刻的少女像获得了生命并成了他的妻子。

(3) 艾伯塔斯·马格努斯（Albertus Magnus，1200—1280）：日耳曼哲学家、神学家。

(4) 科尼利乌斯·阿格里帕（Cornelius Agrippa，1486—1535）：日耳曼医生、神学家。

(5) 帕拉塞尔苏斯（Paracelsus，1493—1541）：瑞士医生、炼金术士。

(6) 这是指英国科学家罗杰·培根（Roger Bacon，1219/20—1292），据说他曾造出一个铜头像，能够说出神秘预言。

拉帕西尼的女儿

很早以前，有一个名叫乔万尼·古瓦斯孔蒂的青年，从意大利南部地区来到帕多瓦(1)大学求学。乔万尼口袋里只有为数不多的几个金币，只好寄宿在一幢古旧大宅中一间又高又阴暗的房间里。这幢大宅看来曾经是某位帕多瓦贵族的府第，而事实上大门的确刻有一个家族的盾徽，只不过这个家族早已灭绝了。年轻的异乡人对自己祖国的伟大诗歌不无研究，回忆起这个家族有一位祖先，或许正是这座邸宅的主人呢，曾经被但丁描绘为地狱里的永恒受难者。(2)由于这些记忆和随之而生的联想，再加上初次远离故乡的年轻人天性易于感伤，不免使得乔万尼环顾着这陈设简陋、景象凄凉的房间，心情沉重地叹息起来。

“圣母啊，先生！”莉萨贝塔老太太叫了起来，她的心被年轻人英俊的相貌征服，正好心地竭力把屋子收拾得舒适宜人。“一个年轻人的心里怎么会发出这样的叹息？是觉得这座老宅太死气沉沉了吗？那么老天保佑，把头伸到窗户外面去吧，你就会看到跟你刚刚离开的那不勒斯(3)一样明亮的阳光哩。”

乔万尼按照老太太的劝告机械地把头探出窗外，却并不怎么同意她关于帕多瓦的阳光像意大利南部一样令人振奋的说法。不过尽管如此，阳光到底还是洒遍了窗户下的花园，把它哺育的恩泽普施在形形色色的花草之上，而这些花草看来都是经过精心培植和受到细心照料的。

“这座花园也是属于这幢房子的吗？”乔万尼问。

“但愿不是，先生，除非长的不是那些闲花野草，而是又肥又壮的盆栽蔬菜。”莉萨贝塔答道，“不是。花园是齐阿科莫·拉帕西尼先生亲手栽培的。这位大名鼎鼎的大夫，我敢说那不勒斯那么远的地方也都知道他。听人家说，他从这些花草中提炼出药来，效力就跟魔法一样灵验。你会时常看见医生老爷在工作，说不定还会瞧见小姐，也就是他的女儿，在花园里采摘那些奇花异草哩。”

老太太现在已经尽其所能地把屋子收拾好了，然后把年轻人交给神明去保佑，径自离开了。

乔万尼发现自己没有别的什么事好做，只有看看窗子下面的花园。从外观看，他判断这是帕多瓦早期的一类植物园，它的出现比意大利或世界上任何其他地方都要早。它也可能曾是某个名门望族的游乐园，因为在花园中央有座大理石喷泉的废墟，雕刻得精美绝伦，可惜已经坍塌毁损，在乱石堆积之中已无法追寻到它原有的格局。不过清泉仍然一如当年地喷涌着，在阳光下闪烁着欢悦的光彩。一阵轻柔的汩汩声传到了年轻人坐着的窗口，使他恍然觉得那口喷泉就像是一个不朽的精灵，永远不停地唱着自己的歌，毫不在意周围的沧桑变幻。而与此同时，一个世纪把它凝聚进了大理石雕刻中，而另一个世纪又摧毁了这易于朽坏的装饰，让它散落在大地上。泉水流入的水池周围长满了各种各样的植物，它们那些硕大的叶片需要大量水分来滋养，有些植物正繁花盛开、无比壮观。其中特别有一株灌木，长在水池中央的一个大理石花盆里，开满了紫红色的鲜花，每一朵都闪烁着宝石般的富丽光彩。整丛灌木是如此绚烂辉煌，仿佛没有阳光也能把整个花园照亮。地上的每一处都长满了花木和药草，它们即使赶不上那丛灌木的娇美，也都显示出辛勤照料的迹象，似乎每株花草都各有自身的价值，培植它们的科学家对此无不谙熟于心。有的植物栽在雕满古雅花饰的石缸里，有的种在普通花盆中，有的像蛇一样在地上蜿蜒，或者不管攀缘着什么就向上高高伸展。有一株植物则缠绕在一尊威耳廷努斯(4)雕像上，将它荫翳包裹在飘拂悬垂的叶丛中，这种景象是如此令人愉悦，真可以成为雕刻家潜心体味的对象了。

就在乔万尼伫立窗前之时，他忽然听见一排绿叶后面传来沙沙的响声，这才察觉到花园里有人在干活儿。这个人很快就进入了他的眼帘，看样子绝不是一个普通的园丁，而是一位身材很高、形容枯槁、身穿学者黑长袍的人。他的岁数已过中年，长着灰白的头发和稀疏的灰白胡须，眉宇间透出异乎常人的智慧与教养，不过即使是在风华正茂之年，这张脸上恐怕也绝不会显露出多少内心的热情。

这位园艺学家无比专注地审视着路边的每一株花草，似乎他正在穿透它们最深秘处的天性，观察着它们的创造性本质，探知着这一片叶子何以是这种形状，而那一片叶子又何以是另一种形状，为什么这些不同的花朵在色泽和香味上会如此迥然相异。然而，他尽管对这些草木的生命有深刻的理解，却绝不试图与它们亲近。与此相反，他避免接触到它们或者直接吸入它们的气味，那种小心翼翼的态度令乔万尼感到很不愉快，因为他那副神态举止就像在邪恶势力包围之中行走的人，周围仿佛全是猛兽、毒蛇或者妖魔鬼怪，稍有疏忽就会遭到灭顶之灾。这位年轻人看见一个养花人居然是这一副战战兢兢的神情，心中不禁奇怪地升起恐骇之感：园艺本来是人类劳作中最朴素最纯洁的，也是人类未曾堕落的双亲所享有的欢乐与劳动啊。(5)难道这座花园就是当今世界的伊甸园？这个人，对自己亲手种植的东西都唯恐受其危害，难道就是亚当？

那个疑虑重重的园艺师在摘除枯死的树叶和修剪长势过盛的灌木时，都戴着一双厚手套保护着双手。这并非是他唯一的甲冑。当他穿过花园，来到大理石喷泉边那株长满珍宝般紫花的美丽植物跟前时，还戴上一种面罩来遮蔽嘴和鼻孔，仿佛这株植物所有的美都只是掩藏着某种致命的剧毒。就这样他还觉得太危险，又退了回去，摘下面罩，高声呼唤起来，那虚弱的声音就像是个内脏患病的人。

“贝阿特丽丝！贝阿特丽丝！”

“我在这儿，爸爸。你要什么？”对面房子的窗户里传来了圆润而年轻的声音——圆润得像热带的落日，令乔万尼莫名其妙地联想起姹紫嫣红的色彩和芬芳馥郁的香气。“你是在花园里吗？”

“是的，贝阿特丽丝，”园艺师回答道，“我需要你的帮助。”

在石雕门下很快出现了一个年轻姑娘的身影，她就像灿烂的春花和初升的旭日一样丰美，其姿容简直到了无可挑剔的地步。她浑身洋溢着青春的健美和生命力，而这一切又仿佛被她那条处女的腰带紧紧拘束着。不过乔万尼在朝园中俯视时，禁不住有点感到毛骨悚然，因为这位美丽的陌生女郎使他觉得仿佛就是园中的另一朵花，是园中那些花朵的人类姐妹，虽然同它们一样美丽，甚至比它们当中最艳丽的还要美丽，但也只有戴着手套才能触摸，不戴上面罩也不能接近。贝阿特丽丝沿着园中小径走过来，乔万尼观察到她在抚摸和闻嗅着一些花草，而那些正是她父亲小心翼翼回避的东西。

“到这里来，贝阿特丽丝，”父亲说，“来看看我们的头号宝贝还需要给予多少照料。可是我已经年迈体弱了，要是依照情况需要去过分接近它是会送掉我的老命的。所以，这株树恐怕必须由你一个人来照管了。”

“我很乐意照料它。”姑娘用圆润的嗓音回答道，一面朝那株艳丽的植物弯下腰来，张开双臂，似乎想要拥抱它。“是的，我的妹妹，我的宝贝，培育你、伺候你将是贝阿特丽丝的工作；而你将以自己的亲吻与芬芳的气息来回报她，这对于她来说就好比是生命的呼吸。”

接着，她便带着与她柔情的话语同样的温柔态度忙开来，给予那株树以它所需要的全部细心呵护。乔万尼站在高高的窗子后面揉着眼睛，几乎要怀疑这究竟是一位姑娘在照料她心爱的花呢，还是一位姐姐在对她的妹妹尽着爱的责任。这番景象很快就结束了。也许是拉帕西尼医生干完了园中的工作，或者是他警觉的目光瞥见了陌生人的面孔，他挽着女儿的手臂离开了。夜色渐浓；花草似乎散发出浓郁逼人的香味，悄然升腾，掠过打开的窗户。乔万尼关上窗子，躺到卧榻上，随即梦见一朵艳丽的鲜花和一位美丽的姑娘。鲜花和姑娘并非一物，却又相同，两者的形态中都充满某种诡异的危险。

不过晨光能发挥一种影响，可以纠正我们想象中的甚至判断上的错误，这些错误往往发生在夕阳西下、夜色迷离或者月光朦胧的时候。乔万尼醒来后的第一个动作就是猛地打开窗户，低头凝视那个给他带来神秘梦境的花园。他惊奇地，同时又略带羞愧地发现那个花园是个实实在在、平凡无奇的东西。清晨第一缕阳光正在给鲜花绿叶上的露珠镀上一层金色，让奇花异卉显得更加明丽动人，但眼前的一切毕竟都并未超越日常经验的限度。年轻人不禁感到高兴，因为在这座荒凉城市的中心，自己竟能获得俯瞰这花草繁茂、景象迷人的花园的机会。他暗自对自己说，这个花园将成为自己与大自然交流的一种象征性语言。这时候，还看不到那位形容憔悴、满面忧思的拉帕西尼医生和他那光彩照人的女儿，所以乔万尼难以确定自己觉得他们举止怪异根据何在：到底是因为他们本身如此呢，还是自己想入非非的结果。不过他打算对整个事情保持最理智的态度。

当天，他带着一封介绍信去拜会皮埃特罗·巴格里奥尼先生，他是大学里的一位医学教授，也是一位声名卓著的医生。教授虽已年迈，态度却非常和蔼，甚至可以说具有快乐的天性。他留下乔万尼一起吃饭，他不拘礼仪、谈笑风生，尤其是在喝下两杯托斯卡纳葡萄酒(6)之后，更使得乔万尼感觉非常愉快。乔万尼心想在同一个城市居住的科学家们彼此一定很熟悉，便抓住一个机会提到拉帕西尼医生的名字。可是教授的反应并不如他所预期的那样热诚。

“作为一个从事神圣医学的教师，”巴格里奥尼教授回答乔万尼提出的一个问题，“对拉帕西尼这样的技艺卓绝的医生不给予恰当的和慎重的赞扬，是不合适的；但另一方面，假如我听任一个像你这样前程远大的青年，乔万尼先生，而且是我老朋友的儿子，对将来可能将你的生死握在手心的人抱着错误的认识，那我的回答又会对不起自己的良心。实话实说吧，我们这位可敬的拉帕西尼医生的科学造诣，可以同帕多瓦大学或者全意大利的任何大学教授媲美——或许只有一个人除外。不过对他的职业道德，人们却持有严重的异议。”

“是些什么异议呢？”年轻人问。

“我的朋友乔万尼是不是身体或者心灵出了毛病，才这么热衷于打听医生们的事情？”教授微笑着说，“至于拉帕西尼，据说是——我对他很熟悉，可以担保其真实性——他对科学的关心远远胜过对人类的关心。他对病人的兴趣仅仅是把他们当作某种新奇实验的对象。只要能给他巨大的知识积累再增添哪怕一粒芥子，他情愿牺牲人的生命，包括他自己的生命，或者任何他最亲爱的人的生命。”

“我觉得他真是个可怕的人。”乔万尼说，一面回想着拉帕西尼那副冰冷的、纯理智的面容，“不过，尊敬的教授，那难道不是一种高贵的精神吗？能够对科学怀着如此超凡热忱的人并不太多吧？”

“但愿这种人不要太多。”教授回答道，神情有些恼怒，“至少，除非他们对医学的观点比拉帕西尼更健全。他的理论认为，医药的一切疗效都存在于我们称之为毒性植物的东西里。他亲手培育这些毒性植物，据说甚至提炼出了一些新型毒素，其毒性比天然毒素可怕得多，倘若这位博学之士不帮忙的话，恐怕早就让全世界遭了灾祸。不容否认，医生先生手里的这些危险物质所造成的危害比预料的要小。必须承认，有时候他的治疗效果的确奇妙，或者说似乎很奇妙。不过我给你说心里话，乔万尼先生，他的这些成功不应该受到赞扬——有可能是运气使然——而他对于自己的失败却负有不可推卸的责任，平心而论，失败倒可能是他亲手造成的。”

倘若年轻人知道教授与拉帕西尼医生之间在专业方面一直存在冲突，而人们一般认为后者占据着上风，那么他对巴格里奥尼的意见就会持相当保留的态度了。如果有读者愿意自己做判断的话，不妨去查阅帕多瓦大学医学系保存的双方论战的黑体铅字文件。

“博学的教授，我不了解，”乔万尼对刚才所谈的拉帕西尼对科学的专注热忱做了一番沉思之后，接着说——“我不了解这位医生对自己的医学到底有多么钟爱，不过，对他来说肯定还有比医学更珍贵的东西。他有个女儿。”

“啊哈！”教授大笑着叫道，“现在我们的朋友乔万尼可暴露了他的秘密。你也听说他的这个女儿了，帕多瓦城所有的年轻人都在为她疯狂，虽然没有几个能有幸一睹她的芳容。我对这位贝阿特丽丝小姐一无所知，只听说拉帕西尼把自己高深的医学知识都传授给了她，她不仅因年轻美丽而享有盛誉，而且有资格担任教授的职位。或许她父亲就想让她来占据我的职位吧！荒诞的传闻还有的是，但不值一提也不值一听。好啦，乔万尼先生，喝干你杯中的葡萄酒吧。”

因为喝酒过多的缘故，古瓦斯孔蒂回去的时候颇有醉意，满脑袋漂浮着有关拉帕西尼医生和美丽的贝阿特丽丝的奇异幻想。在回家路上碰巧经过一家花店，他买了一束鲜花。

他上楼回到房间里，靠窗坐下，但隐藏在高高的墙壁投下的阴影里，这样就可以俯瞰花园而没有被人发现的危险。在他目光的扫视下，整个花园是一派寂寞景象。珍奇的花木沐浴着阳光，不时地彼此轻轻点头，仿佛在互认亲缘、互通情意。花园中央那倾颓的喷泉旁，长着那株绚丽的灌木，浑身缀满了珍宝般的紫色花朵。繁花朵朵在空中光彩闪耀，倒映在水池中又被折射回来，在层层光影映照之中流光溢彩。正像我们已经讲过的，花园里起初是一片寂寞景象。不过没过多久——乔万尼一半盼望一半害怕的事情发生了——一个人影出现在古老的石雕拱门下，穿过一排排花木走过来，一面深深呼吸着花木的种种异香，仿佛是古代传说中靠香气生活的精灵。年轻人再次看到贝阿特丽丝，惊奇地发现她的美丽超过了自己记忆中的形象；她是如此艳丽，如此充满活力，在阳光辉耀下简直是光艳照人。乔万尼不禁悄声自语说，她的光彩一定把花园小径上那些阴暗处也照亮了。这一次能把她的容貌看得比上次更清楚，那张脸上纯朴而甜美的表情使乔万尼惊愕不已——他还从没有想过她具有这样的性格，于是他再次问自己：她会是怎样的人？他也再次观察到或者想象着，这位美丽的姑娘同奇花悬垂于喷泉之上的那株美艳的灌木十分相似——贝阿特丽丝似乎也陶醉于这种幻想，她的服装配搭和色彩的选择使这种相似性更加强烈。

她走近那株灌木，带着炽热的激情张开双臂，将它的枝条亲密地拥进怀抱——亲密得把自己的脸掩没在它繁茂的叶丛中，把自己亮泽的卷发交织到了花朵里。

“请你将芳香的呼吸给我吧，我的妹妹，”贝阿特丽丝叫道，“因为我嗅着普通的空气就发晕。请你将这朵花给我吧，我会从茎干上轻轻地摘下它，放在紧贴心口的地方。”

拉帕西尼那美丽的女儿一边说着，一边从灌木上摘下了一朵最鲜艳的花，准备把它别在胸前。可就在此时，除非是乔万尼的醉意让他产生了错觉，眼前发生了一件奇怪的事。一条橙色的小爬虫，大概属于蜥蜴或者变色龙之类，碰巧沿着小径爬行着，正好到了贝阿特丽丝脚边。乔万尼似乎看到——不过他观看的地点隔着一段距离，也许并不能看清楚那个小家伙——不过他总觉得折断的花茎上滴落了一两滴汁液，正好落在那条蜥蜴头上。顿时，小爬虫的身子剧烈地扭动起来，接着就躺在阳光下一动不动了。贝阿特丽丝也观察到了这个异常现象，她悲伤地画了个十字，但并不显得惊诧；她仍然把那朵致命的花朵别在胸前，并不因此有半点犹疑。花朵在她胸前盛开着，闪耀着宝石般的炫目光彩，给她的服装和容貌增添了世间任何东西都不可能给予的恰如其分的魅力。乔万尼已经从窗前的阴影里走出来，他把身子往前探看一下又退缩回去，浑身战抖着，低声自言自语。

“我是醒着的吧？我的神志是清楚的吧？”他问自己，“这是什么人？我该说她美丽呢，还是该说她极其可怕呢？”

贝阿特丽丝这时正信步穿过花园，走到了乔万尼窗下。为了满足自己被她激起的强烈而痛苦的好奇心，乔万尼不能自抑地把头从藏身处伸了出去。就在此刻，一只美丽的昆虫越过花园的围墙飞来：也许它已在全城漫游了一番，在古城的人类聚居地找不到鲜花和绿树，直到拉帕西尼医生园子里花草的浓香把它从远处引诱过来。这只长翅膀的快活小虫并没有停在鲜花上，它似乎被贝阿特丽丝吸引住了，在空中徘徊不定，绕着她的头顶振翅飞翔着。这一次发生的事算是千真万确了，除非乔万尼·古瓦斯孔蒂的眼睛欺骗了他。即便可能如此吧，他还是恍惚看到就在贝阿特丽丝带着孩子般的欣喜凝视着这只小昆虫时，它渐渐堕入昏晕，跌落在她的脚下；它那对闪光的翅膀战抖着，然后死去——他找不出任何致死的原因，除了姑娘所呼出的气息而外。贝阿特丽丝俯身看着那只死昆虫，又一次画了个十字，发出了深长的叹息声。

乔万尼情不自禁地动了动，使她把目光投向了窗户。她看到一个漂亮的青年男子——与其说他是个意大利人，倒不如说更像希腊人，面容匀称俊美，一头卷发闪耀着金色亮光——他正俯视着她，就像翱翔在半空中的精灵。乔万尼不由自主地把手中一直握着的花束向下抛去。

“小姐，”他说，“这是些纯洁而有益于健康的鲜花，请为乔万尼·古瓦斯孔蒂而佩戴吧。”

“谢谢，先生。”贝阿特丽丝用圆润的声音回答道，就像涌来一阵悦耳的乐音，她脸上也浮现出半带儿童稚气半带女性娇媚的欢乐表情。“我接受您的礼物，并愿以这朵珍贵的紫花作为回报。不过我要是往上扔的话，够不着您站的地方，所以乔万尼先生只好满足于我的谢意了。”

她把花束从地上捡起来，接着仿佛因为逾越了少女的审慎、回应了陌生人的敬意而内心羞愧，迅速地转身穿过花园回去了。可是尽管这瞬刻极为短暂，乔万尼似乎发现就在她快要在石雕拱门下消失的时候，那束美丽的鲜花已开始在她手中枯萎了。这个想法简直毫无根据；隔着这么远的距离，是绝不可能把枯萎的花和鲜花分清的。

这件事之后的许多天里，年轻人都尽量避开那扇俯瞰拉帕西尼家花园的窗户，好像只要他情不自禁地往那里瞟上一眼，就会有某种丑陋而可怕的东西把自己的眼睛弄瞎。他心里明白，自己因为同贝阿特丽丝谈过话，在某种程度上已经被一种不可言喻的力量影响。如果说他的心灵业已处于某种真实的危险中，那么最明智的对策是立刻离开自己的住所和帕多瓦城。较为明智的办法则是尽量使自己习惯于以随意的和理智的态度去看待贝阿特丽丝——这样就会将她严格有序地逐渐纳入普通经验的范围。最不好的做法是，虽然乔万尼避免见到她，却仍然住在与这个奇异的姑娘相距咫尺之地，彼此紧密相邻甚至有发生交往的可能性，这将给他那狂乱想象所不断产生的荒谬幻想赋予一种实在性和真实感。乔万尼的内心感情并不深沉——或者至少其深度至今尚未经过测量。不过他的想象力很敏锐，又有南方人的热烈性格，任何时刻都可能升至炽热的顶峰。不论贝阿特丽丝是否具有那些可怕的特性，那种乔万尼亲眼所见的致命气息，以及她与那些美丽的剧毒花朵之间的亲和力，至少她已经把一种猛烈而微妙的毒素注入了他的机体。那并不是爱情，尽管她的丰美娇艳使他十分迷恋；那也不是恐怖，即使他想象她的灵魂也浸透了那种充溢于她身体的毒素。它是以爱情和恐怖为父母的野生后裔，既像爱情一样燃烧，又像恐怖一样战栗。乔万尼不知道该恐惧什么，更不知道该希望什么；然而希望和恐惧在他胸中不停地争斗着，彼此交替地征服对方，被打败的又再跳起来重新搏斗。一切单纯的情感是值得祝福的，不论它们属于黑暗还是光明！正是黑暗与光明的可怕混合才产生出地狱的炫目火焰。

为了平息精神上的狂热，他常常在帕多瓦的街道上疾走，或者跑到城门外去；脚步追随着思想激烈搏动的节奏，往往越走越快，犹如狂奔一样。有一天，他忽然发现自己受到了阻拦，一个身材魁梧的老人抓住了他的胳膊；那个人认出了这个年轻人，便回头迫来，为了赶上他而弄得气喘吁吁。

“乔万尼先生！停下，我的年轻朋友！”他叫喊道，“你忘记我了吗？要是我的变化也像你这么大，倒也真会被人忘记啦。”

原来是巴格里奥尼。乔万尼从第一次见面之后就一直躲着他，害怕教授的睿智会洞察自己心底的秘密。他极力恢复镇静，用狂乱的眼神从内心世界瞪视着身外的世界，说起话来就像一个梦游人一样。

“是呀，我是乔万尼·古瓦斯孔蒂。您是皮埃特罗·巴格里奥尼教授。现在让我过去！”

“还不行，还不行，乔万尼·古瓦斯孔蒂先生。”教授微笑着说，同时用热切的目光仔细审视着这位年轻人，“什么！难道我和你父亲不是一块儿长大的吗？在帕多瓦城的古老街道上，他的儿子与我就像陌生人一样擦身而过吗？站着别动，乔万尼先生；我们分手前我有几句话要说。”

“那就快说，最尊敬的教授，快说。”乔万尼焦躁得发火，“阁下没有看出我有急事吗？”

正在他说话的时候，沿街走过来一个穿黑衣的人，佝偻着腰，脚步虚浮，似乎体质十分羸弱。他面带病容，脸色枯黄，神情中却饱含敏锐而活跃的智慧，以至一个旁观者很容易忽视他的病弱之躯，而只看到他洋溢着奇妙的精力。这个人经过他们身边时，同巴格里奥尼只是冷淡而疏远地互致问候，却以专注的目光凝视乔万尼，仿佛要把他内心所有值得注意的东西都弄个水落石出。然而那目光中又含有一种特别的宁静，似乎对于这个青年作为一个人并不在意，而只是沉浸于一种科学思辨的兴趣中。

“那就是拉帕西尼医生！”教授在陌生人走过之后低声说道，“他以前见过你吗？”

“我不知道。”乔万尼回答说，他听见那个名字便悚然一惊。

“他见过你！他一定见过你！”巴格里奥尼急匆匆地说，“出于这种或那种目的，这位科学家正在研究你。我了解他的那种目光！那目光和他弯腰观看一只鸟、老鼠或者蝴蝶时脸上罩着的冷光一模一样；那些小动物都是他在进行某种实验时使用花香薰死的。他的那种神情就像大自然本身那样深不可测，却没有大自然的爱的温暖。乔万尼先生，我愿意用自己的生命来打赌，你已经成为拉帕西尼一项实验的对象了！”

“你把我当成傻瓜了吧？”乔万尼激动地叫了起来，“教授先生，你这么搞可是一场不适当的实验。”

“别着急！别着急！”沉着的教授回答说，“听我告诉你，可怜的乔万尼，拉帕西尼对你发生了科学兴趣，你已经落进可怕的魔掌了！而贝阿特丽丝小姐——她在这出神秘剧中扮演了什么角色？”

可是乔万尼觉得巴格里奥尼的固执简直不堪忍受，便猛然脱逃而去，教授要想抓住他已经来不及了。他目不转睛地望着年轻人的背影，不停地摇头。

“这样可不行，”巴格里奥尼自语道，“这个年轻人是我老朋友的儿子，不能让他受到任何伤害，而医学的奥秘是能够保护他的。何况拉帕西尼要从我手里夺走这个孩子，利用他去做那些魔鬼般的实验，在我看来也的确是欺人太甚了。他竟然有这么个女儿！这件事我得操操心。说不定，最博学的拉帕西尼，你做梦也想不到我可能让你的如意算盘化为泡影哩！”

这时候，乔万尼东拐西绕地跑了一大圈，总算回到了寓所的门口。他在进门时碰到了老莉萨贝塔，她满脸堆笑，显然是想引起他的注意，然而并无效果，因为乔万尼激动的感情已经消退为冰冷而迟钝的一片空无。他回过头来盯着那张挤满笑容的皱巴巴的面孔，却似乎茫然而无所见。于是老太婆只好紧紧抓住他的外氅。

“先生！先生！”她悄声喊道，脸上仍然堆满笑容，看上去就像一副因年代久远而变得乌黑的怪异的木雕面具，“听着，先生！有一道秘密的通道可以进入那座花园！”

“你说什么？”乔万尼叫起来，同时飞快地转过身，仿佛一个没有生命的东西猛然变得生机勃发，“有一道秘密通道进入拉帕西尼医生的花园？”

“嘘！嘘！别这么大声！”莉萨贝塔悄声说，一面用手捂住乔万尼的嘴，“是的；能进尊敬的医生家的花园，你在那儿能看到他的全部奇花异草。帕多瓦城有许多年轻人愿意掏出金子，只要能进去观赏观赏那些花儿。”

乔万尼把一块金币放进了她的手里。

“带路吧。”他说。

大概是受到了巴格里奥尼谈话的刺激，他心头掠过了一丝疑云，也许老莉萨贝塔的介入与某个阴谋有关系，无论这个阴谋的性质是什么，据那位教授的猜测，总之拉帕西尼医生正打算把他网罗进去。不过这丝疑虑尽管使乔万尼感到不安，却不足以阻止他。就在他知道有机会接近贝阿特丽丝的那一刻，他就觉得这么做乃是自己生命的绝对需要。她是天使还是魔鬼都无关紧要；他已无可挽回地陷身于她的影响范围之中，只能服从它的律法被席卷而去，被裹入愈来愈小的旋涡之中，趋向某个他目前还不打算去预测的结局。然而说来奇怪，他突然间又怀疑自己这种强烈兴趣是不是虚幻的妄想？自己的感情是否真有那么深沉和明确，足以让自己投入这个难以预测的处境？它是否仅仅属于年轻人一时的幻想，与心灵并无深刻联系或者根本就与心灵毫无关系？

他停下脚步，犹豫不决，并侧身往回转，但接着又继续朝前走去。那个干瘪的老太婆引着他经过几条阴暗的过道，最后打开了一道门，门一打开，但见满目青翠，树叶沙沙作响，斑驳的阳光在枝叶间闪烁。乔万尼朝前走去，挤过阻挡着隐秘入口的一丛藤蔓缠绕的灌木，正好来到了他自己的窗下，站在拉帕西尼医生花园的空地上。

这样的情况常常发生，当不可能的事情在眼前出现，梦幻的迷雾凝聚成可触可感的现实时，我们却发现自己心情平静甚至冷静自若，而这种情况本来是我们苦苦期待、应该使我们欣喜若狂的。命运就是喜欢这样捉弄人。激情乃是不速之客，总是猛然间不期而至，可是当机缘成熟需要它登场时，它却懒洋洋地在后面拖拖沓沓。乔万尼现在的情况就是如此。日复一日，只要他一想到和贝阿特丽丝见面，和她在这花园中面对面地站在一起，沐浴在她那旭日般美丽的光彩中，从她的凝视中获取自己的生命之谜，这不可能实现的念头就会使他血脉贲张、心跳加剧。然而在此刻，他的心情却奇怪而不合时宜地平静如水。他迅速地朝四周一瞥，想看看贝阿特丽丝或者她父亲在不在这里，结果发现园中只有他自己，便开始挑剔地观察起那些植物来。

这些花草的模样都不能让他感到满意。它们的那种艳丽显得粗暴，过分热烈，甚至不自然。要是一个漫游者在森林里迷了路，见到这些树木都会吓得心惊肉跳，因为它们每一株的模样都是那么狂野，仿佛是从乱木丛中探出一张鬼脸，向着他瞪眼狞视。有几株还会让神经脆弱的人大受惊骇，因为那种违背自然的模样说明它们是由不同品种杂交而成，并不是上帝创造的产物，而是人类堕落幻想的恶魔后裔，正扬扬自得地对美加以邪恶的嘲笑。它们大概都是园艺实验的结果，其中有一两株是用本身十分可爱的植物混杂而成的，那种令人疑虑的不祥特征鲜明地体现出整座花园的品格。最后，乔万尼在所有的花木中辨认出了两三种，那都是他所熟知的毒性植物。正在凝神思考的时候，他听见了丝绸衣裙沙沙作响的声音，他转过脸来，看见贝阿特丽丝出现在石雕拱门的下面。

乔万尼来不及考虑自己该怎样应付这个局面，是为自己擅自闯入花园道歉呢，还是假定自己的到来即使不合乎拉帕西尼医生或他女儿的意愿，至少也获得了他们的默许。不过贝阿特丽丝的神情使他放了心，尽管关于自己通过什么办法进入花园的问题仍然使他有些惴惴不安。贝阿特丽丝轻盈地沿着小径走来，和他在那座倾颓的喷泉边相遇。她显出诧异的表情，但满脸焕发着单纯而和蔼的快乐神气。

“您是一位鉴赏鲜花的行家，先生。”贝阿特丽丝微微一笑说，她在暗指乔万尼从窗口向她抛下花束的事，“所以难怪您看见我父亲的奇花异卉，就被吸引得非来就近观赏不可。要是他在这儿，会告诉您有关这些花草习性的许多新奇而有趣的事情；他在这种研究中耗费了毕生精力，这座花园就是他的世界。”

“还有您本人，小姐，”乔万尼说，“假如名实相符的话——您也同样精通这些鲜花和这些芳香所显示的功效。要是您肯屈尊赐教，我一定会比受拉帕西尼先生教诲还要学得好些。”

“竟会有这种毫无根据的谣传？”贝阿特丽丝问道，并发出音乐般动听的笑声，“人们说我精通父亲的植物学！真是开玩笑！不；尽管我是在这些花草中长大的，但我所知的只不过是它们的色泽和香味。有时候我觉得自己甚至连这点儿知识也想丢掉。这儿有许多花，它们并不是不艳丽，但我一见到它们就害怕和讨厌。不过，先生，请别相信那些关于我学识的传言。关于我的情况，除了你亲眼所见之外什么也不要相信。”

“我亲眼所见的就应该都相信吗？”乔万尼隐有所指地问道，想起过去所见的那几幕情景不免使他感到畏缩，“不，小姐；您对我的要求未免太少。您应当吩咐我除了您说的话之外什么也不要相信才对。”

看来贝阿特丽丝懂得了他的意思。她的双颊泛起了一道红霞；但她正视着乔万尼的眼睛，以女王般的高傲回应他那隐含不安的猜疑的目光。

“那我就吩咐您，先生，”她回答道，“忘掉一切您可能怀有的对我的幻想。即使外部感官觉得真实的，本质上仍然可能虚假。不过贝阿特丽丝说出的话字字都真正发自内心深处。对此你可以相信。”

她的整个脸庞上浮起了一道红晕，就像真理本身的光辉一样照亮了乔万尼的意识；但是在她说话的时候四周空气中又弥漫着一阵芳香，是那样浓郁甜美，尽管稍纵即逝，年轻人却出于难以名状的抗拒心理，几乎不敢往肺里吸。它可能是花的香气。或许，那也可能是贝阿特丽丝的呼吸，就仿佛她用心灵的芬芳熏透了她的话语，因此使它们带上了奇异的芳香？乔万尼心中就像掠过一道阴影似的发生了一阵晕眩，但很快就过去了；他似乎透过这位美丽姑娘的双眼看到了她那透明灵魂的深处，于是不再有怀疑或恐惧了。

笼罩着贝阿特丽丝神情的那种激情色彩消退了；她变得快乐起来，就像是一个独居孤岛的少女能与来自文明世界的旅人交谈一样，她因为能与这位年轻人谈话而感到十分欣喜。显然，她的全部生活经验都局限在这座花园的范围之内。她一会儿谈论阳光或者夏季云彩之类的简单事物，一会儿又询问城市的情况，乔万尼远方的家、他的朋友、母亲、姐妹，等等——这些问题表明她是如此与世隔绝，对于生活的方式和形态是如此一无所知，以至乔万尼就像在对一个幼稚的孩子说话。在他面前，她的灵魂就像一道清泉涌流而出，才刚刚瞥见第一缕阳光，对于映射在自己怀中的大地与天空的影像感到莫名惊异。从那深深的泉源里也涌流出种种思想和五光十色的奇异想象，犹如钻石和红玉随着喷泉的水珠向上闪耀跳跃。年轻人心中不时感觉到惊异，没想到自己现在竟能同这位让他日夜梦想的人并肩散步；自己对于她曾在想象中怀着种种恐惧，自己曾亲眼见过她显示那些可怕的禀赋——而现在却像兄弟一样与贝阿特丽丝亲切交谈，并发现她是如此充满人情味，如此富于少女的美。然而这些想法不过转瞬即逝；她的性格的力量太具有真实性了，很快就使人感到亲近无拘。

他们就这样随意地交谈着，信步穿过花园，经过条条小径的道道拐角，来到那个坍塌的喷泉边。喷泉边上就生长着那株壮观的灌木，繁花竞相开放，光彩灿烂。灌木正散发着阵阵芬芳，乔万尼觉得这种香气和他所认为的贝阿特丽丝呼吸的气息完全一样，只不过更是无比的浓烈。就在她看到这棵树的时候，乔万尼发现她按住了胸口，仿佛她的心突然痛苦地狂跳起来。

“一生中这是第一次，”她喃喃地对那株树说，“我把你给忘了。”

“我还记得，小姐，”乔万尼说，“您曾经许诺过要送我一朵这宝石般的鲜花，回报我曾快乐地斗胆抛在您脚下的花束。现在请允许我摘下一朵来，作为这次会见的纪念吧。”

他朝那株灌木走了一步，把手伸了出去；可是贝阿特丽丝猛地冲上前，同时发出了一声尖叫，就像利刃一样穿透了他的心。她抓住他的手，用她纤弱身体的全部力量把它拉了回来。乔万尼觉得她的手的触摸使他周身的神经都在战栗。

“不要碰它！”她用痛苦的声音喊道，“要活命就别去碰它！它会弄死人的！”

接着，她掩着脸跑开了，消失在石雕拱门下面。就在乔万尼目送她的背影时，他发现了拉帕西尼消瘦的身影和苍白而聪慧的脸孔，他一直站在园门的阴影中观察着这一幕，不知已有多长时间了。

乔万尼一回到自己的寓所，就满怀热情地回想着贝阿特丽丝的倩影，从他第一次见到她起，她的形象就一直笼罩着魔幻色彩，现在又浸透了少女的娇柔温情。她富于人情味，她的天性中充满了温柔的女性气质，她值得自己倾心崇拜，她的心灵肯定能升华到爱情的顶峰和崇高境界。曾被他一度视为她生理和道德上可怕癖性的那些迹象，现今不是忘得干干净净，就是被感情的难以捉摸的诡辩术转化成了魅力无穷的金冠，使得贝阿特丽丝越发显得特出不凡、值得赞赏。任何看上去丑陋的东西如今都变得美丽了；或者说，即使不能发生变化，也偷偷潜藏到那些朦胧不清的念头之中，而那些念头则拥塞在我们健全的意识之光照射不到的阴暗区域里。他就这样度过了那个不眠之夜，直到晨曦唤醒了拉帕西尼医生花园中沉睡的花朵，他才进入梦乡，而乔万尼的梦境无疑也把他带进了那座花园里。朝阳按时升起，把光芒投射到年轻人的眼帘上，使他醒来并感觉到某种痛楚。当他完全清醒过来的时候，才意识到手上有一股火辣辣的刺痛——在右手上——正是他想要去摘一朵宝石般的鲜花时贝阿特丽丝抓住的那只手。手背上如今留有一个紫色的印迹，像四只纤小手指的指印，而腕部留下的痕迹则像细长的大拇指的指印。

啊，爱情是多么的顽固——甚至连在想象中滋生、在心灵中毫无根基的爱情的狡诈假冒品也是如此——它总是冥顽地固执己见，直到它命中注定地烟消云散为止！乔万尼把一条手巾包裹在右手上，心中纳闷自己被什么毒虫子蜇着了，很快就又坠入对贝阿特丽丝的梦想中，浑然忘却了疼痛。

有了第一次会面，第二次便按照我们称之为命运的必然进程发生了。接着有第三次，第四次。同贝阿特丽丝在花园中相见已不再是乔万尼日常生活中的插曲，而可以说是成了他生活的全部内容，因为对那销魂时刻的期待与回忆也把他其余的时间全部占据了。拉帕西尼的女儿也同样如此。她守候着年轻人露面，一看见他就飞快跑来，那种信任和坦率就仿佛他俩从小就是青梅竹马的伙伴——仿佛现在还依然是这样的小伙伴。如果他因为偶然缘故而未能按时赴约，她就会站到窗下往上呼唤，把那丰润甜美的声音送进他的房间，激荡回响在他身边、在他心中：“乔万尼！乔万尼！你为什么老不来？下来吧！”于是他就赶快下楼，跑到那座毒花盛开的伊甸园中去。

不过，尽管他们彼此这么亲密和熟悉，贝阿特丽丝的举止中仍然含有某种矜持，她始终是那样凛然不可冒犯，使得乔万尼从来不敢转一转大胆造次的念头。从所有可以察觉到的迹象来看，他们在相爱了；他们彼此脉脉含情地凝视，把其中一个人心灵深处的神圣秘密送入另一个人的心灵深处，仿佛这种秘密太圣洁了，不能把它随意付之悄声低语。在激情奔放之中他们也曾情话喁喁，那时他们的心灵就像久久掩藏的火焰喷出火舌一样迸发出话语。然而他们一直没有相吻过，手一直没有相握过，也没有发生过为爱情所应有和崇尚的最轻微的爱抚。他从来没有触摸过她一丝光亮的鬈发；她的衣裙——他们身体接触的明显的物质障碍——也从来没有被微风吹动而轻拂过他的身体。有极少数几次，乔万尼抵抗不了诱惑而试图跨越界限，贝阿特丽丝就会变得那么悲伤、那么严厉，神情会显得那么凄凉和疏远，充满自怨自艾，不用说只言片语就使乔万尼望而却步了。每逢这种时刻，可怕的疑虑便会像魔鬼般从他心灵的洞穴中爬出来，瞪眼向他凝视，令他心惊肉跳；他的爱情就会像晨雾一样变得淡薄而消散；只有怀疑还实实在在地留驻心间。不过，当贝阿特丽丝在短暂的阴郁之后又变得容光焕发时，她立即不再是那个令他如此敬畏和恐惧的神秘可疑的精灵了；她又变成了那个美丽的、天真无邪的姑娘，他觉得自己的心灵对这位姑娘具有超乎一切的真切认识。

自从乔万尼上次见到巴格里奥尼之后，已经过去了很长一段时间。一天上午教授突然来访，使他感到意外和不快，因为好几个礼拜以来他几乎想也没有想到过他，甚至愿意更长久地把他忘掉。像他这样长期处于全身心的亢奋状态中，除了那些完全赞同他目前感情的人以外，是绝不能忍受与任何别的同伴相处的。而从巴格里奥尼教授那里当然不能指望获得这种赞同。

客人随意地谈论了一会儿有关城市和大学里的闲言碎语，接着就转移了话题。

“最近我一直在读一位古典作家的作品，”他说，“读到一个故事颇让我感兴趣。也许你还记得它。故事讲到一位印度王子，他送给亚历山大大帝一位美女作为礼物。她像黎明一样可爱，像夕阳一样绚丽；而最为特出不凡的是她的呼吸中含有某种浓郁的芳香——足以胜过一座波斯玫瑰园。像亚历山大这样一位年轻的君王，对这位奇异的美女自然一见钟情；可是当时恰巧有一位睿智的医生在场，发现了一桩有关她的可怕秘密。”

“是什么呢？”乔万尼问道，他的眼帘低垂，避开了教授的目光。

“这位美女，”巴格里奥尼加重语气说，“从出生之日起就用毒药喂养，直到全身浸透毒素，致使她本人也成了世界上最为致命的毒药。毒素成了她生命的元素。她用呼吸中那浓郁的芳香将空气毒化。她的爱情也是毒药——她的拥抱就意味着死亡。这难道不是一个奇妙的故事吗？”

“不过是哄孩子的无稽之谈。”乔万尼答道，一面神经质地从椅子上跳了起来，“我很奇怪，阁下在严肃的研究工作之余怎么还有闲工夫读这种荒唐的东西。”

“顺便说说，”教授不安地打量着他，“你房间里有什么东西会发出这么奇异的香味？是你手套上洒的香水吗？香味很淡，但很芬芳；然而闻着却非常不舒服。假如闻得太久，我想可能会让我生病的。好像是花的香气，可是我看你房间里根本没有花啊。”

“事实上一朵也没有。”乔万尼回答道，他在教授说话时脸色变得苍白，“而且我认为，除了在阁下的想象之中也并不存在什么香气。气味是一类由感觉与精神结合而成的东西，常常以这种方式欺骗我们。由于对一种香气存在记忆，只要一想到它，就很容易误认为是眼前现实。”

“嗯，不过我清醒的想象力并不经常开这样的玩笑，”巴格里奥尼说，“况且，假如我要想象到什么气味的话，也应该是某种难闻的药剂的气味才对，而我的手指上很可能就沾有很浓的这种味儿。我听说，我们可敬的朋友拉帕西尼，就用比阿拉伯香料还浓的香气来熏制他的药剂。无可怀疑，美丽多才的贝阿特丽丝小姐治疗她的病人，也会使用像少女呼吸的气息一样甜美的药剂；可是喝下这些药剂的人就太不幸了！”

乔万尼的表情显示出他内心充满了情感冲突。教授用那种口吻提到拉帕西尼的纯洁可爱的女儿，对他的心简直是一种酷刑；然而教授对她性格的这种看法与他自己截然对立，又使上千个朦胧的疑点顿时变得清晰起来，现在正像许多妖魔向他狞笑着。不过他仍然竭力打消这些想法，以一个真正情人的忠诚不渝的态度来回答巴格里奥尼。

“教授先生，”他说，“您是我父亲的朋友；或许，您的目的也是要友善地对待他的儿子。我心中对您只有尊重与敬仰；不过我要请您注意，先生，有个话题我们是不应该谈论的。您并不认识贝阿特丽丝小姐。所以您对她的品德不能信口雌黄，妄加贬抑——我甚至可以说这是对她的恶意中伤。”

“乔万尼！我可怜的乔万尼！”教授回答道，镇静的表情中含着怜悯，“对这个可怜的姑娘，我的了解要比你深得多。我会让你知道关于施毒者拉帕西尼和他那有毒的女儿的真实面目；是的，正像她的美丽一样，她也含有毒性。听着，即使你对我这苍苍白发的老人悖逆不敬，也不能让我闭口不谈。那个关于印度女人的古老传说，已经借助拉帕西尼精深而致命的医学变成了现实，就体现在可爱的贝阿特丽丝小姐身上。”

乔万尼呻吟起来，用双手掩住面孔。

“她的父亲，”巴格里奥尼接着说，“全然不顾天伦之情，以这种可怕的方式来养育自己的孩子，使她成为自己对科学的疯狂热情的牺牲品。原因在于，让我们公正地说，他的确是位真正的科学家，连自己的心也像在蒸馏器里经过提纯一样。那么，你的命运又将如何呢？毫无疑问，你被选择出来作为某种新实验的材料了。结局也许是死亡，也许是一种比死亡还要可怕的命运。拉帕西尼的眼中只有他所谓的科学兴趣，干什么都不会有丝毫犹豫的。”

“这是一场梦，”乔万尼喃喃自语，“肯定是一场梦。”

“不过，”教授接着说，“振作起精神来，我老朋友的儿子。现在补救还不算太晚。说不定我们甚至还能让这个可怜的孩子恢复正常天性，脱离被她父亲的疯狂所引入的歧途而回归正道。看看这个小银瓶！它是赫赫有名的本韦努托·切利尼(7)亲手制作的，完全有资格作为一件爱情的赠礼，献给意大利最美丽的贵妇人。不过瓶子里盛的东西却更加珍贵。这种解毒剂只要呷上一小口就能使波吉亚家族(8)最剧烈的毒药失去作用。它对拉帕西尼的毒药无疑也会同样灵验。把这个瓶子连同里面珍贵的药剂一起献给你的贝阿特丽丝，然后满怀希望地静待结果吧。”

巴格里奥尼把一个精雕细琢的小银瓶放在桌上，接着就告辞了，让他的话在年轻人的头脑里去慢慢发生作用。

“我们会挫败拉帕西尼的，”教授这样想，他一面下楼一面暗笑，“可是我们也得承认，他是个了不起的家伙——的确了不起；然而就其医道而言却是个邪恶的骗子，因此医学界内崇尚古老法规的人们对他是不能容忍的。”

正如我们已经说过的，乔万尼在同贝阿特丽丝交往的整个过程中，对她品德的阴暗猜疑偶尔也会袭上心头；不过她给他的感觉总是那么单纯、自然、温情和坦诚，这使得巴格里奥尼教授所描述的形象显得不可思议和不足置信，似乎也不符合乔万尼本人最初的看法。的确，他心中还留有初次见到这个美丽姑娘时得到的丑恶回忆；他无法忘掉在她手中枯萎了的那个花束，在阳光灿烂的空气中死去的那个小虫子，除了她呼吸的气息之外再也找不出任何明显的原因导致这些现象。然而，这些偶发事件却消散在她的性格的纯净光辉中，不再具有事实的效应，而被仅仅认作是错误的幻觉，无论怎样凭感官来进行验证似乎都是如此。世间有些事物就是比我们亲眼所见、亲手所摸的东西还更为真切确实。乔万尼就是凭着这种更好的证据建立起了对贝阿特丽丝的信任，尽管这与其说是因为他本人的深厚信念，倒不如说是由于她的高贵品质发挥了必要的作用。不过现在他的精神已经无法保持在早期的激情所达到的高度了；他跌落下来，匍匐在尘世的疑虑中，从而使贝阿特丽丝纯洁无瑕的形象蒙受了污损。这并不是说他就放弃了她，但他的确是有了怀疑。他决定进行某种能够令他满意的决定性的实验，借此一劳永逸地弄清她身上是否有那些可怕的特性，而这些生理特性是不可能脱离灵魂的畸形而独立存在的。原来见到的那只蜥蜴、虫子和花束，因为当时他的目光是从远处往下看，也许存在错觉；假如他能在数步之遥目睹一朵新鲜而健全的花朵在贝阿特丽丝手里突然凋谢，那就再也没有任何疑问了。怀着这个想法，他匆匆赶到一家花店，买了一束带着晶莹朝露的鲜花。

现在正是每天惯常与贝阿特丽丝会面的时刻。乔万尼在下楼到花园去之前并没有忘记在镜子里照照自己——英俊小伙子不免都有这种虚荣心，不过在目前这苦恼焦躁的时刻还表现出这种心理，未免显出感情的浅薄和性格的虚假。他对镜凝视，心中暗自觉得他的容貌从来不曾像现在这样俊雅，眼神从来不曾这样活泼，脸颊也从来不曾如此红润而富于生气。

“至少，”他想，“她的毒素还没有渗透到我的机体里。我绝不是一朵毁灭在她手中的花。”

他这样想着，一面把目光投向片刻也不曾离手的那束鲜花上。一阵莫名的恐怖猛然袭遍了他的全身，他发现这些尚带露珠的花朵已经开始低低垂落，仿佛它们的鲜活与美丽已经属于昨日。乔万尼的脸色变得像大理石一样苍白，一动不动地站在镜子前面，紧紧瞪视着镜中自己的影像，就像看见了什么可怕的怪物。他想起巴格里奥尼说过房间里似乎弥漫着一种香气。那一定是自己呼吸中所含的毒素！接着他浑身战栗起来——为自己而战栗！当他从僵呆的状态中恢复过来时，好奇的目光开始注意到一只蜘蛛，它正忙着在房间的古老檐板上结网，在那个纵横交错的丝织艺术品上爬来爬去——与任何悬挂在旧天花板上的蜘蛛同样精力弥满，同样充满活力。乔万尼俯身朝向它，呼出了长长的一口气。蜘蛛顿时停止了它的劳作，蛛网也因那个小工匠身体的战抖而随之抖动起来。乔万尼又朝它呼出了一口气，这口气更深更长，充满了发自内心的恶毒感情：他不知道这到底是自己心怀邪恶呢，还是仅仅出于绝望。蜘蛛的肢体痉挛着紧抓在一起，接着就悬挂在窗前死了。

“该死！该死！”乔万尼喃喃地咒骂自己，“你已经有这么强的毒性，呼口气就能断送这只蜘蛛的命吗？”

就在这时，一阵圆润甜美的声音从花园里传了上来。

“乔万尼！乔万尼！时间已经过啦！怎么还在耽搁？快下来吧！”

“是的，”乔万尼又喃喃地说，“她也许是唯一不会被我的呼吸杀死的生物！但愿我也能做到！”

他冲下楼来，即刻就站到了贝阿特丽丝那明亮而深情的目光跟前。就在片刻之前，他的愤慨与绝望还那样强烈，但愿看她一眼就让她顿时生命枯萎；可是一旦她站在了面前，她的影响力却是那么真切实在，简直无法立即摆脱。他还记得她那女性特有的细腻而温和的天性，这种力量常常以一种宗教般的宁静包裹着他；他还记得她许多次迸发出源于内心的圣洁激情，就像清泉从封闭的深处涌出，使他的心灵感受到它的清澈透明。只要乔万尼懂得怎样去估价这些回忆，就会确信有关她的一切丑恶的神秘现象只不过是尘世的幻觉，无论什么邪恶的迷雾笼罩着她，真正的贝阿特丽丝其实是一位超凡的天使。尽管他不能获得这种高度的信念，但她的出现并没有完全丧失其魔力。乔万尼的怒火消退了，化为了一种阴郁的麻木状态。贝阿特丽丝具有一种敏锐的精神感觉力，立即发现他们之间横亘着一条双方都无法逾越的黑暗鸿沟。他们一起走着，悲伤地沉默着，就这样来到了大理石喷泉和它在地上聚成的水池边，水池中央长着那株盛开宝石般花朵的灌木。乔万尼发觉自己正急切地——可以说是如饥似渴地——吸着那些花的香气，不禁感到恐惧。

“贝阿特丽丝，”他突然问道，“这株灌木是从哪儿来的？”

“是我父亲创造的。”她回答说，显得很纯真。

“创造！创造！”乔万尼重复道，“这是什么意思，贝阿特丽丝？”

“他对大自然的奥秘具有惊人的洞悉力。”贝阿特丽丝回答，“就在我来到人世做第一次呼吸的时候，这株树也正好破土而出，它是他的科学之子、智慧之子，而我只是他的尘世的孩子。别靠近它！”她惊骇地发现乔万尼正朝那株灌木越走越近，便叫起来。“它具有你做梦也想不到的一些特性。可是我，亲爱的乔万尼——我跟这棵树一道成长，一道跨入青春花季，被它的芳香所滋养。它是我的姐妹，我以人类的感情爱着它；因为，啊！——你就不曾怀疑过吗？——其中存在着一种可怕的定命。”

这时，乔万尼阴沉地紧锁双眉望着她，使得贝阿特丽丝住了口并战栗起来。但是她信任他的体贴温柔，所以又安下心来，并因自己对他有片刻的怀疑而脸红了。

“一种可怕的定命，”她继续说下去，“由于我父亲对科学那种要命的挚爱，使我完全隔绝了与人类社会的交往，直到上天把你送来，亲爱的乔万尼。啊，你可怜的贝阿特丽丝是多么寂寞啊！”

“这是一种严酷的命运吧？”乔万尼问，目光紧盯着她。

“直到最近我才知道它是多么严酷。”她柔声答道，“啊，真是这样。不过以前我的心麻木了，所以才感到宁静。”

乔万尼的阴郁情绪中突然爆发出一团怒火，就像乌云中猛然闪现出一道电光。“该死的家伙！”他叫道，满怀恶毒的轻蔑与愤慨，“你觉得自己孤单无聊，就要同样割断我与生活的一切温暖的联系，把我哄骗进你那无可言喻的恐怖世界里去吗！”

“乔万尼！”贝阿特丽丝高声喊道，转过她那双明亮的大眼睛来盯着他的脸。他这番话的真正力量还没有对她的头脑发生影响，她仅仅是感到惊骇。

“是的，你这有毒的东西！”乔万尼重复道，他已激动得不能自持了，“你已经这样干了！你已经毁了我！你已经让我的血管里充满了毒汁！你已经把我变成了跟你一样可恨、一样丑恶、一样恶心和可怕的东西——一个举世罕见的骇人听闻的恶魔！好吧，要是我们的气息对彼此来说，有幸也像对其他所有人一样致命，那就让我们怀着说不出的仇恨接个吻，一同死去吧！”

“什么灾难降临到了我的头上？”贝阿特丽丝喃喃自语道，从心底发出一声低微的呻吟，“圣母呵，可怜我这个心碎的孩子吧！”

“你——你也会祈祷？”乔万尼叫道，仍然满怀恶毒的轻蔑，“就连你的祈祷，因为发自你的唇间，也会以死亡玷污空气。是的，是的，让我们祈祷吧！让我们到教堂去，把手指浸入门前的圣水中！跟在我们后面的人就会像患瘟疫一样死去！让我们在空中画十字吧！它将以神圣象征的面目把诅咒散布四方！”

“乔万尼！”贝阿特丽丝平静地说，因为她的悲痛已经超过了激愤，“你为什么要用这些可怕的话来把你和我连在一起？我，的确就是你所说的那种可恶的东西。可是你——除了对我丑恶的不幸再发一次抖，然后走出花园去加入你的同类，忘掉大地上曾经爬行过一个像可怜的贝阿特丽丝这样的妖魔之外，还有什么别的可做呢？”

“你还想装作一无所知吗？”乔万尼满面怒容地瞪着她，“看吧！这种力量就是我从拉帕西尼的纯洁的女儿身上获得的！”

这时正好有一群夏虫在空中疾飞，因为嗅到这座致命花园的花香而前来觅食。它们绕着乔万尼的头顶兜圈子，而吸引它们的力量显然与刚才它们飞去的几株树木是相同的。他朝着那些虫子吐出了一口气，当至少有十几个虫子坠地而死时，他朝贝阿特丽丝苦涩地笑了笑。

“我明白了！我明白了！”贝阿特丽丝尖叫道，“这是我父亲那致命的科学造成的！不，不，乔万尼，不是我！绝不是，绝不是！我只梦想过爱你，和你短暂地相处一阵，然后让你离开，只把你的形象留在我心中。乔万尼，相信我的话，尽管我的身体是用毒药培育的，我的灵魂却是上帝的创造物，时刻渴望得到爱的滋养。可是我的父亲——他竟利用这种可怕的共同感情把我们联系起来。好吧，你唾弃我吧，践踏我吧，杀死我吧！啊，听你讲了那番话后，死还算得了什么呢？不过这不是我干的。哪怕给我全世界的幸福，我也不会做这种事！”

乔万尼的激怒在那一番话语爆发中已耗竭殆尽。现在他心中泛起了一种哀伤之情，一想到贝阿特丽丝与他的亲密而特殊的关系，还生出了几许柔情。他们站在那儿，处于绝对孤独之中，即使置身在最拥挤的人群里，这种孤独也绝不会减少半分。那么，既然被周围的人们所抛弃，难道不应该使这与世隔绝的一对年轻人更加亲密吗？要是他们还彼此残酷折磨，又有谁会以仁慈对待他们呢？况且，乔万尼想道，难道自己就没有希望恢复正常天性，并与获救的贝阿特丽丝携手同行吗？啊，你这虚弱、自私、卑劣的灵魂！在乔万尼用如此狠毒的言辞剧烈地伤害了像贝阿特丽丝的爱这样深沉的爱情之后，竟然还在梦想可能获得尘世姻缘与人间幸福！不，不，绝不可能存在这种希望了。她不得不带着那颗破碎的心，沉重地跨过时光的边界——她不得不到天堂的清泉边去洗浴自己的创伤，在永恒的光辉中忘却自己的哀痛，并在那里得到康复。

然而乔万尼并不明白这一点。

“亲爱的贝阿特丽丝。”他说，并朝她走去；她也像通常他走近时那样往后退缩，但这次是出于一种不同的冲动。“亲爱的贝阿特丽丝，我们的命运并非绝无希望。看！这儿有一种烈性药剂，一位明智博学的医生向我保证说它具有神奇的疗效。构成它的成分，与你那可怕的父亲给你和我造成灾难的东西截然相反。它是从赐福于人的药草中提炼出来的。让我们一起喝下它，从邪恶中获得净化好吗？”

“给我！”贝阿特丽丝说，一面伸手接过乔万尼从怀中取出的那个小银瓶。她还特别加重语气补充了一句：“我愿意喝，不过你一定要等待着结果。”

她把巴格里奥尼的解毒剂举向唇边。就在这时候，拉帕西尼的身影出现在拱门下，并缓步朝大理石喷泉走来。他渐渐地走近；这位面色苍白的科学家满脸扬扬自得之情，观看着那一对美丽的年轻人，犹如一位艺术家耗尽毕生精力完成了一幅画像或者一组雕塑，对自己的最后成功踌躇满志一样。他停下脚步；伛偻的身躯有意识地挺得笔直；他把双手朝他们伸出来，那姿势就像一位父亲在恳求孩子们向他祝福似的；然而正是这同一双手把毒药投进了他们生命的溪流中。乔万尼浑身战栗。贝阿特丽丝紧张得发抖，用一只手紧紧按住胸口。

“我的女儿，”拉帕西尼说，“你在世上不再孤独了。从你的姐妹树上摘下一朵珍宝之花，请你的新郎戴在他胸前吧。现在它不会伤害他了。我的科学和你与他之间的共同感情业已深深作用于他的机体，现在他已经和普通男人迥然不同了，正像你，我引以为骄傲和荣耀的女儿，与普通女人不同一样。今后你们一起在世界上生活，彼此相亲相爱，而所有人都会惧怕你们！”

“我的父亲，”贝阿特丽丝用虚弱的声音说道——她一边说一边仍然按住胸口——“你为什么要把这种悲惨的命运强加在你孩子身上？”

“悲惨！”拉帕西尼叫道，“你这是什么意思，傻姑娘？具有这种神奇的禀赋，没有任何力量能够与之匹敌，你能说这是悲惨吗？呼出一口气就能打败最强大的敌人，这是悲惨吗？你有多么美丽，就有多么可怕，这是悲惨吗？难道你宁愿处于弱女人的境地，面临各种邪恶而自己却不能拿起邪恶的武器？”

“我宁愿被人爱而不愿让人怕。”贝阿特丽丝喃喃地说，慢慢倒伏在地上，“不过现在没什么关系了。我要死了，父亲，您竭尽全力向我的生命中混杂进的邪恶也像梦幻一样地消逝了——就像这些毒花的香气一样，在伊甸园的花丛中，它们再也不能污染我的呼吸。别了，乔万尼！你那些仇恨的话语就像铅一般沉重地压在我心头，不过在我飞升之时它们将会坠落的。啊，从一开始，你的天性中是不是就比我的天性中含有更多的毒素呢？”

对于贝阿特丽丝而言——她的身体已经被拉帕西尼的技艺施行了如此彻底的改造——毒药就是生命，所以烈性解毒药就意味着死亡。就这样，这个人类独创性与扭曲天性的可怜的牺牲品，这个承受了堕落智慧一切尝试的灾难命运的无辜者，就死在了她父亲和乔万尼的脚下。就在这个时候，巴格里奥尼教授正从楼上的窗户往下看，他用一种胜利中混杂着恐惧的声音大声呼唤，朝着那位如遭雷击的科学家叫道——“拉帕西尼！拉帕西尼！这是不是你想要的实验结果？”

————————————————————

(1) 帕多瓦（Padua）：意大利东北部城市。

(2) 但丁在《神曲》的《地狱篇》18歌里曾写到一个不知其名的帕多瓦贵族。

(3) 那不勒斯（Naples）：意大利海港城市，度假胜地。

(4) 威耳廷努斯（Vertumnus）：罗马神话中的四季之神和花果之神。

(5) 据《圣经·创世记》，人类的始祖亚当与夏娃原来生活在伊甸园中，后因堕落而被上帝贬下人间。

(6) 意大利中西部托斯卡纳（Tuscana）地方所产的著名葡萄酒。

(7) 本韦努托·切利尼（Benvenuto Cellini，1500—1571）：意大利著名金匠和雕刻家。

(8) 波吉亚（Borgia）家族是意大利文艺复兴时期一个以下毒、谋杀、通奸、乱伦等恶行而臭名昭著的家族。

牧师的黑面纱
——一则寓言(1)

教堂司事站在米尔福礼拜堂的门廊里，使劲地拉着钟绳。村里的老人们弯腰驼背地沿着街道走来。孩子们满面笑颜，蹦跳着跟在父母身边，或者模仿出庄重的步伐，留意要显示出礼拜日盛装的派头。衣冠楚楚的单身小伙子们斜眼偷看着漂亮姑娘，觉得安息日的阳光使她们显得比平日更加漂亮。当人群大都拥进门廊之后，司事开始打钟，同时紧盯着胡珀牧师的房门。牧师一露面，也就意味着该停止召唤的钟声了。

“胡珀牧师在脸上弄了个什么东西啊？”司事惊讶地叫起来。

所有听见的人都立刻转过身来，看见一个身形酷似胡珀先生的人，正若有所思地缓缓迈步朝礼拜堂走来。人们全都惊呆了，即使是一位陌生的牧师来占据了胡珀先生布道坛上的座位，他们也不会表示出比现在更大的惊异。

“你敢肯定那就是我们的牧师吗？”古德曼·格雷问司事。

“那当然是胡珀先生啦，”司事回答说，“今天他本该跟韦斯特伯里的舒特牧师对换讲道的；但舒特牧师昨天捎信说不来了，他要去做一场葬礼祈祷。”

造成这一番惊诧的原因，似乎完全不足为怪。胡珀牧师年纪大约三十，很有绅士风度，虽然仍是单身，但衣着却不失牧师应有的整洁，好像有一位细心的妻子为他浆洗过领箍，刷净了礼拜日法衣上一周来沾染的灰尘。他的外表只有一件东西引人注目，那就是箍在前额上、垂下来遮住脸庞的一张黑面纱，一直低垂得随他的呼吸而微微颤动。更近些看，面纱似乎是用两层绉绸做成的，除了嘴和下巴，整个面部都被遮掩起来了，不过或许并没有挡住他的视线，只是给眼前一切有生命和无生命的东西蒙上了一层黑影而已。虔诚的胡珀先生眼前就带着这片黑影，迈着缓慢而沉静的步子走来，像心不在焉的人通常那样微微佝偻身躯，两眼望着地面，但对候立在礼拜堂台阶上的教民们仍然和蔼地点头致意。不过他们都惊呆了，以至于忘了还礼。

“我真不敢相信那块绢纱后面就是胡珀先生的脸。”司事说。

“我不喜欢它。”一个老妪蹒跚地走进礼拜堂，喃喃自语道，“他把脸一藏起来，就变成一个吓人的怪物了。”

“我们的牧师疯啦！”古德曼·格雷一边说，一边跟在他身后跨过了门槛。

胡珀牧师还没进礼拜堂，这件不可思议的怪事就传开了，教友们全都骚动起来。谁都忍不住扭头朝门口张望；许多人站了起来，索性转过身子；有几个小男孩爬到椅背上又摔下来，引发了一阵喧闹。礼拜堂里一片乱哄哄，女人的衣裙沙沙作响，男人的脚步在地面擦动，和恭候牧师莅临时应有的肃静迥然不同。然而胡珀牧师似乎对教民们的骚乱不安视而不见。他几乎是悄无声息地走了进来，对两旁一排排座位上的会众微微颔首，在走过最年长的教民身边时还鞠了一躬，那是位满头白发的老人，坐在通道中间的一把扶手椅上。奇怪的是，这位年高德劭的老人迟迟没有觉察到牧师的外表有什么异常。他好像并没怎么感受到充满教堂的惊诧情绪，直到胡珀先生登上了阶梯，站在了布道坛上，隔着那块黑面纱与听众们面对面时，这才有所察觉。牧师戴着的那个神秘的标志一刻也没有摘下过。在他领唱圣诗时，它随着他均匀的呼吸而起伏；他朗读《圣经》时，它就在他和圣书之间投下阴影。他祈祷时，它就沉甸甸地紧贴在他仰起的脸上。难道他要向自己所祈祷的可畏的上帝隐藏自己的面孔吗？

这小小一块黑纱的影响是如此巨大，不止一个神经脆弱的女人因此而被迫离开了教堂。然而，面色苍白的会众在牧师眼里，或许就像他的黑面纱在他们眼里同样的可怕呢。

胡珀先生因善于布道而享有盛誉，但他并不以雄辩有力取胜，而是尽量通过温和的劝导作用来引得教民们心向天国，并非借助雷霆震撼般的圣言来驱使人们前进。他此时的布道，也具有其通常的风格和方式上的特点。可是，或许是因为布道词中所带的情绪，或许是由于听众的想象，总之，他今天的言辞中蕴含着某种东西，使得大家感到这是他们所听过的牧师布道中最倾力动情的一次。它比平日的布道更带有胡珀先生气质中固有的那种轻柔的忧郁色调。他演讲的主题涉及隐秘的罪孽，那些我们对最亲近的人和对自己的良知都想要隐藏的伤心隐秘，甚至忘记了全知全能的上帝是会洞察一切的。他的言辞中渗入了一种难以捉摸的力量。听众中的每一个人，无论是最纯洁的少女还是心如铁石的恶棍，都觉得躲在可怕面纱后面的牧师似乎已偷偷逼近，探知到了他们的思想与行为中隐藏着的罪恶。许多人把自己交叉的双手按在胸膛上。胡珀先生所讲的话并不可怕，至少并不激烈；然而，他那忧郁声调的每一个颤音都令听众浑身战栗。伴随着恐惧而来的，是一种不期而至的悲怆。听众们强烈感受到牧师有些反常，都盼望有一股轻风能把那块面纱吹开，而且几乎相信露出来的会是一张陌生的面孔，虽然那身形、姿态、声音是属于胡珀先生的。

礼拜刚结束，教友们便毫无规矩地乱成一团，争先恐后地往外跑，急切地要相互交流压抑在心头的惊异；而一旦眼前没有了那块黑面纱，他们也感到心情轻松了许多。有些人围成一个个小圈子，紧紧挤作一团窃窃私语；有些人独自往家里走，一路上默默沉思；有些人高声谈论着，故意放声大笑来亵渎安息日。有那么几个人自作聪明地摇着头，暗示说他们能看穿这个秘密；而有一两个人则断言这事根本没有任何奥秘，只不过是胡珀先生的视力在深夜受到了灯光的损害，因此需要遮一遮。稍过片刻之后，胡珀牧师也跟在教民身后走出来了。他把蒙着面纱的脸从这一群人转向那一群人，向白发长者表示应有的敬意，又以和蔼的庄重态度对中年人致意，犹如他们的朋友和精神导师；他也带着爱护与威严招呼那些年轻人，并把手放到孩子们头上，为他们祝福。这些都是他在安息日的老习惯了。然而今天回报他的好意的，却只是惊异和困惑的目光。没有一个人像往常那样，渴望得到与牧师同行的荣耀。老乡绅桑德斯无疑是因为记忆力偶然出错，忘了邀请胡珀先生去他家进餐，而自从牧师到这里就职以来，几乎每个礼拜天总是要到他家的饭桌上祝福的。这样，他只好回到自己的牧师寓所，就在他关门的时候，回头望了望背后的人们，大家的目光全都紧盯着他。黑面纱后面隐隐露出了一丝忧伤的笑容，闪烁在他的嘴角，随即就同他一起消失了。

“真奇怪，”一个妇女说，“一块普通的黑面纱，就跟女人们系在帽子上的一模一样，可在胡珀先生的脸上竟会变得这么可怕！”

“胡珀先生的脑子肯定出了毛病，”她的丈夫、村子里的医生说，“不过这件事顶奇怪的地方就在他这古怪行为所产生的力量，就连我这样头脑清醒的人都受到了震动。那块黑纱尽管只遮住了牧师的脸，却影响到了他整个的人，使他从头到脚都现出鬼气。你难道不觉得吗？”

“我真的感觉到了，”那个女人答道，“我怎么也不敢单独跟他待在一起。我真纳闷，他自己是不是也怕自己！”

“人有时候是会自己怕自己的。”她丈夫说。

下午举行礼拜式的情况同上午相似。结束的时候，为一位年轻姑娘的葬礼敲响了丧钟。亲戚和朋友都聚集在丧家的屋子里，关系比较疏远的熟人站在门边，谈论着死者的种种好处。他们的谈话突然被胡珀牧师的到来打断，他仍旧戴着那块黑面纱，现在它倒是一种恰当的标志了。牧师走进停放遗体的房间，朝棺材俯下身子，向自己已故的教民做最后的告别。在他弯腰的时候，面纱从他的额头上直垂下来，假如死去的姑娘的眼睛并不是永远地合上了，她就会看见他的面孔。莫非胡珀牧师害怕她的目光，才这样匆忙地把面纱往后拉好？有个人目睹了这场生者与死者的会面，他毫不迟疑地证实说，就在牧师露出面容的一刹那，尸体曾微微地战栗起来，尸衣和薄纱女帽都沙沙作响，虽然姑娘的面容依然保持着死者的宁静。一个迷信的老太太是这一奇迹的唯一见证人。胡珀牧师离开棺木进入哀悼室，然后又走到楼梯口，开始做葬礼祈祷。那是一篇饱含温情、感人肺腑的祷文，充满哀痛，但又深深浸润着天国的希望，在牧师悲怆至极的音调之间，仿佛能依稀听见姑娘的纤指在轻柔地拨动着天堂的琴弦。牧师祈祷说，但愿人们和他自己以及世间众生，都能像这位姑娘一样从容地迎接撕去面纱的可怕时刻，这时大家都不寒而栗，尽管他们并不完全理解这话的意义。抬棺材的人沉重地迈步前行，后面跟着送葬的队列；死者在他们前面，胡珀牧师戴着面纱走在后头，整个街道都充满了哀伤。

“你怎么朝后看啊？”送葬队伍中有个人问他的同伴。

“我好像觉得，”她回答说，“刚才牧师和这姑娘的鬼魂手拉手地一块儿走着哩。”

“我也觉得是这样，也是在刚才那会儿。”另一位说。

当夜，米尔福村里最漂亮的一对男女要举行婚礼。虽然人们认为胡珀牧师是个性情忧郁的人，但他在这种场合也会具有一种平静的愉悦，它常常比活泼欢闹更能激起亲和的微笑。再没有什么比他的性格中的这一特点更能赢得教民们的爱戴了。婚礼上的众宾客都急切地等待着他的光临，都深信一整天笼罩着他的那种奇异的可畏神情现在一定烟消云散了。然而结果并非如此。胡珀牧师进门的时候，人们第一眼看到的仍然是那块可怕的黑面纱，它曾经给葬礼增添了更深的哀愁，但给婚礼带来的却只能是凶兆。它立刻使宾客们感到仿佛有一团乌云从面纱下面黑黢黢地涌出，掩蔽了花烛的光亮。一对新人在牧师面前站起来。可是新娘冰凉的手指在新郎抖动的手里战栗着，她那像死一般苍白的脸色引起了一阵窃窃私语，说是几个钟头前刚下葬的那个姑娘钻出坟墓来入洞房啦。如果说世上还有像这么阴惨的婚礼，也就只能是著名的在婚礼上敲响丧钟的那一次了。(2)仪式主持完毕，胡珀牧师举起酒杯，祝新婚夫妇幸福，他的语调温和而幽默，本该像炉中欢跳的火光，映照得宾客们容光焕发。但就在这一瞬间，他从镜子里看见了自己的形象，那块黑面纱便把他自己的心灵也卷进了淹没众人的恐惧之中。他浑身发抖——嘴唇发白——他把尚未沾唇的酒洒泼在了地毯上——接着他就冲进了茫茫黑夜里。因为，大地也戴着自己的黑面纱。

第二天，整个米尔福村只议论着一件事，那就是胡珀牧师的黑面纱。那块面纱和它后面所隐藏的秘密，成为相熟的人们街谈巷议的话题，也为女人们打开窗户说闲言碎语提供了材料。它成了小酒店老板向顾客发布的头条新闻。孩子们在上学的路上也叽叽喳喳地说着它。一个喜欢模仿的小调皮用一块旧黑手巾把自己的脸遮起来，这一来不但把同伴们吓得要死，连他本人也被自己的恶作剧吓得几乎神志错乱。

奇怪的是，教区里所有那些爱管闲事和行事莽撞之徒，没有一个敢直截了当地问胡珀牧师他为什么要这样做。在此之前，只要他看起来有点芝麻大的小事需要人过问，从来就不缺出主意的人，而且他自己也总是愿意听从别人的意见。如果说他有什么过错的话，那就是太缺乏自信，即使是最温和的指责也会使他把自己无关紧要的行为看得像桩罪过。然而，尽管教民们都深知他这种性格随和的弱点，却没有一个人愿意就黑面纱这个问题对他进行友好的规劝。大家有种既不挑明也不细心遮掩的恐惧感，使得人人都在互相推诿责任。最后只好想出一条权宜之计，选派一批教会代表去同胡珀牧师商谈，以免这件怪事最后酿成丑闻。从来没有一个使团会这么糟糕地履行自己的职责。牧师友好而礼貌地接待了他们，但等到客人落座之后他便一言不发，把挑明这项重大事务的重担整个地留给来客们去承担。话题本身是显而易见的，大家都心中有数。那块黑面纱就箍在胡珀牧师的额头上，掩盖着他的脸，下面只露出安详的嘴唇，大家可以察觉到嘴角边时而闪过一丝忧伤的微笑。然而在他们的想象中，那块黑纱却似乎一直垂挂到他的胸前，成为一桩可怕秘密的象征横亘在他与他们之间。只要把那块面纱拉开，他们就可以无拘无束地谈论它，但不拉开它简直就无法启齿。他们就这样坐了很久，缄口无言，心烦意乱，不安地躲避着胡珀牧师的目光，觉得那道看不见的目光一直紧盯在他们身上。最后，代表们只得羞愧地回去见他们的推举人，宣称这起重大事件处理起来太棘手，即使不需召开教民大会，至少也得举行教会会议才行。

这块黑面纱弄得村里所有的人都胆战心惊，但有一个女人却并不害怕。代表们没有从牧师那里得到任何解释，甚至连问题也不敢问一个，她却以自己性格中的沉静的力量，决心要驱散那片愈益浓黑地聚集在牧师头上的诡奇阴云。作为他的未婚妻，她有权知道黑面纱之下所掩藏的是什么。因此，在牧师事后第一次来看她的时候，她就简单直接地一下子进入话题，这倒使事情对他和她来说都容易得多了。牧师坐下之后，她就目不转睛地盯着那块面纱，但并没有发现那种威慑住众人的恐怖阴霾：它只不过是一块双层绢纱罢了，从他的额上垂到嘴边，随着他的呼吸而微微颤动。

“不，”她一边笑一边高声说，“这块纱没什么好怕的，只不过遮住了我老是喜欢看的一张脸罢了。来吧，我的好人，让阳光从乌云后面显露出来吧。先把面纱摘下来，再告诉我你为什么要戴着它。”

胡珀牧师脸上微微闪烁过一丝笑容。

“到了某个时辰，”他说，“我们都得摘下自己的面纱。而在那个时辰之前，如果我一直戴着它的话，亲爱的朋友，请你不要见怪。”

“你的话也这么神秘莫测。”姑娘回答道，“至少该把罩在你的话语上面的纱摘掉吧。”

“伊丽莎白，我愿意这么做，”他说，“只要我的誓言允许。你要知道，这块面纱是一个表记和标志，我受誓言的约束，必须永远佩戴，不论是在光明还是黑暗之中，不论是独自一人还是在众目睽睽之下，也不论是与陌生人交往还是与亲朋好友相处。世上绝没有任何人能看见它被摘下。这道阴郁的帘幕必定将我与尘世隔绝：就连你，伊丽莎白，也永远看不到它的后面！”

“什么深重的苦难降临到了你的头上，”她热切地问道，“使你要这样永远遮暗自己的眼睛？”

“如果说它是一种哀悼的象征，”胡珀牧师回答说，“那么或许我也跟大多数世人一样，怀着如此阴郁的哀伤，需要用一块黑面纱来做表记。”

“可是假如世人不相信它只是清白无邪的哀伤的表记呢？”伊丽莎白极力劝说道，“尽管你受到人们的爱戴和尊重，但也难免有流言蜚语，说你是因为自知犯了隐秘的罪恶才掩盖住自己的面目。为你的圣职着想，驱散这种谣言吧。”

她向他暗示村子里已经流传开来的那些谣言的性质，不禁脸都涨红了。可是胡珀牧师仍然保持着他温和的神情。他甚至又笑了笑——还是那种哀伤的微笑，它总是像一道若有若无的微光，从面纱的暗影下闪现出来。

“如果我是因为悲痛而遮住面孔，自然有充足的理由，”他只是这样回答，“如果我遮住面孔是因为有不可告人的罪过，那么世人谁不可以这样做呢？”

他就这样温和而又不可动摇地拒绝了她的一切恳求。最后伊丽莎白沉默了。她有一阵子似乎陷入了沉思，或许在考虑还有什么新方法可以试一试，把她的情人从如此阴郁的妄想中拉出来；这件事即使没有其他含义，也很可能是神志错乱的征象啊。尽管她的性格比他更坚强，禁不住泪珠也从脸颊上滚落下来了。可是，在一刹那间，仿佛有一种新的感觉取代了悲伤：在她的目光茫然地盯住那块黑面纱的时候，就好像空中突然浮现出一片暗影，黑面纱带来的恐惧包裹住了她。她站起来，在他面前战栗着。

“看来你终于也感觉到了？”他哀伤地说。

她不回答，用手掩住双眼，转身要离开房间。他冲上前去一把抓住她的手臂。

“对我容忍些，伊丽莎白！”他激动地喊道，“别抛下我，尽管这块面纱今生今世必定要阻隔在我们之间。做我的妻子吧，来世我脸上再不会蒙上面纱了，也不会有黑暗阻隔开我们的灵魂了！这不过是现世的面纱——不是永恒的！啊！你不知道我独自待在黑面纱后面是多么孤独，多么害怕！别把我永远留在这悲惨的黑暗中！”

“那就把面纱揭开一次，面对面看我一眼。”她说。

“不！绝对不行！”胡珀牧师回答。

“那么，别了！”伊丽莎白说。

她抽出自己的手臂，慢慢地走开，到门边停了一下，向他投去久久的、战栗的凝视，似乎要刺穿黑面纱的秘密。而胡珀牧师尽管沉浸在悲痛中，却仍然在微笑，他心想仅仅是一种物质的标记便把他与幸福拆开了，然而它所投下的恐怖阴影才注定会使最相爱的情侣心灵阻隔。

从那时起，再没有人试图让胡珀牧师摘掉黑面纱，也不再径直要求探知面纱背后所掩藏的秘密。有些人自认为见识比常人偏见更高明，把这件事仅仅视为一种怪癖，而这种怪癖通常会与本来很正常的人的理智行为混合在一起，从而使他们的所有行为都带上疯癫的色彩。但在大多数人眼中，胡珀牧师却是个无可救药的怪物。他无法心平气和地在街道上走，总发现温良胆小的人们转身躲避他，而另一些人则故意挡住他的路来显示自己胆子大。后者的粗鲁无礼迫使他放弃了日落时分到墓地散步的老习惯，因为每当他靠在墓地门上沉思的时候，墓碑后面就会有人探头探脑地偷窥他的黑面纱。有一种谣言四处流传，说是死人的凝望把他引到那儿去的。使他仁慈的心被深深刺痛的是，看到孩子们在他走来的时候立即中断最欢乐的游戏，四散奔逃，其实他那忧郁的身影还离得很远。他们本能的恐惧比其他任何事都使他更强烈地感到，有一种异乎寻常的恐怖与黑面纱的丝缕紧紧交织在了一起。事实上，大家都知道他本人对黑面纱也深为厌恶，若非不得已，他绝对不从镜子前经过，也绝不俯身去饮静止的泉水，以免在它宁静的怀抱中看到自己的形象而受到惊吓。正是这一点引起了许多貌似有理的谣言，说是胡珀牧师的良心承受着某种巨大罪孽的煎熬，这可怕的罪孽既然不能全盘掩盖，便只好这样朦胧地加以暗示。于是，从黑面纱下面便有一团乌云涌向阳光，这是一种含糊不清的罪孽或哀伤，紧紧地裹住了可怜的牧师，使得爱与同情永远也到不了他身边。据说鬼魂和魔鬼在黑纱后面与他做伴。他就这样无休止地走在黑面纱的阴影中，内心战战兢兢，外表充满恐惧，在自己灵魂的黑暗中摸索着，或者透过那块面纱凝望着被它弄得暗淡惨伤的世界。人们相信，甚至肆无忌惮的风也尊重牧师那可怕的秘密，从来不把那块面纱吹起。不过，仁慈的胡珀牧师在走过熙来攘往的人群时，仍然要向着世人苍白的面孔哀伤地微笑。

黑面纱尽管产生了这些恶劣影响，却也有一种称心合意的效果，那就是使得佩戴它的人成了一位非常胜任的牧师。借助于自己的这一神秘表记——因为除此之外看不出还有什么明显的原因——他对于因罪孽而痛苦的灵魂便具有令人敬畏的力量。受他感召而皈依正道的人心中对他怀有特殊的畏惧，他们断言，虽然是以比喻的方式，说在被他引入天国的光明之前，他们曾同他一道陷没在那块黑面纱后面。的确，黑纱的阴影使得他能与一切阴郁的感情发生感应。垂死的罪人大声呼喊胡珀牧师，在他到场之前不肯咽气，尽管在他俯身对他们悄声抚慰的时候，他们会因为蒙着黑纱的面孔靠得那么近而浑身战栗。黑面纱的威力是这么可怕，甚至当死神露面时也是如此！陌生人从远处赶到他的教堂来聆听他布道，只不过是出于消遣的目的想要看看他的身影，因为他的脸是看不到的。可是许多人还等不到离开就已吓得战战兢兢！有一次，在贝尔切总督的任期内，胡珀牧师被指定为选举进行布道。他面戴黑纱站在首席行政官、地方自治会和代表们面前，给大家留下了那么深的印象，以致那一年通过的法案也带有最早期宗法统治的阴郁与虔诚。

就这样，胡珀牧师度过了漫长的一生，他行为固然无可指责，却被包裹在阴暗的猜疑之中；他和蔼而慈爱，却不为人所爱，而且为人所莫名畏惧；他与世人隔绝，被排除在众人的健康与快乐之外，却又总在人们临终痛苦之时被召去帮助他们。岁月流逝，在他那罩着黑面纱的额头上洒满了霜雪，他也在新英格兰一带的教会中获得了盛名，大家都叫他胡珀教长。在他到任时已届成年的那代教民如今差不多都已相继辞世，他在礼拜堂里有一批教民，更多的则挤在墓地里。他终于进入了生命的迟暮，在一生恪守职责之后，胡珀教长现在也该安息了。

在老教长临终的病榻前，借着惨淡的烛光，依稀可见几个人影。他没有任何亲属。但到场的有那位庄重合度却不动声色的医生，他只能尽力减轻无可救治的病人的最后痛苦。几位教堂执事和教区其他几位以虔诚著称的教友也在场。在场的还有韦斯特伯里教区的克拉克牧师，这是一位热心肠的年轻牧师，他骑马赶到垂危的教长床前来为他祈祷。还有那位看护，她绝不是一个受雇来照料垂危病人的女仆，她那宁静的感情经历了漫长的时日，忍受了沉默、孤独和岁月的严寒而始终不渝，直至这生离死别的一刻。她正是伊丽莎白！胡珀教长那白发苍苍的头靠在死亡之枕上，黑面纱依旧箍在他的额头上，把整个面庞遮住，随着他愈益艰难的每一次微弱呼吸而微微颤动。在他一生中，这块黑纱始终横隔在他与人世之间，隔绝了欢悦的友情和女性的爱恋，把他禁锢在最悲惨的牢狱之中，也就是他自己的心中。现在它仍然蒙在他的脸上，仿佛使得这阴暗的房间愈加阴郁，并且挡住了他面前的永生的阳光。

此前一段时间里，他已经神志不清了，灵魂疑虑重重地徘徊于过去和现在之间，时不时地仿佛跨进了未来世界的混沌之中。他反复地发着高烧，辗转反侧，所剩无几的精力已耗竭殆尽。但即使在最剧烈的痉挛挣扎和最荒诞的迷思狂想之中，当任何别的念头都已混乱不清时，他仍然显得提心吊胆，生怕黑面纱会滑落开去。其实，即使他迷乱的灵魂有可能忘记这一点，在他枕边还有一位忠实的女人，她会移开目光，为他遮好那张衰老的面孔，而当她最后一次见到这张面孔时它还是成年男子的俊秀容颜。最后，濒临死亡的老人静静地躺着，因精神与肉体的衰竭而陷于麻木之中，脉搏已经感觉不到了，气息也越来越微弱，只有一阵深长而不规律的呼吸，似乎在预报他的灵魂即将逃逸。

韦斯特伯里教区的牧师走到了床边。

“尊敬的胡珀教长，”他说，“您解脱的时刻即将到来。您是否准备揭开这块隔绝现时与永生的面纱呢？”

胡珀教长起初只是把手微微动了动来表示回答；接着，或许是担心他的意思可能不够明确，又竭尽余力开口说话。

“是的，”他用衰弱的声音说道，“我的灵魂忍辱负重、疲惫不堪，要等到揭开面纱后才能解脱啊。”

“难道说，”克拉克牧师接着说，“像你这样一个终生虔诚祈祷、按凡人的尺度堪称思想行为圣洁和毫无瑕疵的典范，戴着黑面纱是合适的吗？难道说一位教会长老能给人们对自己的回忆留下一道阴影，从而玷污如此纯洁的生命吗？我请求你，可敬的兄长，不要让这样的事情发生！在您获得永生的回报之前，请让我们有幸一睹你欢悦的容颜吧。在揭开来世的帏幔之前，请让我先揭去你脸上的这块黑面纱吧！”

说着，克拉克牧师俯身向前，要去揭示这个深藏多年的秘密。然而，胡珀牧师突然迸发出惊人的力量，让周围的人都吓得目瞪口呆。他猛地从被盖下面伸出双手，用力按住黑面纱，决心硬拼到底，假如韦斯特伯里的牧师真要跟一个垂死的人争斗的话。

“绝不！”戴面纱的教长喊道，“今生今世绝不！”

“愚昧的老人！”吓坏了的牧师叫道，“你的灵魂正带着多么可怕的罪孽去接受最后审判啊？”

胡珀教长艰难地呼吸着；一丝气息在喉咙里咯咯作响；可是他仍在奋力挣扎，伸出双手乱抓，想要抓住正在消逝的生命，好把话讲完。他甚至从床上撑起身子；他坐了起来，在死神的怀抱中瑟瑟战抖，而那块黑面纱则低垂着，在这最后的时刻把整整一生的恐怖都凝聚起来，显得极其可怕。他脸上常常浮现的那种细微而忧伤的笑容，此刻仿佛又从黑面纱的暗影后面闪现出来，在胡珀教长的唇边久久流连。

“你们为什么只是见了我才怕得发抖？”他高声说道，一边转过戴着黑面纱的脸环顾四周面色苍白的围观者，“你们彼此相见也该害怕得发抖！男人们躲着我，女人们没有一丝同情，孩子们尖叫着逃开，只是因为我的黑面纱吗？这有什么可怕呢，难道不是它所隐晦地象征着的神秘，才使得这块薄纱如此令人恐惧吗？等到朋友之间能推心置腹，爱人之间能坦诚相见，等到人们不再妄想逃避造物主的目光，令人厌恶地藏匿自己罪恶的秘密，到那时再因我生时戴着、死也不离的这个象征物而把我看成怪物吧！我环顾四周，看啊！你们的每一张脸上都有一块黑面纱！”

听众都惊怖万分，互相躲避，胡珀教长则仰面倒在枕头上，成了一具蒙着面纱的死尸，嘴唇边却仍然带着一丝残留不去的笑意。他就这样戴着面纱被人们装入棺木，也这样戴着面纱被埋进坟墓。年复一年，青草在这座坟墓上萌发又枯萎，墓碑上也长满了青苔，胡珀牧师的脸化为了尘土；可是一想到它是在那块黑面纱下衰朽腐烂的，人们仍然会凛然生畏！

————————————————————

(1) 新英格兰缅因州约克县有一位牧师约瑟夫·穆迪先生，去世已大约八十年了，他因与这里讲述的胡珀牧师具有同样的怪癖而著称于世。不过，他的象征物有不同的意义。他在年轻时曾失手杀死了一位挚爱之友，从那天起直到死去，他一直把脸藏在面纱后面不让人看见。——作者原注

(2) 这是指霍桑本人在1835年所写的短篇小说《婚礼上的丧钟》。